I was recently reminded about a
Featuring JCB that I
Said I was going to elaborate on in an advanced course
A course which I haven't yet
Been able to make because of
Time constraints in my own schedule
But I will nonetheless give it to tutorial in explaining how this concept works
So that we can start collaborating and seeing how we might want to expand on this
Ok so
First just bring everybody on to speed
Let me , sorry play that
that snippe that I made about a year ago
That this also means if there is a form field you want to extend
That doesn't exist already in our advanced Seminar we'll show
You how to add your own form Fields here there's basically two places you will need to change I wish I could tell
Tell you now one of them would be to add the field and update it accordingly
And the other one would be too to add it in a few places in the code
And also in a Jason file called settings
So those are some of the things we will deal with in advance
Adaptation of component builder we will still set up that series very soon it's not finished yet though
So here is how it works
It's not that obvious some of the concepts I'll need to go slowly and make sure
That you all follow
But
There, this is
What are the things that you need to keep in mind is that if we expand on any of these field types
Were actually expanding the custom field
Let me show you that what that means in JCB
We going area in JCB called field types
Now, these field types are editable and extendable
But and you can create new ones but you can only create field types here that either do not
definitely those don't exist if you create a field type with the same name you are going to mess
Things up
So here it's important that you only create field types that do not already exist
And that they are the field types that are available by Default in Joomla itself.
So
It must be
This list of field types
Now there might be more we not listed here
But it must be
Native to
Joomla
That is what this field type area is for.
But there is in this list one field type called custom
Which is like the chameleon of field types
It is the field type that can be any field type
And it's this field type that we are able to extend
It's options now currently if we go to create one of those
You see that it is already extending 3
Field types
So at the moment
It's extending list
Radio
And checkboxes
You see that with the extense
Attribute
And whichever you want you just add that value here in this upon this list that we can
expand
Now let me show you in the compiler how this works
So in the compiler we go to a file called C fields
The compiler obviously located
In the
In the helper
Compiler here's the files, so we opened this one C fields now C fields has a Methode
called set custom field type file
This is the method that built the file as well as sets it's content
And so most of what you need to know happens right here you could follow some methods like this build dynamic
In NetBeans if you click on control
And hold over the method tells you in what
Folder
And file that method is first declared
And then also gives you some
perimeters is if it has them mapped out
So
We can then see that this field
Sorry this method is in the structure
If we search for it here
We see that it is basically starting with a Joomla version data
Now the Joomla version data
Is being set
By another method so we can search for that
Going up
Which is it's
Space we say yeah it's being set by set Joomla version data
It's the method and that method starts by calling this settings Jason file
So
That's where it gets the data
Which we need to build the file no that's already done everything about that is in place
But where the limitation is, is that if we go to this file, this file
is found in the
Like I showed in the editorial
Component builder compiler Joomla 3, you scroll down and you double click on the settings
Jason
That's where this file is
Now
If we want to expand on one of those field types let's say we want to
Create a different type of list field
We could copy this
Slip it and just paste them again
And then change the the name of the file me
And let's also then at that me here
And also add it here so basically this will become the new name
Of the
The file if we goning to use it in the
JCB interface and that means
Let me just save this
If I copy this
And I go to JCB
Then I'll put that in there like that
Now it will be pulling that data
It"ll use that new file but new file doesn't exist so to make sure it's there we go up
And
We take this file we copy it and
Pasted in
Now we just rename it
to
Me like that
And now we have the file
This is how it looks
The thing to note here the moment is that
It's still really the same as the original
So this you'll only do if you want to break away from original implementation
The original implantation updates this value
It updates this value, it updates this value, this value, it adds this information and it adds this information
So
That would be the place holders
Which can still be targeted
Except this one
If you want to override the get input value, sorry get input method
Then this you need to remove this placeholder
And you need to add your script in here
I'm I'm looking at the option to expand
JCB's custom field
So that that specific
Area becomes a little bit more dynamic
So
At the moment it isn't like that but we we were talking about that and see if we could do that
But you could see whether we have done that eventually by this coming to this method
In the C Fields file
And then scrolling down
If you come to the bottom of the method
You'll see that you start running up to these Place holders
Which are being placed in the file content dynamic
You know
array
And
There you would notice we've got this get options PHP
J form get options PHP and that maps to this one right J form get options PHP
So literally this information here
Is being built
Down here
And
This is the value we adding how How did we get this
PHP code value we go up a little in the file we'll see that
There is actually a
value here
This is just me
checking out stuff which check if there is a PHP value and then we load those values in
Into here now where does this value come from well it is in the custom field
It is this area here
So that means you have a placeholder which at the moment is says
Says to Target the get options area
But you don't need to
Target the get options area right I mean it's only because that place holder is inside the get option
Area you could do this
Sorry I it was wrong button
You could do that
Remove all of it
And save and now
In this
Area in Joomla you can now put
Let me show you
You can put the whole
Public function get options method with your own code
Right there
No problems
And you can now write your own get input method right here and it
Will dynamically
Be added
to
To this place holder here
So this placeholder can currently be used
Anywhere you like
And in your new field type
But you could leave it the way it was
And just code in your whatever changes you want to make by removing the add button
You could do the
The get input
So here is the get input method now
So you can add that and you can
Change that to whatever you like this is the default that we usually build for the button
But you can do anything
Here now
And
Then that is what this field would be that's why I will be different because you doing your own implementation
of the get input
You can go to this J form field list method
Right you
You can actually go look at its methods
It is under your libraries, Joomla at the moment it's on the form and fields
And your scroll down to list there is J form list
And you can look at how it is doing the implementation
And you can
Add options, you can change that you can
You can extend this and you can even go back and again check the J form field
And you know have extend that once options
Reality is you could take any
Of these fields
And copy it
So let's say we want to expand on the Note 1 we can say copy
We can take it back up here
And pasted in here
Now we need to rename it so we can always get to it easily and the way I've done that
as I've said ok it should be J form
Field
And this would be note
Simple
J field note
Ok
So now we have it here
J form
Field note
And we can now just
Update some of the areas in it
To ensure that it becomes dynamic
With the same
Let's see so we'll use this value
First of all
We'll have to grab everything from there today right
And copy that
And we have to
Do this
go over like there
Yeah
And I like to change that a bit
Make it look like that
Ok the rest we could leave then again this we need to change
So the best to make sure it will work
If you just grab
That
Well that's grab this whole little thing here like that
So now we are going to extend
The
Form field
But like a note
So
We are also going to change that value
Because it needs to be Dynamic it needs to use the new field type that you going to create in the customer
Field and that's where you have to put that now this is the area you want to now adapt
The input is going to stay like that
So since this is the area want to adapt
This is the place you want to also have Dynamic I would say
Take take this value
I know in the beginning
While JCB still evolving this might not work for ever but
For the time being this will work quite well
You you just basically changing where this place holder gets placed
We wanted to make sure that
To have a different get input value structure we could still do that and now were this one we
We have a different way that is going to build the label and
We can l call it note so let's do this
We go to our settings by Jason we copy again that previous one
And we pasted in
And now this we called note
And so we do this
and that one
Note the capitalisation must match the doing these but not here because this one
Remember this value
Is built, let me save this
Is Built
Here
Up
It's built over here so the first part is field
And then the second part is what comes from JCB in the extends attribute
So that's why I just keep it lower case make it simple
So in our Jason setting it's going to be basically this value
So in JCB to Target this new field type
We'll basically have to add
That
extend Note
Now
Here you need to realise that you are now no longer targeting the get options
Although it says that
We Are Moving the get options value with the note
We are moving it to the get label
So you know how to hit the right code there that's going to be used in the get label
Now If you forgot how that should look like then again scroll down to where you took the file
from originaly
So we open note
And here you can at least see how they started while they started with element
And if it doesn't exist return empty and then and so you can decide to change
This style
How it behaves the get label
And it's your own type of note
So
This
Extending option I realise get options should actually be changed
So that it could be more movable
That is possibly what we will do and if I do that
I want to do it like three, four times I will do it once and have everyone's things break
and everybody change over and then it's done sorry about that but I can't see another way at the
The moment is called get options but it is a dynamic value which really
Links to this
Whatever you put in this box
So
This is what it ends up in that place holder
And so
We could change this to PHP for the
Placeholder
Called and it will give the placeholder a name
get options is to specific we could change that and then
in fact I think I will put the new if I change it I'll put the placeholder name right here so that
In the in the file
You could easily just rename this
To the corresponding
Yeah I think that's what we'll do anyway
This is still
Really a movable concept we now literally extended
Note and we created our own new input for our list
Wish you could do whatever you like here but you only at the moment have one placeholder
For your Dynamic values so there has been a request to have two at least two placefolders
two Dynamic coding
Placeholders
So we will end up having one for here and one for somewhere else
So I'm still
Working on make basically adding another one of these
Text areas to the custom field area
So that is what we are looking at
And
At the end of the day
It's really just to give you freedom to do expand on the custom field
It's a custom field we talking about it's not another field type
It is the field type called custom field and yes and many of the values now like button
You know some of these values become obsolete somehow because
For example the button value
In the compiler
If we go back to that compiler method
Will see that if we go down here
It says add button that's the place holder remember in the original
File we had let's say
Go up here again
Original list file had a placeholder called ADD button
It is that place holder which were looking at here
Add button
So this is dynamic hash is a value
And we have a method called set
Add button to list field
So if that method is right here so we don't have to search for it is easily find and it's basically
Checking
Should we add as is ADD button true
And if it is it builds that code
For the
Get input
And it writes a whole lot of
Code here
So if you are going to remove the add button placeholder
It will no longer
Update it
And
You now need to set your own get input
Method then
So
That is what the add button placeholder does
It adds this
Value in
If it's required
So
Now going back to our new fields
here
You will
And your
Custom code
And you will now know that this field type is targeted with list me so
Again in JCP just for good measure
This will be list me
I think I should run one or two just to make sure
That everything works because to be honest I haven't actually done any of this
Before
I'm in expanding it's just that
Quickly quickly checking ok at note is in place that one is in place
All is been saved
I'm just going just to demonstrate adding extending a note so I'm going to say noted
And the name gonna pull called it nothing
OK
Great stuff
And we are going to
Remove
Most of this
Because it's irrelevant
I'm gonna change to note
obviously no button available No table
no Component no View
Just while we could just leave the prime
That
Make sense
And I just copied the default note
Code
And maybe
We can just add something here
It says if close is true now we don't have a value here for close
So that means
we now need to go to custom
And just expanded to have the close element or
we could just say
That is going to be
we just gonna leave that out
And then the heading
Just to we can see we made it
And then
Give it a name
It doesn't know
That this is
A non database value but ok
So now we have a new field
Which expands note
And let's add it to something to see it in action
Go to demo component
Admin View
Let's go to the admin View
wrong place
Cancel
we should click here
no that was the right place
And fields
Added
OK
Just add a field here
Expanding note
And we make that also full width and me make it
two
and that should
Do
Close
Compile
Demo
Ok I've had forgot that error here and it's something about the class not being there
let me just Check that out and go to the code
Now we go to demo
We see that it created the field noted
And we have here a
Problem ,let see
That's one of the drawbacks of
Basically the
Current implementation we have here
In an our
If we go back to our component
Admin View
Basically back to that field
We have values here
Which are double quotes
And the problem is JCB
Can't handle double quotes in this area
It can only handle single quotes
That's one of the current limitations
So
Knowing that it can only handle single quotes
Makes it harder to do do coding here
But we could in the future maybe look at a work around
So for now I'm just gonna take this out just to show you that it works
And when you code you just keep in mind that you can't use
Double quotes that one
You can't use that one
You can only use single quotes in this area at the moment
Ok
Now it's going to ask me for class
Here
Take that out as well
Just for now
And save
Now let's just compile it again and install
Go back here refresh
And there's Home Run
Nothing great stuff
So our
Little
Expansion on the Note field has worked
And very much similar is how I will be for any of the others
Except now obviously for this identified limitation
Ok so let's summarise what we've done
If we want to add the class here
If you want to add
More values than what we have here now is heading
Title description
If you want to
Add more of that here we need to expand
This custom field type
So we need to come here and
With the
Like your next two buttons maybe you wanna add another
Value that you wanna have available
You will have to do it here
And it will then be available
For any custom field and you'll obviously if you selected and it's not
Related to either the radio the checkbox or the list any two just remove it out
Ok so
Yeah that's
At the moment
This area seems to still require little bit more thinking
You can of course ignore the hole
Having put it here to get the information here yeah you could skip that
And just say the scripture is going to be this and
Titles going to be there
Ok you can hardcode it in there
It's basically just JCB Joomla are taking XML
Values and translating it
And will that's one of the reasons why
Your
Double
Quotes doesn't work here is because we're
Saving this in a
In a way that
Should be XML safe but ok that's
An whole another topic
Have fun
This this is really how you expand
The custom field area
By adding new custom
Field types or field options is that maybe
To make it more
Differentiation between this
You could do that
Just a little heads up if you do that
And you've done a good job at doing that you must consider sharing that
Changes with the rest of us
Because of one issue which it the moment there isn't it work around
And that is that
If you update your JCB install
This
These new values that you've added here will actually be overwritten
It will be taken away and you need to add them in again and if you
You decide to push these new like maybe you doing a
Form field note expand and
Then you might
You need to also include this new field in the file the actual
File that is in component builders
This area here
So this
This actual file
These two files would need to be part of your pull request
I am also going to
Within the next week I'm planning
To sort of expand on this area
So if you really wanna do something big just give it
Another week or so and then come and look at the code look at
In the future if you watch this tutorial come and look at what happened in this area
And then check check these placeholders
You know take take them
Go back to the area which which I showed you in the C field
And
Check out this set custom field type file
Check what's happening here this These Place holders
Are available in your PHP
So that means
The table value the component value all of those values are available in this PHP
Area
And those values are usually what you set up here
So
It's sort of a little Dynamic Place holders so while we are loading the
Code
We are also
At the very end here
we are  taking the the place holders that we setup here
And we are
Updating
Older placeholders in the code
And this code eventually
Then gets placed into the
This get options PHP like a explain before
Now you might come here and see what I've changed some of those and what I'm going to do
and what My aim is going to be is to make this area easily more scalable
And more Dynamic so that
You could
Be even more
Free to create custom Fields that are
Yeah you need to do your application
Ok
Well thanks for watching I hope this even expands your understanding of the custom field
Implementation even more