Ok we would like to look at
The JCB compiler
Quick overview
Of how the works
And what it does
Really there must be better ways to do this I've often looked at
Are the projects even like
Joomla itself and I can see
There are conventions that I have not
Followed
Especially with some of the files being so huge
It's almost like it
The procedural Script
And yet
The refactoring and the remodeling of these
Project this project area that
Compiler
Is a ongoing project
And constantly I'm working on it as from time to time
Reality is that it works and it works actually quite well quite stable
And we are keeping our finger on it so that it wouldn't suddenly become
Useless
Now having said that
It's really one massive class
Unfortunately
Because one inherits The Other inherits The Other inherits  the other and so it keeps on stacking previous functions
Upon each other
Which then ends up being
A huge huge class and you can call
Any of the functions and anytime after a certain layer
So that's the the quick
Overview
But now
Going to those files
There are two ways we could do this we can
You can actually go to
To get up
And
We can look at
Those files there
But you can also do this on your own system
So
Our system when the package or the component is installed
The what is in the admin
Folder should be in the administrator component area
What's in the site folder should be in the
Roots component area
And this be the media
And
Libraries
So that's were all these packages move to so
If you look at it here on get up
And you see basically it says admin and then suddenly these files were as if you look at it on your
Install
You would see that it's component as the root folder administrator components
Component Builder
And then the same
Files except these two
Automatic
Generated from
Notices
Ok so
Basically the files we see here
Is the same files we are going to look at
On get help
So there are three areas where the compiler lives
One is in the actual compiler folder
And the other one is in the helpers folder
Now I said three because in the helpers folder it again has two
File structures
The compiler folder is where
Basically the templates are
So there's a Joomla 3 template area now when we start with Joomla 4 they will basically be a new one called Joomla 4
And we will update this templates
Too match the Joomla 4
And many of them might fall away and new ones will be added
And the file that controls the majority of the work of keeping track of what
Belongs where
Is this setting Dot
Jason
Settings are Jason again is just a Jason file
Which
Basically
Has all these files mapped in it with various settings
So it has a create area which basically creates the file folders for the admin area
And the site area
And then it has a move area
Which basically has a static
Values which
Every component
Should have
And then Dynamic values
Which every component gets based on its
Built
Perspective or
Whatever the developer wants
And there again in The Dynamics area you have an admin area
And you have a
Site
Site area
And you have a custom
Custom admin area
And these are the 3 areas in the dynamic in each of them
Have certain values and things which are used
To actually
When we call the built on any of these function or
areas then
Switches are what is being used
So this file is what
Really gets called
And
Which is used
to then
Built
The Joomla 3
Templates
So you are you have a whole lot of templates some of them have code in some of them majoritly
have only place holders in them
You can look through these
And
Yes
We are
Moving more and more that every little bit of the file is actually becoming dynamic
So in some files you get lot of code still and yet and others you might find none
And that means all the code was moved to the actual compiler
This means that this is just a template the area
And yes
Still it's good to know about this area because you might wonder where is that code I don't see it anywhere in the compiler
Well then it's in the template
No really that's what that's all about
Ok then
The compiler itself the thing the whether real code is that does the work
Is actually in the helpers folder
And it has two areas here it's the actual trigger which is this one here compiler
And then it has these folders
In the compiler again
Folder
Which
Is alphabetically organised
So that when we include those files they get added correct
And in the correct
Order
Which being get is first then structure
Then fields, then interpritation and then infusion
And
Then only
You would see that
The file called compiler which is in the root of helpers folder
Is the one that inherits
infusion
So if we open it
in fact we will open all of those
So we open the
then we open get
Structure
Fields
Interpretation
And
infusion
So
Let's see
The here's the compiler the actual
Class that gets
Executed
On the start of the compiler
And you can see if it actually extends then infusion class
So that means everything that has been done before
This class was triggered by the constructor in every class
So the constructor in every class kicks of a whole bunch of functions
Methods and loads a lot of data into the class method values
And this autoloader
Loads those files
Ok so that's just
A quick structural explanation
Then we go and the first one Look Out Here is
wait over here this one
So here we have the infusion and it inherits the interpretation and here we have the interpretation
and inherits
The Fields and here we have
Fields
And it inherits the structure
Here we have the structure and it inherits the get
And here we have the get
so this is the base class
It's from this class that we build
And basically its name sort of gives you an idea of what's happening here
So in this
Class we really did doing the get
We getting all the information
From the database
And within his relationships
And so forth
And we are
Packing them and making them ready
Basically modelling them
For the next class and for the next step
I'm not sure how to draw a model of all this
I'm not even sure exactly how I got here except that it became
Like a practical Next Step
I
Will usually confronted with a problem and then trying to solve it is how this thing
Evolved into what it is today
So I didn't do the way we should do things and that is to sit down and first to
Use cases
All of the Prep
To get all your class names out and
Get all your yeah
Just to develop the structure in white paper
I didn't do any of that
I started in the longest way I just wanted to build a component with another component and be able to
To reuse that to do it again and again
That's really what I wanted to do and I know therefore that they could be better ways to do this
And I hope that wouldn't actually discourage  any of you
But in fact would encourage you to realise that
There is many ways to actually end up at a
You know
A result
Anyway
So
Without to much apology
This is there for the constructor
Of the get class
Which triggers a whole lot of things
And so just in there by inheritance
This constructor gets triggered and data gets added to the
Model
Class
Values
And then gets used in the classes to follow
And
There also some functions that also lives here
But which we
Called public
Which might be used again
But like this one actually doesn't need to be public
I think
So
It all gets triggered
And you can go through this
Get class and
Basically by the name of the methods
Be able to discover what is being done in this method
And
Then so forth
The next one is then the structure
And here we basically taking the template files
And we are
Starting to
Pull them out give them right names
And put them in the right place for preparation to add the code to them
So a lot of the templates are being
Built here again you got a constructor
And here it starts setting libraries and you can see in the constructor what happens First
So you can look at this
And see ok
Remove folders we physically now then set libraries then set dynamic, dashboard and set folders
and set stastic
Set dynamic
So you can check in the constructor how the functions or there is and then you can actually go
And look at those functions
Quickly and see what happens in them
All the functions that are running alongside of them
And
That's sort of how the structure class Works
And then there are obviously some functions here in the structure class that also again get used
In further classes
We then end up at the fields class
This is where we start
Actually realising the code
That needs to be added back to the files
And we start building the fields
The fields which actually in their relation to their views
Actually starts happening
Well will first check that the view have fields
And if it does
Then we start
Either by using the string method or the XML method there are two methods in which we build
The fields
If it said to use the strength
Fieldset
Then
This is how it will go about and over
About
Where is that almost
Are we here
It says
Well here at Loops over the fields and it uses a set Dynamic field
And it passes it a whole lot of values
And so you can then
Follow this
Get
Go to this
Class
Method and see
Here is the perimeters that it needs
And
Then see how it's being built
So
All the everything about Fields happens here
In this
Class
As much as possible I tried to do a lot of inheritance and
All morphism in all these things all of the time
I I like to not do it too much and you hear that some
Stages decoupling is necessary
for
For stability
And so you'll see that
All across the classes
That I'm trying to reuse things quite extensively
Ok now after the
Fields we are at the interpretation
Now the interpretation basically takes what the fields gave us
Including the structure including the gate
And it starts interpreting what is being
Expected here
And yes this is the class which is where I started
So you if you wanna know from where
What what what which ones are right first is actually this one
And Get and
Fields and
All of those code
Was in this class
So this used to be
Like
Huge I mean
I think it was
Over over 20000 lines
And now
After doing such a ridiculous
Amount of coding and realising ok it's
Absolutely not convention
I started the refactoring in this and breaking it up
And
This is How far I've got so
Please have mercy on me
We've started decoupling these
And yet we are still so far away from
Fully decoupling them
What advantages we've made is that
If you compile a component and you wanna see me where what is being built it actually JCB
Actually has such a feature
It is a feature which I'm sure all of you have used it's this line numbers
Which I could say to you now just yes
And that would basically mean that now in your components
Comments
You'll see references to where in the compiler the code was built
And that is sort of my way of making apology for this massive class
Because I know the objection to it is the difficulty of debugging
And well not necessarily debugging as much as
You not understanding
What's happening here
And so
I'm trying to
Do that at the moment
And yet I must tell you
I've never not been able to expand on this area and actually change it and fix it
Because the class names
And what is being done here
Is actually quite understandable
And easily to find if you in the code can find the line where the code is built
You can then go to that line and very quickly
Actually be able to follow
The path
In which things happens
And so
I would expect the future would hold in
That we do even more
Refactoring on this class
And have
More sub classes actually
And I'm very open for you too
To actually get involved in this area and help
To make it easier
But on the other side
The
The other term that also does stand out is if it works
Don't fix it
So I would say as we improve JCB
And as we adapt it
To do better
This is where most of the refractory will
Usually take
Place
And so every time there is a feature request and a specific area is having to change
I usually come in and refactor that whole area
That I'm currently working at this
It is a lot of code but it's really simple I didn't
I didn't purposefully didn't wanna build something so complicated that if you would read it you have no idea
of following it
I tried to make it
Quite simple
An easy to follow
And hoping that others would easily come in here and
Be able to see you
How things work
I'm in the interpretation class
And be able to
You know
Improve it
Make bull request
The next one is then the infusion the Fusion class is actually where the interpretation
Class gets fired
Most of their interpretation class functions
Actually gets fired here
So
We have a whole bunch
You know placeholders the way JCP works is really the strength of BHP and that is stream manipulation
And so we have placeholders which
Are in those files that we spoke of those template files and those templates files
Are having to be updated
I'm so first we need to load the
Code
Which actually gets built in the
interpretation class
We need to load those into place holders
And then does placeholders in turn
Will be
Take into the files and merge
And so it is in there
Infusion class
That this happens
And so a lot of functions
That are in the interpretation class
Are actually fired
From this class
So sort of sort of looking back
And getting the work done
And so it's like now
The work is getting less so the majority of the code
Which we need to do the work is behind us
And really now it's just sort of organising
the Logic and
This
is really what's happening here
You're so the Massive
Method
Is just
This one class one massive method that loads
All the function values into
The place holding
And then there's a second things that are static
And then there is content that are dynamic
And the dynamic content placeholders work a little different in that
It has to
The things here
What is the for what it is
And then for where it is
So for this one is for the dashboard but later you'd see
And it starts going to a Ajacks
And it has
Oh wait
We go up again
You see here
That it actually targets The View
The list view and actual
Edit view Single View
Here it is
So is
Doing a whole lot of
Building a one massive array
Of data
Which then
At some point it's going to get rid of by placing it into the files
And there are some other functions also in this class
Which are
Useful
To understand
So let's see what's the
OK we'll allmost at the end of this method
Ok so here we have set view placeholders with basically every view has its own set of names
Abbreviations
And then we also got language
Manipulation here
And that's it
Ok so
The next one is the one which is called compiler and it actually then
Extends then extends the infusion class
And it's in the compiler
Where we take
The templates
And the logic of
All the other classes
And we actually merge them with
Files
So we have a class here
Old update files
And really it takes
The new files which been built
And it adds the file Dynamics and the file statics
And updates
via the static values as well as the dynamic values
then places it back and then actually on
unsets the values
And then eventually we packaged this file
And move it to servers and said licences in
All kinds of nice need stuff
And
That is where it all comes to a conclusion
There's also some real fancy gymnastics here being done with a custom coding concepts
We we add code into those files
Really here
And update things
Which is
Quite exciting area this add custom code
Class
Sorry method
Is a
Very
Interesting method it actually ties into work that's been done
All across the other classes
So that's a quick overview
Of the compiler
It's really not that complicated
If you don't If you know PHP If you don't If you don't know programming that well I'm suppose that must be
So like ok
Over your head
But if you are
Fairly
Good developer
This shouldn't be any surprise I think Joomla's implimentations
are far beyond this
They really doing a excellent job
I'm still using old kind of implementations is here
And it's seems to at this stage do the work
But I also anticipate
That we will start
The implementing some of the better
Conventions as we continue
Well thanks for watching
If you have any questions please
You're welcome to
To contact me
either on Get up or on the Forum
I really would want to encourage other developers
Who understand
This what I've just explained
To actually help improve it
Because if you compile a component
And you can see ok this areas code comes from here
And you know that this is not the best way of doing it
And there are more Joomla
Convention better Joomla convention
To do this
I really want to to hear from you I really want to change it
Either myself or you yourself doing a commit
a bull request actually
And that's really how I see the way forward
I'm trying my very best to make this as appealing to the Open Source community
So that they wouldn't know that this is for real
And that they would actually
Yes
Make this their own
Thank you