Now that we've given you a general overview of how are things work
in the new snippet manager
I would like to
Take You The Next Step and that is
Showing you how to take shared snippets
And
Basically
Share them
There are two things that should be done
What is
You need to fork
The
JCB community Snippets
On get up so you need a github account
The second thing
Is once you
Done that
You would export the Snippets here that you would like to contribute
And you will add it
To this
Repository that you forked and cloned down to your developing environment
And you would make commit messages on every change that you are
Intending to make
The second thing you would do Although there are few steps in each of these
Things the second thing is that you would then
Make a pull request
So this tutorial I'm just gonna focus on the first
Few things you need to do
And that is just to get you
Basically ready
All the things you need to do until the very point when you are now ready to actually do a pull request
Ok so now
There are three things that I suspect we can do one is to improve
Already existing snippet
And then contribute that to the community
The second thing is to move and existing snippet
To a new type this isn't something I hope will happen often but it can't happen
That a snippet is in a specific type that is not the best suit for it
And
You might wanna suggest us changing that
So that would be a second thing
And the third one
Would be to actually add a whole new snippet completely
So I think I'm just gonna demonstrate all three of those
And then we'll see how that all plays Out
Until the very point where we are now ready to make a pull request
Ok first things first
We need
Repository
And we need to understand git
Now if you do not know get
The story is not gonna cover that
You need to do your homework
And study upon git
When you do an export of a package for example if I were to click here on these
three herein
Clickshare Snippets
You see that it ends up showing you a bunch of links here and one of them is quick start for git
On Yodomy
At this link here I just searched on Google found it I didn't actually watch it myself I hope it's not bad
If you got a better one
Please share it
On on the issue somewhere and will will improve this link
I'm your even if you've got your own and you would like us to promote your
Tutorials on get sure
Why not
We will support those who support
our community
Very gladly
Reality is
You need to get some
Your head around some of the git basics
So that you can actually do
A
Fork of the
JCB Snippets on github
And then make a pull request
So this
Video here is the one I'm busy making so it will end up that being that link how to fork
JCB Snippets and get all this done
And then after that I'll be making this video
So we'll get to that in a moment
Ok
Now
You need a an account on GitHub
And so I'm just gonna use my own account
And
Simply go and
Fork the repository and use that as the demonstration
So needless to say I've got an account I've gone through all those hoops
And now I'm simply go to fork  this repository
To get to this repository
It's this your all up here
Another way to get here
Is
You go to get Snippets
And then the moment it's finish loading there is a link that you can click which will take you
To the GitHub repository and it's this link over here so we could click that
And as you see we're end up at the same place
it be good
So you could either just
Follow this URL appear all good just use that link
But you wanna get to Joomla component builder snippets
And I suppose
Since everybody that wants to contribute will need to fork it
I suspect this numbers here will change
And of course well this respositry is like 6 days old I haven't even finished the ReadMe
So there will be a lot of changes to this
Repository and it will improve
So the first thing you do is click on this button here and forked repository
This will then ask you to select
Where you want to fork it if you belong to organisations whatever but then
Obviously by then I don't need to explain to you how it works
But if for some reason you don't then you select your personal or whatever organisation
You want a fork to appear in
And then it will basically
copy this repository
For you
Ok so now it's busy doing that I'm basically just copying it into my personal
Account
Now
Good practice
Every time you wanna make it change
Then
You need to follow a few steps
In
Having this repository in sync
With the
What we call upstream repository this VDM dot IO
Joomla component Builders snippets
This is what we call the upstream
All the master branch or whatever you wanna call it this is the main
Branch the one that is being used inside of JCB yours is indirectly being used
So whatever changes you make here would not necessarily affect us at all
But you obviously want them
Commit your changes to your branch
And then
Make a pull request
To the upstream branch
Where you would like to share this with the community
So that's
Sort of a quick explanation we'll do this slowly
I'm not gonna do the pool request
Now in this tutorial
But I'll take you all the way up to the wall and then we will get the ladder out and finish that in the next tutorial
Ok so once you've done this forking of the main
Repository
You need to clone this repository down
to your own developing environment
And
So that is what I'll do next
You would click on this
Clone and
Depending on how you've got get set up on your developing environment
Again those tutorials you need to do before coming here
You would select either SSH or https  I would suggest using https
as this is of course more secure
But ok
So we'll just copy that and then we go
To I'm just gonna use my
My
New users home folder for now
So here I am in the command line
I'm running Linux so if you're running using Windows
You need to watch tutorials on how to do get in Windows
You might end up using a tool instead of command line
But if you did that you also be having had watched
Tutorials to help you sort of understand what I'm doing
Ok
So first thing first we gonna clone it let's get that done
So I've cloned it
And we now have a folder
Call Joomla component Builders snippets
So I'm gonna change into that folder now
Just CD and a folder name and there we go I'm in the folder
And if I do LSLA  will basically see all the files
That was on get up now in that folder
Now we want to change these files
But we not going to change them directly
We're going to use JCB to do the dirty work for us
Because we might have issues with escaping and all kinds of things that can go wrong
So just to have good convention
Whatever changes wanna make even if you wanna add files or new libraries whatever
You do it in JCB and you do the export package
And you should check that if you export a snippet
That it has three
Values always set
And that does three values
Well will obviously scrutinise it when you make her pull request
But that does name conventions
be standard
It's quite important as you can see this but got the library name you like it
And it's uppercase U and space lowercase V2
And then common with uppercase
And that is the type of snippet
And then it's the name
And obviously Jason file
So
This is the convention
And at this stage JCB built that for you
And I'm gonna show you where it gets this convention
Because to follow this Convention is what's really gonna be very important
If you making a new Snippets
For the UI kit version two library
You need to ensure that your
Version 2 naming in your system is the same as it is here
And if you are adding a new library that isn't already in our repository
Then you need to make sure that you use
The naming as found wall
As others will understand it as most common
The most common name in convention
And obviously if you need help on that you can open an issue and ask one of the admin
Do you know
Maybe give you a suggestion of what
To call the library
But
The Long and the short end of it is
Please stick to the naming conventions
Don't change this UI kit
To maybe the remove the space here or something that
Because it will end up
Just miss matching things and
One of word that from happening
Ok so first thing with done with forked repository and with now cloned it
Do offline developing environment
And now I'm going to go to JCB
I'm gonna export does 3 Snippets the one is a new snippet
The second is a changed or improved snippet
And in the 3rd is when you actually move a snippet to a different type
the one I'm going to target here
Is let me see
Think it's
Not showing here now
I hear this
Food table
The food table snippet
Is at the moment in layout
I think there is a better
Type for this snippet and I know the snippet isn't
At this stage maybe the best
We could add some more food table Snippets but I'll leave that to some with you to do
The point is I'm gonna move this one
To the tables because it is a table right
So that'll be the one change I'm gonna make then I'm gonna add one snippet
To the UI kit versions 3
Since those tickets are still coming I'll just add 1 as they mistration and then I'll make a little change
To one of these Snippets just for them mistration ok great let me do that
Ok first thing a food table click on that one
Change it from layout
To tables
I'm gonna make any other changes I'm just changing the type
And this brings us to those three values that must always be set
And shouldn't change unless it's really seriously necessary the one is the name
You wouldn't wanna change this name unless you are 100% sure it should be changed
Because in effect it will create a new snippet
Because the way the Snippets work it builds the filename
With name
The library and the type
Those three components together makes up the file name
To changing any of those will in effect greater New snippet
And create a duplicate
And that's really wanna would try to avoid that
And I realised
This is gonna what I'm doing here now is inevitably gonna cause that
And I think it will show you why it's not a good thing to do it
But so I'm doing this more really for the demonstration
And so the ideal reality is that when we add snippet we added to the correct library and type
And give it the correct name
From the start and it we don't need to change those three again
If we do
Most of the time I would expect
That your pull request will be rejected
Because this will mess up many conventions and cause
Many duplicates across the system
In other developers environment where they would import this new snippet
And yet end up having to the same Snippets
Ok I've said enough about that
I hope you understand that important this part is
So let's go ahead save and close
The next one I'm gonna do
Is basically add a new snippet now since I've done this recording
Second time now
I've already done that and this is a accordion snippet  here
So you'll see that I've basically
Said that is a JavaScript snippet
It's an accordion
It's Yohaa kid Version 3
I look down these types
I'm wonder if some one of the other guys won't be better at this identifying of the types
So I might even
Not be the guy to make the call on this
I really am open to some
With better prospective
Maybe knows these libraries assorting
It is better
I think there's a place called
What is it
Collapse
Yeah collaps
It accordions could also fit other under this collapse I suppose
No let me do that
I know the first accordian we added for UI kit version 2
That is actually found on the JavaScript
But then we didn't have these many types
So
I'll just add it under this collaps  for now
Again I realise that this might be a difficult thing
And
What could help is going back to the actual  library itself
This
This is the
The link for it
And to try and see how they
Organised it and that's the problem
UI kit
Didn't
Give more breakdown besides calling it components
So it's only call the component it doesn't
Specifically added into a type
Whereas Bootstrap is doing a little better at that
So that's why
I'm not sure exactly where to place it now
bootsstrap
Actually adds it on the collapse
I think we won't go wrong to do the same
So save and close
There we go we got now
A very crazy risky change of a type
And a new snippet now let me take another
Snippet and just make a little improvement to it
I think I would use this
UI kit version 2
Form snippet
I'm just gonna add some usage information to it
Ok there we go
And I'm gonna save it
save and close
So now I've made a change
Basically two
This one
This one and that that one and So those are the only ones I'm actually going to share
This one when I created it it added my details
As the
Contributor
Which if you created a snippet
You know add your details you will notice when you create a new snippet
It takes a while before it's finish saving and it's because it's actually phoning
Github
And trying to see if there isn't a snippet
Already with that
Relationship as explained in a previous tutorial
And that takes a while I'm I'm still wondering if that's the best idea
If we should continue doing that
I'm open for
Suggestions
But at this stage we just trying to confirm that
that snippet
Wasn't already created
And to avoid conflicts
Now
That means if it doesn't find it it adds your details which is set here in the option Global options
And as I explained in that tutorial
You can add your details and you would get some
exposure out there the community
With your details there
With these that I've just changed
The contributor will stay the same
But your name will come in on the blame
Layout
And your GitHub name will display there as recognition for your support
Ok so now and next thing share Snippets
Well the reason I
Made it that it actually compiles is zip
File
Because it's easier to move around
We could argue that we might want to just have it zip
Move
Rather move the
Files right into your
A local cloned
Folder
And so I am thinking at this stage maybe
We should add a switch here in the global options
That could make you choose it to do this or the other depending on what is most convenient for you
So I'm gonna go take the snippet
And then I'm gonna go and basically unzip it into
That
Repository that we've cloned
So here we are in that folder I'm gonna first unzip it right here
There there is those 3 files
That we want to make part of the repository
Now like I said I
Actually clone to repository right into my
user
Folder
So let us go to that folder
Just go to cut it here
Cut
And then paste
It right into that folder
Now we are updating
21 file
So it's asking you ready contains this file
Now so when you make an improvement on a file you will obviously have to replace it
So we click replace
Now that you've
Added those two new files
And you have
Replaced one of them
The third one
You see that we now have this
Food table
The tables version
And we have it also
Add the layout version now one of them needs to go
We don't want duplicates
So you have to remove this one but
Don't remove it via the
The Interface
Use use git
To remove the file
So that you can also add a message
So that when you make your pull request and we see their files removed
It will know why you did it
And obviously then it will become a discussion
And this will demonstrate in the next tutorial
Ok so let's get back to command line
Yeah we are we can say git
Status to see what happened and we see wow ok what has been modified and these two has been added
The first thing we wanna do is remove the one that we don't want
Now because we have chosen to leave spaces within a file names
You need to
In put the file name in quotations
To ensure that it actually you know
Not misunderstand what you doing
So we will do a git  "rm" for remove
And then the file name
So
You could click tab after typing food table all about there and then lay out and it
Will basically grab the name for you
And then click enter
So it is removed it if we now to get status
Will see that it's in the deleted
Area and you need to actually
Make a commit
to
Explain what you've done so it's get
Commit "m"
And removed table-layout
Since
I
Moved
Did
Food table snippet
Tables
To the tables type
So
We're not at this stage exactly sure
How we are going to
What kind of conventions we gotta follow with these commit messages
There are reasons to have a few conventions here I just haven't had time to sort of get my head around it
so for now
we will keep it basic
But I'm sure as to community develops things will become more
Explained and so if you need help
Will most probably have some documentation up
At some stage
to get you
Do you know how to
Correctly do a commit message
I mean just what you should say first and what you shouldn't say and those kind of things
Ok so I've got a key that signs of every commit they make
You may not have that don't worry about it it's not really compulsory at this stage
It's just the way I can make sure that everybody knows
That it's me
Ok
Now
The next thing here is we wanna
Add this new file so as we do git
Status
We'll see that now that file is been
Made part of the commit
At the branch
or the local files of this clone
And we wanna add those to other files
The first one I'm gonna Target
Is adding the food table which we just removed
So get
Status
Oops
Ok so now we've got that one added
And we need to give it a commit message
Now I understand
When we are doing such
Dangerous thing as moving a snippet to another type
I would expect us to actually make a commit message for every
Step of what we're doing
But if you're adding Like A Whole New Library and you got like 300 new Snippets that you contribute in
I wouldn't mind you adding all of that on the one commit message
Just making sure that the it was exported
via Joomla's component Builder
So that we don't have
You know the wrong kind of code within does snippet files
And obviously we will at the
Pull request
Will scrutinize those files and we will have to look through them to insure
That it won't make any one system unstable
And so basically got a police some of this to do in sure that nothing gets you know
Merged into the master branch
That will put every anyone at risk as much as as far as we are able to
To prevent that we wanna do that
Well we working with snippet so it should be fine but just in case we wanna be careful
So when you making changes to one specific snippet
And you're not really like doing
Many at a time
I think be as detailed as you can in your commit messages
Because the more we know of What U doing
I think the easier it will be to merge it into
The branch and to basically approve your pull request
So the next commit message I'm just gonna say
Git commit
Message update the food table layout food table Dot Jason to food table
Table
Food table Dot Jason since
It is more correct snippet type
Ok so that would then
Deal with that added file
Now we want to
At the accordion which is the the new snippet
So it's just get Ad and we can select the file name
There is a shortcut to this
Is when you use the dot get dot ad that's usually when you have lots of files who just wanna add them all
It's like I explain if you doing in a whole bunch of snippets it's for a specific library
I would suggest doing library per library instead of just mixing them all up
Because if we target a library and just add a bunch of snippets for it
And then have a commit message just for that then we could explain that within the commit message
that it's for the specific library and so forth
Because usually with new libraries
You know it's good for us too
Sort of take it one step at a time
Ok now we've added that file now just going to add commit message for it
I'm just gonna say added to Accordion snippet
For you are cute Version 3 as demonstration
On how this should work
Ok and then just again
Sign-off that's
Commit
Get status
We'll see ok we've got one file left and we already 3 commits
Ahead
Of our
Our
Branch that we have
Cloned
So just this last
file which is the
You know the update we made
So
We gonna first add the file
And then add a commit message
To explain what we did
Added the uses paragraph to explain how to use the Yohaa kid version 2 layout form
Yeah I think just writing out file name like that is
Clear enough
And enter
again to sign off on that
Again if you don't have
Keys to then
It's good go Google this Start signing your request
But at this stage it's not a requirement as I said
Ok if we do get status now
Will see that we are 4 commits ahead
Now this is here where
We wanna do a few more things
To your
Commit all sorry to you all
Your
Forked
And therefore cloned repository
Is what we wanna do something that will keep
Your
Repository in sync with the upstream
So I'm just gonna go and Google this quickly
This is a very helpful document
We first need to do this configure a remote that points to an upstream repository
So let's first look at that one
So this gives you
Little explanation
Of you know what you should do
So
First you basically
List the current
Remote branches
That you have
So I've done that and it shows us that I've got this git
What the origin
And it's the fetched and they pushed
Remote branches
Now
It's gonna I say specify a new remote upstream repository that will be synced with this fork
So we'll use the original owner and the original repository
Name
Which In our case is the following
The original owner is this
VDM
Dot IO and
The repositories this one
so to get that name
You could come here
And
Yeah think you could get
This name here
There we go
That part
copy
So going back to our little tutotial
We will not type the
Get and I suppose you'll have to get the https version
Since you will not have permission to
Work with the SSH version
So let's get the http one
Which basically means that you should click http here
And then grab that version to jusy copy it
And
Control
Shift we will paste it in
Into command line or some
Command lines even gives you this option to paste
With a mouse
Ok so now we got that there
And we press enter
So it's now
Typo
Try again
I didn't add remote add
So it was looking for a file
Ok there we go now if we did that version
Will see now
It has this upstream there is well
Ok so that was just add to remote
All the upstream
Repository to the
Cloned
Version that you have here
Now let's go see how to keep it in sync
So here it says that you would open the terminal
And you would do get fetch upstream
And it will basically pull down
This
And make sure that there is a branch called upstream Master
When you Checkout Master
And switch the master branch
and do merge upstream Master
Which if while you were busy doing these slippets improvements and things
And there's been commits to the master branch
You wanna make sure
That you
Actually before pushing all this upstream
Before making a
you know a pull request that you first merge
The already Changes from the master branch
Into your branch and then make your commits on top of that
This will help to try and avoid
You not having specific commits in your branch I know it gets a little bit complicated
but
If you get stuck
We will most of the times be able to just help you
Figure this out again
But like I explained in the beginning
To know how to work with Git
Is really your responsibility
So that
You and you are wanting to communicate or sorry to
Share with the community Snippets
You know how to first make a pull
Request sorry emerge
Your upstream with your master branch
And ensure that you are up-to-date with that before making a push
to your branch and
Yes I hope you understand anyway if you don't please Google it and do some homework to get you
Get
Knowledge or freshen up and ready
Now I know we didn't make any changes to the master branch during this tutorial
So
I can demonstrate the process of git
Fetch
Upstream
And it will do that
But since I know that we didn't actually make any changes
In the end of the day
We we will not be
Really seeing any
Great fireworks happening right now
And I suppose some of you will experience it a little different
Especially if there's been changes to the upstream
while you
been working
So git
Checkout Master
It's usually the bronze at your own but just to make sure
You're ready on the master branch
Then git
merge
I missed out to get there
Merge
Upstream Master
And it says like now it's already up to date
If it wasn't it will actually
Merge those two branches
With the changes you've made
Now
That's what you should do before you do the following
Git
Push
Which will now take these changes you've made
And you wanna push them
To origin
Origin Master
Now
Everything you've done
All the commit you made all the commit messages the files you removed
All of that now gets pushed up
To your cloned version
On GitHub
So if we go to your version now on Githup
And we just refresh the page
He'll say
This branch is 4 commits a head of EDM IO Master
Which means you are now ready
To make a pull request
A pull request is what we will deal within the next tutorial
So everything we've done so far and this tutorial is to get the Snippets that you've changed the contribution
You wanna make
Into the branch that you forked
And to do it in a way that you're not completely out of sync
With a master branch
Which is living
Basically on EDM dot IO
Joomla component Builders snippets This is the
Master branch that you forked
So you've got those commits in your forked branch
And now you want to actually make
A pull request
To merge these changes you've made into that Master branch
So that it will eventually become available
To the whole community of JCB
Ok thank you for watching
If you have any issues
Please Google
Do research
Git is an amazing technology and
The quicker you can
Get your hands on it and
Become
Comfortable with working with it the better
Ok
Next tutorial
Will deal with the pull request