I'm doing to Demonstrate to you
The process of now taking
You're committed changes to your forked version
But this one
Not the master branch
Now it's gonna be little different for you because of course I am a
Administrator of the master branch
So I'll see things that you maybe won't see
But
More or less you should be able to actually make a pull request
And
If you're not able to please let us know
So I can
Make sure that you're able to
Do that
And
and there will be more guys involved in managing these Snippets
So it's not only myself that will be responding to issues
But
for the most part if there is really a holdup
I'll come in and help
Make sure that everything
Works as we expect
So you should be able to after having
Done
What we've explained in the previous tutorial you know
Updating the snippets getting out a forked version
Of the repository
cloning it down offline
And then basically it
Unzipping the package into that repository
Updating those files committing those changes with messages
And then pushing it up here after you have ensured that your branch is in sync with the upstream branch
Ok
That if you don't understood
Please go back watch that tutorial is the previous one with playlist
On YouTube
And then this one now
Will be
First steps
Basically
off doing a pull request
So once you are in your repository on GitHub
And you
Push the changes up here you'll see this you know
Message
And be able to click on
Pull request
So
We've done that
Next thing it will open a page
Where
it Basically
Identifies
That you have forked
VDM
On the hyphen
IO for slash Joomla component Builder
Snippets
Master branch
As the base there's only one branch at the moment
And
Then
Your head
Of the fork
But you've got is over here
And if it's says to you that it's able to do a merge
Then
You're in good shape everything shouldn't
Be more complicated
You also now see that those commit messages you've made
Are now actually also showing up here
And exactly every change that was done so basically you see we changed it
From layout
To tables
And we did
shows you that we've renamed it from this
to that
So it actually identified that for us
And we can see ok nothing of the Snippets have changed
You can Scroll and see ok the snippet
Isn't changed only those and the date
Which is good for we wanna
Be able to see that what When was the last change to the file
Here we can see that usage had
A new
Description added
So that means if I was to now actually click
On this link
Added according snippet
Click there
You see ok that's exactly what he did added accorded snippet
And
The same goes for every one of these commit messages
And that's really what I meant when I said
Giving good commit messages
You make it so much easier for us to review the changes
And to make sure that it is correct
If it is very complicated and difficult
Usually this kind of pull request will take longer
So doing smaller amounts in snippet
Contributions of Stead of whole bulk I suppose
Would be
Better
Unless you already a trusted member in the community then I'll suppose it will go easier
So yeah if you haven't done any of these before maybe take smaller steps at first
Until we get to know you and until we more
Confident that you
Are a good contributor to do this project
Yeah so trust is important for us
So we'll be able to check this now no pull request has yet been made We've just come to the
Page of where it starts
You actually need to click on this create pull request
This will now open in area
Which
You should give us information
Of
What would sort of summarise
This pull request
So if it's like a new library let's say 3, 4, 5, snippets to a new library
Then just put that as the title
Whatever would be enough
To actually give those
That needs to review This is enough information to know what's happening
And what's coming in specially
If there is some
Specific detail now I know
That we will
In time at some
Documents to this repository
Which will give you sort of
Demo
Names and stuff in this field
So that you will know what to put in there
So that will still come so I from now just gonna say
Illustration of snippet contribution
Now I don't think you'll be able to make changes here
It's only the admin that actually has the ability to actually add a reviewer
And
Assign a label and
A project and a milestone
And so that will be the responsible of the of the admin
They might not do it
They might feel I will just merges in we don't need to make a much fuss of it
But if it's a big contribution and there need to be some real
you know
Work done here
We must probably make use of these tools
The description
We could either just use the
Commit messages as the description
Or like I said
That which we will maybe set up in the
In the future
We will now then create the pull request
And
Just given another glance and say ok everything is fine and click create pull request
When now the a pull request and really here
Is where we as the admin
Will now get involved
You cannot really take it further
And
Rightly so because we want to
Protect this repository
We wanna make sure only good
you know
Well-documented
Well explain well named
Snippets are contributed
And so once you have come to this point
You'll have to wait for one of our admin
To get back to you at actually
If they have issues they will start discussing it with you
Ask questions
And please
We wanna just
Protect you and protect everyone else
So don't
Be upset if they have questions
In fact be glad that they would
That will ensure that all of us
Will enjoy this infrastructure
So
Once everything is satisfied and everyone is happy
There will be some reviewers that will sign off
On this pull request
And I think at this stage if we have two reviewers sign off on it
At least
Then we can you know we can merge it into the master branch
Now there are different ways on how the merging into the master branch is done
This is mostly related and I'm doing this part mostly for the admin
Who may need to be able to do this
You could do it here on Github
Just click merge pull request
Since there is no conflicts
If there is conflict then it gets more complicated
And usually we will need more advanced admin
Guy who knows Git better
To maybe in a command line
Be able to resolve some of this
You can click on this link here and I'll show you the command line
Way of dealing with it
Or
You could select
One of these various emerging options
Now all of that I'll explain more in editorial that's just specifically directed
At the further steps that is necessary for admins
we're as regarding
You as a contributor
This is really where you end
And
We take over
Now
Wanna tell you that
Once the contribution is accepted and it's merged in
Then it will again become visible
In JCB
In the snippet Git area
Which we demonstrated when we started out giving an overview of how things work
And really that's what it's about it's really all of this complexity that we've now discussed
Is
Not the main focus
The Focus is to
Enable us
to
Enlarge the snippet
Area
Without
Really intruding
Bond constant updates and database tricks to you know share these Snippets
But instead have this easy way of
Maintaining a GitHub repository
Which in
Effect will then be accessible via the JCB git area
When you can add new Snippets
You can obviously delete snippets
Just going to the Snippets area
You can come in there and click here and trash a snippet
And
Then go to
Trashed
And here
Completely delete the snippet from your repository
Which will then
Cause the snippet
to
Be seen as non existent in your surface area
And so there are ways to remove duplicates
And I don't wanna go into a very long explanation again
On how to get Snippets area works
But
Our expectation is that some of you would feel
you know yeah I wanna contribute
Share Snippets with the rest of the community and in the same time
Get your name
Out there since looking at the files changed
You see that this news snippet
Has
Yeah it looks like it just did what it's been doing you now because my name is on most of these
What is because I added them
And that's why I my name is on there
And so
You are now also able to
Add your name in here because you are adding Snippets
And that's really the idea
Well
So we come to the end of this tutorial
Thank you for watching
And I'm looking forward to seeing all of you getting involved
In this area as well