I wanna talk to you about a collaborative workflow now JCB
Like any other Joomla component
Can function in a shared environmental quite easily
Will you have one website or one system that is online
And people can login
And they can
Edit documents
Say that's a components
and they can
Click on a component
And while they're working on that component
No one else can
Because it will in effect
Lock the component out to them so if we open
That list you again you see that it's checked out
And so this functionality
Is available in JCB already
So with it whether it's an admin view whether it's field
If your login and someone else opens it up it takes out the item and so people can work together
Quite easily
In a shared inviroment
Weather have one JCB
But multiple users
More than that
It's also has a very strong
Permissional structure
Which if you open the component Builder
permissional area you'll see that it has quite a long list
I suppose longer than
One might anticipate
But it's huge
List of permissions
And that means you can have different groups in your Joomla
You know groups in regarding to these
But I have access and is allowed to work on only certain areas
And
So your possibilities
Of setting up a development workflow with JCB
In one Joomla website is endless
And that was the whole idea behind here was to make JCB
A place where you could have teams work together
In Joomla
Developing components
So this is the
The one that's worked from day one this or this this approach
And it is it is very powerful and
I've already been told by quite a number of developers that they are using that they put teams working together
On components and it is excellent
So I'm happy to see that working
But like we all know JCB's most
desirable environment is an offline environment
Where you do development in your own local developing environment
Where you maybe have a virtual machine running
And you can do docer appointments
Or something like that when your on Joomla and
You're safe within your own network
And when you do that
The collaborative concept of working together other developers
Sort of doesn't come to its right
And
That's what I've been working on
And the whole idea of the JCB packages was birthed out of this
Need
The need to collaborate with others around a specific component
So we've also started working on a area called servers
In which we now have actually
Added
This option
For SFTP which is
Oh really smart
So you know protocol
And it's purely PHP so it it will function
In
Moving
At the moment only moving zip files and things around
But the idea would be in the long run
That we could possibly create connections between different JCBs
Which could automatically synchronise things like almost like they're on the same
Yeah system
But ok
I did have a thread open on that
On GITHUB
Connecting JCBs with each other to sync development on agreed
Projects
That was The issue that I opened up issue 233
And
Then there was basically discussion between me
And one of my coworkers
And then
Some other in the community
Which ended up in
Saying good this is a premium feature
And although we have sort of put it on the back burner
Like you see me say here
I am still very much thinking about
Taking this and making this reality
and so part of doing that
Is taking a specific area of JCB
And that area is the import of JCB packages
And to improve this area so considerably that we basically
The synchronisation will be nothing else but a JCB package traveling from one to the other
And updating each other automatically and so
To achieve that I started working on a feature
Which now is available in the latest version 2.7 9
Auto
Wait where's it
Development method right that's the one
And what we called it is the default is the way that it always worked
And then there's this expansion there's a tutorial about this
Which really explains that you can select
Specific
Components
That you've developed
And then
On the
Frequency of this
Cron job
It will actually build and install
This project automatically
So that that is the first step of needing to
Sort of make that connection between two projects possible
Now projects literally talking out different Joomla websites right
One being offline one being online and then
This one that's online to serve like a hub
And I'm everybody that's offline
Would be pushing the changes to this online and pulling Again from it so that is the
Long-term aim
So if you are listening
That you would realise where I'm heading I'm I'm trying to get to the point where I can have a team of developers
All having their offline environments
Doing development on the same project
And as they feel they have achieved a certain level of stability in the project in a certain area
They can make
Literally a pull request
To the on line environment where JCB is running
And then others can review those changes and
May that component can come in as a clone
And they can play around with it until they feel yeah this this is good enough
And then it can be merged into the main branch somehow
So it's somehow putting GIT in a in a sort of an interface
And
Then obviously at some point I became
So overwhelmed with the task
That I started doing all these other little things that you now see coming about
One of them being
That I added a BBM package area which basically takes all the packages that we have
Available online and put it right here easy to
So get hold of it
And
So there are some free ones between them at the moment like this demo package here
All of the packages that
Are actually available won't GITHUB
The actual Joomla component of this package
Will have the source code link
Showing up so that you can actually go look if you
If you let say use select
Which one question and answers
Then there's actually a source code
Area we can go look on get up
To this program and you can actually take it and install it on Joomla website to see it's functionality
And to see it's features
And if you then
Yeah that's how you can evaluate the package easily
Basically it means that this JCB package produces this source code that's really what it gets down to
So now today
The
The current workflow
Model
Looks as follow
First you need to realise there is the JCB mapped
Two-piece there
Mapped pack component and then there is the Joomla component
This is the one that is sort of the feels the views the code everything inside
JCB
That can be moved
between
JCBs
Being
One
On one website one on the other
So you can actually extract a package
And give it to someone and you can import it into his JCB
And this is what this
Is
Where is the Joomla component is the produced package which
Then when you compile that map to component it produces a Joomla component and these are two
Different things
Although they are the same thing
Now
When I think about the workflow then
This is affecting this
But this cannot
Effect
This
So you can
Change here make changes to this package and it produces a different
Result
In this package
But if you make changes to this package it does not immediately would make any difference to this
Package unless you make
Use of what we have
Called the custom code implementation
We do editing
Within the IDE
Then yes then making changes to this package will affect this one
But that's a whole different story
And
Little bit
Beyond what I want to explain here
So when I think about a work flow then I would like to see that we make it change to this package
It gets validated by what we have here
And then everybody
Updates again this package to be the same as what we decided on
Here now that may not make sense
So let me add some arrows
And demonstration to this
I'm gonna use this question and answers
Package as an example
So if you were going to become
A
Collaborator on the question answers package
Then you first need to go to the source code of it
So on GitHub you would go and open the source code
And you will work
This source code
Which would then
Give you the option of making changes to this
But not directly
Manually
But instead through JCB
Now
That means that you will then clone this repository that you're forked
Down to your local development environment
And doing it as follow
The first thing you then do
Is you go back to your component where it's installed on your local developing environment
And you open the options area
So that you can set the
Folder path
For your GIT
Files
You gonna have a place
Where all you GIT files basically the component on ZIPPED
Is going to be placed automatically for you
So
here you would
add that
So I'm gonna place it in my
Basically my
User folder
I'm going create a folder there called Joomla I have to do this manually
And then inside of that I'm gonna add another folder called Git
So that's what I'm gonna do and I'm gonna save this
And then I'm quickly gonna create this folders and
So I'll show it to you in the command line
Ok I need to first add the
Company information here
Can now save and close
Call another one too
Choose
This is just the language make sure
To put it to British at this stage that is
The
Best practice
And oh yes another thing
I don't want to have any prefix at this stage
And yes
Save and close
Ok now we've got our GIT path setup
Now I need to actually create this files
In my local developing environment
So I'll do that via
Command line
So first I will
Make
Directory
Then I'm gonna change to that directory
Now
In that directory I'm gonna create another
Directory called GIT
And
Change that directory well
So this is the directory where in my components are going to be placed
Not the moment if we look inside of this directory there is really nothing showing
But
The first time I compile a component
And I say to the compiler to add my
Files to the git repository is going to create
A folder with all the
So code inside it
Automatically
So you remember that I
Cloned
This repository on GitHub
Joomla questions and answers
Now
If I do continue I need to get
The JCB package for this
Installed into my JCB
Program
The way this is done obviously we we go to the JCB package area
And we select
The
Questions and answers package
And we
Get the package
Then we add the key
And we
At the moment there is not really any components
On this in install so it's fine to leave this to yes
I'm gonna also Force local update of anything
And so we can just check again that it is the right package yes it's to correct package
And the checksum
You can read this
Basically there is a checksum for the package and at the moment it seems that everything is fine you can make it final
check of just clicking this link
And make sure that this number is the same as the one seeing
On the page here
And yes it is
So always good
And then we click continue
And there you have it we've got the component in our
System
This component now
If I compile it for the first time
Let's again just this for
For your sake let me show you
That there still is
No
File here whatsoever
Ok
Now
I'm going to compile this component
And I'm gonna say
Add to repository folder
Ok so this
Should the component been moved to your local repository folder now we already set the path for this
So now you work
If we have
Say yes and then compile this
We see that it's actually been done and it's all well
And we now go back to that folder
And we check again we see that now there is a folder with its exact name
So if we changed into that folder
Will see that it is at the moment
LSLA
There's no GIT
Information here so this
Folder is basically just the source code without
Any GIT
Connected
To it
So what we gonna do now
At this point
We are gonna connect your forked version
That you have on GitHub
To this folders here
And that from now on
If you make a change to the component
It will be and you have to push the changes in this folder to the GitHub repository
The way to make this the
GITHUB
Link the two to each other
Use the following commands
Making sure that you're in the correct directory com -
Questions and - and
- answers - - Joomla - 3
You can run the command r m
- f
R
Asterix
Now you know
You might say why
did we
Compile it in now delete everything
Well unfortunately
That is the only way to do this
Without difficulty you first need to get the information down from GITHUB
And
Then you might ask why didn't we just do that first and that was because
It seemed easier to just let
JCB build folder for you
And then
You use the folder
And so I'm gonna just wipe out all the files if we checked there now
Basically no file left
Then we going to
Start by
Actually pulling
The
The files down from GITHUB
First is to say GIT in it
Then to actually add the remote branch
And to get the remote branches URL your type out get remote add origin
Then go to GitHub
Where you forked the branch
So and then here you get the URL is copying it here
You can either use the HTPS or the SSH which in my case is what I prefer
So you pasted in there and click
So to save it
If you now would check the the config information
You see that this remote branch is been added
Now the next thing to do is to pull down the master branch
This is done with GIT
Pull origin Master
This will now get all the information from GITHUB
Which basically is the same as what you have
Here behind my
Command line screen
So if we were now to gonna do
LSLA
Will see that there
There is actually
The files all back as they should be but now we have GIT here as well
And my
My
Command line shows us that we have a git repository and we are on the master branch
Ok
So that was to get
us linked to this repository
Now we can go and compile it again at the moment if we do get status
It should say that everything is fine and clean
And there is no difference between these two
But
The moment we now
Do another compile
Is going to change the files obviously
So now if we do GIT
Status
We see that all these files were modified
And we can check to see what is it that was modified by doing git diff
And we'll see mostly ok it added
More lines
The compiled version
Was the
24th of April
And now it's the 5th of May
Ok scroll down
Ok
So ok here is another one that changed
Ok so there's some XML that changed
Oh yes and we made a improvement
To the Jason to string in JCB
so it also updated those functions
And we removed the abbreviative
sorry , prefix
To the name so that's been updated
So you can look through the diff to see all the changes that has been made
The reason why
The XML file format is changed
Is because we are using different XML compiler here
And I can show you that in a moment
That you might understand
OK hold on
Here in the global options
There is two ways to compile the XML in JCB
It's really about While the reason why there are two ways it's because some servers don't support this one
This simple XML
Option
It doesn't support it and mostly because it doesn't have all the
PHP
Models of things applications
Activated
So
What we then have as a string manipulation option
Which basically doesn't use the simple XML but does actually
Still replace most of the time
Building all these XML field string by string
This one is How JCB started
And is most certainly
Working very well so I like using it
But
It's not necessarily
The best option
It's faster
So we compile it again now
We will most probably see less changes to the exit now
Because I remember that package actually did
Have
Did use the string manipulation option
to exit this
you just press q
And then again
How to go back in
And let's see what changed now dates
And yeah there's much less
I don't see in XML changes
Now
Ok
So
Basically it's just a date
That is changed
And it's talking about the build date
Now this is something we might need to look at
Because the reason why is changed is because we imported it
Answer your your application thinks the build only started
Today
Wait I don't know
24th of April
Times flying that's all I realise that that is actually correct
Ok
So you we have
All the changes is really primarily
Just the built date
And there's a little bit here there which JCB itself has improved
So
It's improved with this variable here
Determines that that it's external
value that's with a Jason string remember I said to
you we done a little improvement there
So it really just actually reflecting the JCB improvements
Which is really the way it should be
Ok
So that means
If you now we were going to make a pull request
I will most probably will say thank you because you basically just updating
The JCB improvements to the component
Ok so let's show you how that will work
You would now make a commit
We should look something like this
and remember I always show you the the simple easy way to do it
There are more precise
Better maybe but
more difficult ways
So update a component with improvements made to JCB
And we click that obviously you sign
Your comment and
GIT
Push
So this point
You have made a change to component via your JCB
Install
And you're pushing it back
To your forked version
Of this components
Joomla component which is on GITHUB
Now that means
That if you refresh this page now
He'll say that it's won't commit a head
Now
I think at this point we need to discuss how many changes should you make before you make a pull
Request
And if 5 or 6 or 7 people make the same changes
Regarding
Implementing to JCB's improvements
Who's do we accept
Yeah all those kind of things
I suppose we'll still be ironed out as we go
But at this point you could click make PULL request
And it will automatically take
Take the
Components and show that it can be merged then you click
on that PULL request
And your comment should usually end up here in the
In the title area
We will for every package that we manage we'll eventually add a pull request template
With instructions
And how to manage it from here further
And at this point you're actually saying I've made changes to the JCB
Program
Package
Whatever you wanna call it
And these are the changes I have made, tested and please let me know
If you
Like what I've done
and
There will be discussions here and please do not be discouraged if it doesn't go
You know quickly
There there obviously reasons for us to always go through things quite slowly and thoroughly
I know in our own
In-house developing team
Things are going quite fast at this point because we have
Sort of come to a place of understanding each other's
Perspective so it goes quickly
But
Working with strangers and people we don't know
Is obviously going to be more difficult and slower
you won't have the option of editing all these values like I do because I actually own this
repository
But you must probably will be able to
Come up to here and actually put in
The necessary information that will ask for
And then click here create pull request
So this point If I did that
It will
create a pull request and
The developers will be notified and will start communicating from here
Now when this pull request with your changes have been
Fully accepted
And obviously you haven't made further changes
To this component
Then
The next part of the
Process needs to happen
So
If I can illustrate what has happened so far
Your first forked
The component then you imported that components JCB package
Then you made changes in this case we didn't make changes but you could have added a new field or a new View
Then you compiled
It
Then in your local development
You committed to changes to the GIT
repository so there's
The here is also
Linked
And commit the changes to GIT
Then you put the changes to the forked
version
And then you make a pull request
And now the next step
And this is the place where the JCB package manager is going to really come into play
Because now
You want to contribute this changes not only
To the actual
Joomla component which already is well-being
You know this this
Pull request
Is contributing it
To this area of the component
When this has been finalised
The Next Step
Is to also contribute it
To the JCB map to component
And this one is
Crucial because then everybody who's
Helping to develop
The map component
Get this update
Via JCB package manager
And
Ok so we're going to now demonstrate the next step
Let say at this point your commit is been accepted and merged into the
Root
The master branch
Of the repository
Then it should look like this it will say merged
And if we were going to look at this here
It says now update the component with improvements made to JCB
Ok so
Really
That was
The the point at which the next step must take place only once
The changes you've made has been accepted
In the
Joomla component
Source
Of the project
Now The Next Step is to do that with JCB the package as well
All VDM's JCB packages are kept
in the JCB packages repository
So the next thing you need to do is you need to fork this repository
I already forked this repository
Few weeks ago
Few days ago
But you'll see that
It's already four commits behind the master branch
I can't really do anything
Until I get in sync again
With this master branch
Making a commits now
will mess things up and so
First thing I'm going to do is make sure that this repository
Is In sync
With the master branch
So obviously this repository needs to be cloned down to my local system
those of you that have quite a number of repositories and keeping them all in sync is a pain
We have this little shell script update forks
Which is very useful
Even if you're gonna run the Shell script itself
you can at least sort of
Peak at some of the commands
And how to get this done
The way this does the moment what it does is it runs you know gets all the repositories that you
You have forked and then it also updates them
So there are a number of
SSH file that you should have a look at
I'm just going to open this
Update repositories
Well now I got the file open here
I realise ok this is not gonna work
Unless you able to understand
Bash
You must probably not gonna actually
Be able follow this
So Let me rather do the commands one of the time
Inside of that Repo
But at least you know that there is a package here
And if you do know
Git  Sorry I mean bash
Then this is most certainly something to try out
I'm it's working very well I'm using it quite a lot
And it's keeping all my forked repositories up to date and then sync
With the master branch so that if I work with them
That it already is ready and I'm able to just you know
Jump in and do it
But it's not that hard to do it manually anyway
So let's do that
If you haven't cloned down the repository to your local developing environment
Then you need to do that first nothing of what I'm gonna show you now will work unless you've done that
there are a few documentations that GITHUB has that helps with us quite a lot so if your on windows
or Mac or Linux
Yeah you can actually go to this URL,s or just type in Google update my fork repo
And do a search
And then look for the one
Which sort of
Well this is a place you wanna end up at
and then I gonna tell you that you must first configure
Your repo to actually see the remote upstream
So click on that and do this first
And then we'll come back to this one
First we do is we gonna just check out
In a repo what is the remote branches
And so we see that it only has this
To remote branches
And it's fetched and pulled from those
Now we want to add the remote branch
Which is the upstream branch
And we gonna use
This one and
Add the original owner so this one is your name
This one must be the original owners name
And the original repositories name So those two
Values you need to
You know update
The way to get them is go back to your Repo
And just
Click on this
Value here
This should take you to
To that
Original branch
And then you can just get it
By coping
This value here
So then your type remote
Add upstream
Like it says there on GITHUB
And you will
Control shift
v
To paste in command line
Or as if you you can also paste
With the mouse
And so there is the repository
I have a little
Change to my SSH which means I use VDM
To identify the server name
That is something you must have you wouldn't need to do
And you click enter
Ok so now
If we do that
Remote branch will now see that there are two
Remote branches
Sorry Two branches
That are remote
And one is the origin and one is the upstream
And that now is
Time for The Next Step
Which is the sync the fork
So first what we will do
we will fetch the upstream
This will basically fetch the files
That has changed
From the upstream
Which at this stage we know
Is the
Main Master branch
Then just to make sure that you are on the master branch
We are going to
Say
Git
Checkout
Master
To make sure you are on the master branch next
We are going to
Merge
The upstream branch into your master branch
This will look differently depending on what happened
But
It will give you a bunch of information and then
This branch is now basically
The local branch is now in sync
With master branch
Upstream Master branch now
To get this
To also update your
Branch on GitHub you just need to do get
Push
And this will push the changes
Back to GIT
Now there are many things that can actually
Go wrong or
Sort of work out different
In in Git
And so I'm not here to teach you how to use git
Made you run into
Some Grey areas or difficult issues
You need to Google and
Figure out how to get this done
This is just
Illustrating
The
Proposed workflow
Of developing components in JCB while collaborating
With the greater community
Around a JCB package
those of you that watched
The tutorial on how to contribute
To the community
Directory
JCB packages
The match of what I'm gonna be explaining further
Is already covered in that previous tutorial
And
So we are almost finished with the circle
We started by forking the JCB sorry did Joomla component
And importing the JCB package
Then making changes to that
And then compiled it
And pushed those changes to the Joomla Repo
And when those changes were accepted
Into that
Repo
We now
Went to the place where we found the JCB's package which in VDM's case
Is the VDM package area
Where if it was a community component then you would follow
The explanation given to you in that previous tutorial
And at this point what we going to do is we basically gonna export JCB package
Add it to these packages that we have here
And run our hash so if we look at this LSLA
We've got a
Hash sh file here
But if you run it now
There're should be no changes to the repo
And
Just as we expected nothing changed
So everything is up to date at the moment
And so the only file we are going to change
Is basically these three files here
Because we're gonna update this package by exporting it from JCB
With the changes we've made
Now
Since you've contributed those changes to this
Question and answers
Joomla
A component
repository
Those who are gonna validate this
Push which we're about to make
are gonna go back to that repository
And make sure that you're not changing things other than we should contributed there
In fact
But some point my Anticipation is to actually build a bot which would validate this
For us so at this stage it will still be a little manuel so it will be little bit slow
but eventually will speed it up and the validation will happen faster and more efficient
So you in JCB
We now basically click on questions and answers
And there is one little snag here which I realised
I haven't actually resolved it
And that is that you now need to actually have the same
Key for this package
Set in the admin or rather in the component
As the one that the developer uses
And that can only be given to you by the original owner of this package
Which in this case is myself
So and where does that what is that mean it means that this export key
Must be the same one
As the one that the package was compiled with originally
now if you have imported this and you see a key here
You can be hundred percent sure it is not the same key
Because this is encrypted field
You are basically just seeing the encrypted value
Not the actual key
The actual key was never exported
unencrypted it always remains in crypted and that's why we have the encrypted Fields all around JCB
Not because we think is gonna make the database more secure necessarily
That is because when we export and move data around
That which is secret stay secret
And only within that specific component developing environment of those
keys is unique
So the way you get this is you need to communicate
With that developer and actually ask him permission
Whether you can extend on this package and then he needs to manually give you this key
And so
Since I can ask that
From
From for myself I'm going to just add that key to me sure that it is the same key
With which it originally was compiled with
Ok so now we've got those keys to be the same
And it's sort of the way to tell everyone that you and that other developer
Are an agreement
That this in fact it possibly could happen
That once your pull request
To the JCB sorry to the Joomla component
Repo
Has been merged and accepted
Then that team needs to give you the key
That's how I think will work
I'm not hundred percent sure this gonna be cemented
Always got it changed
But you do realise that trust and collaboration goes hand in hand
So they need to give you the key if it's not a JCB package that actually requires a key
Then it is a different story
And yet the same sort of procedure will reply except the exchange of keys won't be necessary
But now that you've got the key in place we basically click here
And export the JCB package
So we now have this package
Here in this folder
And we now need to move it
Into the repository
Which is also
Obviously the one we have now synchronised with our forked version
so I have it here I'm gonna copy it
actually going cut
let's cut it
From my templer folder in my Joomla website
To this repository paste it in
And is gonna ask if we should
Replace and we're gonna say yes
Replace it
And then we go with got the package updated
Now
We go back to command line
And we do
Git
diff
We'll see that
That file is changed
Now we also need to run this h
This hash file
To update the
And
Now git
Status
we'll see that those files have updated
So
You would possibly I'm not sure what the vl Convention but
I think
Your pull request to the Joomla
Repository of this component
The idea of that could possibly be useful here
It's just to sort of give a heads up and validate that you did First
Contributed code
To the actual Joomla component and it was accepted
And now this is the change to the package
Which also now needs to be looked at
so now in our case
This is the pull request URL
I think we just gonna use that
And our commit message
And
Use the same commit message
Search it looks something like this
Update the component with the improvements made in JCB and maybe say riff
And then
The repositories username or organisation name
The repository name
With this
power
Hash one
Since it was
pull request was number one
Ok that would
Do and then
Will submit that
And
Now we push those changes to our
Version of the repository
Going back to git up then
after the push is been submitted
and we look at this commit
You see it actually has a link
And this link is to that issue on githup
so it'll be easy for us to trace where you have contributed it to the actual Joomla component
And why it's all happened being the same comment message
Now this stage you again would make a pull request
To the master branch
Where we will basically review
The changes
now Again at this stage
We don't have a pull request templates and everything in place
But as soon as they do get to be placed there and please follow those instructions
We'll try to be as thorough as we can
But obviously being a community is always up for discussion and we will
Try and
Do this
The right way
At the moment we can put the ref in the description and then just again the comment in the
Title if it's a long comment then just put
Maybe a summary here short one and put the wrong comment back in here
Ok and then you basically create the pull request
At this point discussion will begin
Validating to see that you followed all the procedures
And that this package is stable and ready to become part of the
Actual
Repo
And then once accepted it will be merged into the master branch
Become available to the rest of
Community
So that's
At the moment
Illustration of what I consider a collaborative workflow in JCB
So we
Where at
Next Step
And we had to move today JCB
Where
They have now accepted and merged
The
Changes you made
To the Joomla component
And now the owner has given you the original key
Because they trust
The changes you've made
And
you now forked the JCB package repository
Make sure we have it in sync if it's an old fork
Then update the key with the key from the owner
Then export to JCB package
Added to the local repo with a commit message and the reference
As illustrated
Then push changed to your forked repo and make a pull request
So here
Is The workflow
This could
Become nicely documented
I suppose
Someone can take that upon them to even
Make some nice chart
I maybe not the correct guy for the job
And this might
Expand and become maybe much more advanced
or it could be made more simple
But in a nutshell
just
Below an hour
We've 47 minutes
sort of
This is the explanation of the collaborative
Workflow with external
Partners
Around a JCB package
Once this pull request gets merged we are basically back
At the
This is in sync
And
And this will continue and I'll go on and on
And obviously others will contribute so
There there are some other complexities also
In this process
But that is sort of what I can see happening
I know that when you
Pull the changes from the previous package you know this
Where is it
You know the import the JCB package
There is the option to import it as a clone
Order import it with a merge
Now the idea would be that you will only import and merge your JCB package
With the global Repo
As they accept
These pull request
And so that
You would always stay in sync with what actually is currently the community version
Of the package
And you could import it it as a clone and make changes to the Clone and effect that will not effect
the Main Master
Version
But this all is a trial and error process which
You would
Sort of show you teach yourself how that works
And so my idea is to do that within a blank install try it out
Pulling some of the free versions
But play around with it
Until you become confident
And then you are able to also start contributing
Do not only the community packages
But also VDM packages to which you've got access
And so help improve those components
For everyone
Well thanks for watching
Hope this is insightful
And I'm sure there might be things that some of you would not able to follow
And I would encourage you to just Google that
and do some tutorials and
Then you I'm sure you will
Manage
ok Thanks for watching