Hi welcome to Joomla component Builder
Hello world tutorial
It's been asked that we give you
Some guidelines or quick instruction
On how to go from Zero to Hero
Obviously there is a hello world and then there is a hello world
Let me explain
When we go to Joomla's
Repository on GitHub they have a Hello world component here
And
It has a few files obviously it's been done quite some time ago
Even if you open these files
They really not populated with data
And So all it really does is it shows you
The very bare essentials of what's required to make an component work in Joomla
Now we obviously gonna do
Way much more than this I mean the
The reality is
This code here is hardly non-existent
When we are done we'll have an application with quite a lot of
Lines written
And quite a lot of structures added which it goes way beyond just a
Bare bone framework
So keep that in mind we're doing a Hello world component
But when we've done
It will actually be
Much more than just a wire frame component
So you can go over to GitHub
Forward slash VDM - IO
Fordward slash Joomla - component - Builder
And download the latest release
Just go to releases
And
Then download
Or copy the link
Do this JCB file
Then in a blank Joomla website
I'm gonna install this
File
And
Build This hello world component
There we go
We have the component installed
We can now open it
Component Builder
Is ready to start
First thing we'll do is we'll create a field
There are Fields But just that you can see just We're creating a simple basic custom text field
Field
And we're just gonna call it
greeting
We're gonna give it a name
Greeting
Now as you
will see is
It already had a lot of demo material here
I'm not gonna change any of that I'm just gonna remove a few things which
I know it's necessary
And actually
The field will work even though
These lines are removed
So
I think we'll do that and
Well here say
greeting
Ok
I think that should be enough we gonna change this to
Varchar
I think that's also good enough
And basically save and close
So there is our new field
Next thing to do
Is great in admin view
The admin view is really what links
Your Fields to the Database
So we gonna call it greeting
For single record and greetings for
a list of records and
Greetings
Just for a sister name
So that we can identify this
Across the system and I'm gonna add their greetings
We gonna add a few generic icons here
Then we're gonna link that field we made
You want it obviously to show
to be the first one act as a title be sort of all searchable
And be a link in the first tab
And first in that tab
And give it permissions
And save
The rest of the
The structure could be left as is
And actually
We will have a working component
With this as an admin View
So save and close
Now we need to create the component
So I clicked on new
and loads a
Add new Joomla component
I'm gonna call it Hello world
For the most part I'm just
Adding
It's some dummy data here
Can I select an icon
make the image which
Will be shown after installation of the component as well as in the back of the component
Ok so we have that set
The rest of the features
Besides in the settings we need to link the admin view for now
so just select greetings
One of the main menu want to add yes submenu autocheck in history
Has metadata
has access
allow Import export
And
This is important
Add a create site view so on the front end it will already create for us
The editing view it will not create a listview
Only to edit and create
Greetings on the front and we obviously want this to be the first
So
There we've linked our admin view and we click save
Save and close
Now we actually have our component set
Let's compile it there is obviously
Not a very workable front-end yet
So
I'm just gonna compile this and install it onto this Joomla install
We don't need that
Just select
Hello world
Also don't need that
And then compile
So just like that we have 8000 lines written
Spelled 160 pages A4 book
So
That's way more than the hello world component we just looked at
Now if we open the back end
Oh we haven't installed it. You could install it via the
Normal installer in fact let's
Let's see if we can get that going
So
I've pasted the URL here
That we find on this page here
And we'll click
Check and install
Ok so we have the Hello world component installed
We can open here and go to Hello world
And there's the component
We can go to the list and
This is where a list of greetings will show
Click new
And we can
add some text say hi there
James
Save and Close
And there is our first greeting
We can open it again
And there it is it has a publishing structure that has permissions
It has version control
So if we change this
To hi there Michael
and save and close
It will actually update we can open it
And if you go versions you see that all of that is working you can open the previous version
You can see it was James you can see who changed it
All of that was done in those few Clicks
I think that's worth noticing and in just a few Clicks we have a whole workable
Component
Which is installed now let's go look at the code just quickly
So here's the installer script of the Hello component
And
It actually
Adds the whole component into the content types and
Into all the relevant areas
It does a check to see that we're at least at Joomla 3.6
And
It also
Has created
The greeting table
Modules
It has created helper structures
There is a
Helper class been setup
Which has many features of functions methods
Wish you can come and browse through the helper class and
you know
If you know PHP you'll
See that this is a very helpful method just grabbing one value from the database and
So there are many functions in here which you can now use around your component
by simply calling the helper class
Ok so that's just quickly looking at the fact that
This all of this was built I remember when we looked at
the other
Hello world component
This is really all that there is in the app and area
Is a sequel folder with a few sequel files
1 php file and that's about it
Now I give you yes this is a wireframe but
JCB has built
a
Very
More
Populated
Hello world in a very short time and you can look through this back end
Folder and see the structure and exactly how you know you need to have the components structure
done
Ok so now
For the next part of the tutorial we will focus on adding a front end to this component
And you must remember that
We left the front end
Open ended really
Because we want to allow developers to
Actually be able to express themselves in unique ways
And not have a cookie cutter recipe you know that just
Gets used over and over
But that there could be such diversity and difference between components that are
Built with JCB that only the back end really look similar but the front end can always look
Completely different from anything else so to avoid you know
It always looking the same and that means a lot of custom coding is needed for the front end
And you need to know quite a bit of PHP and even how Joomla works to make this
work so I'm just gonna give you
The quickest shortest path to getting a front end which firstly can display
the items and secondly can
Edit them
So
Let's get started
First thing to build when we are setting up the front end
Would be a dynamic Git
Dynamic Git is
JCB's way
Of giving you
An easy way to
Grab various tables in combined datasets
And deliver them to the front end of any
Site View
You can reuse them
You can even add multiple ones of them
I'm not gonna go into those details I'm just gonna build a very simple one so let's get
Started with that first
I'm going to call it greeting list and I'm gonna make sure this is a list query
And I'm gonna
Link it to a
Back end view
Greetings I'm just gonna have it grab all the data
I'm going to say no I don't want  pignation
And I'm gonna just have one
Where filter
Basically
Gonna take published here
Copy that
And put it in here and say
When published
Equals 1
Just grab published items and nothing else
And there we go
We grabbing
All the data from this one table
And we are putting it on the front just filtering it with this where
Option now like I said you can join other tables
On relation with this data
But I'm not gonna go into depth
Just quickly and brief
Here we go
Greeting list is done
So there's our greeting list
Now we want to have
Another
Dynamic Git just to view One greeting
So let's create that
I'm gonna call it greeting leave it as a Git item
Again
use a back end View
And then select greeting
And this time I'm gonna use filter
And just add here ID and
A dot i d
So that should do it save
And save and close
So now we have our two Dynamic Gits in place
Second step Side views
So we'll create firstly a site view for the lists of items
We'll select
The get query for the list
If we wanna see how it possibly would look I mean the PHP we have a
snippet
You can select the same
Option and it'll give you a suggestive idea of how the PHP may look
This May differ
Depending on how you set up your
Dynamic get
But in reality most of the time it is correct and you can simply copy paste some of the
Snippets write into your code here
And
Immediately start using it so I'm just gonna
Add a little
unordered list here
So we will have a list item basically
And we'll just
Echo
Greeting as a text
And
Then
Grap that
Snippet
Paste that in there
Close the unordered list
Now we wanna
Use little nice unordered list here
So we gonna grab this
As this opening tag
And then
Close it
And we gonna call this
greeting
Greetings I think will be best
And greetings
Again
Greetings
Initial description
Ok so we're all set here
And
For now as you see there is no links here
We haven't we will actually have to come back and add some links
For now I'm just adding
An iteration over there
The items and displaying the greetings
So we're gonna save and close out of this
And now we gonna create one
Where we only look at 1
Greeting
So again we'll just select
That one greeting
Git method
And here as well and we see that the greeting
Possibly look like that
So we'll echo it out
And
we're gonna make it
an H2
Header tag
And then
We can't call it greeting
Because
We have an editing
View
That will be dynamically added to the front
Now because the editing view on the back is called greeting
We cannot call another front end
View
A greeting we have to call it something else otherwise it will conflict
So I'm just gonna call it
Greet
For now
We can call it here we could call it greeting but here we'll call it greet
And then
greeting and
Greeting on top here as well
So here we go we've got all the necessary components lined up for this
specific site view
To function as expected
So save and close
So now we have our two site views set
I'm gonna now go to the component to add them to the component
So again we go to settings
And we go to site views
And we will add
greeting
It doesn't have a menu
It has metadata it's not the default view
We can
Add access and then make the default public
The second one is greetings
This must have a menu
Also metadata
This is the default View
We can also
Give it access
And make it by Default public
There we go we got out two site views save and close
Save and close
So we go to the compiler
And we compile the Hello world component
For the second time
And then once compiled
You now see that we got nearly 13000 lines of code
And we can now
Just click here to install which is the easy way instead of going to the installer
Now if we go back to the code
And we scroll down
We'll see that there is now a component
in the front end called hello world
And it has the model's greet greeting and greetings
It has the views greet greeting and greetings this one is an edit View
This greeting
And this one is a display view this one
Is it where you can look at how it is getting the values from the database so that
Dynamic Get
It built
Basically this function for us
As well as parts inside of this function here
Now
You see that it added that little
Where filter for us
And
All the values are here as expected
Here it's having that permission check
So it is gonna check whether you have the correct permissions
Now because we have not
You know installed the component
As a blank component we installed it and then made changes install it again it will not be by
Default be set public
The way that it sets the view public
Is during
Post flight
Install
It actually
Set a rule
And adds the side greeting access to public which usually is the ID Group 1
And then it updates the asset table
And since
This isn't a new install
It actually doesn't do that
And so you won't have the expected result of the view being public simply because the component
Wasn't installed
As fresh so how to demonstrate to you how it will behave if a user install
This the first time fully
you know
Compiled as it is now I'll just simply uninstall a component quickly
And install it again
Which will then activate this feature
Now some you may not understand all I've just said that's ok
I would just suggest that
As you've developed the moment you add the front
Side views to the component
And you have actually tweaked its access and all those
Related parameters
It might be best to just uninstall the component and install it completely Fresh
To see the fool behaviour working as expected
you might say but I already created some demo data and now I need to put them punch them
Back in again well there is a way to sort of resolve that
And that is going to the admin View opening the greeting
Going to the MySQL tab
Select yes
Select Table
And then
Click add to select the table
Then scroll down to that specific table in your database
It should be
hello world
Greeting
Then you'll see it loads the specific values from the database
And how they will be named in your
Backup I usually remove this created by modified by because it
May cause conflicts if user ID is changed from one Joomla install to another
And I also sometimes remove
The access
Value
As this may also differ from system to system
And the acid ID
So I'm only exporting values which I think are consistent across
Systems
Ok
Obviously
This one is well
And this one
okay safe
Now save and close
Now this isn't enough just having have mapped the
Sequel table if you wanna retain the data now what what date am I talking about
well we installed it right and so if we open the component
We added
This greeting so the retained this greeting if you've created quite a few
Dummy greetings then to retain them so that they get installed again
Even if it's a fresh install that's the way you do that but you have to compile it
The component you have to compile the component before you uninstall it
Otherwise it will shout at you and say that it couldn't find the database
Because you obviously gonna remove it when you uninstall it
So I'm just gonna compile this again
And then after it been compiled
I'm gonna uninstall it as I said I would
So you're in the extension manager I'm gonna click
On the hello world
And uninstall
And it would have successfully uninstalled it
Then I'm gonna go back to the compiler page
and just click on the install
And then if I go back to the component
I see that it's added that greeting back in
And I haven't lost a beat ok
Now let's look at the front end
By linking it to a menu item
So have greeting selected as the menu item type
And I'm gonna just make this the the default page
The home page and save and close
Now I'm gonna open the homepage
There we see our greeting it says greeting
Hi there Michael
So it's actually worked as expected
Let's just add another one to see it how it will look when we have more than one greeting
Ok I think now we have enough
If we go back to the front end
And refresh
There we go there's our greetings now to make them clickable and editable
Let's do the opening it and just viewing it first
So in the site view area I'm gonna open greetings
Now around
This
Greeting Echo I'm gonna add an H ref
And a link we gonna build a link using some of the helper methods and
And also what is called The Slug
The Slug wouldn't necessarily this time function because we didn't add an alias to our table
But when there is an alias the slug will dynamically be used within search engine friendly URLs
I'm not gonna demonstrate or explain too much about this
But
I'm gonna just quickly at the link in here
Now I know
You may be wondering where is this
Items slug come from It's not showing here on the side
Well
Like with most of these developing components
You need to know a little bit about how
To read code and understand code and that's why you would compile the code
And then actually go look at the compiled code in your IDE so if you were to open the
Model
Which
Is using this Dynamic Git
You'll see that it actually builds a slug in the model
So here in the model here's the get items
So it's looping through them here and then it's checking with it as an alias
And then ID and if they are there sure then
It actually
Combines them with this
And
Creates a slug otherwise it just plays as the ID in The Slug
That's how you would know that the Slug is already created and you can just use it
And so it's always good to
While you're developing a component with JCB
Go into the code read the code look at what it's done and it'll help you see and understand
And how to extend it
We trying to follow the normal way of how
Joomla's able to you know develop and be used so
That you can
Easily follow along and that it wouldn't get
we're not trying to reinvent with the wheel but doing things the way that you would expect if you know
How to build Joomla components
you know by hand
Ok so
Now we created that link
You basically used j route which is a
A common class in building routes in
Joomla here is the helper out class you can look that up
It is in the
Site area of the component under the helper folder and it has a function called
Greed route
And we just passing it The Slug and that will crank out the whole URL for us
And so we gonna save and close here
I just save for now
Now we gonna just compile it again
and Install it back in
since we haven't made any changes to permissions or any of those things now the permissions just
A short
tip on that again it is only when the related to the site views that we need to maybe just reinstall
The whole component do keep in mind that you could go into the backend and set the permissions
If that is what you would prefer so in the back end you can just go to options the back end
Of the component I mean
And there's the permission tab
And you can see this is a whole list of permissions just for the greetings and because we install
The component afresh it's set the greeting site view access to public
As well as the greetings site view access to public so that's really what we did
We just
had that done automatically but you could have come in here and just change that to allowed
And save and it will have achieved the same thing
You'll see that there is a whole lot of features here in allowing
You to edit certain parts of the values for specific groups
And so all of this
JCB is just placed
you know for you and ready to use
Now did we have installed the component let's refresh this homepage
and we will see that all of these links are now clickable
If we click on one of them
We see it only displays that specific
Greeting you can click back
And then click another one and it
And so it's working as expected it's generating for us the links and it is
Actually opening that View
And displaying the value as expected
Now to add an edit button
Which can then edit these
Items on the front end of the site
I would mind you noticed we just crossed the half an hour barrier so everything we've done now
Taking you half an hour to build a hello world component which is far more advanced and superior than
Any other Hello world component I've seen
And so
I think even just if we were to end here JCB is already proven to you that
It is actually able to build
Very
Dynamic and powerful components in a very quick and short amount of time
But now just to
Push the boundaries even little further let's link the editing options in for this
Items
Now you might want to have permission or checks here
When
The user isn't in the correct group that it wouldn't display the edit
item sorry the edit link
Now
If you do not know how to do that just a little heads up I can show you where to look
so in the back end again going into the code we open the Hello world component
We go into views
then into greetings
And then we open this view HTML dot php file
you will see that we are pulling a
Helper class here
And using the Git actions method
we're passing greeting to it as saying we want the permissions for the
Greeting
Now that delivers to us a
An object which we then can ask
Whether the user has edit rights
Whether the user can create delete whether he can say the state and so
That is how we can get
You know
Into the permissions you can look at this
Git actions
Method in the front you'd basically go to hello World helpers and
Open the
Helper class
And scroll down a little
And you'll get
The Git actions method is right here
So you're passing it the views name you could even pass it the record ID because we know
That you could set permissions not only per view but even per item
And so
Then this helps you
Actually determine the permissions and sends back the results now
We're always open to improving this this is what I've done so far in in
Helping us getting a quick answer on permissions from anywhere in the component
And so you could make use of this to determine some of the permissions for actually
Being able to edit the items
Yet
Even if you left out Those if you just dumped the button right on the page
The controller actually has a lot of these permissions already in place and
So it'll shout at you and tell you, you don't have permissions to edit this item and so that's what I'll demonstrate
So I'm just gonna add a little
Link here
To actually edit
The the item
Now again you might not know what that link should be
And you could go back to the back end of the component
To find the link
So here in the back end
I'm just simply opening the templates view and then I'm opening
The body
File and then here it has the link obviously it's in the back end it
Actually is related to the admin folder but in the front end it is related to the site's root
So you could just grab this
Snippet here
To build your link
Scroll down a little in the page
And basically search for this variable
And you'll see that we're using that edit variable
Adding and ID = and then just adding the ID
That's how we're building the link in the backend
And you could do similar in the front
The add some custom PHP to the front of the site there is a
PHP tab
And
Custom view script and it says here add custom PHP script to the head of the file so I'm just gonna
Paste that in there
Basically
We now have an edit variable on the page
And so in the default View area
I'm just gonna Echo that edit and then again to the add ID
Echo ID
Around the edit
Link
And how just click save
And then compile
This component again and install
And now go to the home page and refresh
Now we see there is a new edit link here
If we click it now
It's gonna shout at us and say no you don't have permit you're not permitted to edit this item so
I'm just gonna log in here as a user
That will have permissions
Ok I'm not logged in I'm gonna click on this edit link again
And as you can see it's opened and edit view where I can see the publish conserves the permissions
And
I can change
William
to Joomla and save and close
And it's edited that value
And that's it we have
Demonstrated the build of a hello world component
From scratch
And in just a few Clicks
We have successfully set up a component with tremendous advanced features already
At its fingertips
Ready to go
Well I hope this will be helpful to many if you're out there and
Enjoy