Hi
Welcome
My name is Llewellyn van der Merwe
I'm the developer of component builder for Joomla
I would also be
Giving you the instructions of how to use it
Just wanna look at a few issues
Component-Builder was built
to those who know PHP
If you don't know PHP there are some
Great places to
Start
Learning from and one
To those I would mention is
Lynda.com
And udemy
You could go on to their websites and you can simply search for PHP
And you would find
tons of courses
that I suppose would
do more than enough to to get you on your way
If you don't know CSS JavaScript HTML then certainly you need to go visit these website
And get that knowledge
It was not developed for those who
Have no but developing skills
Because
Simply I developed it actually for myself
As developer of components
So that I can easily and quickly get
Most of the bulk of the code done
And I could just be focused on the actual custom
Code which
Goes beyond the norm
So that's what it's really made
To do
If you don't have an understanding of the Joomla API
It's only gonna be to your own
Disadvantage
It's not that difficult to get it understanding
You just need to be able to read PHP
And open
a Joomla website go to libraries start reading with
Classes
Even go to Joomla's own components
That means
you would Simply
Go to a Joomla install that's this one here
And you go to components and you would go to
Content manager
Look at its folder structures
then open
obviously if you know cmv
And there's the controllers there's the models there's
the Views
Open a view
Start opening the script itself
Read through it
If using NetBeans
You can hold onto a function like that one
Press Ctrl shift
It'll show you where
In your Joomla website
That function is declared
And
You can
You can open that file
And you can let's see I think you click there
Open source in editor
there we go
And you can start
By doing these kind of things
You can start learning in the way that the code
Connects to each other
Through just looking at Joomla's own
Components
Basically that's how I got to know how things work I simply went here
Helper content control shift
and Then opened
that in the next window
Look through the
Class
Methods
class variables
Which ones that is extending
This one isn't extending any
So
That's how I got to know how most things work
And
That's also how most other developers I suppose are able to get their hands on this
And so the better you know the Joomla API
To the more advantage to yourself
Because you will understand that this application is really implementing the API itself over
and over
I didn't reinvent things I'm trying to stay as close to the conventions
as possible
And as I become aware of
Better ways of implementation
I would like to
At that again
So even if you know a better way to doing it
Please communicate with me
I would likely
Updatening
include and change
Whatever is needed
You must be willing to get your hands dirty it is not one of the issues
that are quite important
This simply means that if you have built something and it doesn't work
You need to debug it
Which means
Possibly you would like to run a local Sandbox environment
I'm running here on Ubuntu
Is my local sandbox
And so
I have
PHP on it and
Got
My sequel installed
and Joomla
So if I was to open a browser
And
I would type in
this Local
This is my local install so you can see I just typed in VDM
And I have
Basically a few sites here
Test one is one we'll be working in
And
The one in which Component-Builder is being developed
Is this Component Builder 1
And
those sites have admin so this is just my own little
Script that I've dumped onto my own little server
And I can now
Change that
Say
Ok
Let's go to
Builder dot
VDM
That's another
Site
And it's loading some of the
Test
Displays that I'm working on
And I add
Administrator do that
Open the back end
And I can login
So I'm running in a Sandbox environment
And what this
The advantages as you don't have any internet
Involvement
those of you that already do it know all these advantages but those of you don't
You you can basically work offline mostly
And
And as well you can
add
Things like XDbug
And other script
Which help you debug
Your application very easily
We doing that in online developing sorry
Off-site environment is
Time consuming and
Difficult and
Expensive
So it's much easier doing it offline and again if you don't know how to do that
Please visit Lynda.com and
Look at a course called I think it was
Up and running with PHP Linux developer Linux server
Running my next
Wait let me quickly go find out hold on
Ok here we have it up and running with Linux for PHP developers by Jon Peck
Is an excellent course to get your own
Local
Developing environment setup
I don't know this
URL is gonna be helpful
But there it is
Apache-tutorials up and running
Linux PHP developers
and
I'm sure if you've watched this I've watched it
Any
Moons ago
And it's been very helpful
To get my
Initials
Sandbox setup
Obviously since then
And I suppose with yourself as well you'll find it you you get better
And you find better ways
But it's a good place to start
Ok so that is about getting your hands dirty
Component builder best place of
Function of being functional is offline
If you gonna do it online please realise that there might be security risks
Especially when you've compiled
An application
It places it into your temporary folder which can be accessed
From
From anywhere
Anyone can access your temporary folder on your
Server
Of your website
So
Yes you can delete the application from there in mediately with a button which are show you later
But it is still I feel unsafe and the purpose of the application was
Live in a developing environment where you have Joomla installed and where you can really test it
intensly
So I would still suggest it None the less you do it that way
Ok now
Finally we almost there
Finish with the introduction since it's free please help me to ensure the future
of this component
By not sharing it's training videos online
or with anyone else this is really the only way that I can sustain this
Development
is if you
Don't share these videos so please if you be so kind
If you have an organisation or you your a company and you have a
Others that's gonna view it
I suppose I can't stop you from doing that but I would encourage you there for then
to consider making a contribution when you are starting to reap the benefits of
The time that this application saves you so that this application can be further developed for the rest of the
The community and also for yourself
We would like to also involve you on Github so you can go to GitHub
/VDM
- IO
/ Joomla component builder
Basically this place here
And if you if you have issues or any requests or anything really
Please come here and go to issues and open a new issue
I want to be sure you can do that if you've got an account of course with GitHub
And then we at least our discussions you are logged and it's public and others can see it and
We can also come back as do it in reference
If you want to make a feature request then you can start
That feature request obviously herein the issues
And possibly if it exist I'll point you out to it and if a training is needed we will add it to this training
Video set but if there is a feature request that has started here
and you feel that you you can't wait because we possibly will create milestones and we will add
feature requests to milestones in you wanna ensure that a feature request ends up being done
Before anyone else is then you need to communicate with me at this email and I can send you
a link to to make a donation or a
Yeah I'll give you an invoice even if needed so that we can ensure that feature request be done
Before
Others ok so that's maybe all of it just looking at sort of an introduction
If you have any questions please let me know
Obviously not regarding the component itself but just these points I've mentioned
I'll be grateful ok
It's so let's get on with it
Since I'm really looking forward to showing you how everything works