Ok here we are in component builder at the dashboard in the back
End of a Joomla website I would like to
first show you may be the tremendous power of what it's already
Able to do and then step back little by little showing you how to build a component
So I'll first show you components that I have build and how I have been able to
To manage them so I've got a few here obviously got a lot a lot in
Archive But these are few that I've done and as you can see there is component Builder
for developers there's component builders for developers and how to's
And there's the three component builders and they are all three of them are living inside the same
Component builder the only change between them is really the
The database in certain things that they compile but they all are using
The same admin views they all using the same
Infrastructure information settings and so forth
So really it is it is that simple to have one component
And have it in different versions made available to your clients and
with all possible in component builder by Simply copying one and then making changes to
that copied one now it links to views and all that I'll explain as we continue
What I need to do now is I'm simply gonna take the compiler
And I'm gonna compile the public the free one because I'm gonna use that to show you
How to build your own component ok so I'll compile it
which start up the compiler and all the script taking all the data in the database
and puts it into the code that we would then need to run the application
Ok it's done compiling as you can see
it tells me how many lines is written it tells me how many hours I saved if I had to write
those lines manually you can read through some of that it's quite interesting obviously
I spend much more hours on this than what they says there but that's why these are just estimates
And based on calculating the 9 numbers and not really
Calculacting the actual interaction that we've had you can install the
Component if you've done it right just click in there or you could download it and install it
elsewhere or we could use this URL which is now at the moment relating to my offline
Environment and once you've done whatever you wanted to do if you click this
Whom you needed it but if you're running on the online
Environment and you use some of these links to install it elsewhere then play
Please remember to clear your temporary folder because if your don't this component
Can be downloaded in your temporary folder and to show you that it me open that website
And then let's go to it's temporal temporal folder
And you can see there is the component in a zip file and
And you you realise that anyone that can access this file can download it
So just let you know it I'll be mentioning this a few times because I realised part of why
Are you might be interested in using my application is because you want to ensure that what you do remains
Yours and this is part of what you need to know to ensure that
Ok I'm gonna run a I have a bash script that reminds me
That I haven't made a commit on this so that's just my own little
Script let me quickly do that before we go on ok
it's done I'm gonna open a test website and I'm
Gonna run everything there let me just login ok so I'm in the installing
Area is basically a blank test website just installed
And I'm gonna use this link here I use a URL
paste it in there and click install it should say the following to you
When you have done that just a side note if you've started working with component Builder
As a free version and you've purchased obviously one of the paid versions
The difference between them is only the data that is in the database the features and the functionalty
Are all the same
And so if you have installed the free version
You would need to now add the database
Information from the paid versions
Now to access the database information in your component
Let me see
I'm gonna go to the zip file here in my file system hold on
Ok we've got the zip file open here
Would go to admin
Then go to
SQL
Then you'd see there is an install file
Now this Install file
You'd wanna open it
And
Guarantee you would see it  it's the file that we are using to build a database
Once you've come finished looking at all the
Tables at the very bottom of the file
After the tables
Will be dumped information
Now with the free version It's basically the field types
That we've added
And also some
I think help menu information
If I'm correct. I think I've added that
Anyway
With the paid version there will be many more
or much more details there
And
and there are two ways for you to do this one would be simply to uninstall the free version
and install this one that you purchased
When you do updates it will never
Update this information
Joomla only uses this when it doesn't fresh install
Because that's the only time you create the tables
I didn't add this data to and install instance since that would be
Way too much
And
So I've realised that
They are I might look at building a script that could deal with this but I haven't done so yet
The second way to do this is if you might know My SQL
You can actually
Cut and paste this into My SQL replace this with your prefix of your tables
But first remove
The data that are in this tables
Let me show you that please hold on
So here we're in My SQL and there is the
Database
Tables of component Builder
And if you look at our archive were is it now this one
You see that this is gonna target the field types
So
You go to field types
If you're now importing the new data
And you go to operations
And you
Truncate that table
Like that
Then you go to My SQL
The sequel button
You go back to that file
Obviously
First replace
All those with the
Prefix like that
Let's make sure we don't by accident grab the wrong
stuff
So we have it like that
Match case
Says backwards
And then
Find
So we would replace that
I'm gonna have to replace all
Here we go back to our data you would see it now I has updated this field there
So I would select that
Like that
Copy
Go here
To My SQL
paste it
And click
Go
Test
The mistake I made is to leave to underscores in that name there
should just use one
Let's try again
Ok it's added it
So that is how you would
Add the data
Without
Uninstalling
The whole component
But I would suggest that this is maybe
More advanced than and difficult
And not ideal
So the other way would be to go to the extensions manage
And click on
This manage area here
Select
Component
And just uninstall it
And then reinstall the one that you now could download from VDM.IO
So once you've have
Got it installed it should look like this in the backend
You should be no components
No
Nothing while the free version
Should have none of this
The only things that will have his the field types and only a few of them
Now the paid version looks different and so I'm gonna uninstall this free one
And then I'm gonna install the paid one so we can use that as our example let's go
Uninstall and as you can see it not only remove the component but it also
Removes any trace of it that was integrated into Joomla
These three and tags and all that
Which is quite smart because then if you install it again it's doesn't start creating duplicate values in the database
Ok so let's quickly get the paid version
Ok we have it installed
So now if we go back to the component
And to field types
You see that it has
A whole lot more field types
And it has a few Fields setup as well
In fact
This is the version called
Developer which only has the demo component in it
I'm basically gonna use this version to show you how to build
Sermon distributor
From scratch
So I possibly would skip certain things because it might get too long
But I'll certainly show you
From the ground up how 7 distributor is to be built
And I'm gonna do it inside this version
And at least we have something to start with
Ok well
That's enough for this tutorial
We'll continue with
Field types in the next