What do you want to build a component
In component Builder
You need to come prepared
There's a number of things that you need to know
You need to know what you wanna build
You need to know the database structure that you want to
Set up
These are mostly things that you will only know
If you have a great
Good
Understanding
Of
A table
And
A database and
How you
Would like to have it mapped
Now if you do not know that
I could give you some pointers on some of the things you we
Needed
And at the same time try to
explain
Why you need to know these things
Ok so
We are using
Sermon distributor
which is a component that I've
Developed
For Distributing
Sermons
We using that as our demo
Component that we are demostrating
and how to build
So you need to know what you gonna called it
So we called it Sermon Distributor
Then
You would need to know
The backend views
Now the backend views in Joomla
Must be
Tightly connected
To a Database
And possibly
In such a way that it
Makes sense
that the database
Naming conventions and everthing follows soot
I am not going to be able to
To do an extensive
Explanation on all this
By just
By illustrating what
Is the best
Convention of implementation
Obviously component builder will allow you to
You break these convenstions
But later you would
Regret doing so
And Possibly
have to
redo a lot of things
The purpose being that
A lot of these conventions
They add up
To implementation
in other areas like your costum field types and so forth which we will get to in a moment, well not a moment, well not a moment a few videos from now
Ok so
We first knew that when we were gonna build
Sermon Distributor
That is four field
Sorry backend views
Needed to
To be set up
Because we wanted these
Features
Inside of our component
And that is the sermons
I had a
List View
Of
Sermons and
as well and
Editing
View of a sermon
And they shared a common data
Database table
And so we had preachers
As well as
Series list
And series And statistic and statistic
And they all share and as you can see they actually
Represent two
Views
But one database table
That means two views a listview
And an edit view and you will hear me repeat these concepts over and over and if I get
Confused are please forgive me as just so much repetition that you need to understand that
When I talk about views plural I always talking about the list View
If I talk about View
Singular
I'm always talking about the editable view which is basically in relation to the backend relay
Sorry connection of the database itself
So you backend usually forms the connection to the database
Your frontend is much more dynamic and that's why we also have a dynamic
Get concept which links to site views which is the front of your component these
Things will take quite a lot of explanation if you not new if you sorry if you're new to coding and
PHP and all that JavaScript CSS
You possibly get lost but if you're not you'll be very happy in the way with implemented because it leaves
With a lot of Dynamics and maneuverability
Which is obviously partly why I developed this component because all the others felt
Other component Builders out there felt like a cookie cutter you know you you can really only
Crank out components that are sort of common to each other and
I wanted to build something that's really Dynamic so
Partly for that the site views and the custom backend views are
Mostly the same kind of implementation both drawing their data from The Dynamic get
Feature in component builder
So you can think of these two, three sorry as working as a team
But the backend views stand as the database for these
So you need to set up these first and add to them
All the necessary Fields which will then map the database
Columns which you can then through the dynamic get connect to so that you can
Formulate a data model
Which can be reused in your custom backend and in your sight views so I don't know
Does that explain it to you let me try again
Just to make sure I have everybody on the same page your backend views are very
Tightly connected to database structures so even if you were to look at
Component Builder itself
You have what is called components
And if you were to open one it has fields in it
And if you want to go to the database
And also open component Builder
Component the same table
And you to click on structure you would see that the fields
That we are seeing
Here
Here name name in code version version updates
Bugs
Short description description
Copyright
All these names
Are actually mapping directly into the database add licence
There is name is obviously alphabetical name Codename number images license
Email
CSS copyright
You see it really directly Maps to the database and it is in a way
Editing the database through this view
So
When it comes to the components you're your backend views are all being limited to this kind of
Structure
And this is not a limitation on component Builders behalf really it's really the way Joomla
wants you to implement it by doing it this way your class is your model your controllers and
Everything else just behave right because of that implementation now I know some might feel
that is a major limitation but that is the Joomla API's implementation and if you want to
Go Beyond that kind of infrastructure you must probably need to look at another
Way than using component builder because we only implemented it that way so that your
Your backend views directing Maps to the database
But because we know that from time to time there is backend views that do not have even there own
Database but rather takes these already saved information in the database
Either from other third-party components or even your own component because we know that
You would like to take that information and remodel it maybe into a spreadsheet
Or into a
Table sorry not a  table but a chart
or Any other kind of
Way we added this custom backend views which behaves on the same Dynamics as
The site views which means
We trying to give you Best of Both Worlds first being that
Strong tightly tight
Tighting manage maybe datasets which relates directly to the view and the list View and so forth
But at the same time the option of adding a custom backend view which can be dynamic and
You know you can really do custom scripting in it you need not need to be concerned about all the other
Overheads as you would usually be
So
You first need to know your backend views and then any possible custom views
That maybe combines backend view so we could possibly in the future we haven't done so yet
Possibly takes statistics and sermons
And Preachers and series's because these statistics
Are taking only the downloads
Where us preachers has in them a field called hits
And so does sermons have a field called hits that's just when someone opens one
Without downloading is necessarily so does series's
But statistics only counts the downloads of sermons so we could possibly add an extra
Backend field sorry View custom backend view
Called
Analysis
or anything
And
Then in analysis we can use the dynamic get
Option
To get data from
all through those tables
These tables basically from that one
And
Preacher table
And a series table
Let's shortened it a little by removing
That
and statisctics
And then from them
Do what we would call model
Modelling
Modelling the data
And possibly end up with
A whole new
Data structure which we can then
Place into a table or into a
Chart
In that view which means that it is now dynamic
And no longer directly connected
To the
Database
As these above
Views are
And it won't won't really have an edit view it will be a Single View
Just displaying rows
An analysis data
From does multiple backend
Database
Tables
And this
Can also be done on the front of the site
So
That means this whole
Get
Feature
We could
Take it
Put it under get
And we can give it a name and we can call it
It is the analysis
Get
Get analysis
We could call it that
And then the analysis view basically get used to get analysis
To get the data
And then
Takes that data and models setting
Sorry
Displays it
on a Page
And the same can be done
To the front
So the same
Dynamic get can be use in
The front again
So that's sort of how component builder works
If you not looking at the fields itself
The fields is a discussion on its own but
This which I have now sort of just typed out your very basic and alimentary
Is really what you need to know before coming to component Builder
You need to know what you want to achieve
What do you want to
Build
And
If possible map the field
Under each of these
So in sermons we will have name
And
We will have
Preacher
Right
And we'll have series
And we will have
Files
Right
So they should be under
Sermons that under preacher
We will have also name
And we will have
Maybe email and
discription and
Website and what else
Oh maybe I can't
I can't hear
Same goes for series
We will add a name
And
I think that will be
Description of course and
by statstics since we only counting downloads we will have a
File name
And
We will have a counter
And we will have a sermon
Which is the ID
but let's just leave it as sermon
for now
And
That will be it
So
That means if you can
Somehow
Map these things
Before hand it will help you tremendously
The reason being
That
If you start in component Builder
You can
Start by creating
A new component
And you can add name and all this information
But then you'd get to obviously you would skip most of these for the initially just getting started
You just set up these Fields that are compulsory
the ones with the Stars
And
This component image that tells you here
the Dimensions right
300pix X 300pix
And you must put it in the image folder
And then you can access it from here
Let me see
This version updates
Is a
Nice feature which we will really look into detail later
So you'll add all these compulsory fields
At settings
You would hardly do anything at this stage
Scripts as well you just leave blank read me also blank
Then add views
After you've saved the component once I mean
That means you've Now added name and you've added these and you clicked save
Then
You'd basically be able to start adding views to it
Now the way to add a view to a component
Is different from the way to create a view
You adding the view through the settings tab
But you can create new views through this area and you can also see you're ready connected views
and I'll explain this again so maybe this is gonna be a duplication
What are you really primarily wanted to show you
Is that if you start building a component
You feel very lost if you do not know where you going
And
This will help you know where you going it will help you know it you need to set up these views
And you need to add these Fields to those views
And
That that kind of information and knowing how to construct this is something that you
Need to know before hand
Now obviously you can always add more fields
And you can obviously add more views it's not that you need to be that forough and be That sure that you didn't miss
Missed something
It's more that you just need to know what you wanna do
Component Builder cannot decide that for you
And you need to realise it you literally have to create all of these Fields before you can add them
Into a view and this
Line
Are seen as a view although it
When it's compiled will represent two views
It is in component builders
Component
Backend views
It's seen as one view
And these
Fields will need to be created before they can be added to this view in the same goes with these
The nice thing though is the name field
Can You can create it once and use it reuse it
3 times
So you can reuse the name field
You can also use the hits well
Sorry the hits
Are already added
By Default so you don't need to add an hits field
We'll be talking about the default Fields later
In showing you which Fields you don't need to add
Yourself but it's add dynamicly
To each backend View
This being a backend View now
This is also a backend view but I'm I would always mention that there is a custom backend View
The purpose being that it doesn't directly related to a single Database
What gives you the option of pulling from multiple databases as I've explained here
And modelling the data and then displaying it
So that's sort of a quick overview of how to get started with a component
I realise there's so much more to say but it's very difficult to cover all of that and
Hopefully as we go along
Whatever questions still remain
Will be answered
We will be starting
At fields
So it seems sort of turned around right
You might feel we must start at the component
and then build the views
And then build the fields and you possibly right
And you can do that I mean you can after having created the component
You can click your own admin views which is the first
Things you need to create is the admin views
And click new and create an admin view but again even there
You just like with the component only be able to set the bare bone information and not all the needed
more
Nitty gritty complex information if I could say it so
And that's why I usually
Sorry wrong file
I usually start at the bottom the bottom and work my way up
I usually start with creating all the fields I know I'm gonna need so I will basically
Collapse this take these away
Like that
And
Just go create all these fields
And when I see there are duplicate Fields I would remove them
Because I know we use them
So I'll just create Fields that I know are unique
And then when I come to certain Fields Like These
These are custom fields
These I won't create initially
These are the custom fields
These are custom fields
And I won't create them initially
So I would also separate the custom field now how do I know it's a custom field
well because the preacher
Is a I wanted to pull IDs from the preacher view so if we
Ok let's mark those custom Fields again
I would like to have
This field basically link to that name right a list of these names
And the same for the series I would like it to link to that value
And
In Joomla you can create what is known as custom fields
And component builder makes provision for you to do so
But this is what I would call an advanced field
And so we'll only look at advanced custom fields
After we've looked at creating
Normal fields
And creating
Actually back end views
Because only then will you understand the implementation of this custom
Field since it will be linking to a back end views value you see
It is not just linking to a bunch of values it is
Linking directly
To this back end views value called name and so we can't really create it until we
Really know how this is gonna look and that's why we will be only looking at that after I possibly
Explain this again but
Just that we
Let you know where we're going
Building a component needs these kind of things
thought through and sort of mapped out
Some of us might not need to write it down some of us do depends on who you are
To me that doesn't really matter even if you have these things in your head
As long as you come to component builder knowing exactly well sorry that's the wrong word
At least knowing partially what you want to achieve and what you want
to build
Now that means you can do a lot of paper
Planning and do do a lot of sort of structuring
Of your component long before actually getting to component builder itself
And that's really what this
Short
Tutorial was trying to illustrate
That if you haven't done this you might get lost and not know where you're heading when you start mapping
The Fields and the views and the
Things in component build itself
Well thank you for watching
Next stop
Start looking at Field types
And then we'll look at using field types
to create fields
And so slowly we'll be
Progressing to eventually ending up with having this component
Fully functional and working
And we will be illustrating all of these
Fields as they relate to this back end views that
are linked to
Database tables
And
Hopefully that will give you
A good enough insight and
understanding
of how all this should be done
Ok thank you for watching