If you have a good knowledge of Joomla's API
You will know that it has a means by which it builds its forms
The forms that you use in your component
And it's basically done through what is called the XML file
Now I can show you that XML file but maybe this is
a little bit Too Soon
So all I'll tell you is that
Component builder basically builds that XML file
And place it in in the right place
So that your model
View and controller
Can access that file
Through the Joomla API
And with it builds the fields which you would use in a view
So
we Need to define a few terms what is a view
What is a field
What is a component
All those kind of things so
We would like to start with what is known as field types
There is always a field type needed
If you are building a field
Field types if we were to just go to Joomla itself and maybe create a new article
You basically this is what we would call a view
In fact even the
URL which I suppose you can't see
let me Scroll down a bit there
URL says that it's in a view
View equals article
Ok so
This is an article View
If you close this and you see a list of
Oh there's no articles here it's a blank website
Then this is a list of articles and it's articles are plural
So if you create one it's article single
And if it's the list of the articles it's plural
Both of these are seen as views
So this is the
List View
And if you click on new
This is the what we call the edit view or the Single View
So
Your components mostly will have these two views in the backend
When it comes to your different datasets
Now
This title here is what we would call a text view
the alias here is also a text view
This editor block here is what we would call there sorry not text View
I mean text field
And this editor here is also called a text editor field
This is a
List
Field
This is a radio
Field another list field
Another list field this is a tag field
This is a text field
And so you have all these fields
This is a
Date field
This is a user field
This is a text field
Is a text
Area
Text area
Text field
List
So we can continue this is a
Normal text field but that's got a certain feature called
Read only
Added to it
As we will see these things are all in place in our application
For you to make use of all these different changes that can be made with one type of field
So these are all seen as Fields and they all live inside a view
So that's one concept that is quite important for you to realise
That you have Fields which live in views now
You might not think that the list view has
Fields and you're partly right it more displays these fields
Let's do a dummy
test article here
Hi I think that's about all I need to fill in save and close
So we at least have a list item
But that is also a field
That is a field and if you are to click on search options all these are fields
And
So your list view also has certain Fields which are primarily
Only available in the list view. The list view is also the place where we do most of our
Features for a multiple items where as opening one item
you do what's only required for one item
Ok and then there is obviously a table here which is part of the list view
now Component builder sets Up the back end List view and edit view for you
Based on the fields and how you map them into your view
We will look at each of those concepts
More
Deeply
But I need to have you understand from which angle we are coming
We are
Gonna try and
Show you
That inside of
This article
You will be creating Fields even put them into different tabs
Which will eventually be rendered in a specific order in Joomla in in the component when it's been
Compiled through component Builder
So
That's using Joomla's own
Article manager as sort of an example
But we could just as well
Go onto component Builder
Since it has the demo article sorry the demo application in it we can select the demo
Compile it
It says that there's a copy warning this is because we haven't set some options in the global settings
It doesn't mean that there's been an error in the compiling it just means it couldn't move the file to the Git repository
You see we selected this Git thing here
And also that one
If we've unselected those let's start again
let me unselect those and we only do a compile
You see it doesn't give you the same warning
Because it's not trying to move things around
And since that
it couldn't move the others because they are Global figures
Settings that we haven't set
We'll look at those in a moment
So
Now we could just click install
And it is installed the component
Into this Joomla site
Now as you'll see it doesn't have any images because we don't ship the images with the components
that are sent as demo
So
Unfortunately at this stage we might change that in the future
But you already have your demo component running
If you click on add a look
It will open the edit view if you click looks It will open a list view of where the looks will be displayed
We added an import feature which your normal Joomla
Components don't have
We will explain that
Later
But we click new
You'd see that we have a text field here a radio button if I
Add something to the textfield it opens an alias field
Also text field
We have a repeatable field
in here
And we can add information to this
And that is sort of
Look at
The fields that is in the demo component
And so these are all fields
And they are mapped into the component
Through Joomla's infrastructure that
If we go to
Admin views
There is Look
if you look
It has in it
Those Fields we just looked at
Right
there's the name
There is the earliest acronym all this information
We just looked at
And
They are all mapped into this view
Through the field add button here
Reason why these two are Why you're not adding in through this area is because this simply is to edit
Existing
fields
Instead of adding them
So if you were to open an admin view you can edit them from here and it's maybe easier to get to those
Fields especially
If you
Have many components already
You'll have many Fields and this is a way to
Sort of just look at the fields related to this component's view
Ok so
If you were to add more Fields you would open this box and this is where you'll be adding Fields I see we are missing
One
Possibly I need to
Ensure that it's with the export and it's been dropped ou
I'll look at that
Ok
Now let's step back to
Field types
Because that's really where it all starts
We've already added
All the field types that I think you would need
The field types are
Basically
Mapping to the libraries inside of Joomla
Joomla has many field types
And for each field type which you build
You need to set certain values in an XML document
These values are
for example if you with use checkbox
Set
Up in Properties
So
You have these
Be certain changing properties that you can adjust for each
field
So this is
This is only the properties for
the checkbox field
Now you might wonder if you need to set these and most of the time you would never need to do that unless you become advanced
You would want to add more field types which we haven't covered
Or if you want to extend the existing field types
But for the most part you would not probably need to
You know tinker with this
I am simply trying to explain to you where
field type
comes from and
Amazing
Scalability that exists
You see with most other component
Builders you need to wait for the developer to add a new field type
Where as in this one you can add your own field type which simply needs to map to Joomla's
Library
And the way that they have their field type set
Now there are certain few types like repeatable field which is quite tricky and
Needs special attention even in the code of the compiler
But the majority of field types are very straight forward and simple to implement and we have implemented
those already
We have not implemented all the attributes that can be targeted though
And those would be the ones that you might need to come and add if you want to use them for example
I added this showon
option
quite recently to old field types which I found
Because this is a way of showing and hiding Fields based on other Fields' values
And although we have a very excellent
Application in place in component builder to take control of those
Features
of showing and hiding fields
This is an added feature which Joomla itself actually has and if we can in a component
That we are developing if we can use show on instead of the component Builders version
I would obviously suggest we do that
And none the less I would still explain much more on this topic as we continue
So just
Briefly let me start here at the top
You have name which is called type
And a value for checkbox
And it
Must be set to not adjustable because that is the way Joomla expects it
If you don't understand any of this information that I'm showing you here
Then a place to go to
Is this URL
Let me open that for you
It's called the form fields
You'd see a whole list of form Fields and these are the same form Fields you just saw
In our application
If I was to take
Checkbox (where is it?)
Up
here it is checkbox
Checkboxes
Ok if I would open that you'd see that they give you a list of those
Fields type
Name and they tell you what is mandatory
And what is optional
And basically we are just mapping those
Data
Into this
form here
And if we wanna add another attribute you just click on the + and it creates a new field and we add the name add
The value tweak these switches in correspondence
And some information
This is really for yourself this information block here
We put information there when later when you use this field type you are reminded what this specific attribute is for.
And I basically took this information
by
Copying it right here from
Joomla's website and placed it in there
And where I felt there might be more said I added some customs text to it
And what these values will do is it'll create an XML string like that
In your form
Which Joomla then uses to build those forms
So
Basically we first setup a field Type by
Telling you
Which input
Values would be able to use for the specific field type which at this stage is
Check boxes
And then we save this
And then later you can reuse this field type when you start creating fields
So let me just close this check box
And go to text field
And you'll see that here is a
List of the fields
That used text field as its type
Now you can open one of these fields
And here the bottom you see very something very similar if I was to go back here
And go to text field
on Joomla's website
You see that it shows you examples of how that XML line should look right see
Now
here
In the
Field area where you've created the field
Basically gave the field the name this is just for the system
The name used here is the one that is important
That should be the correct name the label
This name is just that you when you add it to your view
You know this is what we use to identify it
We'll still explain adding it to the view
In more detail
This data type and things will also explain when we go into more depth around
What a field is and how to build one
I'm simply now looking at few types and showing you how the changes that you've made in field type
affects
fields that you would build with that type
So here is that
Detail that was in field type
remember on change
And it tells you
What is mandatory and what is optional but that's basically because I placed it in the description right
I mean let's we can click close to go back to that field type
And then click on property
And we'll see that I added optional and mandatory
To the description
So that I can know is this optional or mandatory
Yes you could
Possibly argue that I should have done it from here and that it's not shouldn't be necessary to add it there
But you know this
settings here is used when we compile the component
Where as this
Here is used for you
to know what this field attribute is all about
And maybe as we
Continue to develop this component I might
Make a change to that
But I wouldn't make such a change that it affects anything that already exists
Dramatically in any way
Ok so let's go back to a field
The way the compiler works it is doesn't really grab the string and just put it into the XML
In fact if I show you how a string looks that the compiler has built
Wrong window
Let's go to a string that the compiler has built
Assessment type
You'd see that it is completely reformatted
The label is turned into a translatable string
So as has been done with the description
It also tells you where in the compiler if well we'll still look at that because this might
Sometimes show and sometimes you can
Tweak
Your
Your component that it doesn't show it
But it tells you
you know in which line in the
Compiler it was built and also in which file which is very nice
I think those of you that are developers will appreciate this feature tremendously
It also tells you the field types
Obviously as you can see as we scroll through this
You can see that
Component builder really goes way out of its way to
Reconstruct
That
That field
It is not using
This directly
It in fact
Grabs
That area
And that
To determine that this is a
Text
Field
So it actually is really dependent on that part
Which is up to name come now
And
That part there
So the opening
Exclamation and the closing one
And the value in between those is what is used
So if you by accident drop off this
Or that it will still work perfectly
These are really the only
Things that are
Really needed
And part of what I am
Hoping to achieve eventually is that this becomes just input Fields Like These
And yet I'm wondering if I should go that way
The fact that they all in one big text area
Leaves us with a lot of room and freedom
to really adjust it easily without major
Complications
And any case if you start a new field which we'll look at later
It populates this with the demo data and the demo data
Is actually values that you set
When you create a field type
You see
there it is the demo is this
Value or example
That is placed here
It's from these values that it region if you create a new text field
It grabs these values as the values which you can then
Adjust to your purpose
Of you know
Implementation for that specific field at that moment
If you leave it blank it will also build it without any value
Between those two
Exclamation marks
Ok
That is looking at field types
I'm not gonna spend much more time on this
Primarily because all the field types has been setup
And you hardly ever would need to come here and change things unless you really wanna do your own thing
And then you will be able to do that without my help I suppose
So our next tutorial will be on how to use field types in
Fields
Thank you for watching