Ok we are looking at creating Fields there are two groups I would call
Call them
Easy or
Plain or
Common
Field types
Which we will be looking at first
There are also advanced field types which primarily is your custom field types
Which we'll only look at after we have covered the admin views and how you connect
Fields to views
It's quite important because those custom field types
Really only makes sense if you see the relationship between views and fields
And if you've already have that knowledge
Well
Well acquainted and able to handle
Ok so we'll First look at the most more common field types
Not all of them of course I'm just gonna illustrate to you the text field type
And a list field type
And all the other sort of follow the same kind of implementation
So let's create a new field type
We would select
Text
As our first illustration
and it will automatically load
The fields here set on the field types default settings we looked at previously
When it comes to this information here
You need to have a well
Formulated background formulate is not right word there
Well a good background
On
MySQL
To understand exactly the What is a varchar
What is what is a text what is a medium text long text
these are basically the data type
In relation to the database
Now I've added the feature of you being able to change that
Because I want to liberate your ability to develop
Applications that are more advanced
Than
A cookie cutter kind of component Builder
So this component builder really wants to leave
Enough room
For you too
Make
Very advanced choices
And the more I constrain it
To a sort of just click here there
Don't know any code just go on and build something
The more I am gonna frustrate the real developer who is wanting to design something more advanced
More versatile
So I didn't choose that option there are component Builders out there that most possibly have done
Done that
But I don't want to
I wanna give you enough tools to really be creative and so that means a little bit
More complexity all over
Because of that
But if you know PHP and you have worked
with PHP in relation to sequel
Or any other sequel database connections via
Java or any other language
You will know that there is such a thing as a data type and that it has a length
And it you can
Set some default value to it
And you can decide whether it's a key or a unique key just realise if you set it as a unique key as a
Index type then that means that specific field will only allow a value once
And if that same value is placed in it it will you know shout at you and it will be an error
So
You hardly ever use that
Not even for an alias will you use that because the alias
Implementation in Joomla deals with the duplication within the model
When it saves the information
It actually checks whether there is an alias in the database and implements the alias so that it doesn't
Conflict
so even there you do not even need the
That feature
But it is available and you might see a need to use it so I added it there so you can choose it
And then your normal null switch whether the table should be null if it's empty
Usually
you would use
One of these default values and then set it not null
Ok and then
The story method you will most of the time use default
This being because these other methods
require much more knowledge
Of what you are trying to achieve
And if you do have that knowledge
Then I could say that JSON
Will mostly be used
When
You are storing
An array of items
To the database
And yet
When you are using list which we'll look at just now you wouldn't need to use JSON because Joomla's
implementation of the list field type
Deals with arrays already
Unless you are using sorry I'm not saying that correctly
If the list
Allows for multiple selection
Then you need to use JSON
But as far as I can remember I think let me just check here to be sure
I'm in the code
And here is the place where we sort of deal with you know how are we gonna store the data
Or we basically tripping the switches for it
And let me just look
Down here
Ok
So
If the field type is checkboxes
It will
Going here
And it will add it
Is it JSON
Object
If there is multiple selected
It will add it as a JSON option object
If
The type name is tag
so if you using a tag field type
It will not go in here no matter what you do
Let me see
Store
If it's not zero which is default
Then it will fall back onto this
Now if it is check box and you haven't selected
One of those
Features
For example
If you haven't selected one of these
JSON
base64
And it is a checkbox
Field type
Then
It will fall back
To JSON
So that's the default switch
So in the switch it takes what you've set
If you set it to JSON it will use JSON if you set it to base it will use base
if you've done an encryption it will use that
But if you've set none and it is a checkbox
it will set it
To JSON so
Even if you set
The checkbox to default
We are still gonna make sure it's safe as JSON because Joomla doesn't deal with checkboxes correctly
In fact it tells you that has a warning on their pages
The component Builder
Knows that and so well I know that is why I coded it in
So that it will anyway make sure that we storing it JSON Object and not just the array itself
And so
This is just looking at the check boxes and other JSON items
for the view
And
So for most things
That we are looking at the UI
If we are not sure how the implementation works
Looking at the code is the quickest way to actually understand what would be the way to select and now
That means if you're not a PHP developer
And you cannot figure out where this line
Or this that particular area of code is being addressed
Then obviously this is to your own
Disadvantage
But if you're able to
Read PHP
Then the compiler itself leaves in the
In the XML files and
Another files that you are building wait
I'm way off line here
in other
Models of things that it's building
It is showing you in which file
It is actually building this part of this group
And exactly on what line
So that is the way for you to get in there and see exactly what is being done
And that will also help you to determine what you need to change for it to possibly work if it isn't working
Now there is no way for me to avoid this
And the reason why there is no way to avoid them
by Joomla themselves
Ok so going back to just a normal text field
We would just leave it
to
Default
These other options of encryption
We will explain in a later video
And possibly will not
Ever use these
I had the need for them in a component that I had to develop
And so I added those features in
And at this stage it's really
Quite difficult to implement
If you do not have many
Let me put it this way
The basic one
Which is actually more secure if you would ask certain people
Is easy to implement
But the advanced one
Which is for other purposes than just your normal encryption
Is a little bit more advanced and difficult to implement
So for now if you're not that advanced in your programming skills then
You should just avoid these
This base64 is often used
where you're storing code into the database
Most of component Builders areas where you can add custom scripting
Is using this base64
As the story method
Ok so now here if we gonna create an email field
And I'm gonna say that it should not be required
I'm gonna change this to
Leave this to default
Change that
to Email
This is the name surnames
We
Uzusally don't do uppercase
And then
That's what's gonna be used for the database right
So this field
All over
The system and all the code
Is gonna be called by that
Name
Email
Underscore
Sorry
Lowercase
Email
And here the name
The label
Is what will be visually seen in the form
So
There we'll be adding enter email
We'll leave the text size the same Max length is good
I'm not gonna use the default field and it is if I sorry did
default is optional so I can just leave it out
Description
I'm gonna say add enter
Email
okay
we're remove those we're going to leave required to
False
To ensure that it isn't required
And then I'm gonna use validate email
And
I'm not gonna use the field option
The field option is to validate against another field that they both equal
Each other
We don't need that for this field
I'm here I'm gonna place demo
Come on
And
I'm gonna leave those out
So there we have an email field
Now this validate
Option
There are some custom validating
option in Joomla
Email is one of them
Then there is a way to create
Your own validation
And
The way to implement that would be to write PHP up for that so you need to know
You know what's needed to
Write your own validation
And to place it
via the custom adding in our fields
Sorry files
To place it in the correct location
Where the Joomla
Form builder will be able to get that field validation type
And add it into your field
So if you know
What I'm talking about
Then you will know where to place it
And you'll later see that in the component
itself it has an option to add custom
Files
And how to map it to the correct location
Then you can use your own validation figure type there
To extend on the validation options
But currently component builder itself doesn't do you know extra custom validating
Options it only uses Joomla's defaults
Now that means you can also leave it out and then it doesn't do validation but it still will do filtering
And here is a list of the available filters that Joomla has
Ok so that's to create an email
A field
That is a text field
You can target these text Fields with CSS and JavaScript respectively in the list and in the
Single View
The views plural is the list you
View single
Is the Single View will the edit view in the backend
And all Both of these are most
Is targeting
The editing view and the listview in relation to its backend display
If you extend the editing View to the front
Then it will also load the JavaScript to the front
But
You cannot extend the list to the front you need to build a custom front
Which we will eventually get to which is called site views
Ok so this is primarily targeting your admin area
with these scripts altough
Like I said you can extend the the editing one which is this view
the Single View
To the front
Which means it will also extend that to the front
The way to Target it this field
Whould be
That is the ID
Plus j form if you forget that
You could look at any other
Field
And you'd see it says j form underscore
And then the field name
As a ID
I'm just using fire bug to do that
And
So you that means you can just infront of this e-mail
Just in front of that email you just put
Not in here though
But if you want to Target it
In your Java Script in your CSS let me show you
Are you there
J4
Underscore
Now you can target it with CSS maybe color or something
That's gonna make it invisible but you can target it anyway
Let's make it black then
And
The JavaScript in the same way if you use j query
Add j form
underscore in front of the form name
The field name sorry
And the nice thing about this
Is that you can
Add this group to the field
And in any view where you use this field
The Script will
Follow it
It will go along with it
So it will be added to that View
Dynamically you don't need to rewrite it everywhere
So soon as you working
For example I have a
I have a script
The means to show you
That I'm using for numbers
that will be
Nice to show you hold on for a moment
Ok found even a better option to demonstrate
I had to create a repeatable field
Which we will look at later as a advanced field
But inside of that repeatable field I wanted to add a
A date field
Now
Those of you that work with Joomla will know that you can currently
Not add
A date field
Repeatable field
So what we did
And this is gonna
Possibly be very impressing
But let me show you
I simply used a text field
And I added that
To it
As you can see here we have PHP
right in this JavaScript block
And way to add PHP here is we would do the open brackets
Question mark PHP
And then again
Question mark close
There is an a PHP and we are adding the  j Query framework
Now this script I added to the repeated fields
Script area not to the actual text field
The reason why I didn't add it to the actual text field
Because the text field is obviously gonna be repeated right so you gonna have
10  20 whatever text fields
That that specific text field
But with this code
I'm able to Target
Up to 50 repeats of that
Field
With
that saying ok field number we said at least 50
And this
JavaScript area is being repeated 50 times and  incrementally
And so the course date field
Date again this ID I got from after creating repeated field I went in and looked at the ID
That field
Added a date picker
Can I set the value of the datepicker
And
Basically added to the field
And it works very well so
this custom scripting area
For JavaScript can also take PHP inside of it
And JavaScript
That will be then added to the view in which this field is gonna be used
And it's I think it's very very nice feature that we have
And it's very useful
It's come in very useful for myself anyway
Ok so we not gonna do that we just wanna use it for creating a simple email field
So we will just click save or save and close
and save and new
So that's looking at creating a text field type now let's quickly do a list view a list field
Sorry
Not view
So we click on list
And we see that has
An option
aray or
String here
now the options are set with a zero
and a pipe
And then the name
In a coma now that basically represents one item
In the drop down
So if you see this drop down here
Then
Then that is one item
That is an item
That is an item ok
So each of those
Would basically be represented between the comas
The pipe
Makes a separation between the value being stored in the database
And a value being shown
To the person accessing the form
Now if that value is the same value
So if it
If you want to store in the database the same value as the one that
Is being
Displayed
then you simply drop off
the bipe with the
Initial values like that
So it will say option 1 2 and then that should be 3
right
Option 3
Now
That is another
Allowed way to use it
Or you could say
I want one option to be viewed as having not selected anything yet so if you wanted to say
Say option 1
Ok I wanna add another option
You would say
Please
Select
option
Comma
By
By adding
leave that please
Because it's getting too long here
Select an option
By adding a pipe without a value
Is being treated as a nul
So when the form when the dropdown is built
Then it will it will be like nothing is selected
Basically that option see select an option
It's exactly what I did here although this is a custom field this type field
I don't have one of those here
Sorry
But just that you know
That will basically
Behave the same as that one
OK
And then the other values would be selecting
And I have a you can use it as it is
Or is even a total different value like that it doesn't matter just know that it possibly
We would make everything lowercase which if you put it that side of the pipe
Now
This could be left
Out
And you can fill in these information based on your requirements
So that's how you set up a list field
I hope that
Shows you what is
Possible
But as you can see this list field isn't dynamic
In the way that a custom field possibly can be
You see the list field here you staticly set a few values that is unchanging and which should be selected
But with the custom field type which will look at in a later video
you can
I have another tables values populated the list for you
So as it's been created your list gets longer
Dynamically and will still look at that and that is obviously available but this is a
More static said it once and use it over and over where is there is actually
Were there is also a dynamic list option which I will illustrate later
Well that is creating a list view
Let's
Quickly also look at a radio button
Just very similar
If you do
Creating a radio button
There is though one point to make here
If you create a radio button
You see that there are only two values
And you can add more than 2 to the list but
I always
Think of it this way
As soon as it becomes a list of values then use a list
A radio button should at most have 3 selections or maybe at most 4 and really depends on the
Length of the text
So if it's yes no and maybe and
No thank you oh my Yes No Maybe
Not yet decided so that's four options
Ok so that could be ok
But as soon as it gets a  5th value possibly you should look at a list instead
again with a radio button you can just leave it at
You know the default storing method
And again the field
Attributes are
Very similar to the text attributes
except for this
Options array option here
Then also liked the list
Field type it is separated by comma
And the store value and the display value are separated by a pipe
Now it is important to note that
You cannot use
These
Exclamation marks inside
Sorry not exclamation quotation marks inside of your values
If you wanna use
Quotations inside you need to look up the html equivalent
Of that
quotation marks and use that
And then it all
It will work but if you add a
Quotation
Inside here it will literally break off
The String right there and you have only one value show up so that's just that you know
Ok so that is a radio button let's look at another one quickly colour
Colour is quite straight forward it has a default value you need to remember to set the label and the name
Always the type
It must not be changed
And if you select colour here
And you do change the type
You realise that the component builder will simply ignore what you did here
And also back to back
It will not
Because it is a field which
When we set up the field type
The type itself
Was said to be mandatory and unchanging remember
And
That's why you you cannot override it
Everything that you said to mandatory and unchanging
Will fall back to the setting that you said there in the field type and it even if you change it here it will not
Change
Ok then there is the description
And if it's required and show on again the show on feature is something that is very nice
As we go we will get to see it in action
But you can have a field like
For example A list field which has an ID 2 which should be selected
So did this colourfield should show
So you could say
Let's say that this Fields name is
Access
Or
What would be in our ideal
Let's say
View
And then
One
Would be
If in the view field
The option with the
Value
Of 1 is selected then will this field only show up
No you can have it
if 1
Or 4 is selected
Then it will show up
And this implementation is your Joomla
Default implementation of the show on field
Unfortunately It cannot target multiple other Fields yet as far as I know
And that's why we have
in component builder our own implementation which is far more advanced
And which will look at once we get to views
Ok so that's just looking at colour
And and
Let's see
Another one that's quite interesting is category I suppose
In category
You have
Extension
And this extension if you read it
Is the name of the extension for which the category will be retrieved for example
To list content categories use the value com content
You can add also target 1
View
Use the value
Com underscore component Dot view
What that means is that you can just by adding the category field
to a
View
You
Automatically add a category to your component so it will you don't need to map the category at all
in fact you cannot map with even if you wanted to
Joomla
Already has a category component in place
And if you add a category well this category type field to which we are looking at now obviously you can
Add your own category
View
And then use a custom field to link it's values to you to other views
But if you are gonna use  Joomla's category implementation that integrates with your component
Then this is the way you do it and then you don't write anything for the category area
Because Joomla do that itself and adds it to your component dynamically and the only thing
You need to do is actually an extension
Add your components name now we haven't looked at your component name
And that
In fact I think we possibly come back to category
When we have
Come to you know that area of
Sermon distributor and where we add in categories to certain views
But that you know
The categories
Can also be targeting just a specific view instead of the whole component itself
So it can only be related even to just one specific View
Which makes it nice that means you can have a category for listviews you can have a category for
that you can have a category for this you can have multiple categories in one component
This is maybe an overkill but it's none the less possible and the way you do that is
Simply your component name
and the specific views name
And obviously the view must be in singular
You you cannot target a list view it must be a editable Single View
So it is only saying View
Ok so that's looking at category will look at category again later stage where we actually will implement it
Editor is also a very Common Field
Which were often using
And the editor is what is in your Joomla content article manager is that big block in which you articles are placed
To here you can add such a block to your component
And
There are some
Important things like the buttons and if you read the description we have here it explains to you how it works
And including the
Hide option
And what kind of editor you want to load
Obviously You're preferrable one and the alternative one
Desired or alternative
And the button option here is really like I said you can read it
Hide buttons based on what you selected
And then you have a filter option here and required
Basically again your normal attributes as with with other field types
In Joomla
Since most of them are extending your base field in Joomla and then
Type in name and label and defaulted
These things are also available to all the others
So that's quickly the editor
let's see
Media
Just make sure with media that you
Select the correct directory
If none is set I think it falls back to images
but you can target with a specific directory inside of images
And I can see there it's mandatory so you need to set it
And you can only Target
Images itself which is a limitation from Joomla side
So that that directory starts at images right so says the attribute should be relative to the top level
Images folder
So that means let's see you you want to Target a specific folder inside images
called foo
Then you would add that they're like that
And then preview if an image is been selected do you want
Image to be able to be previewed
By hovering over the side of the field and you just change it to true if you want to
Again the show on feature is here in the other default concepts that we've already discussed
Another one that's nice Is notes
Notes is basically above a field or like here if we said this is a note
that you see here
And so you can add notes
Around your fields
And it has very nice
Implementation right over there
But you can read through
And
Yeah I think that will be all for us looking at field types
Well basically looking at the basic field types or
Common Field types
If there is any other feel types with you felt
You need help with
Please look up the
Joomla documentation since the implementation is more or less a straight forward
Trying to not
Redesign the wheel
We simply trying to implement Joomla's way of doing it
And if there is a field type you need more information on you can simply
Go look at Joomla's documentation on that field type and if they don't have documentation then
Can you can go into
The field
Like I said libraries
there are 3 places to look
CMS
Joomla and Legacy in the libraries folder
Is the places where these Fields of found
So if you look under the CMS folder you got
captcha field type
chromestyle content editor so there's the editor
So you wanna know if there is more attributes that
Can be used in editor
You can open the editor and look through the code
And see the
The attributes that are
Being implemented across the board here it set height with $ value author value
author field set So It Goes On
And if you see that there is a attribute that we are not already targeting
You can like I have to explain
Go to the field type open it
Add the attribute
Add the name add the value set with it is mandatory obviously I think if we left it out it's not
And whether it's translatable translatable is an important concept
Which not all fields are translatable and And when a field is translatable
Sermon sorry component builder basically translate it for you
So
If you look at
The
It's use this acronym for example
You see I added there the label as acronym
Then while component builder builds this field into your component it takes that value
And it
Converts it into a translatable string which adds it to the language file
And it adds that
In here so that if somebody updates the language file that updates everywhere in the system
Which is basically means that
Languages are implemented everywhere in component Builders components
All the components it's building it translates label for everything that you said to be translatable
So if we If we look at
Let's go look at a certain
Field type like text
Any property
That you said is translatable like here the label is yes
And description is yes
And that seems to be it
Hint is also translatable it's also said to yes
Means that
Component Builder
Will dynamically take hint
And translated into a language string added to your language file
And replace the XML with the language string like it's done here
So
That is
How you can extend existing field types
And create Fields with them
I hope that is
Good enough for you to get your hands into
or to get excited about it in to use it
Obviously having Fields might still feel very
Primitive
And so next up will be looking at
Adding those Fields to views
And basically making building your view
Itself