Hi
We are looking at admin views
Which is
The next thing to be setting up
In
Developing your component
So first we started with
Field types
Looking at
How to setup field types or improve on them
Then
We looked at how to use those field types to build
Basic
Common fields
Now we gonna look at how to take those fields
And add them
To admin views
Admin views
Like I explained in our initial
General planning
Video
It is basically from the BedRock
The basis of your
Components database structure
so your admin views is where your Database
Structure is being
Developed
All your admin views which have their own table
Now as we explained admin views have a single
Name and and has a list record
or a plural name
And then there is a system name
And the reason why there they actually have 3
Is that let's say you have
Wanna reuse this
Specific admin View
In another component
With the same name but obviously adapting it to that component
The idea would be that you would then have two preachers
Showing up in your selection list
When you added to the component
And so that might be difficult to discern
Which is which
And so
You can add the name of that specific component
As part of
Just differentiating between
The same
Names
That means you can have
Admin views with the same name
But with different implementation
Fact that is how
You can do different version control
Concepts on
Components
Using the same admin do
Just inside of it
Making a few changes and in Saving it
So you could do that
Open preacher for example
And in here
You could say free version
This is the free version and then save as copy
And then you can
Change the field that is linked
You can change some of the linked views
You can change some of your CSS will whatever
Other things you have done
Regarding this admin view
And then go to the free version of that component
And Link the
That specific one
That specific view instead of the other
Away maybe I'm getting ahead of myself I usually do
So let's focus on admin views now
to create a admin view you obviously just click new
I'm gonna
Open preacher again because this is the one we are using
As our illustration
And
You would
See that there should be a name for a single record
Again that is where you would edit
This records so that is
In this case I said preacher
And then there is a list of Records
And that's preachers
Then a short description
And a normal description
Depending on
What you would like to say
Then there is a type now the read write and the read only
Changes the components editing
view
If you say read only
Then it will basically limit
The fields to being not you will not be able to edit them
If you remember in the
In this area
Here
The modified "By field" cannot be edited
Because it's done automatically and when it was modified is
Is also updated us every time you
You click save
So this area can not be edited and that's how all
The fields are gonna look
If you select
Read only
If you if you leave it on read write it will look like this
and you will be able to edit it
Ok so that is
Looking at these
Fields now there is a place for an icon
if you hover over the icon It gives you the dimensions that is needed
This basically is the icon
Then when you look
At
The dashboard
These icons
Are the one selected there
Ok so
You can see that
The icon has two of them one is the add icon
And one is there just a normal icon so if you hover here
You should see the image if it is
Set in
In your
In yours
Images folder sorry
So if you open the this
It goes to your image folder you select the icon
When you hover here obviously those images
are not in this image folder so it does not show up
And then if you gonna add preachers are you if you gonna add a field
Just a field
called category that is of the category type
Then you should add a category icon
Since then
The system will automatically know ok there need to be a category setup
And it will look for this icon to use
For that category
And
If you select a
Category field that is a general category for the whole component
Which isn't directly linked
To this
View
Then it will take the first view
The system will look at which view when it processes it
Which view is the first one
And usually that would be the first one you've
Created
And it will use the icon in that
But to be on the safe side if you using 1 category for them all
Just set the same icon on them all
But if you are gonna use a category
Which is primarily focused on the preachers
And you just gonna put preachers and a category
Then you need to add a category
Icon here
Four categories
now permissional switch
It's got to do with your accessing and
Updating of data
So like you can see here
We have
View edit
View edit State
View edit own
Views create
Admin views delete
admin view access admin view edit version
Now this edit
If it's set if your own this managing group and it set to a aloud then you can edit it
If you are a guest and it said to
Deny
I no Matter Where You are in
The front or the back of the site
You won't be able to edit
this information even if you have a Direct Link
It won't allow you to edit it
Now it also has view access
So somebody who might be not allowed to
Edit it
May be allowed to
View
This
this content
in the back end in the list view
Then it will show in the list view and they can see that it is there
Now you might
Think yourself why would I ever wanna do that
And you see because of your custom admin
Views and the way that you can connect them to your admin views
Which will look at later
You might want to display the record and
Just leave an custom admin link
to
the data
Let me give show an example of a
Component that does that
You see here
There is a button underneath
The company name
So it displays the record
But
If I was
Like this one whose profile is set to
To being locked
If I was to click on this
You tell me
That I do not have the permission to edit it
But if I was to click on this icon
It actually loads the information that I
Looking for
And
That is the difference
The differences sometimes you wanna use a custom see this is a custom
Admin View
And you might want to
Do something
That is not a
Editing view but a custom View
And then you would like to
see the record but not edited
So that's really what
What that is all about
Ok so
We are back here
And we are looking at the missions
So
Opening this permission tab
You'd see that there is edit a view edit
View edit own
View edit state and
All these have been created usually when you open this it might look like
That
Look like that
So you would set the first one and that you would see there are
Two options one is core edit and one is view edit
The core edit
Means
That
You want to do a global
Switch
Now
Let me try and explain that by opening
Component Builders options
We haven't actually looked at this yet but it is quite important
You see that it all components in Joomla you have what is called the create edit
Delete
Edit State edit own
it is this list
Of options
Which means that if you select
This
You know that they can't create something
Then
It is applicable to
Everything in this component
Because it's a global setting so
Everything that doesn't have a view name behind it
Like this is a view name
And it says access
This is a view name
and it says batch use
But this is only batch use
So that's the global for batch use and this is only related to this view
So you can say I am allowing them to
Do a batch function
But in this admin view I don't
Want to allow
Sorry
Don't wanna allow them
To do a batch function
Or you could say
You know what I wanna use inheritance
So that means I'm gonna do that
I want them to be able to do batch functions here
And in this view
Now the reason why you can do it in two places then
Is that you have a global switch to stop them from doing it
But you can also locally to the view
Tweak whether they are able to
To edit
Do some of these features
So coming back to the
Way that you would set that up
If you don't want to have a separate
Control
For this
View
In relation to whether it can edit it or
Or whether you could
Change it all view it all these
Possibilities
Then you would use core
And core would mean that you would have only this one switch
And if you say deny it will it automatically deny it for that View
And any other view that is using
core
or core can be seen as Global
When when you are setting it as
View
edit view
It means that the system will generate
A specific list of items
Specially just for that View
So if you look
From there to there
That's for your admin View
from there to there is for your custom
Admin View
Now that means
What I set up
This in a component Builder
I selected view edit
And then I said in relation to each record in relation to the whole View
And I selected
Both
So
Then it will implement it for the
For both
And single record and it will implemented
For your Global settings
Now again it might feel
I won't blame you if what I have just tried
Explaining
Makes you feel
confused
But
Really
The only way for you to make sense of this is if you know how Joomla provisional structure works
So if you are using a Joomla website
And you have actually ever
Gone to articles
And opened options
and then look at their permissions
Then you'd see that they only have create edit
Delete
Edit State edit own
And then these accessing of the control
And this batchally
This big
Global settings
Now what we are doing as we simply adding
More control
Then only these default because the way this works
In article manager you basically have
1 view
That view is articles
These are the views
Own's as categories is another view but it really has another component
It's not really
Content
The content component
An admin features
Is just another implementation
It's not really a whole new Database
It's ok so the point is
You only really have two well the most two views here
And so when they look at options
They know that if they tweak this permission they want it to be implemented
For all the views related to articles
Right
Well with component Builder you are able to build components
That are far bigger
Then the content managing
Article manager
Ok I'm because of that
We felt that your permissions must extend
That you can target a specific view and not just all of them at once
So if you want to Target a specific View
You will select
The
View edit
Actually this view
Prefix
Must be in your selection
If you select
Core
That means you are saying
I don't want to specifically target this view
If I change it in the global settings which would be
The ones without a view name in
Front
Everything
From
Here
to There
those are the global settings
Global export Global batch
global version
Edit version
Global create
Delete
Edit edit State now edit state is changing it from publish to unpublish those things
Edit own means you might not have edit rights but he has edit own rights
So that means whatever you create c can edit again
In and created by is a field
so can he edit created by field
Or Can he edit create date field
Now
You'd see that
This basically targets
Fields that are sort of the default fields
There is a way to Target
Custom Fields Fields that were developed
Outside of the default fields
But that is not done in
Here
I'll Show you where that is done this is just controlling your default Fields and your default
Features with regards to
Permissions
And
So you would first set up these permissions make sure that you set up all of those that you want to implement
There is a list here of those I think is most general
This list might
Grow with time
But because we've moved
The control of a single field
Out of this
Structure
It actually means that we've made it scalable
So this
Permissional implementation here
Is really only Targeting your
or default fields
or the fields that
Already the system put in for you
And the default
Concepts like accessing
This specific View
Or deleting an item in the view or creating an item
Or editing the created
Field or editing the created by field
Changing the state
Edit own So those are the custom
Default features
If you wanna do a control on a specific field I'll show you that in a moment
But
That is the implementation
Of permissions
If you do not really
Understand this
I would suggest you make
Effort
To study up on Joomla's own implementation
Sorry
Off
The promotional structure
Then once you've really understood the way Joomla
Handles this permissional structure
Then you would have better grips on
Setting up these
permissions
Per view
What is done in the code if you would like to see that
It's basically in the code
If your ready have developed a
Component
You see that it sets up
Your Globals
This is the global now when I say Global
I mean
If you click on options
let me just close this
If you click on this button here options in any of the components
You're going to the global settings
Ok
And
These permissions here
are
Those first that I've highlighted
So it all those
And they have
Links
To the specific
Views so there is the field View
There is the
Dynamic get view there is the custom admin View
And you can see that they have there
Related switches
Ok but then there's also
For each view their own Section
And that causes Joomla
to add in an item a permissional tab
With switching to control the permission for this one
Individual item
And
We have tried our very best
To implement these permissions actually
The way that you want might expect
I can in later videos going to the code and show you exactly how
This permission structure is being implemented
and I think it's one of the features that makes component Builder
Far more advanced
Then other component Builders out there
Is the ability to add permissional structures to your component right inside of component Builder
Through
This
Permissional switch
Ok
And so we will will definitely be speaking about this permissional structure
As we go along
The tab structure if you look at these we call them tabs
Settings Fields CSS JavaScript PHP my SQL
Published
And permissions
The Publishing permissions
are
tabs that are built
Automatically
For all
Backend
Admin views
Old admin views
Have this permission and well the permission only if if set
And
Published
Will always be there
In published we basically bundle your
Your the fields that are built
Dynamically
Without you having to set them I think
that is what you could say
With publishing all those Fields that you do not need to set
Are always placed in
Publishing
And so everything else this MySQL tab here the PHP JavaScript CSS
Fields and settings
Are actually an example of what tabs can be
Now in preacher
I actually setup
Two tabs
1 called
Details
And one called sermons
Ok so there are two tabs in preachers
So that means if you were to open the preacher
Backend View
First one would be called settings
The second one will be called
Sermons and then you'd see publishing and permission
So that's how I would look
Now when you create fields
You see that there is a column here called tab
And you then will select the number now the tags
Are number from one to
Whatever
We don't start at zero or though that might have made more sense for programmers
We started with
One
So first tab second tab
And
Because we are using
A place different
From the tabs we don't use the names
So you need to remember that this is tab one this is tab two
So when you set up a field
You need to tell us in which tab
Do you want a place that feel
Ok
So
That is what this tab
Number here is all about
Now you might say but where is tab two's information because their sermons right
Well
Because of the fact that sermons
Is an actually
A table on its own
If we go out here
We will see that there is a
Admin view called sermon
And it is his own
backend View
And it has its own structure
So
How can I
Get
The sermons
That is only related to this
Preacher
To be showing in the second tab called sermons
What we created the thing called linked views
now linked views is the place where this is done
So basically
I selected sermon as the view
I said it should
Be placed in the second tab
And in child key
Is preacher so if I think about sermons
Which is the child
Sermon is the child
Preacher is the parent
So you would always think of the parent as this the view in which you are the moment you are setting up the linked
View
So that
If you are in preacher
The parent is preacher
If you are in sermons
The parent is sermon
So depends on in which view your busy editing
And so here
When we talk about the child key
This would be the database field name
That that is to be looked at
And the parent
Field name that should be found inside of this
So when we look at preachers
You would let's go back to
Sermon
let me quickly close this
Ok we got sermon open here and if I open there this fields
Well I don't need to open it
here in fact let me us another place
It is Easier to see
Let's go to fields
You'll see that there is a field called name
Ok wait there's a field called
Preacher where is it? preacher preacher
next page possibly no why am I not seeing it
custom there it is
Sorry
Ok so this is the field
That we want
Connected to
With each other right
So do to get
The sermons that belongs to that preacher
We need to get the ID of this field now that's a custom field
And we said that we are gonna look at custom fields
Only after explaining the admin
views so I'm gonna go into detail now
But I'm gonna open that field None the less
And I'm gonna show you that it's name is preacher
And because that field
Will be connected
to sermon it means that in the database
the ID
Which is the key field
Is gonna be saved in preacher
So that means the ID of the preacher
Is saved inside of the preacher
Column
In the database
now let me show you that in the database itself
Ok so here I am in the database
With Sermon distributor
And I'm opening sermons
And you'd see that we would scroll
Until we see preacher
And it has ID's in it
And those are the ID of the Preacher's themselves
So if I was to go to preacher
it basically means that we are linking
To this ID here
Ok
So
Going back to our
Linked view concept
That means the child
Database table
In which the ID of this preacher must be
Found
Is in preacher
the parent
Key
Would be this preachers ID
And so by doing that
The linked view will only show the sermons
That are related
to this
Specific preacher
And that is how the linked views can be linked
If you didn't select these correctly it won't load all of them
Ok
well it won't work well
So there needs to be that tight relationship
Between the parent and the child
View
So
there's also a way
To actually link
An array from an array
So let's say
The person is able to select more than one preacher
There is a way for you to also
Type that but that would all be dealt with in advanced
concepts
Since that is
Well I could
Explain some of it here
but best
be let me show you
That would be one of the syntax to use
But like I said
Think I possibly need to deal with this in advanced concepts
Because who will know to look for the answer in this video or tutorial
So we'll stay with the basics here
So the basic
Way of linking a
Another view would be to select that View
From this dropdown
Then say in which tab it should display
Then
What is the child's
Database table in which to look
What is the parents value to use
to
Build a relationship
And then this add new button or no
Is basically  when you look at a
let me Close this
When you look at Fields here
You see it has a new button
So you can in that switch there decide whether it should
Show it would not
I should tell you that if you say yes
And you have
In that view created the correct permissional of structure
for
Whether somebody can create
An item
You can control the display of that
New button
With just setting the permission of that users specific group
So if that user is in a group that doesn't have permissions to
Create new items for
In this example
for
Preachers or for sermons
Then that new button will also not show up
So we have that permissional wrapped
Round that button's display methods
Ok
That is
The tabs
Just looking at the tabs
That's really what we were looking at
And then explaining to you
The how to link
other views
To it
To other views
So that you can have the data displayed inside of each other
Basically this feature we have here
So the fact that we are busy in preachers and we are able to display the fields
That are being used
Well
As you can imagine
These fields
Are linked to preachers
From this column here
So we are using a
Repeatable field structure
And we are able to
Link
Connect
The field names
To this
View
Now let me show you how I did that so I'm
Looks like I'm gonna show you anyway
Ok I'm opening the admin The View
Which is the one we looking at
I'm going to link two views
And you see that I have there and are in the pointer
And the world field
So if you are
Trying to connect
A View to a
To the
From the parent
An independent it is stored in at fields
That's the database
column Name so if we go to the database
Go to
Component Builder
Admin views
And we
scroll
You see there's add fields
And if I open that
You see that the way it stores it
Is it stores the ID is then it stores the list
So there's a way in which your
Repeatable fields are stored by Joomla
And the value that I need to look up is in field
So in the repeatable field called
Addfields
There is a field called field
And it should look for the ID of the
Sorry of the
Fields
So it need to look in Addfields
In the field
Array
For the IDs
That it needs to fetch
And the way you would map that in the
Connect a
A linked view
is you would say that this is a capital R
For repeatable Fields basically that is the convention to
To tell the system it's a repeatable field we looking in
And inside of the repeatable field
We must look in the
Field array
For those ID's and they should map to the child's
ID
So does that make sense
I hope so
Because that's the way it's done
And if that wasn't a repeatable field but an array
You would simply say array
And
If if the array is just the values themselves you would drop off any pointer to
Specific value
But if it's an array with
And it's actually a
So if it's an associative array
You would just add the name
Of the
associative key
That it needs to look
If it's just a normal array without Association
Leave it like that
So this would just tell the system it is a array
And it needs to look
Inside of those values for these IDs
Ok so that's sort of explains the linking of an admin View
To another admin View
Now getting on with
The
Setting up of fields
Now since we've already created the fields
Beforehand
You will
Usually start out this way
It will looks like that
And the fields that you have created you would scroll down
if it is a long list
You just start with typing that Fields name
and it will sort of bringing it up to you
Then it ask you whether you
Would like to show this field in the admin View
The admin list for you
And that means
If you've closed
Your
Editing area
There is a list of names here
And if you want
That specific field to show up in this list
Then you would select
Show
If you have selected show you could tell us in which order you want this
Must be the first one second one
And we thought while you shouldn't do more than 100, it will look
Ridiculous
So you can say I want this one to
show up first
Now
The title  Alias concept in Joomla
Is is quite interesting
An obviously
It's actually needed
Especially if you want to do
History control
Or
Integration with Joomla's infrastructure when it comes to
their history and tagging systems
You need to add
A title and a
Alias to all your items
Sorry to all your views
Especially if it is a view that is gonna be used in the front
So in this case since we are gonna use preachers in the front to display list of preachers
We most certainly gonna add a title and we gonna use the name as the title
Then again back to the backend
Do we want to have this sortable so
Do we want this thing to be clickable there
So you can click on it
And it sorts the table
Alphabetically
On the basis of this table
Sorry column
So if you wanna have it sortable
then do you want
to have this
Field be searchable
Do you want someone to type into this box
We take warehouse for example
Type it in their search
Do you want it to
Show
Only that
Specific field
So if you want them to be able to search for it
You say yes
Then the filter option is a tricky one
You don't wanna set name to filtering because then it will show a list of all the names that already is being
shown in the table
you only want to use filter on things that are like a radio box
or a
Other
View or
You know Fields that actually are not all being displayed one after the other
In the table so for our example I added let's go
Go to sermon distributor and preacher I added
No extra Fields there but at sermons I added preacher
So there's a list of all the preachers here so I could sift and say ok I don't want to see this pictures
Sermons and then it shows up only those so that is the filters and the way that you set up
The filter is simply by clicking yes or no here and it will set up that that filter for you
Then this link if you are setting up it custom field and you want to be able to
In the display of the list have it clickable so I can click here and actually go
to that preacher you see and then click close and then I'm back in the
Sermons list view I could also click on series and all take me to the series and I can edit the
Series immediately click close and take me back to the list view so if you want that
Feature for the specific item then you need to tick yes here now usually we used
the name as you see here to be the clickable field the title sorry
If you select your title here and you click link then your
Actually Telling us that this item this field item here is actually what we should use
Use as the clickable option to open that actual sermon
So here we'll have that actual sermon opening up and all it's related fields
So that is the way for us to know which field should be used as the clickable field
If you have a title now
This concept is something that you might need to play with and since it's so easy to change it you can just click a button
Here to compile your component install it look it it's behavior change it a little compile it install it
Look at it's behavior by doing that you'd get a good understanding of what What happens if you change these switches here
Ok now we said that we wanted the preachers name and stuff on the settings
And our Tab for settings as the first have now we gonna look at the backend setup in
Off where you wanna have this Fields display now there are these different
Placing options left in tab right in tab full width in tab a
Above tab underneath tabs left of tabs right of tabs and then
There is the order in which it should go that means if we look at this again
This is left in tab this is right in tab I think I have
Another view that goes beyond some of those parameters let me go to this one
And we do question
So that is right off
Tab not in tab you see there is an option
It says Right in tab left in tab and then it says left of tabs and right
Of tabs now that means that you can put it out
Side of the tab area So even if I was to click here it will remain displayed right there on the side
And that is to put it a right of tab know there's also a left of tab area over here
Then a above tab is this one here that's above the tabs so it also shows all the time and
And then there's underneath tab so we basically added the option of
Placing data I just show you
At the right in tab left in tab and then right
Of right of tab and left of tab and above tab and beneath tab which is
1 2 3 4 5 6 positions in the backend of your
Template and the places are being set simply by these alignment assignments here
So select the field alignment inside the tab or view and you select these and
Then once you've selected them let's say you've selected left in like this one above tab and you select
1 then this is the order in which you wanted to display the first this one
Then that one left in tab this is first right in tab this one is first and then that one
And full width it is a description now full width will also this will always display
Under the left and right of in tab so you need to
Select your left and right and then only your full width so full width his always the last
Thing to show up in a tab and then here is the switch to add permissions to
Is a specific values so if I was to say you know what I want the control
Which group can edit the name field you simply need to click this yes and that would
Add this field into the permissional structure dynamically and so that is how you
You control the permissions of fields that's how you add Fields to a view and those are
All the different switches now obviously you can only have one title per view and only have one
Allias per view so you should not have more than one selected and then in any case I think the system will
ignore the others but just to be safe let me tell you to set the others to know
And then those that are actually the title to yes and the one that's actually the allias to yes
And so we will be able to you know be sure to use the correct field values
And then when you set any of these to show you should set the order of their
Display here and ok so there is the filter the filter then is added dynamically
by Simply clicking a yes here so if we go to sermons as an example
And we click on their Fields they have many more fields which will help to illustrate some of these things
And you'd see that we have sermon series and we have it set up
As filter so filter is the second last column
Sermons series let's see we said that to yes so that means we can sort this
sermons by series that is how you set the filters for the backend remember this is primarily
For the backend Although some of that information will relate to the front eventually especially this
Permissional Swiths will be able to access it from the front if you need to
But this is simply to add the fields to the actual
view in the backend ok if you have any questions
About this please give me a heads up if you feel like haven't done a good enough job explaining this then
Let me know and I'll redo this video so that's adding fields
To the admin views there are much more things to explain here and I think the only thing I'll still
Cover in this tutorial is the actual conditions this is an amazing feature
Which goes beyond Joomla's control on the show on attribute per
Field remember we looked at the show on attribute and the show on attribute can be control
can control which Fields to show when you are clicking on other
fields so for example here we have a field called
Add JavaScript if I click yes it opens this area Java
Script where I can add custom scripting now that behavior are being is being controlled
By this condition structure and the condition structure for sermons
Are the following if you can see there is a few already being set so what we will
As we are first decide which field are we targeting which field do we want to
Show or hide that's the behaviour do you wanna show a field or hide a field now most of the
Time we'll use show show means it'll be hidden unless these criteria's are met
So show is the one I use the most and I think most will use that mostly now here is the
The list of all the fields in your system now you might say why don't you just show the fields that I've selected As part
Of this view and unfortunately that feature isn't Place yet so you need to remember
Which Fields you selected in the fields area and so for our purposes
It's these Fields and you need to remember their names and then
Then when you go to the conditions when you type a field like name
You need to know oh it's this one that's how you would link to them now I've
Build on option for files is a field and I wanted to show
Now this isolate and chain function is a concept which I believe would
be best explained when you think about that not
Only one field must start sorry be
Used to show the other one but more than one field so in this case
Dropbox Auto note in sermons should not only show when fields
Source is Dropbox but also when built option is automatic
So that both of these should be true before it shows
The the Dropbox note and so you would select the field
You want to control obviously you can control more than one at a time but the logic behind this
Might not always work so you need to try it tested if it doesn't work come and tweak this until you
you find it working in behaving the way you expect so most of the times
You would only link one field to one validation
But as soon as you have multiple Fields you use the chain option so it's either isolate like
This one to build option of files should show when file source is Dropbox than it's
Isolated it isn't connected to any of the other settings here as soon as you click chain
It means any other field that has this any other row is a row that has this field selected
as well we'll be chained together so that it must be both being validated
as true before it actually will show the field so here let's look at it
It says file source and you can select any of these if it if if you know that this file
File this sorry file source is a list then you can look at ok this is a list and see the
List options so this is only for text and it says that only for text Fields only for text fields
If it's only for text fields only for text fields only for text fields this is only for list and radio and check
Boxes and dynamic lists this is only for list radio and checkboxes this is only for list radio and checkboxes
So and then you can say is or is not
Sorry if it is Dropbox then it should show if it
Is not Dropbox then it should show that is the the logic behind it
Now here this one is when you're dealing with a dynamic list unfortunately with dynamic
List it's quite difficult to set these values since they are dynamic
And so the best way to deal with a dynamic would possibly be to leave this blank
So that means that if any of the values are selected show show this item
We will still look at Dynamic or custom fields
Sorry Dynamic list all custom Fields and we will explain
to you how to set up those custom Fields but that is basically what that option is for
Most of the time we are using this is and we are when you select that specific
Field and show you so if I select file source
So you would select let's do that again if it if it is
If the field that you've selected he's a text field the system will show you that by saying
Keywords or length so you can say I want if he has put in a
Length of 2 characters then show so then you take keywords away so
So then that that's how you can use the text field now
now you would Change this to
Active that is active and that it has a length of 2
That's how that that's what that would mean you if you know that what you've selected is a list it will show you the list
But show you all the values and then you can remove the values that you don't want to use
And the only value that's really important is that 2 the other side just for you so
You could even just leave 2 that will be the same as that we are just showing you in
in fact what I do is I explode the string at the pipe and I only use the first value to develop the
The JavaScript in fact the Java Script that is being written we are in the sermons view
Let me show you that so we would go to
Component Builder admin components
Sermon distributor modules
Forms and then you'd see there are two there's a XML which is the fields
And then there is a js which is actually the Java Script so we open that and here's
All the JavaScript that component Builder would build now if we look at this let's go there
It's only these permissions sorry these
A conditions ok so these are the conditions it's not even that long of a list
But to implement these conditions component builder builds this
JavaScript so it starts up here and all of this JavaScript is the
Implementation of those things that we set there
All the way down to there ok so that means about
500 lines of JavaScript gets written by component builder just by these switches
That you set up here now I'm showing you
Where the script is being written so did once you've set up these switches you can come into this
Script and if you remember the field name that you are working with
So for example let's look at it build option is the field and files source
So let's look if we can find that here
There is source ok so it gets the value
When the page is ready it checks the jform on this called source
What is the value in it puts it in here and our first function obviously I'm using
A random function name generator as you can see and it's
Start with V and the next one would be VW and so on and so on and
Ok so that means you need to now to see how we implement this function hiding and
Showing of the source you would search for the V function by
just adding a bracket there and search ok so it's the first function
And I'm basically saying is it set if it's set
Then I I add a source constructor and if it's a
In array is this an array checking the value whether it's in array
If it's not an array I put it into a temporary array here we go let me see
There we push it into the temporal array
And if it is an array and it isn't set we just create a blank array then
We do a validation here and again this you can go check
So basically the function is that one
So let's check that function and all that function does is it checks is it 2
If it's 2  it returns true if it's not 2 it returns false so you see it's quite simple
And the value whether true or false is returned to source we put source into
if its true then we close that View
Sorry we get the closest class called
Control group and we check is this field required if it's
required and these are some homeworks that we do now if it's false then we hide it
And there's also if it's required we do some house cleaning so that is simply
Quick looking at the code which is being generated just by this one switch
This is not the only code there is another place and that is in the
view itself so we can go to view and then preacher no wait we are looking at sermon
Then template and edit and then from around
Here we have JavaScript again and again of a we have on
Keyup for source or on change because I'm not at the system doesn't know is this a text field or
Or is this a list field or what is it so we have these two check function on it and also
Let me see
There is another place where source is gonna be used for another
Functions just focusing on this one and so it gets the value and it runs That Function
Which is in our JavaScript file so here's the JavaScript file there is the function so it's reusing the same Function
The moment that there is a key up or a change on that specific field so
That's what I've done obviously other developers who are more advanced in JavaScript than I am get's
Involved I could show them where in component builder The Script is being generated and we can
Improve this dramatically I am not that good at JavaScript and in fact I I feel like a
Most probably a little bit resource-intensive here but this is the best I could do
so far and obviously if we can improve it and if you know how to improve this then you
Welcome to get involved and GitHub and start with a discussion on improving this infrastructure
I can tell you that this infrastructure is done in the compiler
of course and I can show you exactly on which line This was developed you know built
In fact all you need to do is when you compile your component just a if we
Go back to components close this
Ok here we're inside a component all you need to do to know where that is being built it's just tick this to yes
And then it will add in the in the comments it will add a line
Line reference of where that specific script is being built ok
Let's go back to the admin views we're not really finished so this is
Structure that you can use to actually manipulate the conditions upon which field should show or not show
And I I really think we have done a very good implementation here
It gives you so much of its possibilities of structuring and training and
Working with fields in its relationships if you want to not use this and just
Use the on show then that is also gonna work just as well if fact I think it will work better the only problem on
Show is that it doesn't actually provide the ability to target as
A text field like we have here where you can add a keyword and say OK if they if it types in his for example
then immediately this other field will show up which is it
Excellent feature I mean I don't think you can get that kind of intricacy with
With the show on option and furthermore It cannot look at multiple other fields
If they have certain values and if it evaluates true then only show the other field
Those kind of controls are not yet available in the show on implementation as far as I know and
Yes I possibly would like to get involved on the get repo of Joomla and see
If we can add these nice features but for now we have add them to Component Builder
And in component builder you can implement these and we are writing the JavaScript to manage this
For you ok so that is your conditions for fields
So we've looked at all of these the next one is basically the list of the fields that you have already
selected and click save you will show a list of all the fields that you've selected again any of those
Fields if you wanna update them you could just click on the field name in all take you to the field and you can update it
The Next tab is a place for you to add custom CSS that is just related to the specific
View so you can add CSS here which is for the edit view or the
Single View and you can add CSS here which is for the listview or the
Multiple views plural and then it will be
Placed in his prospective places the same goes with the JavaScript accept that you have four
Places to Target instead of just one if remember we when we looked at the way that we are
The building the JavaScript there is a file a JavaScript file which just has JavaScript
For the view and then there is the footer area which is under the HTML and PHP
At the end of the file there is a whole area which is just JavaScript at the footer of the file
And so we decided to add the option of adding JavaScript to the file
Or JavaScript to the footer of the view or the file sorry the view file or the view footer or
Views file or the views footer so it just gives you the option of targeting
You now listen this script can run is a function and I just wanted to be able to be on the page
Then you add it to the file and then if you wanna use the function you can add it to the footer that
it's up to you Ok then there is a PHP area and here you have the option of adding
Adding JavaScript to your editing View
Primarily so if we look at editing views the moment you click on
Add JavaScript it opens a tab and now the way that we want to implement
Ajax is Primarily
Via the controller and method implementation
So if I explain that to you the component has a controller called Ajax
Dot Json PHP you can open there
Then it has a model
But we just called Ajax ok so you have a controller and you have a model now the controller is
Like the gatekeeper he first does a few checks and balances to ensure that the data is
Correct that that the token is right that if you have set this to be
Validating whether he is a user then it also checks that there's a user ID
If you have said it that it doesn't require them to be a user it basically would drop off this validation I will show you that
in a moment so that you can follow me
there is a controller area and then there's some model area and the model is
Basically a place where you can write a method
Which is queried from the controller so you can see in the controller it basically is getting the
Ajax model and then it is querying a method in that model called Dropbox so here
We are querying the Dropbox method and it's getting the view
Name there it seems that I'm
I'm not even really using it just make sure the moment I'm not in
Even using this variable but it's none the less it is here and I possibly will use it later
If it becomes necessary so I'm basically just activating this method to run
And when this method runs it Triggers some Global methods to run and
On the return of that value it Triggers another local method so again I'm not
Trying to teach you PHP here all I want to show us that this part of
The code was custom written so if we go back to our component you'd see that there is that code
So when you click on Ajax you add that name
Basically writing a method make sure that it's set to public and your write your
method in here and in the in Ajax input you would say ok listen that
the Task name is check Dropbox this thing the values I want to pass it is view and
Type and both of them are integers and it
Needs to run the view needs to run a Dropbox method
And the type needs to run an update dropbox and both of them should check wither it
is a user so only users can fire This back end methods and the
You can see that you have control to tick that
Obviously the
Filters are
The same as with
Any field
that you can select
And so integer here would be fine and if there's no value you said nil
This task name
Is what you be using in your JavaScript
So
I first wanted to show you the PSP side
And then the task name itself ok so let's just
Make sure I do not miscommunicate here
The method name
is set here
And that should correspond
To the method
That you set up in your
Ajax method
PHP Ajax method
Which is possibly the method in which model the data, get  the data
Structure the data and give it back to the Ajax call
So you return the data
Inside of this method
But in your JavaScript you will be using the task name
to
To get
to the
System
So if we go to the JavaScript close out
go JavaScript
What it seems I used the JavaScript example which is gonna get
Way ahead of us
But
Since we started Let me not leave you and mid air
So I like I'll have to close out here
And I'm going
Quite ahead of myself now but I need to otherwise you'll feel very lost
In summer distributor
Which is the component to which that view belongs
There is a place called Scripts
And
I have added a feature
Which is called
Chronic
Global
Events
So
I have added a feature
To add Global events
Now Global events or the way I
am implementing it
Is simply an event that should run every time
A page opens
Anytime any page in the system opens I wanted it to run the global event
Now the way I target it is I say load Dropbox Ajax
Ok
It's a
global event and it
Needs to do that
And The Drop Box Ajax
Is basically
Set up in the
Helper class
So I have a helper class
Which is called load Dropbox Ajax and it gets the document object
it takes the job document object  it adds a script declaration
to it And here is the JavaScript
That it is adding
And you see
That in that it is using check Dropbox listing
As the
Task
So it's targeting
The
Ajax
Controller
And asking
for check Dropbox listing
As the task
And it's passing to it
A token
And the view name
So possibly we would like to use that View
ID later
to log from which area this automated
Feature mostly gets
Triggered
I'm not doing that as yet
So
This is just what the script will do
So there is
j Query
Which only fired after page is loaded
And at the moment it's just adding a dummy 3 in there
to just trigger the method
And so
That is really how this script ends up on the page and I'm sorry that I used that as an example
I realise it's
A little bit
Ahead of ourselves
But
Nonetheless I I want to
Not leave it at a loose end
So I
Redoing it actually for you
That is where this PHP
Script really gonna be used
So since I need to add this somewhere I just selected a view and that
to Advantage it to this sermon view
And I added the Ajax control the concepts here
But the actual JavaScript that fires off all this
Is set to the global
Event and that means every time a back end
Area is opened
In this component
It loads that JavaScript to the view
And a JavaScript execute Ajax request which starts updating the Dropbox listing
Now I'm not gonna explain all of that Dropbox listening to you now it's a
quite an advance concept
But it's basically
Sermon distributor is able to link two
Dropbox sermons
Oh sorry
a media inside of a shared Dropbox folder
And this whole method here that be looking at
Parses that
Dropbox folder every so often
To make sure that it's
To date
That's what it's all about
So that is just looking at adding Ajax
You can see that
If you know
The Joomla API
You know that it has a get item
Method
It has a get items method in the
In the model
So in the model there's a get item method
In the editing model and in the list model there is a get items method
Then there's a get list query in the Jay model list
And there is a safe method
There's a post safe method
In the in the controller
Is allowed at
Edit method
There's a batch copy method
There's a batch move method there's a script before edit
Sorry before delete
Method
There's a script
After delete
And these are all PHP places in which you can dump custom scripting
So you wanna in the safe method
Now
Obviously again
You need to know where the safe method is
It is so if I would open
Sermon here
Scroll down
Ok so there's the get item
So you can add custom scripting to the get item method
and if I Scroll down
There's the batch
That's copy
batchmove
There is a safe method
And so if we go back here and we click on the safe method
It says here
That should run
PHP year that should run in the safe method
And then
You have the data
it's a array
And it's called
Data
So
If you look here
It means
You're able to Target that
Value
The gets placed into
Save
Ok
And I am sure that your custom
Value
Code
Will be placed in before the parents saved
But if you do not
If you do not know in any of those
Custom scripts
Where that code will be set
What you can do
is just type
It is
Loaded
Here
And then compile save it and compile the component and then go look at the code
And you see where it is showing up
And then you can add
Ok I've got all these values already
In the script
Because all that component builder is gonna do it's just gonna
Let's say
It will just say
That's that's how it will look
It'll just add to string so when the component itself runs it will treated as code
This is a comment but I mean if it was code
You just execute
So it is the way for you to add custom scripting
Right into your component
Almost anywhere really
You are able to Target
Through these switches
The post save hook
Is actually in the controller not in the model
So
You go to the
controller
Sermon
Scroll to the bottom
And you see there is a post save hook
And it basically gives you the model and it gives you the valid data and you can
Actually
can perform extra features on it
But in all these things
You you should just read
the description here it says PHP here that should run in the post Save hook method
And there's the object model is the data model Object and the erased validator is the validator
So if you just read our little note here
Then you can start coding
For it
Ok
That is so adding custom scripting
To the view
Basically the list view as well as the
Each View
And then the MySQL dump area
Which we looked at earlier
You can do two kinds of dumps now
What is this used mostly for
Well what I found while I was
Busy developing
That I would be
Busy setting up a component
and install it and then add dummy data to it to see if it works
And then every time I make a change
And I uninstall that component and install the new one
Because whatever change it made to the database
Won't be
You're not added to the database via an update
You need to uninstall the component and install it again
To get the database back to where you want it
And so
the only way I could do save myself
Time
Is to actually say listen I'm gonna
Re-install this component and the dummy data for sermons I would like to retain
And so I would go table
and I Open the tables it will show me a list of all the
Tables that are in the database at that moment
And then
I would scroll to sermon
the Sermon table
click on it
And it will load
The table and
What it should be called
In the data set
Here is some explanation if you want to do
Other tables so let's say you wanna
have it mapped to multiple tables then this is the explanation on how to
Do that
I would not recommend doing this because possibly
You will not get
What you expect
And so
Just going with the values that it populates for you
will Possibly your best call
Unless those values change
And if you are making changes adding new fields
You must realise that you need to come and reset this by clicking on something else
And then clicking on it again
And that it loads the new
list
of Fields that are related to this table
To this
Back end view Table
And that way
When you compile the component
then component builder will actually grab the data
From the database and build a dump file for you
Now that is one way of doing it
I might be a little bit complex but it is saved
Tons of hours
The other way would be to just do a dump file itself
So you'd go to
Your
Your MySQL
you would open the specific
let's Use this thing
that is Smaller
Field types
And you click on
Export
And then you would select
A sequel format
And click go
And this will create a dump file
Of all the data in the table
And you can basically
Paste that dump file in here
Now
I was looking at
Important
So you click export
click quick
Then SQL and then Go
And then just save it
Then
Go to that file
Open it
And having it open
You just replace
This
String
With
Hash
Underscore
So and then replace all
And you will not use the table
Structure because that is already in component builder
You just use
This area here
Basically you would copy
this Area
like That
Cut
Come here
paste
And click save
And that will mean that you have to dump file
And it will always be added
To your new
Install
If a dump file is way too big
You will see it by just after your clicked save come and look
At the end
And see if it cut it off somewhere
So let's say
it cut it off there that I know my dumb file is
To big for the
use
Structure
For your dump
File
I used medium text
let's see medium text
Here
Prosafe
There it is
Sequel
I used medium text
So that means
It's quite big
You can really put a lot of
Text inside of it
You wanna know exactly how much just Google it
and you will see
I'm gonna remove this obviously
because It's not related
to sermons at all
And
In fact I'm not even go to use
the dump here, save and close
Ok
That is basically setting up an admin View
I know I've run around and it seemed
quite hectic
And I possibly will redo this video at a certain stage
Try to be
Structured
But I think it is informative enough
And
if you
Have any questions please email me
and I will
Try to communicate with you
And if I see that a certain question comes up often enough
I will add it to the
Video
Possibly redoing
Specific area
Admin views
is quite intense
And we will possibly revisit many of the
Concepts that we have looked at today
Thank you for watching