Hi we've just finished with admin views and we now would like to start
looking at advanced field types now there are a few advanced field types and the one there
Is most advanced is the one called custom field type so I'm gonna sort this
Here by custom Fields it's that one
And you see it in This moment we have quite a few custom fields in place
Now let's look at two of those one is the local file
List the other one is let's do a sermon sermon one but let's first look
Look at the local file list you'd see that basically from there
All the way down to there is simply PHP
So I'm creating a view which is most basically
Taking information if you know PHP from the global settings of your component so there
need to be a field with a name local folder in your Global settings will still look at how to set up
Global settings when we get to component and if it hasn't got a
Setting it falls back onto the image which is in the Jpath root
For your component this will be replaced with your component name and it puts it into local folder
And then I just start the options and
The options array which you gonna return and the first thing I add to it is a Please select a
File add files oh yes if there isn't files
It will say please add files to and it will give the local folder name if
There is files we gonna update those then over here so first we bring in
the File system classes from Joomla then we
Basically check whether that folder exists and if it doesn't exist we create it
That's just in the field type now once it's created and if it exists it obviously
skips this doesn't go in there and it just starts by grabbing all the files
And from that folder and place it into files and then start something array
Where it Loops the files and put it into options and
By doing that we are basically let me just check here and make sure
we're adding the file name and the file name
To our options array and then returning the options array so you can add your own custom PHP
Scripting in the when you extend a listview so the list sorry list field were
Extending list field so it's just gonna be a drop down list of all the files in that specific folder
either images or the folder that it was set globally in local folder OK so that's your setting up
a folder now there is a field type
Called filelist I think Ya there it is the reason why I didn't
Use filelist is because finalist has a static directory to where
You need to add the files so that you can view them and we wanted
To have it be able to rename the file folder sorry the folder
For the files for the media do anything and then have it update itself automatically so that's why we then created a
Custom field where we extended the list type and let me just refreshed this
to get that Detail back so we chose a custom field and then
We just extend the list type and we don't want it to have a
You button because you it won't work you will just break and we don't want them to select
Multiple oh yes we are allowing them to select multiple now since we are using multiple
We need to go back and make sure that we are storing it as a Json so the Json is when have
Multiple or erase any kind of arrays in a value you need to store it as a Json
And the component builder itself will check if it is a multiple
Selection is true it will automatically store it in a Json object even if you forgot to select this
So we have got some things in place to sort of ensure that it's system
Behaves as expected Ok let me see that's just quick view on
Doing a local file custom field as a local file now
Which I'm sure you all if you've been waiting for is let's look at how
How to create a sermon preacher custom field so basically it's a Preacher custom field
So what is this field gonna do it's gonna show a list of preachers
But is gonna basically display the preachers that are set up in the preacher listview ok so let's
Open that so let's see the convention
Is that you would call that type preachers that's the listview name
But you'd called the name you would use the same as the editing
Name which is preacher without the s so if you go back to your admin views you would
Use this name as the name of the field but you would use that name as the type
You see because you now creating a custom type and the logic behind it is it it's gonna show
A list of preachers but you gonna select just one preacher ok so that's just the logic the label
You can really put whatever you like whatever is descriptive enough for your user to understand
And then there's a place for adding a description then here we are set
Multiple to false we want them to only be able to select one preacher at a time
default zero these are all basically left to their default values and
Extending list is the most common custom field that we have if you wanna
Receive a list of custom Fields that is available you can go up here to extend and you see that list
Radio and check boxes are available I think I should update that too also say users
User is also a user option to extend users
If you want to see if we are what is available then look at that name
Jform field and go to component builder go to the
Back end of component builder so that would be administrator components component builder
Then go to compiler that's a folder then go to Joomla 3
Which is the current version we are targeting and then search for that
Jform there's it is Jform so
Ones that are available to extend let's see
it's the user Jform field user you must it must Jform field
So JForm field user Jform field radio Jform field list
Jform field checkboxes this also means if there is a form field you
Want to extend that doesn't exist already in our advanced
Seminar will show you how to add your own form Fields here there is basically two places
you need to Change I wish I could tell you now one of them would be to add the field and update it accordingly
And the other one would be to add it in a few places in the code
And also in a Jason file called settings there so those are
Some of the things we will deal with in advanced adaptation of component Builder
We will still set up that series very soon it's not finished yet though ok
Getting back to extending a listview sorry listfield you Simply
There list ok then there's also a few
conventions one of them being that if you are gonna be targeting like this
Example we are targeting the preachers you will be using the preacher
Table as the table that is being targeted so the question to ask
Is where is the data gonna be found that is the table
That needs to be added in which component is it gonna be found and that is what need to be added by
component now the reason why we have this hash hash hash component here
Because it's a placeholder which component builder will replace with the components code name
Once it's built it's a It's a feature we add it because some times
We want to rename components and if you had statically added
The actual component name there then you have to and every field go and update that name and in every
view go and update that name and you know every where were you actually statically the added the component's name
You will need to update it but to explain to you exactly what the system
Is doing I can go to components open sermon distributor
And then take the name a in code like that copy
And see that it's under underscore C if it was an uppercase
sorry not Underscore lowercase if it was a uppercase like that it mean
It would mean that you have to place this  the component
Name as well with an uppercase so you would do just a s lowercase
so that is actually what the system is doing it actually is
Just replacing these these Place holders with the with the actual component name on
Fly so using the placeholders basically saves you time in the long run
Prompt making changes everywhere if you make a change to components name
Which is quite normal to do very often you start with the component in his think of calling it something
and later Realized that name is actually been used in the Joomla repository and you need to choose another
And to do that is gonna affect the whole component and so we added this
Placeholder structure which should make a data less painful at least anywhere
in all the code custom coding that you're adding and you need to use the components name
You can simply use this hash tag format of replacement
In some areas you would need to use brackets like that
But most of the time it will work either way the best
Measure to to ensure is to try it with a hash's is first and
If you go into the code and you see it didn't replace it then you know it's the angle brackets that needs to
be used anyway so in this case we are using these hash hash signs
symbols sorry characters and then the view again that is this
Single variable of the view so if we were to close this and go to the view
Which would be then preacher or lowercase
Is what you would be adding here make sure that it's always lowercase
And then the listview or the views plural would be
The add value there or lowercase as well and then the value field
Is the field that the user will see so that is what is visible
in the UI user interface the key field is the
Value that will be stored in the database now these field relate to this table so in
Inside the table what field do you want the user to see now that would be the name of the preacher
And inside the table What field would you want to store
In the other database because we are looking into preacher but we gonna store it
Wherever this field is being used right so that would be the ID and
The column name in that data base of that view where this field will be used will be called
Preacher so to show that to you in the database itself can open it there
Scroll down to sermon distributor open sermons
click on structure and here in the back end
let's close this go to
Sermons new
And we will see that there is a place for preacher
If I was to look with firebug for it we'll see that it is basically
The name is preacher and remember we spoke about this J4_  as the ID
But it's actually Simply the preacher field which is being stored directly in
In the database in the preacher
Column of the table and it's stored as integer 11 and that
It was set up here right integer 11 and we say that it is a key so we can Target it
So here at the bottom if we look at in indexes we'll see that it
Has actually added it is a key and we go ok so that
All is done right here in the database structure and then in this area
Now again in this part which you can add your own custom PHP
The fact that I'm using 19 18 17 it's just sort of creating
Line breaks and spacing and tabs for me dynamically I could have placed them
All just under PHP one with without this
Quotation marks you know
Wrapping around them all like we just did with the  file folder list View
Just a note inside of this code you cannot
These quotation marks you need to
Use single quotes unfortunately at this stage it is not able to
accommodate you even if you try to do an Escape it will not behave as it's as you might expect
So my apologies for that at this stage you can only do single
Quotes between these two quotations...double quotes
Ok so that is adding a custom field which is a little bit more advanced
If you know PHP you will know exactly what's happening here again these Place holders
reflect back to these values here so basically A dot  ID will be written there
and the Text value which is the field value is gonna be called a dot name
Name and then ID and code text this code
Is build-up by the view that we are in and the text so this would read
Preacher sorry sermon preacher in in in the code and in fact
I can go show you how it looks when it builds it it's quickly look at that
So the show you where it starts let's open that
Field list so that is what it starts with basically it replaces this place holder
With your code ok and it replaces all these features
Up here as well
And updates that and
So every where you see these things
It's gonna be updated through component builder
And obviously everything up here will be replaced with your licensing tags
.
Then now let's look at the
Finished product
Sermon
it's placed on the modules field
and there it is preachers
Open it
You see that it added preacher there
And in the input
Add it and it also shows you
Where if you had trip that switch like we have explained
to show the line numbers in your component
It shows you in what file
These files
are found
Under
The
You go to component builder
under helper's
Compiler
there are these files that is
Being used to compile your component
.
I'll possibly when we go to the advanced section I'll go much more in-depth
in Regards to
These files
Now we just trying to get across how to build a component
Not to extend
Builder itself as yet
But at least here you can see where in the code it is actually building this
and compiling this
and Putting it together
And
Remember we talked about
It's it's
Getting
The structure let's
Go down
this is used for
the button
This is to generate a new button
when you
Can click on new
Basically that is the
Button there ....this area
from there to There is generating the button
This is what controls whether the button should show up or whether it shouldn't then
And even if it is to be set at all
Ok so this is basically what generates the button...this area
This area here the get options
You see we said that it will show the name
And it will show ID
And so
Go back to our
Structure here
It basically we dynamically replaces these with those
The reason for it is it's actually done a few times
And I felt like ok let's let's make it that you only need to update these values
And then if you get update gets updated all over in the
Bottom of the code
And it makes it just much more easy to
To change your custom
Fields
So it
Build a field called preacher name
Which again it uses here as a object value
Because it
Retrieves the object
From the database
and it looks as if that object
exists
it actually reiterates
And builds up
option list
Which is returned to use in the drop down
So it dynamically generates your list
and so component builder through that infrastructure through what I
Just explained here
Actually compiles all of that code for you
And puts it in the right file in the right place and all of that
And obviously once you build a component and you know where you have made those changes in
Builder
You can go look at those files
If you know how to build a Joomla website
I used the same conventions as decor
In regards to implementation
Of your files
Ok
At the moment we are only pulling values that are published
This is what it is all about
That is the custom fields
I feel like I am
Maybe just
Mumbling on without purpose so let's get out of this one
I think we can quickly look
At this
One which is this manual file list
Dropbox
This one is much more advanced
What we are dealing with here
Is a file
That actually
Is stored if I look here in it
What I did is I created a function in my component
Global helper function
Called get Dropbox links
it tells it that it
wants manual links
And it passes a
Specific
variable
And it would return a bunch of links
And those links it will check if it exists
Check the array not only that it is an array but it actually has values in it
And if it does it actually just backs it into the
Options
And gives it
Over to
The options array to the list
Now
This part here
Means that you can in your
Custom field types
You can add a helper
Static
Method call
If you know what those two symbols there mean
It means it's a static method
Being called
From a class
Now this class is something that if you
know the Joomla API and know how to work builder component
You will know that
You can add to any component what is known as a
Component Helper class
Now
If I was to go to summon distributor
The component helper class is always
Located
In
The helper
Folder of
The admin as well as the site View
The admin is then in the back end in which
Administrative components
And then
There is the component
And there is it's helper
Folder
And the front end  you have the same convention
componant
sermon
distributer
And there is the helper
Structure
Ok and here is some of the
Java
Script the
Components sorry which sermon distributor structures
Through it's helper structure
There is the
Helper file for the front
And here
helper file
For the back
How to add methods
Do they already
Helper files
Have you don't want to know what all the custom helpers is
That we ship
With all components
You can open component Builder
You can go to the compiler
Sorry compiler not controller
Go to Joomla 3
And then look for the helper file in the site helper file
If you open it
You see whole lot of helper methods obviously with a lot of Place holders
Which we will
Customised for each
Component
so that it Targets that component
And you see there's a Json to string method here that's to get bars
there's a get bar singular
This is just to get one variable from the database we don't need to always to rewrite
.
This whole string
To get just one variable
You can actually come and
Look at how this works and use this
To get a variable from the database
We also have is published to
Check if a
Specific
Object is published
I get actions
But again
This is way beyond the scope of
Just looking at custom
Fields
We will go into great depth into all the features of a helper structures
That when we deal with advanced concepts
But I'm just giving you a heads up so at least you can start looking at it and
Possibly get yourself going
We are I wrote these
Functions check object check array check string
Check Json
Shorten
Merge arrays
Save string
And
Escape HTML
Replace numbers this one I'm using
quite often
You know if you basically do
Save string
We change every number in the string immediately
to
Text
So that you can be sure whatever you get back from safe string
Doesn't have numbers in it
This is sometimes quite necessary in fact
All the time
Especially if you don't know if there might be a number is that
First
Character might be a number
This way we are insuring that
it Always
It's actually text
Ok so there is just a whole bunch of
Custom
Methods that we ship
With all components that are developed so if you were to
Open
Like I have said
Sermon Distributors
Custom
Sorry
Helper
class
You see that these helper classes are now
all Showing up here
get actions
Shorten string merge array
So you can come and any of you feel that the methods that I have to used here is archaic or
Outdated
Please go on the forums at Github and talk with me about it
All very gladly look at it
and see
I know I recently tried to improve on this check
String
By doing
That
So I could actually dump
The part and
Save on
the Query
But
For some strange reason
This started
Causing problems
All over and strings that were strings were being returned as not being
strings
But what I can tell you is that
I
Obviously
Went back to the old
School way of doing it
which is This way
I don't know
There might be an easier way
Obviously we first one to ensure
That it's set
That actually
This value is set
And then it is string and then it actually has a length you see something can be a string and yet don't have a length
I might be wrong on that and yet this is what I found
I've only been coding and PSP for 3 years now so
I'm definitely
You get teach me a few things
You been at it longer than I am
Ok
Back to the UI
That is where I get these values so showing it to you
In here
Go up a bit
Says get Dropbox links C
Now
We see that
Has this thing of return
Which is set to false
Now that means if I only was to say
That it should return the manual
Values
Then it will only return the value manual links
But since I've said it
to 2
It will actually return all of those links and not just
One of them
Ok so because you can actually target that it returns
One specific sermons link
So this method is
Quite dynamic
And that's all that I'm calling
In in this
Advanced
Field type
Which is called custom field
And it gives me a link of all the
Sorry an array of all the links
Which I didn't just load like I have explained
Ok so that is again as you can see quite
Advanced implementation of this
Custom fields
And
Obviously
As you
As I hope you would realize
Is there you can do anything
You can with that list conception
You could even grab a bunch of website names from somewhere
You can put any PHP in there and build a list which can be used
To save to the database
Ok let's see that would be the custom
Custom Fields there's also one called custom user
Now the custom user at the moment it doesn't look like I have any
in the demo data
for you
So I just click on new
And then select
Custom user
And
You'd see that the custom user basically
You don't need to set or changed
Change anything
From
Here to there
All those should actually just work
the only parted you might want to consider removing
Would be
The
PHP
This part here
Basically what this part does
Is it limits the
The user list
To only a certain
Group
That means again you need to set up a global
Value in your component
Field
In your
Global
remember we talked about that previously
Basically the options button
If you click on options
It Opens a Place which you said Global these are all
Global values this is a
Area for Global
Values
Now
You can get hold of those Global values through the component helper
Getparams with a component
Name
And get
When there you would place the field name
So that's how you can get a value from your Global settings
And basically I'm getting a specific
Groups value and placing it in here
And then I am
Returning that group that's all this part is doing
In fact
Those two sections are actually independent
So this one
Is what helps you
Set
Ok I wanna just return a specific group
This part
Helps you
Set
Any users you want to exclude
Now this specific feature here
Ensures that only one record per user is set so let's say a user has already been
Added to a previous record
Then
That user should not show up again
It should be removed from the list
So this is what this
PHP is doing
It's simply looking to this current View
And checking if the
If there is users and getting their ID's
And then setting them
Up in the correct manner
They are unique
And then returns them
So
Those are the users that already have
So if you are building something
Which are supposed to
To have
Student details for example
You don't want a
Student to have more than one
Entry in that table right
You want every student to just have one in
And so if a student already is selected
You wouldn't want them to be selected again that's what this
Exclude feature Actually does
How to show that to you in the code
Let's go to
Another project that I am
Working on called learning manager and modules
And they have a
Field Called student
Student users and user
Now
There are two kinds of
Ways to
To do this
One is to not
Allow more than one user
To have an entry
And then you would basically
The one is saying ok exclude users that already have been used
So that means if a user have been selected that whole thing that I've just explained
The other one
Actually returns null which means it will always show all users
And the way to have it set this to null
Would be simply to remove
That part
Of your
Of the code
Then it will automatically set
This value to null
Now when I gets about the group part it's the same principle
If you don't want it to just show a specific group
You can actually it will also be set to null
like That
And component builder will do that
And all you need to do is simply remove
What is part of the code
And then it will actually
And so
That is true
Target a specific group
And also to Target
Or to remove specific users
So let's say
That
You want to remove users that
Belongs to other
Table or other structure then all that PHP that you need to write
You can place on the
Type
phpx
So you could do
like That
type phpx1=
All your PHP can be placed
for excluding
And
For the group
It's simply
sorry not
Directly one
You can just
Take that
And
This one will be used
For the groups that actually says it there
Getexcluded method
PHP for the get group
And in the code
Which is stored under Fields models
You see what it will do so you can do things and then come and look
What did component builder build
How does it
Look
Then you can actually go to the view
like we have here
And see does it's actually work is the preachers showing up
And then you can use firebug
like That
And you can look ok so
That one is
Index
Here is a select list
And here you have the values
So that's the ID
And that is the actual name of the speaker
and the ID and the name
So that is how it should
Display the data in
Component Builder
Sets up the XML structure that Joomla uses
to build this actually
Joomla is Building this whole structure
For you
So even this nice button and everything
is Joomla's handiwork
It is doing that
For you
And
This is all done through these
XML
Input values that you are adding here
So you would change the type to
You might say staff members
Oh yes there is something to
To remember here
The type names
May not have under scores
Or any spaces in them
Fact anything that is not translatable
Usually needs to be
you know
Not not have any underscores
Sorry not have any spaces
So you can't do this
That would it will just not work
So you must
Remove the underscore
You can do that but that's
Sort of
I Think it will be made lowercase anyway
So you could just
And then it will work because that is used not only
In the file
Database but it's also used in the name convention
and Everywhere this file type
So as you can see
In here
That file type is called studentusers
And even the file is
called that
And here it is called
Student user and here it is called student user
And this one is with the s
that one with a s in the file is also with a s
So you can see that that that specific name type
Name
Is used everywhere
And you cannot have underscores
In this class name
Neither in this type name
You know maybe you can but
So far my experience is that it doesn't work
If you do
Have it
So for some reason it
It doesn't work
So that's just a heads up on
Naming of this type
And so you can update these Fields they are mostly
Feels that are
Sort of
Related
To all the other fields
But this one specifically says extends user
Ok so it actually
Shows you how it's gonna extended
So if you removed all the PHP then this field as it is now
Whould show all users evertime
Ok
So let me just
Close out here
That is looking at the advanced field type called
User
Custom user
Another one we need to look at is the repeatable fields
Repeatable fields is actually not that difficult
But you need to understand how it's sort of structure
You need to first create the fields that you want to repeat
Inside of repeatable fields
The way repeatable field structure looks
In Joomla
I mean
When we look at it
in the actual application let me
See where did I used a repeatable field
OK here we have one
So this from there
all the way to there is one repeatable field
And
If you know a little XML and you worked with repeatable Fields you'll see that
Here is the
The fields that are being repeated
Inside
of the  Repeatable field
So basically repeatable field is a field type that has
Other Fields inside of it
Now you don't need to write any of this
The way you would
Structure a repeatable Fields actually
Very very simple
You first create the fields that you want to
Repeat
And do realize you can't use repeatable fields in repeatable fields
But you can use custom advanced fields in repeatable fields
So if you look at that
We have here again
You see there is a field type called cause and risks
Now you if know Joomla
You know there is no such field type cause and risks
So that means this is a custom field so if I were to go to fields
You see that there is a field called here cause
Cause and risks
And it basically
Get set information
From
From this database table
This is another component
That I've done with component builder
And it
Is
Displaying
those data also making some model changes to the data
And adding some
Some style to it
nonbreaking space and stuff like that
Ok so that is that is just dealing with
the Cause and risks
So looking again at our repeatable field
You're able to add an advance custom field
Inside of it
But what you need
To add it
Is let's
Open
Females
For our example
As you need to have the field ID
And you need to order it according to
the order you want to displayed in the
Line
Where you do repeatable fields
So if we If we close here and then
we go back to
Creating a new admin view and I click on fields
You see that there is 1 2 3 4 5 6
7 8 9 10 11
12 13
Fields
In one row
And if I click next and they all appear again
And if I click next they all appear again
And that's what repeatable Fields really is about
Now this structure these Fields if we
Would you look at it how did I develop
This specific
Pop-up
Repeatable
Structure well I can show that to you
Here is a list of all the repeatable fields that I've already built
This three pages of 20
If we were to click on add
Files
No wait we were lookingat add
Fileds let's see add fields add fields
There it is addfields for views
Open that
So this is the repeatable field for adding fields for
Views
And all you see here as I'm saying ok you could add 800 fields it way over kill
But ok
And we call him the button
Add
So if we go back to
the view
See it says add
And then I'm adding an ID in a class to it
A description which if we were to hover over it
Here
It has a little setup fields for this view
Which is the description
Same there see
And the label is fields
So it says
There fields
And
Then the icon is list
Now the icon
Is what is shown in the button
That is a list
All the custom Joomla icons
are
You can can be used
How to know these icons you should go to let me see
There is a URL
Docs.joomla.org
/
J3.x: Joomla_Standard_Icomoon_
fonds there you go
That is the URL
And you'll get to this page
And
These are all the available icons
And you basically use that
that part
well this part
So if I wanted to checkmark-circle
Copy checkmark-circle
And I would
Sorry in here
Simply
The icon
Change that to
checkmark-circle
Ok
So that's how you change the icon
And then these are Simply the ID's
Of the fields I want
Inside of the repeatable field
Ok
And so if I was to
Show you where to get the ID
It simply would be close close your
Repeatable field
And you'd see the ID is next to the fields there on the right
So you would create
The the
Repeatable field that you o sorry
The fields that you wanna use in the repeatable field
And you would get a list of those ID's jotted down so maybe somewhere a Notepad or something
Just add them in the
In the order that you want them to be
Added
And then inside of your repeatable field
You would simply
Pasted in the fields
Area with a comma separating them
And then component builder will
Dynamically
Construct this whole structure
For you
And add it
To your
Component
I think it's really Stunning and I hope you enjoy using
the repeatable fields
Structure
I know it's little buggy still and there's a lot of talk about it not being as
Stable
But you're more normal basic Fields like text Fields and radio Buttons and so forth they all work
Well now the only thing about the radio buttons that use that you use in
In the in the
in the repeatable fields
You need to remove the class
Of your radio button
So It cannot be a button
It must be a dot
Unfortunately it still they don't
Yet make it possible to
actually load  the button
Now what's the difference
Well the difference is let me see if I can quickly show you
That is the button
version
Of a radio button
Ok
And
That is the
Dot version
Of the radio button
And it doesn't look like a button
And so in your repeatable Fields you cannot use the button version
It needs to be this one
And what makes it a button is obviously the class
That is
Being added to the field
So you need to remove the class
uh
Values
From your radio button
If it's gonna be used in the
Repeatable field
But anyway if you forgot
To do that and you compile your
component
And now you looking at the repeatable field you'll see that the radio button is
You know that it's not working
That it is messed up
Until they possibly fix it
This is unfortunately the case
Ok that is looking at advanced field
Sorry fields
called custom Fields custom user fields
As well as repeatable fields
These are really the advanced field types that there are
The other thing that I wanted briefly mentioned let me see how long if we already been
At this
Ok see this is getting a little long
So
Let's move
What I wanted to share to a later topic
Thank you for watching