Hi
We've looked at setting up admin views we've looked at
Creating fields for admin views
We've looked at setting up field types and how to use field types to create fields
Now we would like to look at
Setting the admin views to the component
Obviously the component itself has so much things that you can do
I'm gonna try and
Deal with it
Little at a time
So I'm first gonna just look at adding
The
Admin views to a component
Ok so
We'll go to components
And will go to sermon distributor
And you would go to settings
Here you'd see
Admin views
So to connect admin views to your component and you need to go to settings and open this button here
Usually when you start it will look like this
So very straight forward
You have a drop down here
And you make a selection selection
And then click next
And you do the next one
And if you have a lot of Admin views like I Do here
You would
Type in the name of the admin View
And there you have it
So I'm gonna type in the name here sermon
Now these icons here I spoken about them previously
They are the icons from Joomla
Which is called I think I let me just look
Standard
Icomoon font
Ok so it's this
This font here
Now
If you select a
an icon here
It'll show you that little icon but only during the selection face
So
That is the icon
That is gonna be used
For the view
Here in the right
See this icon there
As we click through
Component Builder
It updates that icon
Ok so this icon
Is what is being set here
Now you can select the icons to
Reflect
to the admin view of your choice
Now we have a bunch of switches here and I'll look at them one at a time
Now admin menu
Is basically this menu
So the question is do you want that View to show up next to your main
View
I'll be the first
Tick box
So we would say yes
Then
Do you want to have an add record
Icon
For this view
Now the add record icon if you go to the dashboard
Is this
This icon here
Basically a shortcut to creating an admin View
From the dashboard
So
Will say yes
Then
A dashboard list of records icon
So maybe you don't want this icon just a Add new
Then you can tick that as no
But again here we would like yes
Then a submenu
Now the submenu if you've opened
Your
View that has a submenu here that can collapse away
Now this submenu
You can add this view
To the sub menu or not
Then
auto check-in
Is a
Little tweak that I've added to to my Joomla components and I'm possibly gonna
Make a pull request to add it to Joomla itself
What
auto check-in does
Is it Adds a feature to your component
Since you see I have clients that complaint
That some people will open an item
And then in the browser click back instead of clicking clothes
And that will keep the item locked out
to that
Individual
And so others cannot access it on less they have admin rights to check it back in
So we created an auto check-in
Now auto check-in checks
Whether this item has been checked out longer than a set period
and ever it has been it checks it in automatically know that set period Is
Something that the administrative sets in the global settings of the component
I'll show you that later
Just that you know
You can add auto check-in to a view
By either saying yes or no here
Then keeping history of a
Backend view
Now the history component I must tell you is maybe one of them most exciting things that I could integrate
You see what it does is it keeps track of every change you make
In any article or any item in your application
So for example
If I was to go to
Let's just look at just a moment
To a Preacher
And I would open up this acapella music
You'd see that it has that version button here at the top
No if I was gonna make a change here let's say I typed in
Info@vdm
And I set
Some text here
And I clicked save
And then I clicked on version
You see that it's now locked a new version
And there are the old ones
And I could click on one of the old ones and click Well
First let me say I could take the one I'm on currently
And I get say keep
That would sort of lock it in because
You can also set how long How long How long amount of History should the system keep
The default is 10, 10 changes so I can click on the previous version and say restore
And this will restore it and you see there
Email address is gone and this description is gone
If I want to go back to the one I have done I could just click there on version again
I then click there and also restore
And
Now
We would see wow
The details are Back Again
That is the feature of history now history component is actually a Joomla extension
Which
You're able as a application to the component developer
Integrate into your own
Components
And it's not that easy in fact it's maybe very
Difficult
If I was to show you the amount of code let me do that
That you need to write
First of all you need to add
An asset ID to all your
Backend view database tables
So if we were to go to
sermon distributor
And check our wait this is the
Frontend let's go to the backend
And we check out it's sql table so we'll click on that
You'd see that all of them have asset_ids
Now
That is
Really not as easy as it is
Once you've got the asset_id
Then in your model
When you basically save
Sorry not in the model
I think it is in table
When you start your table you should set up observers
The check
The specific
Item to add history options
to
to that
Asset_id
So this is this is part of the whole
Part of the script that is being add this is being added on the right place
As well as in the store method
There is another
Tweak which I
might take too long to look at all of that
Will go into more detail in the advanced courses I suppose
But just let you know
I create an import export method
And even in the import and export of data actually
Primarily in importing of data
You need to again
Do a quite advanced trick to ensure that the history of that I can will still be tracked
and these kind of features I just added dynamically to your component because of that switch
No that's not the only code the code that really throws people out I suppose
Is this script code
and this is if Script that is used
When the component installs
So if you look at this
This is the uninstall area in the script code
Which runs when you uninstall the component and it's looking in many places it's looking in content-type it's
Looking in the content
Tag map
Is looking in the ucm base
Looking in the content types again and per view I mean
This is not just
Once off per view these checks are done and we are removing any items
That might remain there
Because when you uninstall a component
What you don't realize
Is it so integrated into the Joomla system that just removing it's on tables actually doesn't do the job
So we added the feature that if you uninstall it actually cleans the Joomla system of that extension
Completely which is ideal because you won't want any traces left you you would like to uninstall something
You want it gone
And so this uninstall method does exactly that
And then with the installing of this component we
get here which is the postflight install
We actually add
Many records to
Areas inside of Joomla so for example
Inside of the let me see
the contents type
We we need to add this information
And we have to do it for every view which you've selected
either tags or
History
We'll look at the tags in the category concept
Just a little bit
Later
Just to get a heads up and I realize this is not the place for it
But let me just say we will look at that OK so let me continue
Ok content types as you see we are adding it for the
Sermons we adding it for the series's we're adding it for the statistics and for the help documents
And that is when we install their component we are needs to add
You not seeing the whole picture let me scroll a bit look at that
String that needs to be
Written and
Added to the database
Of these specific areas
To create that integration where it will track the object change and just do it automatically
So all this is generated by component Builder
And then when you do an update now here is the issue
When you do an update and you're adding a new
Field
to I view
This update will make sure that that specific field also will get tracked
So what it first does
Is it gets the data it tries to see whether it already exists if it exists
It means it's here
It just updates it
If it's been for some reason removed
It then inserts it
So that is the update method
The update method also takes care of the little lot of discrepancies
Because as you develop your extension now
These two faces to development
The one fase when you're busy building it and no one else in the world that has it
That's very easy face in fact then you don't really use this nice feature
You just uninstall it and reinstall it every time until you happy with what you see
But then once you put it out in the public you can't just step up your database structure without
The needed scripting for others to do a easy upgrade
Because they already got data in the database there can't just uninstall and install
That's that's ridiculous
No component builder has a way for you to actually address that
Well obviously because I have to deal with it and I don't wanna have my clients complain
So I added a feature which will look at it inside of component Builders component area
and I'll explain it in detail but just that you know this part of the update feature you making use of
You're a specific integration to keep track of your
Backend view changes
To items is in Place already
Written by component Builders telling you here
On which line it was done
If you have that switch trip
Ok so that is just giving you a quick glimpse into the code
Of
A little switch
Sorry
a Little switch called
Keep history
So this weeks does all that for you for this specific View
Then
Depending on whether you gonna use this views information on the front end as your main base for your
For your page you might wanna add
Metadata
The metadata is I know isn't that
Useful anymore but you know what
Although Google and others are maybe ignoring it
It still plays a role to making a page
Very search engine optimised
Component Builder
If
If you do your homework and you do things right
In relationship to implementation of your metadata
You'd see that it actually adds tremendous good features to
Do your front end of your site
So I would suggest that you add
Metadata when you are gonna use a specific area to the front and when we start looking at us setting up the site
Views
You'll see this
Coming up again and
The necessity of using it
Obviously you'll be remodeling the data because you can get relationship from many databases but
You need the area in the backend to get the data right
Ok then this access switch
Might throw you out
This simply adds
The following feature
If you open an article in the open publish
It says here access
Public super registered
Which is relating to your user
Let me just close this
you user access levels
And as you know user access levels can target multiple groups into one user access level
And so this again is only a feature that will really be
Extremely useful when you look at your front end of your component and the backend you can also make use of it
Of course
You can change the access of a specific item but since we also have such a intense permissional
Switches
I hardly ever make use of it but it's there and I mostly use it for front end
When I want a certain area in the front of sorry set an item not to be accessible to the front
Ok then do you want to add to import export function again this is a
Extended area which component builder dynamically just adds so you don't need to do anything is to
relation to scripting at this stage
You could just click yes or no to import export
Feature at the top of the page
Of every View
So every View
Will have an import export at the moment it's a direct relationship import export what I mean by that
Is
You need to follow
If you export this then you'd see the the way it should look to do import
And the import is really nice you can map the headers to their specific database tables
Obviously there's work needed especially when you're dealing with
Information that was encrypted if you export it it will decrypt it if you have the permissions
To access that item of course but the problem is because it's decrypting yet
When you imported it doesn't know that it should encrypted so there is a little discrepancy with the advance
Storing methods so as long as you are having a data backend database table that at
Actually doesn't require these advance storing methods it's just your normal defaults like me explain before then
Import export method will then works seemingly
Without any problems
I'm so I'm still working on this area but it's already working well enough that I felt I could leave it in there
Ok that is the switch here and obviously if you don't like the feature just click no
Then here is a feature which I think I'm most excited about
And that is
Every backend view
Has of course and edit area right if you've selected that
Read write option then the edit area you can change the values of that backend listview right
So
The admin create site View
Means that the system
Is gonna dynamically build
The front
Area
Which you can access
To edit the data at the front of the website
Now Yahoo this is the hurray whatever that's excellent tool
So it takes exactly this if I was to use this and as an example
It takes
This editing area and place it on the front
Of your website
Now obviously
You are controlling in the permissional structures who has access to edit this who access to edit this
The status was access to edit specific fields
We looked at adding the fields to your admin views and you could tick
Whether this field should have permissional structure
Now
That means that
If you have those things set up in the back in the
Global professional tab
Then it will be implemented in the
Front if a certain user is in the in the correct group
They wont be able to access this then if they have access but they don't have the right to for example update
Maybe the modified date or
The status is then in the front there also will not be able to do that so you have
Immense control over who can do what
But at the same time you have the ability to actually edit items on the front I think that is
Excellent
To be able to do that and that all of that just possible by saying yes
But
Realize this
The fact that it creates the
The view if I could says so
And places it on the front
Doesn't mean that there is a link somewhere to it
That is something you need to add to your site front custom site
As you develop it
And this is partly a feature therefore which is you don't know PHP and if you're not that familiar with
How to setup your links on the front of the component
You would possibly would find this difficult to implement
But I will show you
What it builds in fact I can show you that now
I have a component which I'm using that feature quite a lot
And it's called
Costbenefitprojection this is the backend
So if we look at the views we have here
called company
And we have
One called
Scaling factor and intervention
Now these are editing views as you can see those other list views those are the editing views
If I go to the front of the of the the website
and I open that component
And I click on View
You see that there is company
There is intervention and there is scaling factors
they
Are basically being extended here
So what the component build does is as is it adds this view
It also adds the module for it
And I'm also adds the controller for it
So basically it puts all the script in place so that all you need to do is inside of for example
I have here a
I have here an area called cpanel now let me show you this component briefly
Ok so this is just some dummy data that I
Placed in here none of them is real
And so here
You can open multiple items
This is all stuff that I built in component in fact none of this was built outside of component builder
It all was done in component builder
And you can click on edit advance profile
And it will open the editing area
As you can see and now this is the backend editing area of that now let me show you sorry this is the front end
Editing area
And as you can see there are all the
Tabs
Now let me show you the backend
Here's the backend area
So it's basically a showing up the same information in the front
Is only dumps the permission and
Publishing features
But that is because of access permissions is done automatically
Because that front-end user didn't have permissions to edit things
In most of the things in here in fact
You didn't have the right to edit any of these
Therefore it didn't need to see it and so the system just remove that tab same goes with the permissions
And if you didn't have the right to do scaling factors on interventions
You also have dumped that it won't show it up
In the front
And so this is the back end of that same dummy company
That I've set up
And you can see that it basically
Moved it to the front
Not only did it make it possible to edit data but also to create new companies
So if you click on that
You see it opens up in the area for you to start fresh so you can create a company from scratch
Now
In this specific example you see that it cannot actually add a user
So what the system is done through some custom scripting that I've added
If you click save it adds his ID in here
And he doesn't need to select that
Ok so that's just a quick look at
That specific button
Called edit create site view it adds the whole codebase to the front
And integrates it to the
Way that the front
Needs to be able to control the permissions
Then the order of of the items are Simply the way in which it will be displayed anywhere
So if we think about the order
For a moment here
Of
Example component builder
The order of which these icons are laid out and even if you opened one of them
The order in which this is done
And also for the sub menu
All of that is controlled with this order
Number here
Ok so
That's a quick look at adding
Admin views to your component
I hope that is insightful enough for you to understand how to do that
If you have any questions please you're welcome to send me a mail
Thanks for watching