Now that we've added the admin views to the component
Let's look at some of the features that is still available inside of components
As you can see adding your custom admin views is done there
And the site views is done here
Then there is a custom admin menus now this this don't let this trough you out
Controlling the menu structures for these are
Custom admin views in the site views are done inside of these
This is if you are actually adding
Custom backend
Views
Which hasn't been developed inside of component Builder
So for example
Component builder its self has a compiler View
You all have seen that
If I
quickly go there
It's this view here
Now this whole view is done outside of component Builder
I I actually
This is just hand coded little script
That kicks off a bunch of
Events now
It needs a model it needs a controller so I wrote that
With my hand know just manually
with hand coding
And it also needs a view
And so basically the view and everything
In regards to it
If you look at my infrastructure of component Builder
You would see
That
I have let me just look at this
compiler
I have a place called custom
you see
Now Inside of custom
Is where everything that you want it into you know include inside of your component is added into the
Custom folder
Any files any folders anything that you want to integrate is in here now you might look there
See there are a bunch of things already there
And I would encourage you not to remove them because depending on what you do in component builder it will
Automatically include those
Specially the the footables
And the import View
And the uikit and I think some
Not sure I think you would have sound manager as well
That is for sermon distributor
And in PHP Excel which is the use for the exporting
of data to spreadsheet and
Importing a from spreadsheet we using this
This library
So all of that is in the custom tab
And then he will see a bunch of files as well now the
Component builder itself has its
Compiler view here
So as you can see it's basically just empty folders
And then I have the actual files
Here is well there's the default compiler file
Which is
Then if I open it up
It's basically the The Script that shows the
That little dropdown of items
And I have
That in there
And
I also have the controller somewhere
Let's Scroll down
Obviously it should
Compiler there's the controller
There's the model
There is the compiler as well
The helper
File
And so I am including that
Into my component
If we look here
Let me open
Component builder quickly
Go to settings
In files I'm including
A bunch of things adding and that also means I'm including that here it is the compiler
And I'm saying take this file
And put it in admin views compiler
And view
And rename it
See it's got the wrong name here
So if you add the right name at the end of the string
And click Yes it will rename that file to this
so that is adding custom
Files
And
As well as custom folders
So on
Grabbing the compiler views and I'm dumping it into views
And I'm also say rename it to compiler so compiler views becomes compiler
Inside of the views folder
And then
Obviously we first the system will first build the folders
And then move your data your files to those folders so you you you will put the files here
And then have the system do the folders and then it will move the files
Ok so that's adding custom files to any component and this custom admin menu
Is basically what I use
to the map the compiler menu so I would say
I wanna call it compiler the code is compiler
I'm not using a link because it's not another extension or another website or something like that
Which you can also do
And then I would select an icon
Here is the information
It's the same kind of switches
As you see with adding in custom admin sorry
A backend admin view you can tweak whether it should be an admin menu or be a dashboard
And be a sub menu
So you can tweak that
And then also in which order behind it says select before what admin View
This one
Should be placed
Now
That we are placing it before component
So that means it can
Go
at the very top
Ok so that is adding
An custom admin menu
Because of custom
Fields and files and folders that you have
Created by hand and are importing
Into your component when you
compile it
The same is done with the compiler of component builder I'm actually including it as files so
There is the compiler let me see
Oh you know what I am I took
All the compiler
Files and I put it in the folder called compiler there it is
And so it's a folder which moves all the files at once that obviously can also be done
Like for example as you see here
PHP
Excel
Which is a folder
Has a lot of content in it if we were to open it
You'd see all these files and folders and things
And so I put everything I wanted
To move Inside of this folder
And then in in my component I simply target that folder
And it pulls it in
Ok so that
That's simply showing you how I have added a whole lot of folders to
To component Builder
And then
When I need a backend admin view custom
Added this feature here does that for me
Now I also want to quickly cover the
The area called config
Is it this area deals with something that is actually
quite
Useful
And that is to set up your
Back end
Global fields
Now
It let me go out of this one
because it's definitely not the best in demonstration let me go to sermon distributor
There we've done some really amazing things
sermon distributor
Settings and then config
And as you can see it is a very long list of things
But then if we go to
The actual component
It me open it
And then I'll click on options
You see that has many many tabs
Ok all of these switches
Are done in the config area
All of them except some of these default switch
Is added by the
simple switches
For example the global timer remember we spoke about the check-in
here you can set it all whether it should be every 5 hours 12 hours once a day every second day once a week or never
Checking in your items automatically the version control buttons are added automatically as well
Which means the person can set the version control on or off
And also said how many
You know records should be set
if zero
Then all versions will be saved
So this is the version control
And then
The author
Areas also added automatically
And you can when you click in the component here
just close this thing
You see here is a contributing in area you can set whether you want add empty contributing level
The fields
Here you can add contributors as many as you like
Those involved in developing the component
And then the amount of empty ones you want to leave there
Is also
Tweak able
And that'll basically
Let me show you add this area here
Contributor 1234
And
When you use this witch
IT controls whether it's been shown in the back or the front of all these kind of features
Which I am not gonna go into much depth now
But they also added automatically on also the permissional and structure is added automatically
And if you have in the component
You can actually
Set that it includes UiKit
you can said to that: yes
If you do that
it automatically adds This feature
to your component
And every where where Uikid is used
Ok so everything else this Dropbox preachers preacher categories category
Series list and series and sermons
Is all done through that
Config
area here
Now to use to add Fields to the config area you first need to add that field
To fields
So you would you go to fields
And whatever field you wanna use there you need to create here
So you first create the fields
Then obviously you need to remember the system name that you're using
Because then when you open up this
You would be able to
Type in the name
And it will be selected
And then by Convention that tab name
As long as you use the same tab name it will be bundled in the order of which you said it here
So this is where the Dropbox
Area
All there
Fields are being set
Now the reason why we include this
Demo
Component
Into the
Application with the tutorial
Is that you can go and look and see ok well he's using
Dropbox update method
Here
And
Then you can go look at this file
And then you can go look at
And how it looks here
The Dropbox update method
And the files and the text and even
Some of this I mean here is a button
If I click it
It starts an update
And it even shows it here
Now how to do this is very tricky
It's not that simple to do that because we not inside of our component as you can see were actually in the config
Component
In the global if you have Global settings
So
This whole feature that is building into sermon distributor is so smart I would tell you
For you to be able to do that is just stunning
So
You can look at how I've done that by Simply going to the
To these fields
And you would find
The answer to how did he do that
And you can look at these things in this list View
All the Dropbox
Information is there
And then there is some Global
Like local folder download link
And then space hr
You can see that I have that Space HR quite often it's a It's a field that it will be included in
the Paid
version of
of component builder
It already has that spacer hr in it
And since Spacers you can use the same spacer
Over and over the system automatically increment it so it doesn't have conflict in name conventions
So I'm just using the Same Spacer so every where is putting spacers which is which is this
Little
Line
you see that line there
It's very
very
Very small but it gives a space between these areas
That is why I'm doing that
Then also he can put default values which will be used during
Installation of the component
So if you have
Switches in your config
That you want to populate with default values should just add those values here
And then during the install
Those values will be added to the database and
Component builder puts all that in place for you
So this is where you add the config
Fields
And there is another Convention which is maybe
Not
Is not
That
It's not that obvious
But
I added a convention that if you use a tab name
Which is exactly the same
As a
Front-end View
Then
I will add
This field
to that front-end views menu
Now
If you can see it if you think about component sorry of Joomla's
Content
Manager manager
It does the same thing
In the global setting of your article manager you can set features for categories and for articles
But if you create a new article in a menu item
Then you can overwrite those you can say use global or you can overwrite them now this feature
Of using the same tab name
So let's look at this
The features name is
Preacher
Switch
Whether should be a table or a grid
Ok and we set the default 2
And we called it preachers plural
That's quite important
Now
Let's look at the front
Close this out
here Do I have a bunch of menus
I'm gonna go to a menu that I've already created called preachers
And then I'm also gonna go to this components backend
called preachers
So you see there is a list of items now all I did in the component Builder
Is I simply added
The name preacher as a tab name
That's all I did
And then the fields
So there is the list of the fields from there
to there
These are the fields you can see them here
These Fields I simply created in the field
Area
With field type so is basically some radio buttons
A drop down list
Another dropdown list and again some radio button
Ok so these are the fields
And then in the view if you click on sermon distributor
You see those exact same Fields and it has the option of using
The global
Instead so there's used global or you can overwrite it
So you can decide ok this specific admin view I want to use grid and not the global
option
So that whole system
Of adding
This extra features to every item view of the front end
Is integrated simply by a convention
If the front end is called preachers which this case it is
As you can see there it's called preacher see I just selected a menu item called preachers
Now we haven't dealt with setting up your site views and all that so this might be
How did you get that item name right in everything
But
I'm trying to
Sketch a picture which we will revisit when we eventually get to this area
But just that you know from where it comes it's simply in the config
I added the files and used to convention of the actual
Front-end
Page that has a name called preachers
And
So there is as well for preacher which is single
So if I closed out select
sermon distributor and then select preacher
Which is another View
And then I clicked here you see all these switches
They also
Mapped in here
From there
All the way
to there
And they have some default values in there there there are there
Fields
And in the back end of the component if I click on preacher
Here is the same Fields so you can set Global settings
And then you can overwrite them sorry in the menu itself
Why not using Global
So that this whole feature
Is possible
Through this config
Little tab sorry it looks
Insignificant I suppose
And you might not expect it like I said it's not that obvious that it does this
But that is what it is doing
And so as you can see all of those certain areas I just mapped it in config
And because of the name of the tab let me stress that
Because of the name of the tab
The system knows oh so this is related to any front end menus as well
Therefore it will automatically create those front end
Things for you
Now to show you how it is done it's quite
Simple
Not that I want to teach you how
The Joomla API works but I want you to at least know
What is doing so I'm gonna go to the front of this component here it is
And I'm gonna open that view preachers
And you'd see in template there is a extra file called
Default XML
And then I'll open that default XML
Basically all component builder is doing
it is adding
The convention to this file
So if you're running into troubles and it's not working as you expected
This is the file in which you can come and look
To see what's happening
That is in the front end
In views
In the specific view that you have to it must be this view must be the
The tab name
And then
In that file called default XML
Obviously
This is important
Since we haven't dealt with adding site views
The site views here
I need to quickly touch on it so did you at least know
Something that relates to this
That is if you didn't click on add as a menu
You sets its to no
Then that file will not exist
Ok so that file only exist if this is set to yes
So setting it to yes
Tells component builder to build this default XML file
And setting the tabs to the same name as this view
Tells component builder to add those fields
To this
Few and make it so that
your user can then
Have
Unique
Implementation obviously
And this is important
It doesn't make use
Of
This information necessary inside of your site
View
You need to
Make use of this information in your site view
Now If you're a developer you would expect that right you would know
Oh yeah ok so inside of your
Component
You have
A place where you check
params header
Should it show then it shows it and it basically you getting it from the parameters
The parameters are set inside of the view.html.php
You see here we set the parameters
We get
We do on this app get parameters now this actually gets all the parameters in relation to this view
The gets that component parameters it gets the menu parameters and it automatically
If it has the
custom
So
I feel like I'm
maybe going Beyond the scope but if they've used Global
It will automatically fall back on what the set here which is excellent
So you're using the same name
Display
And display where is it
It's the same name
And so if you are using Global basically what parameters does
Is it getting this place parameter
The display field it's getting that parameter
And it first looks at the menus
Settings and that one is set to Global it automatically Falls back to the global settings
That is done by Joomla itself it's not really something I build it's just the way Joomla works which is excellent
And
That means that you immediately
By using params
And then doing a check-up
So remember now this value
Is inside of this params
And if I didn't go to the default View
And let's see where am I implementing some of that
Let's go to
Here the preacher display
Ok
So the field name wasn't just display I'm sorry it was called preachers display
That's the
The field name
In the global
Configurations
So
You're not with me
It is what we
Used for this field
Switch preacher
Table grid
It's called preacher display
If I was to go and open this field in fact if you do that so if you see the whole picture
Switch preachers table grid let me just remember that
Ok here is the list of the switch preachers
Fields as you can see I'm in the fields
Tab
And I'll open that
Specific
Field
And you'd see that the name
Of that
The name
Of this field is preachers
Underscore display
Now
You need to make sure that none of the fields have the same name
That is quite important
What I mean by none of the fields I mean
This field must not be the same name is that field
Every field in this Global area must be unique
It should never overlap
So that is why I use the convention of preachers display so that I can also use preacher
Without the s display and I can use
Category
Underscore display in you see so that I have that site of convention of implementation
Is it all around as you develop think about conventions using sort of
Logical repetitive scalable concepts
And so this is one of them that I've done
And then I just added it here
It's that specific item
And then in the
Global area you go to preachers it is basically this view here
Sorry field
This field here
And in the code
On
I'm simply saying
If preacher = 1
Then show the table
If
Preacher display = 2 then show the grid
And if non is selected and show the list
Which is the three options if you look at the button
The button has Table grid list
And
So
I'm not asking does the global have this or that none of that I'm just calling the field directly
Because the way that Joomla gets that initial data like I showed you here
Is they sort that out for you and that's quite nice
And I've obviously test it and made sure that my
My explanation is the truth
And so goes with the colours you can see here I
I again just do params get colors
But this is actually knowledge that you would have
If you have developed a component for Joomla
You would know about these tricks I suppose
And I'm just showing to you how of component Build It makes it easy to implement these kind of things
which otherwise would take so much time
to
Write this up and then make sure it's exactly the same inside of the XML folder menu and so forth
So component builder does all of that
Out of this config file
Simply with a
Convention that relates to the actual front-end
And that is as simple as that
Ok so
I think we have covered that
Thoroughly enough
And
That will be all for this tutorial
I will continue looking at more
Concepts of the component
And it's features
Possibly it might be ideal for us to
Stop here
With the component
And go look at setting up a custom admin View
Or setting up a site view
And yet I'm thinking you know if we go that route
It's gonna take us on a very long
Road so
The ideal with me let me sort of
Dealt with some of this component features First
And finish that
And then as soon as we've finished it
We'll jump into the custom very
Nice area of your front-end development and custom admin development
And then we will obviously be relating back to what we have discussed here
As we go
So I've now looked at the setting tab
And try to cover as much of this area as I can
I didn't talk much about mySQL  tweak
This is a very advanced feature
And
You can know that what it really does if we have dummy data
You're able to
Exclude them
Through this area so that if you have different versions
You will through this MySQL tweak
Be able to exclude certain information
Which I realise it's a little bit advance and so for most cases people will just not use this
It's only when you start having multiple versions of the same extension
And you selling them at different pricing and
Want to be able to
From Within component builder just export the different versions
Then you start using this feature
And
I think we possibly deal with it with when we start looking at more advanced implementations
Ok thank you for watching
We'll start in the next run with scripts