Hi
So we just looked at
Settings
Of your component
And now next we be looking at the scripts tab
Here is an area where you most probably
Add a lot of custom scripting
So this area is focused on giving you
Area you know
Interface to add custom
Scripting to your component in a global way
So obviously you can have custom scripting per
per Admin
Sorry per admin backend view
But you can also do that within the global scope with
Regards to many
certain values
The the one thing that is
Nice to have here is
You can add
Create user helper method
To the component
Now the user helper method is simply code
If you do not know how to write php this method will be of no use to you at all
But if you do
Then this this method will come in very handy
Let me illustrate that to you
If you click this yes I have a component in which I've already
Implemented This feature
And it's called
The cost-benefit projection tool
Now if you click on companies
You can actually
Click new
And then
It has an area for you to create a company
And ideally you would connect that company to a user in the system
But if you don't add that company to a user
Because a user can have multiple companies
So that's why
If you click on this tab
You could select the user
But if you haven't selected a user and you've entered an email address and a name
Then
And also the needed information of course
Then you will
Once you click save
Close or save
The system will actually create a user for you
An automatically email the user details to that user
And that is because of that specific helper class that I
Added
So
Ticking helper class
Now obviously it doesn't do it
On its own
You need to write the code for it
So let me show you where I did it
In the controller
You have an area
if we open up company
You have an area called Post safe
OK it's this one here
Is the postsaveHook
Remember
When we'd looking at the admin views
We could target this area in fact that's exactly what I did
So let me show you
So I'm in the admin view for company
And if I go to PHP
You would see that I have some Ajax there
And then I have
Area
Which is the post safe method
I need a post safe method
I'm basically checking something some values
And then when I realized that this user does not exist let me just check here company
Here it is
If the user does not exist
Basically I'm doing a check here
Then I'm using the helper
No wait that is not the feature
There it is
Create user
So again I've spoken about this placeholder Convention before
I here you are using the brackets Convention not the
Hash one
So three brackets that must be uppercase component
And then I get 3 brackets and helper and this will be replaced with the components code Name
Ok so
That is what that does and then it basically
Gets the helper class
Create user
So in the helper class of this component
If I close this down
Can I go to the
helper
And I open
The helper class you see that is the name
So it is the components name
And then it's called helper
And in helper class there is a
Feature called
Create user there it is
So basically it gets an array in it
And that array has some values
Which will be using
Like password 1password 2
And it will set the password so I'm not gonna explain this code basically just showed you where the function is
So the function was added to the components helper class and in that script
I'm simply calling that function after having build the the user
So I said the erase name and the email is that obviously the function if there is no password
Set it will set a random password and again use another method
Which also is part of the helper class we explored it with all helper classes is random
Random method we can get a random string so
That is creating a user and then it sets up the password and then it gets the
Array ready get a model now the model I
Got from there get model again we are using a component builder
Custom method which gets the specific model from the system
And then basically fires the register
Method
upon this dataset
And then
Updates
The parameters for the system
Regarding this new user
Sends in the email
And then returns the ID because obviously we were looking
Foreign ID
That's actually what we want
We want to
I want to get the
there we have the ID
If we have the ID
If you don't have the ID will send a message
To the user
And if we have the ID will basically store it into that database
To connect
That item
To that user
Automatically and then click save
Now
That is
Custom scripting
So this little switch
Is this adding that
Method to your helper class
That's all it does
Where as this switch adds the Uikit library to your media
folder
As well as integrates
it Dynamically
Wherever
Are you use
The uikit class names
So you won't need to write that any in any custom way
Automatically adds it
The same goes with food table
This CSS is global CSS for all the backend views
entire backend
So
if You wanna add CSS that would target the whole back end and then you
do it there
This is a place for you to add your own custom scripting to the helper class the admin helper class
so as you can see
I have a whole custom
Scripting here for
Sermon distributor
For the admin
Area
And as well
As an event
Now I spoke about this event concept briefly before
But what we want to achieve with the event is basically on every page
If you look at
This sermon distributor
Back end part of it
It has a file which is the in Main file
Which Joomla calls first calls sermon distributor
And in that file
It basically triggers that Global admin event
And the global admin event is nothing else than a function inside of your helpers
function
So it always Triggers
If you add that switch
And then it passes at the document object
Ok so the document object is being built up here
So I'm just passing it over to the global event so we don't need to really clear it there
So if I was to open the helper class
Which we have here and
Scroll to the top
Then you would see that I have
It was the top I was just in the wrong file
It says here
Load Dropbox Ajax
Now
This again it's just another function right so I wrote that function
So you can basically add whatever functions you want to run globally
Every time a page opens
Now that is a way to run it like a Chronicle job
On the front and the back end of the component
If you have things that you want to be done chronically
This feature is really targeted at doing that
So
Here we are loading the Drop Box Ajax
So if we go back to the component
You see that I am
Just adding
That script first I just ticked Global admin event yes
And I added that script that's all they added
And that script was taken and placed inside of the global event
The trigger
This trigger is set by
Component builder itself you don't need to write that
It will insert this trigger itself
just because you clicked yes
You need to then just Add the script that must run inside of the global event
Wich I decided to be another function
And then this function
Which I want to run
I added
To the admin
View
You see here at the admin helper class
I added that function here
So I basically just used
That name
And called it "self" because we inside of that class right so that's how you call
Static class
Method
And a past the same information because
In my method
I'm adding JavaScript to the dorm right
So to the document object so I want that document and then I said add script declaration
And simply that means on every page of this component in the back end it adds this little script which then calls
By Ajax
Which I explained previously
And it starts checking the Dropbox listing automatically
So that's an automatic feature I wanted to add to my component
And this is way that I did it
And then I felt that I wanna add it that you can do this in other components and that's why I added this event switch
Ok
This event switch here
Ok and then this same goes for the site area
I also added that same class
You might ask why I have different helper classes for the front and the back
Well it's about
Pretty belt security I suppose and permissions
There are things that I wanted to in the back end which I'm not asking that much questions
Where on the front I might be more
Protective I would suppose
And
So for that reason and implementation also is often different in the front then in the back so that's why we have to
Different files helpers site class
And the
Helper admin class
And you can add custom scripting as you can see I added that same script to the front
And I also add it
A site
Event
Which also trigger is that same script
Now you might say well if everybody Triggers The Script
Then it's gonna be running multiple times
Well
That's exactly part of what I did I actually added
A feature
In the Ajax call
That logs weather it's already Active
And if it's Active it just ignores that call
So
Basically it has a controller over
Whether it should run or not
Meaning that if it needs to run
Because it even has a timer you see you can set
For the Sermon distributor you can set how often you want Dropbox links to be updated
Every day every 2 days
And so this Script If it checks wants to update and it's not time it just dies
Doesn't do anything so it's very light since it's Ajax you don't the user himself don't
Even notice a delay in his page so the page opens as fast as it always do and then fire that
Ajax call to the server
Which starts this whole process on the server
So that's primarily what this is all about obviously you need to know programming and you need to know how to secure all that
And I'm not gonna try and explain that to you now I'm just saying that this is all possible inside of component builder
Simply through these custom areas you can also add a SQL dump
Instead of adding it to the actual views you can export all the views and add them
here and it will be actually added to the same file
And so don't do it twice but this is another area to add
A SQL dump file
And
Then
We have this nice feature called dashboard methods
You see
Let me show you what I've done with it
Again just that you know all this data that I'm showing you is dummy
Not related
Just me testing it
So I wanted to add this
Usage statistics to the component so you could see
Which country has done what
When in what area
So
So I needed to take a lot of different database tables and calculate used by
certain ways in and I wanted to have that on the dashboard
The dashboard really had always icons and so I didn't want it
Add another custom view wish I could have done custom admin view
I wanted it simply right there at the moment of the page load
And so we added that feature
Component builder and we called it
We call that dashboard methods
Now let me go to one where I actually implementing it so I could
Spend more time in explaining unless on typing
Ok so here we go
Basically
I created a
Method called get usage data it's a public function
Public method
And inside it I added my script
And obviously inside of this script
I'm calling other methods which I made it made protected so the script that
Must be called from
The dashboard tab I'll show you that at the moment
You said that up here
So here is the tab and it's HTML so we called the tab
usage statistics and a header we made Table
And here is the HTML
Ok which we are using and in the HTML
You see that I have PHP and the way we do that is with that convention
of Open bracket
? PHP and Echo and then closing it again there so basically
I'm checking whether the usage data is there
Now how do I know that I should target usage this usage data and then items
Well this is a convention this area there
And the way that that Convention works
Is
By that one there
So usage data
Relates to
Usage data
So the moment you add to word get
This word get in front of a function it will be
Added
to a Global the result of that Get will be added to this
And without the Get
Name so that the convention
The convention is you could've called that
Get
the man on the moon
Then this would be Man on the Moon
This and obviously all lowercase Man on the Moon
So
That will be dropped
And this is gonna be used
Lowercase as the this
So
That's the convention I know it might not be that obvious but it works
So your other functions
If they are protected
Shouldn't have the word get in it
At the moment it's set to
Set that as that one is set
And then this one is
Visit check
This one is set companies
and set countries
So you can see I could add a lot of PHP in here
And all these PHP together
Basically gets the data
That we want on the page
And when I get the data I placed it
In what is seen as the item
Ok
Oh you know what let me see set statistics return this statistics
Ok so
I'm returning a field here or a a method value
And this method value is being populated in this sub functions
And in one of them
It is adding
Over here
The name items as a
a Pointer
So it becomes an object
Well it is an object in fact I
Think I set it is an object up here there we go
And
There I look through the companies and as I look through them I'm busy totalling and adding and going on
I guess so
I'm not going explain the code itself
But basically this is getting returned
And because he's an object
If I look here
I'm able to Target items as an object
And then if it's exist
And if it's set I start looping through items and certain places I'm using totals and
Different values so that is just adding some of that data to the page
And this area here
Now I could have made this much simpler right so maybe not look that intense to you but this could have been a simple
Class in fact you could have let this out completely and just put a
Comment so you could have done this
Because it's gonna scream at you for you know this is if you see is not compulsory so you can set is
Not needed and then in here you could just do HTML so if you just wanna give information
To the user about who made the component maybe or some
would like to run a rss feed here you could have done it right here
Ok I'm just showing you that you can reach into PHP here and that the PHP that
you reach in has the convention
Of dropping the get and then using that front area usage data
To place information in which you can parse in your HTML here that you would do and any other component
View
Ok so that is just quickly looking at the script area of a component
I realize there's so much more to say but I really can't
Elaborate too much on this it since it requires skill in in PHP
It's something that I think will only become very useful if you are a developer as
Developed a few components
And can then see how you can easily add custom scripting to his component through this
Methods ok well next up will look at the ReadMe
And maybe their FTP server concepts. Thanks for watching