Next in the component view we are gonna add the ReadMe script to a component
The reapme script is commonly used as the components
Homepage sort of so if you were to go to gethub for
That's open we are on the demo components page for example
Let's open GetHub and you'll see that it has this nice image here and it has some
Details and some layout
Now this all is done with the ReadMe file so it's with this file here we can open
That and then look at the Raw
And here you can see the It's basically the same text this we looking at previously
So inside of component Builder you can add this read me and read me text and
This is basically placeholders
Now
I know that that is part of the markup for a header so
You need to
Know a little bit about
Markdown
Sorry not markup markdown
to you know what is placeholders and what is not
That is why I added The Script so you can sort of get an idea of everything that are placeholders
And these place holders are
Automatically updated from the details that are in these Fields here so
So you can see
The the actual placeholders
Names it's nice so if you change the version here
It'll updated there
Automatically
So that is just read me file
Really a place for you to give a lot of information to those who are using
Your
Application
so Maybe you can add some links to it or you could
has Some links to help menus or even instructions on installing it
or anything else that you'd like to share through the ReadMe file
I would ask if it's if it's not too much for you you know for you to leave this area this commenting
The more people using component builder the more involve within a community
Others getting
This training set
Help us to sustain this project
So if
you leave that in it will certainly be helpful
you not Compulsory
I mean it's only if you want to
And then if you wanna know more about markup markdown
markdown not markup
Then you can open this link here
And it shows you the
this little bit of a cheat sheet of everything that you can do
Ok so that is looking at the ReadMe area
This admin View area
And the site View area
Should be seen as a place where you can create new admin views
Do realize that if you create a new admin view it's not necessarily linked to this component
You need to still link it in here in settings under admin view
This is more a place to create admin view so if you click on new
Or to edit existing admin views that are linked to this component
Same goes with the site views so it's simply a way for you to to gain access to editing those
site views that already linked to this application easily
And then the third one
forth actually
one two three four we wanna look at is the FTP server that FTP server basically been added to
Give you a hand in moving this application this component
to your server and also add the feature of that automated updating that is inside
of Joomla. So the update server
Is actually a Joomla concept
And if you open a component
So I'll open
Summon distributor wait over there
This is the front I need to look at the backend
And we look at the
XML file of this component
Component builder obviously built this whole file for you
But at the very bottom
You see that there is a
App updates server
That is being added
Now this is not added if you
Have not
Set the service it will set to no
It will not be adding an update server if you add this
Then you can set the link
To where the update server is you know gonna be hosted
And it will automatically take that link
in added into your XML file like it's done here
And
That file itself
Component Builder Can also build that file for you
The way does it
Is that
This obviously
Should look like that host = hostname
And port = port
Int&
And option bracket type
= FTP BINARY
Now this FTP binary
usually is 15 sorry
That is the the default value FTP binary
Where is that would usually be 21 and that would usually be 15
And then username and a password
Now this FTP details should actually login directly
To this folder that you have up here this updates folder
Ok that one
So that basically all component builder does is it loggs into your server move this file in there and then this disconnects
And this information is what will make it possible for him to do that
Same goes with the sales server the sales server usually
Would be
Very much the same concept
You'de Simply be adding the same kind of string here except usually the
The update server and the sales server is not the same place
The update server let's the user know that there is an update where is the sales service actually where this component
Zip file will be stored on your server so you have something like whmcs
Or Another
Component through which you are selling your extensions you can
Use the folder in on your server which it's looking for the files
You can use that folder you know great in FTP Account to that folder and then set that details
In this field here
And then
Component Builder on the moment that you could compile
It has a
An option here it says add backup folder and save sales server you click that to
Yes and if you compile it now
It will move
The zip file to sales server as well as creating a backup now the backup and the Git
Folder is actually set up in your components Global options so we
We haven't really spoken much about the global options let us open it now here
We saw in this area here
That it says that this field is encrypted now in component builder if you go to Global
Settings it says
Encryption settings in in here
You would add a your own key
By which it will encrypt once you've added this key
You shouldn't change it because it will obviously not be able to decrypt
Because it's used to encrypt and as well to decrypt
The data so if you well that just means everything that's been encrypted it is now needs to
To be redone which in this case is is gonna be these these login
Information is FTP login information
That's this is the basic encryption which we spoke of on talk about storing types you got basic encryption
and advanced encryption now this is
Basic encryption way basically having such a
Is also called basic key
Then you have files here or folder paths
These two first folder paths called compiler folder and custom folder I would leave them
For now they are a little buggy I haven't fully managed to achieve them being
Flexible so to move them at this stage is difficult
For a number of reasons for now I would suggest you just leave them blank
But here you would add a backup folder
And this obviously should be related to the root of your server
So
As well as a Git folder
And Git folder would be where component builder creates a folder with all the compounds
Files without zipping them
And then you can go to that folder and create a git
create a git repository there
And from that folder you can push to Github
Or any other git server
Respectively
So basically it's able to create a folder from which you can do Github or any other kind of
Repository work
Which are separate from your backup folder and also separate from the temporary folder in which
compiles the component so you can move it out of your Joomla install basically
And that's what these folder paths are for
So when you do the compiling of the component it does that git repository it won't delete
the Dot git file sorry folder it will just replace all the files in it
Basically first remove the old ones then add the new ones and git obviously we'll see that
Only the files that is been changed it will notice and those who you need to do a recommit well just obviously a normal commit
To get it into your repository obviously if you don't know Git then possibly this then possibly doesn't make sense to you
There's some great courses as well about Git on lynda.com as well as Udome
So you can just go look at those ok so that's a backup folder
And the sales server the same goes here this FTP
credentials should be that direct folder in which these zip files should be stored
Unfortunately component builder cannot
Storing and subfolders at this point so the FTP details he will just login to that FTP account
And in that very folder which here is which he has the access to you'll put the file there
So no subfolders or
Other folders the FTP details should be going directly to the folder now
In the component builder I was thinking just for your own
Peace of mind if you look in component builder so
That will be in the backend components component builder and then
Helpers there is a file called compiler if you open that file
You would see that we have a function here built me and here's all the place holders
That you can use in the built me file and will be replaced with the relative information
And then there is a function here called move file to FTP server
This move file to FTP server calls another function called
Where is it getFTP now getFTP is this function here
And basically it takes the signature checks whether we are ready made such a connection before
And then loads that object
But here basically I'm using this parse string function
To convert the string into the variables so all the
Variables in that string is converted to erase all variables respectively
And that then is used to actually make use of
Joomlas own client FTP class so if you wanna know where that is you can
NetBeans you'd click control spacebar and it shows you it's in library JclientsFTP
.PHP that's where the file is you click there open it
So we basically using Joomlas built-in FTP client and we passing the host the port the option the
Username the password and making a connection and then we sending that off
To do this move file which then basically takes the file content and moves it
To the server
So that's just for your own piece of mind that the data itself is not
Being leaked or compromised
It's
So all handled right here and you can
Follow its events in component builder from
Relations to the update
Server as well as to the
Sales server
The other thing that I know is quite in
Important
Is this update server
Is an XML file
And this XML file
is basically build up
of versions
And download links to those versions
So
Like I explain to you in a previous video
There is this reality that while you are developing your component
Your users
Excuse me wouldn't need
Any
change
Updates or anything are there
The moment you put your component out there on the web
Immediately
You need to
Consider
When you make a change in the application
How will you user to be able adapt
to that change
And the biggest changes you can make
Is adding new views
or adding new
Fields
To the component
And so that makes it a little hard
But like I explain previously
With the history component
We've done scripting to take you know take control of
That problem
But
You also need to think about the database
So we created this thing called
Version Updates
Which
Gives you the ability
To actually add sql
Scripting
Which needs to be executed upon the updating
Now the way for you to think about this
If you have a new version that's a 1.2.9
Then and now you know that there needs to be a table alteration
Obviously you need to know see if MySQL commands
To do that I'm not gonna teach you that you just
Need to put that MySQL command in here according to the Joomla conventions which means
The table name must have that hash underscore underscore in front of it and Joomla will dynamicaly
put in the prefix so you might just simply will do a
MySQL script here but if you are making a change and the new releases 1.2.9
And
1.0
Didn't have that
Specific field of view
Then you must realize that
You're updating this one and so the sql must come next to that specific version
The update must be placed
at the version
Which Needs the update
So if you make it change don't put it here
Because it won't
Update correctly
You need to put the update next
to the Version that needs to be updated
And then over here
You would put the link
To the respective
Downloads
Ok so
Like here we had
Version 2.
And then we had version 1.3.
And
We added the 1.3.0 link here
Obviously I'm using GitHub as my distributing
Platform of the application
You could use any URL
And these URLs is what will be used
In your updates
Server
So the update server
If I was to open that for us first let me close this and we will go to the update server
Link copy that
You'd see that it has this
URLs here for the download
And as we move on it
3, 3.1, 3.2
And so it's getting these
these
Details
It is getting them
From
This version
update area
And so the last version in this
List being 1.3.
Must be the same
Is the one that you set here
That is important
So that it will know ok now we are at the current version
And it will do the necessary you know the adjustments to that
Ok so that is
Basically
All the concepts that would be
Necessary
To cover
Regarding the
Component
Area
We've looked at adding admin views
We will again look at site views and adding them
as well as your custom admin views
And we will possibly
Going to more depths
about this MySQL tweak
What we briefly spoke about
But the
For most part that's or the
at Component
Area
And all it's nice
Features
Obviously it all stacks upon
each other from the
Fields then the admin
Views and then the components themselves
And if you have come this far
you Set out your component
You have added some admin views
You are now ready to
Start building the front
and the site area
Which
You wouldn't be able to
To really do effectively until now
It is really necessary to
First do the admin views
And then only do the site views
Well Thank you for watching