Hi
We still working with
Sermon distributor
So I'm gonna use this preacher
Which is a
Get that I already have set up here
I'll use that
In our illustration
So here we can see that I have
This
Back end
View selected
So
It's been select nothing
This is usually how it will look
When you start
So
You'd look
Select
This
Depending on which
Area of the
Backend you wanna get the data from
You'd select
Backend View
Which is the
Best way to do it I would say
Then there is the Joomla Database
option
Would basically gives you the access to draw data from any other component installed that moment in the Joomla
Website
So if you select your Joomla Database
You can select any Database
That
Is actually at that stage
On your
Database
Installed
And that means you can reach out to other components
Through this dynamic get
I'm gonna not do that
In fact that's also an area which I haven't tested so well
I
You possibly might try to implement that
And ran into some bugs
And this stage I can't make any apologies for that since
Really thing you should do is instead using
Back end
View
Option
Now
You might say but why is the other option there
Well it's because that's a feature we certainly want in the application right
And so I'm busy working in that direction
And busy
Programming so did that feature will work without any problems
In fact for the most part if you don't do very complex
Mapping
If you just do a simple
Direct database fetch like that
Are you be able to use this it won't give you an issue
What it really is about these other
Linked
or Joint database structures
That really would make it complex
So
And that might
Cause problems
I'm not 100% sure
Obviously it did work
But I haven't tested it well enough as well as I have tested the other part and that is this back-end view
There is also the custom option
Where you can just dump the whole
Option of
Using component builder to sort of write your
Your your
PHP for you
And here you can add custom PHP
it will add
The methods data for you
So this is a custom get option where you write the code
Basically by hand
Where is this option
Write the code for you
So
You select the back-end view that you want to use
again that back-end view
Will be the the view that you connected to your component right
So you need to type that you name in here and then select
That package
And it will load
All the field names
As a.id and a.asset id and a.name and allias and icon
So these are all the fields inside of this view
And I will load it and I'll put this as
Asset ID
Now again I would suggest you don't change that
What you can do is you can take
Out
a row
You feel ok I don't need that row
Then you can
Remove a row
Like that
And you can say I don't need the row
I don't need these
Way to there
Basically that's all the data you might want
And then you will know
That this would be the variable name
Of the data on When do When these get is used
So that's the
The basic part of setting up a Get
I need to mention that you have get types as well now the get types have 4 of them
There is the get item
Which will get one item so that means from this preacher table
It will get one item
Then you got the get listQuery
Which will get
Multiple
Items
Ok so depending on how many items you want to get from the database you would select either get item or get list
Then you get custom
And then you got
Get customs that
plural
And
The difference between these two
or four
Is the get item
Is what you will use only once per
Per view
So if you are building a custom admin view
You will select a main get
Either of a get item or either of get list
But you can add multiple custom get item
Or custom get items
So
You can see these as
Other
Methods that you're adding to the page but it's not the main method
so you have main methods which are these a get item and get listquery
Which by the way is the exact naming of the methods that will be used
And then you got this custom get custom and get customs
Which is really
almost same as these two it's just that they are not Main
There will only be another method in the
model
Which will bring data to the view
So you can add as many custom
Get custom and get customs
Methods
To your view as you like but you could only add one get item and you only add
one get listquery
Usually the way we would
decide on this
is that we would
Say what is the main objective of The View
What is the main dataset that we want to use in the view
And that is what we will use the get list query and get item for
Respectively
So if the main purpose of The View
It's a show preachers, a list of preachers
I would use the get list query as the main
Selection here
Now you see that you have when you do a list query you have the option of adding pagination
So
Basically that would mean whether the data should only return a certain number
Now Joomla has a global number there
Which you set in the system administrative area
under your Global settings
let me show you that
So you go to system
Then
Global configuration
And then you see there is a default list limit
This one here
And
That is what will be used as the amount
That limits the data being returned to the page
so it will only return at this stage 20 item
If I set that
pagination to yes
And if I set it to no it will load all the data
So yes would just load some of it
And no will load all of the data so depends on what you wanna do if you wanna do an Ajax
Well you wanna be sure that all the data is being loaded every time and you rather use JavaScript
Set up pagination for yourself for your view
Then that is why you would use
the no switch most of the time you're just say yes
And
Joomla world
Sorry component builder will automatically add the pagination code to the page
It will also automatically add pagination
code to the model
And at the bottom of the page it will show a
one two three pagination now possibly depending on
The template you are using
And the styles that are on the page
Bootstrap is not on the page that
one two three might possibly not look right and you will need to add styling to it
component Builder doesn't
know what style is on your page so they cannot make provision for all of that
But it actually can load the pagination itself
And it does
Do that
Ok
Now here you have data and
You can join this data to other database tables
And now again here like with the main source
You're able to select
Joint Views From a table
A view Table which is basically the views of the component
Or just any database table
And to one of the database tables I often
Connect to these categories
you see because component builder
Integrates
It's application
If you add a category field
To any View
It dynamically set up a category for your component
And integrates the category concept into your component so it writes all that code for you and basically the way
that Joomla's own
Applications like
Article manager does it so it's using the same conventions
So if you know how Joomla article manager is bringing categories into the articles
Then that is the way your component is gonna do it as well
And
Here
You can now select categories
You can say
These switches I'll
Deal with
When we come and look
in More detail at this area
And then you can model the data there
And model I mean decide what you want to return you don't want to return everything from categories
But the one I want to look at first is actually this joint view Table we'll come back to the DB option
The joint view Table let you again select from any of the other views that is
Part of your component
And again you can select whether it should return a single row
Or a
List of rows
Now when you say single row it means it's gonna literally join it
To this other data set that you have as your main data or your main source
It will just be another
Item in the array
And so that's why you can't use the name
Name
For example here
It needs to have that
That series underscore in front of it
So that it doesn't clash with the other data set that possibly also has a value called name
So again here if you selected
you know let me just select
Anything here
Series
You see that it will populate this area with all the fields that is in that View
Then this as
Button here
Basically
You can't use the same
Alphabetic number
twice in the whole
In the whole query
So
So the whole get function can only use a once and then b once and then c once
and then D
So
You need to make sure that the
That these are set up that you can
we'd made provision up to z z
How many tables you can
have
Only in this area here
and So
Basically you would
First decide whether this row
Type what type of return it will be
If you set it to multiple you see that these names automatically update
Because now
The way that the get method will
Work
Is it will create a new
Method
Which will get this data
And add it into your item list
Via this relationship so
I'm adding the on field
as the Dot a series that's where the ID is for the series
And the joint field I'm using the C ID which is that one
So that means in the main Database
That is the a database
There must be a field called series
And it has the ID of the series
And it corresponds to the ID in this list
And if I wanted to return a multiple it means that
The main database which is in that case a sermon
Can be linked to multiple serieses
But in the system we are working with here
That is not possible you can only
Connect a sermon
to one series
So that means it's certainly a single return
Then it will immediately add this
Series underscore in front of everything
to insure doesn't clash with your a table
That's What It's basically doing
Again you can remove the fields you don't want but
Please do not edit
The string
It possibly would make it break
I wanted to be possible that you can change this name to anything you like
And we are gonna try and do that eventually but for now it's still doesn't really like you doing that
And it it in fact you can be changing it it will still
write it this way in the code that's
That's part of why I'm saying you shouldn't change it not because it will break something but because it will be ignored and you might
expect something else than what it is actually doing
So it still is gonna use this
Implementation even if you change it
But it will drop the fields you don't select so if you say I don't want these
That
Then it won't get those Fields and you will only have this data returned
And
again here you can have equal
Not equal
Equal or not
And
we also have in function
That means
if This joint value
Sorry
If this on field
Is an array
Then you can use the in function
To make sure that it
Actually looks whether the id in this
That's the in function
And again
Remember when we started out I told you that you need to be willing to get your hands dirty
Now
This code
If we go to the component itself
I'll show you where it writes this code
So
Let me scroll down to the bottom here
And let's see we're looking into sermon
Preacher ID
Now we'll still get to why it says preacher ID
When we look at the filters and the where
but let us go to the code
Now you can actually see
I'm gonna refresh this page and then go to the code
Ok so since this get is used in the front
Of the component we will go to the front end and not to the admin area
So we go to the front end
Of sermon distributor
And then we are
Looking at the model right the get
Dynamic get is used in the model to get the data
And we are looking at sermons
let me just make sure of that
Yes it's sermons
Getting a list query and it's using pagination
Getting all this
So
we're Looking at sermons
Sermons on the
Under the preacher ID so it should be this model
I'll still show you the way that I know all that
But just that I could get you into the code
here You can see
the main
Method
Which actually has this dot ID
or the main
Data set sorry not method
data set
It is written here
So here you can see ID, acid ID name alias link types short description
If you look at the
UI it says the same things, alias, link type short description
Icon preacher series category ID
So this is where it writes it
And it shows you where in the complier it's done that
Then it sets up the Second one Series you see
And
Then
You can also see it says series
Equals
c ID
So series
There is series
Equals
The c
This table series
ID
And then it also tells you what it wants from c it wants the name and the alias and then it wants a series name
that Changes it to series
Since this is in the select
Query this is one
function there
And
So that array
Transposes to this array
That is the way that you make use of Joomla's
Database PPI
So it has a thing called quote name
Which you can pass to arrays
And the first array being the actual
Name of the
Value which in this case is name and alias
And the second array
What you wanted to be once the query is completed
So it links this into the the query
One-by-one
See all of those even the category one is linked in here
And then
It does a check whether there's an ID
And if it exists it checks whether it's a string
If it's a string it adds a quote
And if it isn't if it's a number
It just adds it directly
and That is where
Where the query is done
And
here basically return false if there is no ID
And so we'll look at this area in a moment this is done
To the filtering
and the wear
Ok
So I just wanted to show how it adds this
Preacher as well as series
To the query
if we Look at the back
Open up here
You see that series
And preacher
And statistics but statistics
You see we select
Multiple statistics
Because for one
sermon
There can be multiple downloads right
So there's multiple statistics
Oh sorry not multiple downloads multiple files
And per file there will be a a a number
So if we look at how he does that
It is first does the query and hearing get item
It actually
Adds a new function
Called
Get ID sermon statistics and with a
With a random
Key
To ensure that it doesn't conflict with any other method on the page
We had to add this random key here
And it puts it into this variable and that something that you need to
Come and look at
And
Possibly when we look at the the site
Layout area as well as the tablets
I'll be talking about this transition here again
And the fact that you need to know
That it is in this variable
And I'm trying inside of your layouts and your site views
and these things I'm trying to give you the correct name
But it is not
Water tight correctly
Possibly you need to come and check this if it doesn't just work
But again I'll explain that when we get there
just that you know
We're adding statistics into this variable through a method which is also on the page and we passing the ID
Of of the sermon
So if you look at UI
This exactly what we're saying here
We're saying
Okay get statistics multiple
so we Went to the left
Can you can select any of these
And then
Use the main table dot ID
Must be equal to e.sermon
And then this is the only values I want to return
From the e.sermon
So the e.sermon is this value here
okay
o I'm saying a ID must equal is e.sermon
And then if you look at the code
It basically if we go to this function which should be just here
there it is. It takes that ID
And
Places that next to e.sermon
and puts into its place
Basically also here's the two arrays what it
What it is in the database and what it should be now
And
it checks whether executes, checks whether it's got any arrays or any values
And then returns that is an object
List
And that then gets placed inside of this
Space inside here
Now you would see this area here
Is actually custom scripting
So if we go back to the dynamic get you see that there is a custom script area here
If you click on that
You'd see that there is
Different switches
You can select
Get list query
Or before getting the items
After getting the items
If you select after getting the items
And you place any code there
Then data gets dumped right after
The initial items we've
Received
It will it will add that
Code in there and then only return
The items
So that is why you can model the data
Right there in the dynamic get
You gonna write the code
For the data
After it's been get
And you can check
If I remove this
Code here you'd see tells you that there is an array of items
Where all values are
And then I'm just saying
I want to be sure that those items are set and that they are there
Before I start doing it on each of them
And so again here I'm using
Some double
You know the street bracket component helper functions
to check whether the String is there
So you can dump some nice PHP
Even before getting the item you can add some filters or get list query
Before the if you if this is model list
If this is item
You'd see that
Then there's a different set of
Switches is available
And so it
Adjusts to
To the type of
Query type up here
Ok
Coming back to this area
Let's again look at the database table option
Basically you see I selected category and it's a single row that's returned I called it b
I joined it left and I said a
Cat ID must be equal to b ID
Which is the ID of the category
And I only want
The title
And the alias
So that is
how we set that up
I need a title in the alias
And it returns that for us
Then
It links it in there and that's part of what you saw here
when You looked at the query option here
Basically the sixth section here
Now let's look at the filters
You see where we've a filter
And a where and an ordering and setting of Globals
now the setting of Globals
if you have a value in this query
That you possibly want to use in a custom query which isn't even
Setup yet but you want you know I'm gonna need this value in the model
Then you can through this
Global
option here
You can set a global area
now Again here you should maybe test it
There is an option of using this and State
there is the different type of
Set types
You can set the value to state or you can set the value to this
And
here you need to know
key so
So let's I wanna do the name
Obviously in this case is not gonna work ideal
Because you got more than one name
So usually this Global function only functions well
When you are returning a single
Item so when you only do get item not get list query
But you do get
Item
Then this make sense and then you can give it a name
And
it will add it to the global
Scope of the method
or the model rather
Which you can access through other
Model
Methods
Which are custom
Ok so that is setting the global
The filtering
You have a a list of possible filtering
So
Depending on what you wanna do
You might select ID or user or access level or group or category
or Tags or date
Some of these are not really well formulated yet like date doesn't work that well yet
But categories does user group access level user and ID does well
You know this function variable works well
and Array
Array value repeatable value and other
All those already work very well
And you can already use them and
Implement them
Now the only way for you to really
Know exactly how it works you need to know a little PHP and then you need to
compile and go look in the code what it has done and where it's placed what
And that
Is
Why I showed you that this is all set in the model
Ok
So currently
We are saying we wanted to
do a J request
Get into here by ID
So this is the
get area that I added
I look in The code it says
State the key
and it's this Here
you see and we set it is a function variable
So it doesn't change or adapt this at all
And then says it must be equal to preacher
So what we are doing since component builder doesn't know where the this variable is gonna be a string or integer
That's why we have this function which first checks were that is string
And then checks whether it's a number
And related and builds up the query respectively
You might feel that is too much and
you're Possibly right
But that is the only way I am implement it at this stage
And
getting more developers involved
May possibly improve this long run
Then you see there the Access
Now we have a bunch of values that fire every time in a custom
Dynamic get model
And it is the these values
And often times you you might need these values
So instead of you
Having to do custom scripting to get these values on the page
We add these values dynamically every time
So the user ID the group The authorised group the access level
The app and then the input values
Which by other URL or post
is on the page
And it tells you that it's been initiated
so This is set to true so that if you have custom
Methods
Like this one
get Preacher
It's checks whether it's been set
And if it has been set it doesn't set that again it can just use it
But if it hasn't been set it sets it and also again sets it to true
So
variables Global variables
Can then be used inside of the coaches like the global variable we spoke of earlier
Ok so
Out of that Global variable
We are
Actually accessing
This levels
And so it's this one here
Which basically has the get authorized view levels
Of the specific user
That is now
you know accessed this
Model or the view that this model belongs to
And if he is in these access levels
So you remember that public is another access level
And so if the user isn't signed in he's a public it will this will validate true in the query
Ok so
We set that up simply by adding access level
In
A access
So you must check in the
Main
Source table
For access
And whether this user is in that
So that means you don't need to add a state key because
The code is done for you
Ok
That is some of the filters
then the where
Is you can add any table key
Equals to a certain value
now that Value could be another table
like b field
or it could even be a global variable like we said we could set up
So it can also be in ID, a user ID now the user ID is already
On the table so it could be
Just user ID
And or it could be like we've done it this case just an integer which is one
So we wanna make sure that all the
Sermons returned
Is published
And if you have an unpublished sermon it shouldn't even
Return it at all
Ok so That's what we doing with that
That is setting up a get list query
With pagination
Through this
Ordering method we just saying use the a ordering
and a send now you can order all the items
Just add many as you like
Be sure that the table that you
ordering
You could even use a name right
So could be a name
As an ordering
Table key
Then it you could do it a descending or ascending
Then it would be added to the query
Ok
That is also added ordering
To the data set
From
Your Dynamic get method
and so here with the joint view tables you can do very nice
Dependency
Calls
From other tables in the backend
And bring the data together into one items array
That's basically what Dynamic get is for
and as you saw
We have
A
The normal what I call main source on the table
sorry in the model
And then we have this other one called get preacher
So
That is another
Dynamic get function which we
Looked at
it's called this one
Get preacher
if we Open it
We see it's a
It's a custom
Get custom
And we gave it a cluster name called get preacher
and this is It's relationships
So it is basically having No
Relationship there
Neither here so it's
It's not linking to other tables
It's simply getting the preachers details
Right there
Simple as that
But it has a filter which is basically using the same integer
And access levels as the filters
It's also using a where I suppose yes published and it doesn't need ordering
Because it's just one preacher but I none the less added the ordering I could actually delete this
And it doesn't have any globally settings okay so that is get preacher and so from the
This settings here I don't think there's custom scripting nope from this settings here
component builder writes all this code
You'd see that we have this function everywhere called UI kit comp
And then we using a global method a static method get ui comp
it's a method that I built if you know uikit if you don't know it go to get UI kit or just google it
It's a It's a JavaScript
Library CSS JavaScript library which really makes modeling of your views very nice and easy
And it has components that you can use
So like tool tip and model
All these kind of models but Gordian is another component
And we don't load all of it's components every time so what we've done is we've
Written in PHP a method that looks at Fields that are text area fields
And normal text Fields no mostly okay it's
Not looking at every field is only looking at the text Fields and editor Fields so in in this
Component we know that this description field is a
Editor field and so we are sending it to this method now you can go look at this Method Method
In your helper class it's over there
Here's the method so
So it has the classes that already has been identified which is what this
Initial this component area sorry
Field name field value model field value is actually holding
it's Holding any component names that already has been identified this gets
past also here with the content then we check in the content whether there is a class UI
UK underscore and if it's not false we start looping to check what
What what are all the components that are in there and here is the list of the components that are available
and so On-the-fly we are determining whether these components should be loaded just by
Looking at the content that was placed in the description field and then we added back to this
Array so it updates this eventually you have an array of
All those items and in the view we go to the view
Which in this case is gonna be preacher
We open the view dot HTML
We get to a place which basically everything is gonna be happening so
These are of the components that go in component builder compiled
the application it looks inside of the content of your site view as well as your custom admin View
and it identify that these components must be loaded for uikit and so it
Places it here dynamically but since you could've added some components inside of the script that
that is stored in the description area it now has this get uikit component which basically
reach back into the model and in the model gets this
Variables value through a method which is here at the bottom of the page there it is
Get UI kit component basically through this method it is reaching in
Into getting that array and once it has that array we basically check whether it is set
Whether it is an array and if it is an array we set
To the array that is already on this page then over here we loop through that array
And we load in those components CSS and JavaScript as required
so that You always can be sure that the UI kits needed components will be loaded on the page
simply by user adding some of that components to its description as style
Because the way uikit works is you just like Bootstrap you just Add the class name
To the specific div or tag html tag and then it activates
the needed scripting around it which is a nice library but it's
Quite heavy and you don't want it on the page every time now I know you could have done this through JavaScript
You know it is fact they have a way for you to do this through the JavaScript but to me I felt
Let me do the most work in the html so relieve the load on the on the server
And that the browser already has much more Leverage and Freedom so that's why we
This feature this is maybe Beyond the scope of the get the dynamic get
But since we ran into I quickly mentioned it here okay so it is all
Also placed in the query that is developed by Dynamic get that's partly why it
Fits so once you've got your Dynamic get set up you now will add these dynamic
Gets to either site views or to admin custom admin views so these Dynamic gets is what
What gets the data for you and it's where you model the data that you want to work with and you can then
Use them in site views and custom admin views. Now next stop we will look at adding it to a site view and how all of that works. Thank you for watching.