Hi now that we have the dynamic Get in place let's add that to a
Site view and look at the initial implementation we will go to site view
And then click on new but since we already have
That you created we just gonna open it called preacher
You would see there on the right-hand there are 3 Fields that you can
Populate with your Dynamic get methods the first one is where you would add
All the custom Dynamic gets and there you can add multiple custom dynamic gets
The second one is where you add your main Dynamic get as we explained in the dynamic get
Tutorial you can add 1 Main get method per
View or site view since it's going to be build in the model
Either as a get item or a get items it is all depending on the
Main get weather it's gonna be a list or just an
An individual item
Yet you can include Dynamic Gets
Custom Dynamic gets as many as you like
You also have this data available in your view
So these two first fields are used to load
The Dynamic get to the view
The third one
Is used to display the possible way that you might want to implement
The code of a specific
Dynamic get option
You'll see that
This one only displays
Possible main Gets this one only this place customer gets
Where is this displays both
The custom and the main kind of Gets
Now
If you select a
let's go to
One of these Main
Gets
Sermon
This one here
You see that it shows us
A list
Print out of the possible ways that you might
Use the result set
Obviously each of these you can copy by clicking in it and then clicking on
either right click
And
Copy or you could click on ctrl V
ctrl C and command C
to copy respectively the content
Sometimes you might only want to use part of it and not the echo statement included
Then you can pick from the area where you want to copy and then before letting go
Click on control C or command C in a Mac
to insure
you only grab that section of the text
Once you let it go it will select the whole block and then
Obviously if you copy it you will copy everything
As you can see
We then use
This code in our default View
To  display the data
In a PHP
Fashion
You can also get the the customer get here let me show you that one preacher
Like you see it says that that
Value is gonna be in this preacher
And if we look here at the top that is what we are checking for here
Make sure that you have a Preacher
And then this block
Basically deals with displaying the data related to that
Information
This one here
Checks whether the main items are on the on the page and now the main items as you can see
Is sermons preacher ID get list
So if I go down to that
sermon preacher
I get List
You see that again it shows me that the values are in items
And it's in array
So I can loop through it and target the the object values
And that's what's being done here
We first checking whether it's
On the page the values
Then
If we see that it is here
We use make use of templates
to
to display the various
Layouts
And
I will explain in a next tutorial  how to use templates in layouts inside
Of your site View
But this is just quickly showing you how to connect
A dynamic get
Structure or
Methods to your view
And then how to make use of the data that are being passed through to the view
So this data structures here on the right in red
Is basically the the data structure that you can expect
From each one of these so if I was to take number sermons
As the
Method that I want to see
Then it shows me that
That's possibly the way that it will be packed into the data set
So it'll be found in this number sermons is how
Now that could change
Depending on your custome
implementation
In your components custom coding areas you might move this data from that
Position to something else
But the reality is this at least gives you how it would have looked without you
You know I'm leaving the
The normal Path
So this is just
Proposing the dataset structure
Which ideally would be that you would take this value here
And
Maybe do this in the code
Do a var_dump
And then exit
And then
Basically do a build and go look at this view to see exactly the structure
If  you are finding that this structure that we've shown isn't working exactly as we expected
Often this helps us
To sort a map the array and see where What value is found same goes with any of the others
You can just grab that area
That you want to peek into
Put it in var_dump
Do a build go look at this page
In the in the front of your site
And you can see exactly the structure of this
This object here
Whether it is an array with objects or whatever
Is placed inside of this value set through the dynamic get method
Now I just want to quickly
Peek at the
Way that these methods are actually becoming available in your view
by going to the code
And just looking at
Some of the implementations that we've done
Ok
As you can see we've gone to the front of the site
sermon distributor
Models
And we've opened
The preacher model
Use the preacher model
And
As you scroll down you see that there's a get list query
This get list query gets sermon as the a
Table
And then
Series as the C table preacher is the D
and Categories is the
Sorry
C D B
Is the B table
And then it looks for a value
in ID
And then
Sets it equal to preacher
And in sure that it
The person has access level to the item
That's published
And then returns it
So that is the
Get
List query in the model
Have you go back to our
interface you see that we have
sermon preacher
ID get list as the main
And I've opened that Dynamic get here
let me just see where is it
And you can see that
Sermon is set as A the main table
And if you open here you see that series is set as C the only looking for those values
Preacher said is d only those values
Statistics
E
But it's a list
it is Multiple
These that are single are part of the list query where is the multiple of it will have its own object sorry it's
Method
we will Look at that quickly
And then
We see in the DB table
That we have category a single
as B
Only those values
So going back to the code
This is the get list query in the get item
After we have received the items
We look through them
And then in this function here get
Sermon statistics and then a
A generated string
Randomly generated string to ensure
No conflicting with other methods on the page
Puts the values in
ID sermons statistics e
So that's where the values of place
And then basically we have a custom
Method here like be shown in the dynamic get you can add custom methods
And then returns the items to the page
And in the page
You have a
A file
That is called
View
Sorry view HTML dot. PHP
If you open this
File you see that there is a get items
Method being used to place the items in items
And so
At the moment we are actually in the view at this stage
And that means you can access
This set of values
Inside of that
Class field
And so if we go back to our
Component Builder
You would see if we were to select
That method
There is the items
Corresponding to our code
And so we know that the ID in the asset ID in all these are in there if you scroll down
You see that there is it sermons is too sticky see it there
So that means
In the array there is a
key value
Which has another set of array values in it
So you can target these data sets
By corresponding
pointing
Values
So that is just looking at the main get
Now if we were to look at
The other custom get
That is been added
We'll see that here's preacher
Which is a custom get
or custom method
That is been added
And
It also has its set of
Values and it's database structure and remember we said that we want it to be
Link to the preachers ID
So can I check for the ID
And then
Set it to ID
And returns the result
Same goes with the number of downloads
It's also custom method
That said
To this view because of the custom get that was added
And here is the number sermons
And we go back to our view dot HTML dot php file
We see that those values are respectively being added
To preacher
Number downloads and number sermons
And you can actually use these values in the view by targeting with this number
Sermons
Now the view itself is
As you should know inside of
the template folder
Under the views preacher
And this Main
View as we call it all the default view is where that code that we on the page that we looking at right now
Being placed
All these others are the templates that are extending the site View
And they possibly are extended through layouts that are available in the layouts folder
So
We are we are now just looking at adding
The custom get methods to the page in our next to tutorial
we are going in depth about adding templates to your
Custom
Site View
And making use of these data sets
So
That is how you link them your first create the custom get then you come here you link these
So these are the linking
Fields and these are just so that you can see the code snippets are making use of these fields
Respectively
And
That is custom
Gets added to site view
Thank you for watching