Hi
Now that we've added a dynamic get
to
A site view
And we have looked at how to access the data sets
Through the
Examples snippets
We need to understand
How layouts and templates
Link into site views
basically to know
What is the site view in the code
And what is the templates
What is the layout
In the code itself
And how
Joomla load those things
Well
If we go to our example
component
Sermon
distributer
And then
View
And preacher
Template
or Tmpl
You see that there is a
Default
File
PHP
And there is a default underscore
preacher Box
preacher panel
preacher small dot PHP files
A whole list of them
Now those are all templates
The reason why we call them templates
It's because of the method by which they are included into the default
File
The Default file is the main file
And That's what we call the site View
So everything inside of this file
Is actually build
In the side view so let's open the site View
So all this code here in default View
From here to there
Is added
To that default
File
So you see it says default View
And the way it adds to templates
It's with this snippet that says this load
Template
Preacher panel
And you can get these snippets
At the bottom of the
Site View
So if you were to scroll down
You first with see the layout Snippets and then after them that template snippet
And scroll down to the one you have
Made by
Looking at these names
And then here
Is a Preacher grid
List
Table
Panel box
Small
So
That is the snippet that you will use
You might sometimes
Change the way
possibly stay in the PHP instead of going out
into the HTML
So by the way that is what is happening up here
If you look at the code
From time to time I go out of the
PHP I go into the PHP with that tag
And I go out of the PHP with that
Then I go in again may go out again
And then I stay out that I'm
Basically in HTML
So here is
pure HTML
And
Then
Ok this part here is obviously
Uikit
Class and the implementation
And then I go back into
PHP
And I go out again and here is HTML again
So that is a way that you can work with
with PHP
In the view
so if we are going to look at this in the code
And we open that default file
you see that exactly what is placed there cimit
So basically we
End with PHP there
Then we go into PHP again
And here is the same text that we just looked at in that
Editor
So that text gets placed here and then it through these
Snippets it includes the template so basically I'm using a global setting here
And I'm checking now this Global setting is set in the components Global settings
And I'm checking what type of display has been set
And then on the basis of that I either show this template
or That one
or that one
in your Template view you have access to the same Global Fields or
Class Fields and public class methods
As you have in the default View
So in the default view we have access to this preacher but the same is true of
templates these are the templates that I've just opened
And you see I'm using the same this params
Here
This preacher website so I am using the same Global
Class Fields or values depends on how you wanna call it
And that is true of your templates
So if we go back to our
Interface the way that component builder knows that it needs to add this template to
To this site View
Is simply because of this code snippet
so you place code snippet in there and you'll go look in the template
List
For a template with this name
and it will simply add it
To that site View now so what I mean
I mean add it to this
Template with the
In the right folder
So
You can you can by doing that
Add your
Templates to the site View
And will look at setting up templates we also look at setting up
Layouts, layouts work a little different
Let me see do I have a layout here in this site View
It seems I'm mostly using templates you can use templates and layouts in the site View
I have just used
Templates mostly it seems
And that means that possibly the layouts I've used in the templates View
But if I wanted to add a template sorry a layout to this view
Without doing it inside a template which doesn't matter it's just a way of bundling your
Scripts in a more concise manner so that he doesn't be overwhelming
When you look at the code but that you have it
Broken up in pieces
The layout structure is mostly used
When you are dealing with a part of the display area
That is used
across
Other
Display areas
So I usually used the layout structure
The moment I'm using a piece of code
In more than one
View
Or in more than one template
The reality is you could
You could use
Template inside of templates
You cannot use templates inside of layout
But you can use templates inside of templates
And you can use layouts inside of layouts
But you cannot use templates in layouts
and so but these are all conventions that are set forth because of the way Joomla implements the structure
These are not limitations because of component Builder
This is just how Joomla does it it will allow you to add templates
to
The default
Site view
But
It will not
Allow you to add
templates to a layout it will just scream at you
And why
Well the
easiest way to put this
Templates
Have access to the global values
All the class values
Where is layouts do not
You need to pass layout the value that you wanna give it
Now that's important
Point because if you look at these Snippets
You see that we're just passing it this items
But you can even pass it just this
Or you could pass it
A specific value
You have your custom classes
And you can pass it that specific value
From your custom
Class
It all depends and when you setup the layout
You have an area just like this where you select
The
The Dynamic get that you were using in the layout
Now that is not gonna add that dynamic get to your side view
or to the model
It just helps you to see the Snippets
And it helps us to set up
The snippet for you
So if you've selected the wrong
Code here
In your layout we'll talk about that again when we get to layouts
It will actually just changed the way it looks here
But you can obviously override it you can copy this
Snippet like that
Put it in your code where you wanna use it
And then you can just change that
Area that
Is passing the information to the layout because the layout
has not got access to this
And so you need to pass it through it
The values that you want to use in it
It will still look at how exactly that is done and possibly I will
explain it again but just script
Basically renders a layout
And this is also how component builder knows it should add a layout to the components layout folder
And
it looks for a layout with that name in your layouts list
So you need to have these layouts set up before hand
Before you can include them
Into other
Views and
Tablets
And do note that the layout concept and implementation
Together with the template is the same in the custom admin View
It works exactly the same
And just by adding the snippet to the default View
Component builder know it needs to add that layout to the component and knows at least
Add that layout template to that site View
Ok so that is adding
Site views
Sorry templates and layouts to a site View
And
Looking at the code seeing ok so
Component builder builds these site views because when
We look at the default View
They are actually
Loaded here you see
Preacherbox and there is preacherbox
This preacher panel
preacher panel
There is
Preacher small
And there is preacher small and there is
Table grid list there is
Table
grid and list
So that is how you can
Add your code into
Smaller chunks
And next up will look at setting up a template
And
Making use of this implementation
Understanding the difference
So
That is adding templates and layouts to site views