In the previous tutorial we where looking at setting up
Of
Templates and
Layout to a site View
Now inside of the side view we see that we are loading preacher panel
Preachersmall
Preacherbox
So
Let's go look at how to create those templates
I'll go to templates
And here they are already created
You can click on new to start with a new template
You could also copy an old one
By selecting
The template
you would like to copy click on batch
And then there is a copy feature here
And click process
And it'll copy it for you
Ok so
here I have
Preacher panel open
In Preacher panel it's the same concept it's an HTML area so if I wanna use PHP I need to go
Into the PHP
And then I can go out again
And I can also add this text placeholders
Which helps us to ensure
The text itself
Is translatable
You can just do your normal English text like that sermon count
Sermon total downloads
And
Component Builder will add these strings to the language file for you
You don't need to be concerned though at this stage only does
Your
British English language file
And
If you need to add more languages
You need to look up the documentation of adding languages to a third-party extension
And
do that same implementation
Ok so here we see that you can add layouts
To this template by using any of the Snippets
to this template
And you can add other templates to it
So you can use templates inside of templates
And you could have use layouts as well so more or less the same behaviour as in site view
You also have your snippet box here
Which you can make use of adding
Script quickly
To your page
Like that
Refresh
We see that that script that I just looked at here
In the preacher panel
If we go to the code preacher panel
it Is exactly the same script that you seeing here
Ok now
There are a few
exciting points here
One of them is a side note is that in your details tab
In the template area
You're at the bottom
You can add
JavaScript
With your normal script tags
So you can just add your JavaScript in there
And
It will work
And be loaded into the page
Through the small snippet
That's That's a nice
Thing to know
As well as
You are still have access as I said before
to all the global
This field values
Like you can see there
You can access those
quite easily
And that is basically how to set up a template
Is the same kind of conventions as setting up a site View
Except that this is not the main view it is a template used
Somewhere in a main view through
Adding this code snippet
With Joomla class get
template
Method
And
Then
Basically this
Load template
Is the method
That is being used with that name
And then it adds it
Do your component site view as well as
Adds the code to it and everything else
So that is a template next up let's look at a layout
And it really get excited there