Ok we gonna look at setting up layouts now
And we setting up layouts you have
Some nice ways to reuse code across multiple
templates or or site views
and one of the things that I found is that I would like to know which template or
Not Not really which tampered rather which side view
Is actually calling the layout
So that all the bases of that I could use Global settings
That are related that specific site View
So what I've done is I've just in the dynamic get
I've added little string
Since each Dynamic get Targets only a specific site View
So if I was to open
Sermon preacher ID
Which is primarily gonna be used in
Preacher side view
If I look at the custom script
You see that I added a view key called preacher
And by doing that I know ok since this Dynamic get
Is only used in the preacher view
That when the layout is called and
I'm in my component I'm only passing
The item
So not the whole list of items but just one item
To the layout
That helps me to know ok this this specific item is calling from preacher
And I can on that
Basis
You know do certain implementation
To ensure that the layout displays in the way I expected
So that's just a little heads up on making your layouts even more
Dynamic
Then going to the template
We will open
Your
The layout
Sorry the template that calls the layout so we wanna see that initial setup
and one of the templates that really
Illustrates this very well
Is this sermon list
So I'm gonna open sermon list
in sermon list you see that I'm looping through the items
And then
I am
adding
Some parameters to the item
Object
One of them is the Params the other is , I'm taking the description
And making sure that it's escaped and no longer than 19 characters
And then
I'm adding that back to the description
without the full name
And
then adding that item
To the layout
Study class render
Layout help J layout helper
study class Render
sermon
List item as the layout name
Ok and that basically is gonna populate
The Script between
List items
That is gonna be placed in an unordered list on the Sermon list page
Ok so now let's go look at this specific layout
Layout helper
Sermon list item
So
In layouts
Look for sermon
List item there we go
and in sermon list item
You see that I'm using that
Global
The item that is being passed is placed inside of displayed data
I'm so now display data is basically
The item object
And since I
Placed the parameters in it so I can use different
Get method
With the specific Global
Field name
Which is set in the components Global settings
And since I'm
Targeting a specific layout
Sorry
View
I'm using the view key
Adding it to the string and checking what is the value for this specific view in the globals of the component
And
On the basis of this
I'm actually able to make this view very dynamic
And can use it through multiple layouts
Based on that
View key
Now I know if others want to use the layout in their components extending this one it possibly
will not work that well
But since we are using it for our own component
And really for only implementation I don't think that's too big a deal
And
At the same
Token I am able to check
Simply what is the view key is it preacher series or category and on a basis of that I ask different
Questions that have different implementation of certain
Values like series name preacher name and category
And there is another Convention that I think is very worthwhile mentioning here
And that is the convention of actually
In the template
We go back here
And we go to custom scripting
There is the S
View placeholder
S view placeholder
Will be replaced
With the actual views name
Now since we using a template here
So you see this is a template
But this sermon list
That one
I'm adding that template
To multiple site views
So I'm not just adding it to one site view
I'm adding it to multiple site views
But since I want this template again to be Dynamic so wherever I add it I
I want it to dynamically
Add
That site views name here
And then is as you can see I'm actually asking
The global parameters
For that site view sermon list style
So
That means
Is is going to add
For example preacher there or it's gonna add series there or is gonna add category there so it will say
category sermons list style let me show you that in the code
So now I have category open
I've got preacher open as well as series
And you can see
That I'm adding sermon grit sermon list sermon table to them all
sermon grid sermon list sermon table
Sermon grit sermon list  sermon table
But if I was to open
Sermon list in series
You see that that name
was changed to Series
If I was gonna open
Sermon list in preacher
You see it was changed
Preacher
If I open it in category
You see that it actually added category
And that means that our Little Place holder
Was dynamically updated by component Builder on the build
And then
It behaves as you expect now
That you would know
where is it getting these values
If we If we go to the component in the backend
And
We open it's config
File
Scroll down
We get you an area called preacher custom config
Which is again this is a tab
And tab's name is preacher
and in this tab
We have these value preacher display
preacherbox contrast
preacher list style
And we scroll down we see preachers sermon count
preacher email Preacher website
and then preacher sermon display
And preacher a sermon list display
Now if we take that sermon List display
And then search for it
across
The file say make it
Cap sensitive
we see that it has 6 matches
So that means there is 6 places
Actually 3
Because one of
Each other 6 are in the comments
one is category
one is series
And one is
Preacher
So those are the different the three different views
Let make use of that series list style
Now the Series list style
Is then being implemented
On the basis of
That Dynamic updating of the string here
And so it's simply getting the style
Then doing a switch that when setting it accordingly
And that is
Another nice
To have tool
To again make a template
More Dynamic so you can build a template
And you can reuse it in multiple site views
Simply with this place holders
Which is called site view ,I should have mentioned that in the templates
Explanation
But since we only came across it now I mentioning it here
Going back to the layouts
Your layout
Concept is more or less the same as templates
It has a layout area in which you put your script and here you can see
We are using that key replacing
You can see that if you select certain Dynamic gets we are taking
Liberty of showing you that we are starting with display data
But this this
Snippets here
Might not correspond what you're doing because you can really pass anything to a layout
And we are just assuming that if you're using that dynamic get you possibly passing it in this
This way or that way
So you can't just copy paste this necessarily
But at least you can know when you look at a specific Dynamic get here
What are the values in it
And you know how you can sort of try figure out
Which ones to use here
This again will be only really
Something you need to use
If or can use if you are actually aware of our PHP and
Everything will
Do the implementations here
And if you do not if you're not that familiar
You don't need layouts I mean you can you can build your whole front-end right in your site view
It might be a long lengthy script but it still work
All the only reason we added layouts and templates is simply for our own convenience
And if it's little confusing to you can even if you skip this whole area
For the meantime
Beginning layouts you have the same concept of adding custom scripting
Which will be placed in the head of the file
And remember that your Global data or in the data being passed is in
Display data
And then here again you have your
HTML area
But you can jump into PHP and
Check the sum values and then on the basis of that to your certain implementations
And
That is really setting up a layout
Just another note you can actually use a layout in a layout
And you can pass it values
as any value you like
I realized that this here is maybe not that appropriate
So you need to keep a heads up that
This doesn't exist on the layout page
You need to use the
Display data as the global
or as the main
Object from which to start
Your implementation
OK that is layouts thank you for watching