We need to have a quick look at custom admin views
They do have some nice ways of doing things
Very similar to sight views
But some
Aspects and adding it to component builder is different
And so in the next video We will look at adding site views  as well as component
Custom admin
Views
To the component
The reason I didn't speak much about the custom admin views is simply because
Summon distributor is not
Using
Custom admin views yet
Where is I have another component here I can use as a example
Called component
Is called
Cost-benefit projection
It's a It's a tool that is used to show companies the cost benefits
Of intervening on certain diseases and causes in the company
Anyway
In it we have what we call a company results
And combined results
Respectively used
To display custom data
In the back end of the component
to the certain different
people who has permission to view those data
Now in the component itself
If we clicked on companies
You would see there is an icon underneath each of these
Names of the Companies
And there is a new button here the top called combine
Results
Now
This button as well as those buttons
Are dynamically added by component Builder
And in the next tutorial I'll show you exactly how that is done
What I want to show you here is
Simply how a custom admin view will look
So I'm gonna click on one of these,  this is all dumb information so
So you'll see me
Let's open this one
Now basically you have this big area where you could put a lot of HTML and PHP
And you have some custom buttons that you can add on show you that
And then
So all of this in this white area is simply done in the custom View
So if I was to click around
I've got a menu here at the side
All of this is done inside of the custom
Area
Of the component
Which is now the
Custom admin View
And
That is basically how it will look
It has Different
Value sets
And you can from here add an edit button
Since we've linked it to a specific client
Or company or one item in that list
We can actually click on edit
From here we go right into the company's data
And edit it
And
What is nice if we were to click close here
You actually take us back to that
Exact result page
And you can then go and look at
The implementation
What you've done
Is it that is just simply showing you how a custom admin view could look
Let's go back to the company's list or we could go back to dashboard
now look at component Builder
And we looked at this company results we open that one
And here is all PHP and HTML
On my page
Doing all the work
And of course
As you might expect
I'm loading in a lot of templates here
So I'm loading in templates
Directly
From here
And
Then I have a custom button area
Where I can I can say yes I want to add custom buttons
Then I click on
Custom buttons here and you see I have
Icons I can select
Call it
The name of the button
And a controller method
Which I would like to use to actually make the button work so in this one I'm saying go to company
This one is edit company
And
here I should say
Is this gonna
What kind of Target are we think looking at
Is this a
A single a list or both
And you said that respectively
And
Then you click save this only saves it to the form not to the database
We should have made that done
But this is the Joomla's way of implementing it
And now you have to add
In the PHP controller method
Add scripting
to respectively implement the buttons click
Method
You can also to the model
So in the controller
You can add script and then in the model
Add scripting which is called from the controller if you want to separate your code a bit
In the in the and if you're not gonna be adding
Any script to the model Just add none
with this two
Spaces in front otherwise it might scream at you that you
did not add Script there
And as you can see the go to companies is simply
Take me back to the company's View
Where as the
Edit company
Implements the Joomla's convention of opening an item to edit it
By the correct channels so this is just
Joomla knowledge At work here
And we are checking a token and all that
So do Component
Builders sets of all the tokens and everything
So you
The snippet you can reuse for your purposes if you want
And obviously we have an area for custom scripting and as you can expect
There's a lot of custom scripting
Going on
In in that View
And it has its respective places again if you wanna know where what's happening at some snippet here
Compiler components search for that snippet and you'll see where this comes up
If you're not certain by the naming conventions we have used
And that is really how you setup a
admin custom admin View
To look at the other one
Let's close out here
That is the combined results View
Now the combined results is this one up here if you click it now I will tell you this in we need to have some item selected
And then you select the items and click
There again
And it will do a combined resolve
Taking both companies
And
Adding it's data together
And giving you a nice layout structure
Of it's data sets
Ok
That is really the combined concept
If we go back
To the implementation of it
It looks very similar as the other
Again just a lot of HTML PHP here
And then
Also some custom button is again just going back to companies
And it's really just same implementation V card companies go back single
And then some custom scripting
And that's how I set up both of those custom views
quite simply
Adding that the data here
And then making use of the templates as well as layout implementation in both of these
So you can set up layouts and templates and
Only use them and site views
But you can also use them in admin views
Now
In our next tutorial
We look at how to add site views and admin views to your component
Since there are some differences
And you need to be aware of them