Hi
Now let's look at adding admin views and site views to component Builders component
And looking at all the different switches and the nice features that we have there installed for you
So we first login here
Then we have component builder open on the component builder
And then we will go to
Let's see components
And we will open
Sermon
Distributor
And then go to settings
And in settings you see there is a place for admin views we're ready illustrated adding the admin views
Then there's custom admin views and their site views
And we wanna look at those now so I'll just click on add custom admin View
There isn't any added to this component because component builder
Sorry
sermon distributor does not have
a Custom admin views
But I'll illustrate it in another component for you
Then site views
It has quite a few
You might sometimes open it and see
That some of the buttons are not selected
Although you know you selected it previously and saved
You know now doesn't show
This is a glitch and
In the
Joomla's own
JavaScript or whatever
That is causing this and so the only way I have found to solve it as yet is to simply
re-open
Like for now you see the admin view that's same issue
So if you close it and open it again
It has it all selected
This is a heads up keep a look out for this because if you make changes and save it with those buttons unticked
Your build will
Not include those values
Since it will be stored as null
And
Yeah you might get unexpected results
So always make sure that your old ticks are
All in place that just a heads up
Not really something I can change at this stage it is a
Joomla thing
of the repeatable fields
Ok so if we go to site view
And we just
Close it again and
Open it again
You see everything is selected
You see that it has 123
4 options here
Obviously here you select the site views
Just add as many as you like
Then add menu means that this site view will be added to the add menu
Aspect of Joomla
You know If you go to create menu
And then you go to add menu
Item
Then there is a select
Type and when you click on select type then there is this list
Articles and whatever
Now if you say yes there you'll create a XML file
Which allows
Joomla to notice that your component needs to be in the list
And the XML file we will look at in the moment
But that's just you know that's what this
Switch here add menu does
Add metadata means that
this page
Is gonna actually make use of the Net the metadata
That is being passed to it
Usually that means that in your model you've set up your data
So that there is a
Metadata in the items array or in the
In the item array or in the this array
Either By by
The global setting or
By the the actual item
So this is meta implementation
You even if you set yes here
And you did not
Set up the data in the in the model
Correctly it won't work and the way for you to look at that is obviously click yes here try
your best setting up the data the model then compile and go look in the view
.HTML.PHP file to see how it grabs the meta data because it will still add
The Script that is needed to load the metadata into the
the document
But if it doesn't
Grab it correctly
Then you'd see that as well
Ok then
Whether you can only have one default View
So don't click more than one to yes
but what the default view effectively is is that sometimes when
You make a change and the system doesn't know where you wanna go
It actually throws you back to the default View
Know that default view could either be your sights default view being home page
Or it can be if your in this component it could be for example on this one it's preachers
So
Let's say some of these views you set that they don't user
a Public user don't have access for example to sermon then if they try to access that page
The system will throw them back to the default view and give him a message saying you don't have access
And so that's what the default View
Primarily used for at the moment
But I can see it being coming even more useful as we continue to improve in component Builder
Then add access
It's basically making sure that a Sydney user has the specific access rights
You see in a in an item you can set the access rights
As well as the view rights
So it's multiple implementations
Different implementations one's access groups the other one is just groups
And so you can tweak whether you want access on this specific View to be monitored
And
If you tick that
Then
Component building will ensure that the access
Table is there
Ok
So that is adding a site view
to
to your component
Obviously after having created the site view
Then this is how you can add it to check it
See how it works
Ok now next up we gonna look at
Custom admin views being added
Thank you for watching