Hi
Now we'll look at adding custom admin view to a component
We'll make use of cost-benefit projection
As our component
And then we
Go to settings
And then we'll go to custom admin views
And we'll see oh let's just
Close that
open again
Now will see you there has to custom admin views added
Now
It has more switches than the site view because of its implementation being more dynamic
You can choose an icon
Because in the backend
You possibly
want to have an icon when your on that page
on the right
of the page
Then you can decide where this should show in the main menu
Selective if you should show in the main menu the main menu
Is a menu that drops down out of Joomla's menu item list
Right
And then the dashboard
Which is that
Dashboard we go to every time when we start with a component that
All the icons are showing up
Then the submenu is the one on the on the left
Which you see when you are in a view
So these are all placements where you can possibly add
This
Custom View
Now if you remember
The company
Results we didn't add
to
Any of the
Views individually we added to items so that's why all of these are set to no
And
That means we are targeting an item
In a view
And so all we need to do a select the view which we are targeting
Which is company
And we say ok
It has metadata yes or no
And it has access yes or no
And
That's basically it
To ensure that
Targets the correct view is simply by selecting company here
If I close this for a moment
And then open that component
Show you what is happened with the settings
So here we have that component open
If I was to open
Companies over here
You see that has a button here
for company result
Now
If you remember when we set up this custom admin
View
We we ensured that
We are targeting an item ID
And by selecting company we are saying we are targeting this company's item
ID
And that is what makes it work
And then we said we want to see a chart
I'm so if we look at these this little charts what shows up in
The icon itself
We click on it
We see the custom view shows up and that icon shows up next to it
And all works well
We also see that there is a combined results
Button showing up here in the toolbar
And that is because combined results
Which selected we want cogs
To be the icon
And we set
List of records is set to yes
And has metadata
And has access and also company
And so
These selections before
Is only really necessary when you select main menu and submenu
Because then you want to say before what
Item you want this
Menu to be created
Now we selected dashboard list of Records
And because of that
It places that in here
And you need to select the records that you want to look at
And then you can click on the combined results
And they'll grab those IDs and
Since we are modelling a data in the controller and the model
It gives back to the view these results
Through the custom implementation we've done
So
Just a quick refresher
If we go to component Builder
And custom admin views
and we open company results
We see that in the custom button
We added the PHP
We also added the button
We explain to
To component builder what we what kind of buttons we want
So we set we are targeting a single item you see those
Edit company go to company now those buttons
are
Actually related to
Going inside of the view
And
Then if you come out of this
We saw that even and combined results
We also added buttons
But again those buttons Vcard companies gotocompanies
corresponds to this controller
And if we go to the view itself
And we'll see that that's not responding to this button but actually
To the buttons inside called companies and edit
Those that's the buttons you were building in the custom View
Where is the buttons we are looking at in here
Is related to opening the custom view itself
So
That is just a quick
Refresher
Same goes with the combined results
The combined results is the button that you are setting up here
Where is the other buttons are once you have combined them
And you've click combined results
You see that it adds two buttons dashboard and companies and those two buttons was set up in the view it
Self
So that you can know and sort of
Understand what
Area controls what set of buttons
This area controls the buttons before opening
the view where is in the view the buttons your setting up there is for when you have opened the view
Ok so that is setting up a custom admin View
To your component
And some of the switches obviously again
If anything is unclear or you not exactly sure
You can obviously come on and do anything
So simply go change it to what you would think should work and compile a component and go look in the code
And see what has been done and look and the
Joomla
if the face
See what is being displayed
And play around with it until you get that what you expected
Just a quick heads up this
ordering before is only compulsory when
Actually selecting add to main menu or add sub menu
And if you use those
It means
That
If
If you go to your component
You have the icons area and here in the top you have your your
Your
Main menu items
And once you've opened
A
Then you're here on the right you have sub menu
So this is main menu this is dash list
Now dash list is that one which goes to the top
Of the
Of the components
Toolbar
and then submenu is the one here on the side
So if if this
Custom admin view is simply needs to be placed in the submenu and its lives on its own it's not related to any other
Dataset
Then you can use the submenu method if you only wanna
Featured in the main menu these are all the features that you could set
Where is the dashboard
List record
Feature
Helps you to sort of
Link it to a specific set
Of
Data data structures like
Like this one does
So you can select these ids and when when you click
On this combined results the ids of the selected items gets passed
to the controller
And if I go back to that quickly
Show you that how we use it
Combined results
Custom button
You basically see that
Go to companies
Is not in here
So we see we're using the main get called companies data get list query
So let's go look at that data query I think that's we will find
The use of the implementation of those ids
So we see we are basically reaching into the
Input array
Array sorry object here
We getting CID
Selected ids
And we saying
It can be SMD
And
Then we are exploding it and
We are making sure it is intervals
And we placing it in ids
And so this actually gets the value
From the post
Object
And
Places that into ids and here we do some validation
To ensure that the person who's trying to access
the data has actualy the right
To do it
And once we past that
We basically use those ids
to
to get
The data so in in the filter
We use ids
And check whether
All the IDs
Are in a ID and that in the code
Basically if you look at the code
It's on the models combine results
We see that it uses our checking method here
Later
down here
It checks the IDs
Puts it array check if it's in array then implodes it
And checks whether it is
You know only gets those IDs
That's how we we filtered the dataset
With the results
of the selection
And
So
That's just a little bit looking into the backend
On how to make use of those
Features and again as you can see it's some custom scripting we added to the dynamic get method
To take those ids and to use them
In the way we intend
now you you can ignore them
But here is the way that I implemented it
If you wanna drop that down pause the video
And copy some of this area here
Think would be the only part that will be
Useful to your purpose
And then you can use the IDs in your code
As you please
And know that this PHP as you saw
In the code
It runs before the get methods
So it basically is a filtering option as you see there
So then this query starts
Then that code be wrote
Is entered in here and then the rest of the code which is
build by component Builder
Is being done and you can use a filter option with whatever you
Collected up here
Ok so that's
Looking into adding custom admin views to component Builder
And just showing you again the tremendous
Leverage and
Design choices you can make
In ensuring that your component is dynamic
And
Get sort of breaks out of the mould
So that you can achieve
Nice
Complex components
Write inside component Builder
Thank you for watching