Hi
We wanna look at MySQL tweaking
In the component area
It's open a component go to settings
And then there is MySQL tweak
What is this able to do is if you have multiple versions of a component
And
Partly you have demo that relates to a certain version of it and
Implementation of
Items
And
In another version you don't want those items that you know included
We have this MySQL tweak area
Where you can actually
First you've select that specific View
That you
Want to tweak
And do note that you can only make use of this feature
If you're actually using the
This
Area
Where we actually add Database
Connection between The View
Dummy data
And view itself
So let me quickly show you what I mean
So here I have opened field types which is one of component Builders own views
And I have it connected
To my Database
Through this MySQL I added yes I selected table
And then I selected
The field types
In my Database
And basically
Just let it all be taken into the build file
And
Now
Since you know that some of the versions that we distribute with component Builder
Doesn't have all the field types in it
And it's a limited
To only a certain few field types
So to show you how that was done I will go back to
That tweaking
Feature
So here I have component builder open
And if I go to settings
And I go to
this tweak feature
It's see that
I have
Added
Values here
and certain of them like custom admin
I said no don't
Include non no
Add MySQL to view Table if set in the view
So if the if the in the view if you have the MySQL selected
you can through this feature
Control which items actual IDs
Should be
Included like in the admin view
I'm only including these two ids
From my Database
And so it's the ids in the admin table admin view Table
And I'm also saying that it's ID based
You have the feature of
Just including all
And then you have id based
So it's a
A way to say what you want here
You can also if you are using ids between let say 1 and 50
Then you can use this arrow
Notation with an equals
Open open bracket there
to know take between 1 and like here 500
You want to add
And
You can actually
Do it quite simply with one two three and then
Comma
Ok here I'm explaining it nicely it says 1234 or
And then you can put a comma and then 20
And then another comma and then 40 to 90 so you can in the same comma
Delimited list
You can add this notation
To show that we need to include 1 to 4
And is immediately after it
Add 20 and we will
Grab all that
Ids and
In fact it illuminate any other ids and only use the ones that you have
Actually notated
So here is another
Good example of
Using 1 4 2399
So goes on in here
We going from 597 to 604
682 - 68
And it's in the same comma delimited list
And we saying is it's id based and we say include these
So that is
That is partly what I'm having why why this is here what it can be used for
So you not including dummy data or example data in your component build structure
Then this area is really redundant and you don't need to even use it all
You can just ignore it system ignores it as if it doesn't exist
If there isn't any
Data selected
Well that is some tweaking feature
In component Builders component area
That helps you
Manage your
Dummy data between
Versions in
In your applications Thank you for watching.