Hi
Today we would like to look
At
Component builders
Options
Or what we would call Global settings
Now I possibly through the
Tutorials have
From time to time touched on certain areas
Now we would like to give a more
Precise look at
The options area of
Component Builder
It's accessible through the options button
And if you have the
Permissions you'll see this button
and I can open it
The Permissions
By that I mean certain users may not see this button if they are in it
Different group than that Global
administrator
And
You can change those permissional structures is as needed
So you click on options
And this will open
The component builder configurations or global settings as it's often referred to
or options or settings
And there are number of switches here that is worth knowing about
These areas here you could add your own details if you would like to
have it displayed
In the components front-end
Then there is a switch here at check-in timer
We build into component builder the option to check in the items
Every so often
And here you can check
If an item have been locked out for 5 hours it brings it back in 12 hours
24 hours
Every second day once a week or never
So the check-in timer is set here
And you can change it to whatever is best suited to your system
And then enabling version
Version control
Is what this area is all about
You can disable it by simply saying no
Or enable it by yes
And then you can say how many
Versions should be kept of the item
If 0 all all versions will be saved so 0 means
Everything
And so you can Limit it
To sort of prevent your system from
of being overloaded with data in the database
Then
You have minify JS
Feature
Basically all the JS that is being built
In a component Builder
Can be
Changed to be minified
So
Why you are in production
You can export your components
Without minifying the j s
In the files and in the footers of the of the documents
But the moment you feel that you've reached
The place where minification is necessary and you want to use it
Then you'd simply trip the switch here
And that would minify JS which is your
JavaScript
In the component
While it's being complied
Ok
And then just some details my wife
Being very involved in
Discussing
She is a Java Developer
And
Helping me look at some of the implementations
As well as my own details
And like I said you can add more contributors here and they will show up
in the dashboard underneath contributors
Then the
UiKit
settings
This is primarily for the backend at the moment being implemented in certain areas
But this is only really needed most of the time and the front-end framework
Of your component
So I've added it to component builder simply so that
There
If I
At some point decide to start adding
a front end shop for the components that's being developed
That's part of what we possibly would design eventually is a front end Distributing
Software
That was built by component Builder
So you could install this and
Then run it from your
It's Like factory with a front end basically
That is still in planning
We still looking at some of the security risks since so far we've been encouraging people to use the
Component builder offline and not online
So we not even sure how this will work possibly we might end up with two
Components ok then the encryption settings component builder has a few places where it encrypts
Some of the data in the database
And we are using a basic encryption which means we are using this key that you enter here
Once you've entered this key
I think because it shifts without a key in it
So look like that
So once you've entered the key
Please ensure that you don't change it
Because
This key is what
Locks the data and it's the only key that can unlock it
So if you remove this key you cannot unlock it so you could remove it if you wanted to
Prevent people from knowing the data in those fields
But then you need to save it somewhere else because if you don't have it
Then you can't retrieve the data
And decrypt it
Ok
The next up his folder paths
.
There are two folder paths that you already can make use of the backup folder and the get folder path
Please read related
Notation here
Where is the custom folder path in the compiler folder path
I would suggest at this stage that you don't make any changes to them
I added these fields because I envisioned the possibility that we want to move these folders
Out of our
Web
Area of developing
Since these are part of the security
Concerns we have
That these files and his folders might be targeted
But I haven't fully implemented this all cross the compiler infrastructure
So currently it's best to leave that
folders the way they are by not adding any data in here
Sorry I clicked on the back button there anyway
Said by just leaving this fields blank
We ensure that
The
Next type we can look at the permissions
Now the permisional structure in component Builder
Is not that intense
But as you can see there are a lot of permission switches
With the latest Joomla release of Joomla 3.5
This permissional structure updating construct is made much easier
In the past
We had a problem
Were the data set of your permissions is so big
That when you save it it just freezes up your browser and even the server doesn't wanna receive the data set it's to big
Now they have added Ajax per field
Which makes this so much easier
That means that currently
Without clicking save and close You can make changes to the permissional structure and that
Immediately will be stored to the data base
That's from version 3.5 Joomla
Now
How would that be a see we still have these areas that we also want to store
So
What I have thought might work
Possibly my implementation isn't that accurate
But
You have here configurations only as a permission so I would say take a
Certain group
Give them that configuration only
Access
And then
Log out
Of this user login to a user that is in that group
Then this permissional or tab won't show
they will only see the settings
And which are in these tabs right
And so they can make changes to these and save them without any
Browser latency or
Overload
Where is you can come in and you can just tweak the permissions when you are in the global or super administrate
So you can come in here and you can tweak the permissions accordingly
So as you saw previously
What I was here the manager area I could just changed
Change this and it does a Ajax storing of the value in the database
Which is really smart I am very grateful that they've done that
Search for the main reason that this this set of the
Remissions
Became so huge
That I had in some places had to do server adjustments on some of my components
To to ensure that the user could still save and change the permissions
Now
So you have your
You're a global create delete edit edit State edit own
Edit created by and edit created date
And then you get
The per
View
permission structure
So here is the admin view then the custom admin view the dynamic get
And they all have their own
Different areas that you can change permissions
Four groups to be able to do this or that
The same permission implementation
Options and
Structures
Are available to all components built by component Builder
As you trip the switches for the fields as well as
For your
Certain
Views
Let me just go out of this to show you
Components
Then first be look at
components
Sermon distributor
here
In the admin views
You have here
This access control
But this is not the only place of implementation
save and close
If you go to the admin views
And let's say we open
Preacher
You have the permissional structure here
Edit
Now if select view is gonna use the view name if you select core
you will fall back on the core edit
And
Delete
Features corresponding
So if you use the word View
View dot edit
you will see in the permissional structure and edit
Switch with this views name preacher dot edit
Where as you use the word
Core dot edit that you would only see
Edit or delete or create whatever
Select
And this in relation to its record means that it will be added
To the record itself you can tweak the edit structure
This is only the global setting or this is for both
And so that is party how you control some of the permissional switches we just looked at
The other area is in fields itself
You have your a permissional structure
Where you can say ok this specific field let say the preacher name
I wanna control that permission who can edit it
Is what you would add
who Edit button
Currently we are not yet implementing who can View
Since we were having problems with
Tremendous overload of
Switches being added to the permissional structure
Joomla now made this change we might possibly add that in
Then you can't even have a
View who can view that
That field
Where is this is currently just who can edit it
Ok
So this is how you get a Fields permissional switch
Now
Let me give you this is an example
Let's make that one for now
Name
Say that it must be permission
Save and close
Here I have sermon distributer open so I will open it's options
Go to his permissional tab
Then scroll down
And I see first here is the help documents
And here's preacher
And preacher has side access and an access to preacher itself
And batch create
Dashboard add dashboard list delete edit
edit created by edit created date
Edit own edit State edit version
Export import submenu and then it starts with series
So as you can see it doesn't show name here yet
So what we'll do is now will go back to component builder go to compiler
And we will select sermon distributor
And compile it
Wanted completed I'll just click on the install button here
To do a quick install
Now that that is completed let's go back to the configuration and just refresh
The page I'll just click on the refresh here at the top
Now if we scroll down again it we'll get here we said
See it got a new field here called preacher edit name and how I can decide
Can this group edit that name or is it denied or should it be inherited
So the permission or structure per field can be added in this way
I'm gonna go back and revert that
Because I actually don't want
I don't want that area to be monitored
So go back
Open preacher
Back to the
Fields
Say no
Close compiler
Select sermon distributer compiling it
Then installing it
Going back refresh
And we see that the field is gone
So it's no longer being controlled by this permission
Infrastructure
And so that is how you can
Tell which
Group is able to access which fields
And even a which
Views are accessible
Through the permissional of structures
This is an amazing advantage of component builder in its ability to integrate the
Permissions not only per view
But also
Per
Field in a view
And your normal control also related to a specific view and not only that it
Also adds these permissions to every item
So you could override an item
And say ok this item I don't want that group to actually access this field
And this is one of the advantages that component Builder
Has above other
Similar applications out there
It's it's ability to implement some of the most advanced concepts that are currently accessed
Ok so that's a quick look at the
Global configuration options
for component Builder
Thank you for watching