Hi
Ok I would like to quickly demonstrate how to set up a time
field
Now you know that
In programing obviously a time must always be linked to a date
Because time is stored as an integer
And
therefore
If you only want
A Field Where only a time is set let's say
5:15 or something
Then I would suggest to use a normal text field
And you
Create a regex
Method
This could be done via a
I just close this
Custom form
Filter
The way to setup a custom filter
let me use
This component
you go to modules and then you would see rules
And in here you can create a rule
And then you would use that as the filter name
So you would
component Builder you would create a file
And you would place it in your custom folder
Any any name
Put it in here
So let me illustrate that let me
Well I'm gonna illustrate that
I'll just use one of these files to illustrate how to include it
But you would basically create a
Rule
How to create to create a rule
I think let me see if I can get you some documentation on that quickly
I think the easiest would be to basically go to your
Scroll up here
go to
Your in component
You're in Joomla right
So you go to libraries Joomla
Then form
and then Rules
Can You can open any of these rules
And you can look
And what they've done
And you would follow the same convention
you basically extend
J form rule
You give it a unique name
Make sure it isn't one of these
Jform rule
And then
We are already component Builder
Already when it when it constructs the
The XML document
That is used
In your
Construction of your form
Sermon Distibuter  modules
your Form
If I open any of them let say this one
it already includes the rule path
you see and that rule path is This rule
So if you are using a filter
So how you would apply it is this you would simply add the word filter
equals now in component builder there is actually a way
to add This
But basically
That would be the same name
As
That I suppose
that Tel
would be the filter name
Ok
And then in here you have your
Test which
Basically tests
Whether this is
Acceptable
And in here you could do regex and all kinds of nice
Means to to validate whether the input field
On the server side is actually acceptable
So this is a server side
Verification of the input
And so you'd see in component builder if I'm just go there
It's a new
And I would select text
Just a normal text field
You would see that it has here
Filter
As well as validate
Now I think the rule gets placed here in validate
That's right
Validate is where you place your rule name so your custom rule name might be time
for example
And then that would ensure
On the server side that only time was submitted
Now The Next Step to
Ensure that
The user only types in
.
numbers and a colon
Instead of anything else
would be able to do some JavaScript here in the
View footer
You could add JavaScript here that targets
This field
Via adding a
A class a unique class name here
Or
Going to the form where the field
for example this is a field right
it use firebug
And you would select
That field
so in firebug you will see the ID
So with JavaScript
You can
target the input of that ID
And if that
ID has input that is not what you would expect from time
Then you could
either scream at the user or shout or just
Emptied the box with a little note under it
But that would be a JavaScript implementation on top of your text
Field
Now
That is maybe a long explanation
But that is how you do a field if only you want time
If you want time and you don't mind that there is a date in volved
I actually have
Build a field like that already
That I'm using
You see because in
In the repeatable Fields you can't use the calendar
Field
So I created a field
That's sort of
Allows me to still do that
let me show you
There is a component I'm working on
registration component
So if we go events
Open an event
Then you would see that ok
Yeah I can set dates
But these dates
If I click in the box
You see it has it time
Adjuster
And I can select a date
And adjust the time and click done
And it updates the field
With that selection
If that is the kind of field
That you're looking for then implementation is quite different
I can I can do to show you that
Ok so I'll open it you can see it it the type is a text type
So basically I've just added it added it hint
It's just a normal text type you could pause the video
And you can look at the field XML
Now since I'm using this field in a repeatable
Field
the JavaScript
Is quite different right because you
You have a working with a repeatable field that you can add as many Fields as you like
But you want this date field to be active on everyone of those
And you can't really
Target
A repeatable field
Simply by adding some JavaScript in this area here
Unless you know that feels ID and so instead of doing it in here
I actually added to Javascript that is needed to make this field work
Into the repeatable fields structure so let me close this and show you that
Case I think it's event dates
So one of those
Values there is obviously the ID
Of that date field that
I did I just showed you and so in scripts
Again here I can maybe zoom in a little
You can you can pause the video
and exactly look what I did there
Basically including
Some Styles as well as some JavaScript
And then I have a loop
Which Loops 50 times
Because I'm only allowing ,if you are looking at the repeatable field
I'm only allowing 50
Fields to be added
So I only need to loop 50 times
And then
In the loop I'm actually targeting through the dynamic
PHP
I'm targeting each of those fields
At the moment there's a row added I'm checking whether that row exists if it does
I'm simply using the jQuery
Date
Time picker which is actually
Brought to The Page by this
The Script here
And then it has some options which is tweakable
And that's it
That's how I add
That kind of date selecting
picker method
In a repeatable field
Again I will hold it a bit there you could pause the video
jottle that down if you want
and Scroll down again
This is this is actually the end of the code
that is the start
Ok that's all that it takes
To to add
O, yes another thing because I have multiple data Fields so if you open that again
You see that
here I have a start and an ending date
And here in cost adjustment
I also have
A
Target date
And so if you look at my script
You'd see that I have a field type array
Which basically is used to Target
those different fields in there different pop-ups
So
You would if you only targeting one field
You wouldn't need this extra iterating
Method or
Variable which I'm using here
Instead of having to retype it for every field I just added
A loop
In the PHP it's just code Ok that's
I think that should do it
About further documentation
I realized that that might be necessary
And
Honestly I just don't have time at the moment
Because their component isn't earning me
A great deal of income
Besides the fact that I myself
I'm using it and developing components and I have developed quite
a lot already
I realize that that might be a community project
And something I would
Actually encourage
So
Everywhere in component builder in any of it's list view
We have an help menu
Already
Which actually opens up
A
Website
Which has a wiki
Option
it's Actually a redmine website
Here is the URL you could see it
And if if anyone wants to get involved in in the community
We help improve the documentation
per list view as well as per function as you can see I've already done quite a bit in writing
Documentation for every list View
Explaining these buttons
And
Even So on so this help button here you could add your own Help by going to the help
Documentation
And here is the list of the already set up help
If you open one of these
You would see that here is the URL that we're using
And
Obviously
As we develop this component further
We would eventually add more help documentation right in the component
But it will in actual fact map to this
This website
Because that way or everybody can benefit from any improvements
So the website URL
For those of you
Might wanna go there
It's  projects. VDM
Again projects and
Joomla component Builder
Wiki
And yes you could I
Suppose just go there and from there navigate
If you want to get involved in editing the
The tutorial or the documentation
And you say to me, OK Llewellyn
I would help you setup
Documentation
Give me a greater discount on accessing the tutorials
We could strike a deal
Because to me I really I have a time
Constrained
and so at this point
As a community project
I hope you understand
Thanks so much