Hi
I would like to give you a quick tutorial or demonstration on how to use
user creation method or function
In your component
What is the user
Creation function
It is basically a part of code's helper function actually
That gets added to the helper class
If you don't know where the helper class is let me quickly show you
now if you go to your
repository where you
Find basically your Joomla install
you would go to administrator
Now there is a helper class for the front end of every component as well as for the back end
so looking in a backend
We go to component
Expert Database
Helpers
And it's basically that file there
that is the helper
Class if we open it we
See that it's the abstract expert database helper
Now that helper class gets included
Into your component on every page so if you to open the main backend file with that one
Which get loaded by Joomla first you'll see that it actually
includes that helper file in every page
So that means everything inside of that
Class is available to you everywhere in your component
When we actually go back to our
Interface
And we go to components
and the Expert Database
You would see that there is a libs or actually stand for library and helpers and you see
We have to switch Ticked yes add create user helper method
Set to yes
That is the
The switch that you need to trip
So that component builder and knows that you actually want the helper class
that Creates users to be
Added to the helper class of your front and backend of your
component
I'm gonna close out here
I am going to go back to the code
And then I am going to do a
Simple search
for user
.
Here is quite a few users
there it is
Create user
As you can see this is a public static function
So you would basically call it with that class name
Then colon colon
and the name of the function, right
which is create user
And you see that it is set to new
Now
New has in it
A few variables is basically an array
So you can go through this class and you'd see that it has a password one or is just password or password two, it has a user name
it has a name
aswell as a e-mail
And
it then creates the user
That's what this class does so it calls in the Joomla
Component users
It calles in it's registration model
And then it basically uses that model to create a user so that's what that switch does it
adds this class to your component you can then use it in your component it doesn't automatically
just sets everything else in place you still required to do as a developer to add to correct code
I'll show you what I have done and how I am using it
There is a admin View called experts it's in this view that I would actually like
Option for someone to create a user now let me first demonstrate how it works
So I would go to expert data base and click on experts
Let's click on new
So you would see there is a
field called Expert
With which you can select
Users within a specific group
I will also explain some of that more later
But underneath there is this button create user
If you Click on it it basically has a pop-up where in you enter a user name
I am just gonna say
Testing
Use that as the username
And as the password
There we go, got the user name
So everything is testing 123
And if I click create it basically has this nice effect
where it is busy creating it
Setting it up, sending out the email doing all of that for you
And once it's done
It lets you know that user was created successfully
and the login details was e-mailed to the user
And then it says here ready to select
You can now select testing 123 that you just created from the user list
In the above field simply click on the blue user icon
Click here
and you can type in that testing 123
click Search
And there is the user created
and we click enter
You see that it basically used a very strange conversion here
Basically converting the username away from the numbers now you can you can fix that
By clicking edit
And then changing it to 123 and say save the update
Does not want to allow that.
So clearly my little application doesn't wanna allow you to use
actually any numbers in the user name,.That's not the point
The point is that we have this integrated user now that is connected to an expert
And if you were to click there again
You can still selected ok but once you select it once you can't create a new expert
And select that user again
So it's basically one profile connecting to one user
To set up a expert
So that's the feature I'm using it for there is different ways that I have implemented this let me show you another one
Obviously you realise I'm using a lot of JavaScript on this page
I will show you some of that JavaScript but
That yourself
Ok let me just get out of here
for Example over here I wrote this job tracking Extension
And let's say we want to create a new job order
then I can say whether it's a new client or a existing
if it is an existing
I Simply select from this list
If it's new I click here
I can enter all the details of the user and when I click save
It Creates the user
Stores the data in the user table not in the job order table deletes all these values
So did the job order table never stores any user values in the relation of this job order of course
And so that's another way that I have implemented so if we were to close this out
And where to open a client
A new one
You would see it's basically it's the same values
And
Everything is the same
So that's another way that we integrated this whole
User integration
So there are really many different ways to this
The way I have done it I've just listen to my clients expectation
What I really would like to see and how they would like it to work
And then simply Make It Happen that way
I personally I prefer the Ajax Way much more
It's it's just seems to me easier
So let me illustrate some of or let me show you some of the code that I used to do that
Ok so we back in The Experts View
As I've done before I previously in other tutorials explained how to make use of the
Ajax concept
Within
Component Builder
Now for those of you that like to understand what's going on let me give you a quick runover
At the code level
Within every component that makes use of Ajax
A model and a controller is created
The controller is named Ajax.json.php and the model is named
Ajax
Ok let me open the model
And also let me open
The controller
As you can see the controller basic fires off
The register tasks within the construct method
And then it adds the tasks
Into a switch
And tries to run the task basically
Also in
The model it
It Gets the model Ajax
And then runs the method that basically corresponds to the task
And so that is how
It runs
It uses the Joomlas default
Filtering
Method in the way that it gets values that are being posted
And then value dates that those values actually are there
Then sends the values over to the model
Now that's looking at it from a code side so if you look at the model
It simply shows you
Various methods
Some of them are protected
And some of them are public and those are usually the ones
That
gets called from the controller once the Ajax gets the
Verification level and it's
Verified
So here is the create user class
Basically
We first check
Whether this user now this is custom script I mean this I wrote custom component build does not write this so
Basically when you go back to the user interface
You see that
If I scroll down here
create user fields
And then there's great user
You see that I wrote this right here
And that basically gets placed into the model
So that's the Ajax method here
I simply in that Ajax input
I annotate the specific tasks
The task name
And specific variables
And again the method name
You could have different method names from task names and
What should be validated whether it's integer, float or whatever
And if there's no value What is the value by Default
So this is where you set up there basically the controllers information
And then here your customised these write your script so basically
create user gets data and seems from what view is it
then validates with this
current login user has the permission
To actually
The Experts area
Then it
Converts the data because it's a json set of datasets that I'm sending across
So that we can see if it's an array does some other checks
So you can see I'm still here I'm using that
Global helper
Class and methods
Here are number of custom methods obviously that
That is available in that class to go through it we just added in there as freebies and
And you wanna always see the Need of them but I'm using them often
And even if you have with
Improvements on those methods please make a pull request and we'll make those changes
Then you over here once we've
Become very sure that we've got enough data on the right data
We basically get that same method and we need to create user
Get result
And if it's not
the correct result we deal with it
accordingly
And if it is the correct result we create
Add the user to the user group
That's something that the user does not
that you create user does not do
So we
Then have a user group setup
And
Basically in the component
And we get that user group
Set into the correct User Group
This is a return message
If it's an error
or whether it's a
Success
So down here is the error message
So if it's if it's successful this is what we do if it's unsuccessful this is what we do
And so that's just a quick look I mean obviously we can pause this video and
Look at
What I have done
And then here is getUser when the page loads initially
we get the id get the data
packs it into some html
And sends it off
So
This is the PHP side obviously
We we do this create user and then there is a ajax
Site right in Javascript
So
In the JavaScript when the page loads
Would you get user with the user ID
We get the user ID from the field
And then it loads that data that you saw
If you if you looked no this is the wrong place
Basically shows you that is the data it loads
And that data can be edited
Except over here
You cannot add numbers in the username but you can
do that and it will update it as you see
and will say that is updated it
Obviously if there is a
Error with the email already used or something it will also give you an error
And this is all part of how we basically have setup
the JavaScript
Ok we can scroll down to
So I've just added to Javascript to the view file
And here is get user the server side and there is the the function
I have two functions usually one that sort of deals with
Waiting and then eventually setting up the data into the The View
And here's one making the call so this is how you call structure would usually look
In index.
php
?option = your components name
And the task which
Must go to the
Ajax controller
And then this is the task
And you then here can stipulate what format you would like the result set returned in
if you
Want the result set returned the raw which in sometime sometimes is the case
There is if you look here
There is a raw
Variable
You can just set the raw variable to true
Then it will give you the results set
just Like that without
Braces around them
Or a call back or anything
You see when you make calls from JavaScript
It usually
Wants this call back to be added
If you make calls from other JavaScript libraries you might just want the braces around it
But if you want it raw which also is often the case
you just add the variable raw to the URL = true
and then end up passing it back to you with this
So that's a little heads up on
Ajax function so
the format must json
that's Important
Ok and always use a token
Have the token on the page this token is necessary
To prevent cross site scripting of course
I usually add the token to the page
Through the
Java oh sorry php
So there is a place down here if you scroll down where is it
I just remembered remembered
If you are working in a backend
The backend the backend and the admin area you
don't need to have the token its get added to the page dynamically
Since we Basically parsed the JavaScript
Areas
And if we see token we actually know oh token is to be there and we add the token for you
Where is the front end you must actually literally add the token
There was just too many reasons for us
Not to do the Automation in the front end so but you
could literally change to the variable name as well
To something of your choice
Where is now it's just token it's backend it's more secure ok so
You need to always add a token
To the request
and check whether the token is there if it's not that it wouldn't make a request at all
Ok so I was looking at another function there
Ok so that's simply how we create a user
And integrate the user concept within this component
I hope that was helpful I realize if you not that fluent in programming in JavaScript
Or in jQuery
As well as in PHP
This might not fully resolved your questions
Like I said where the beginning of these tutorials
I wasn't planning on making a component that is
Very easy to use
but rather a Component that is very powerful to use
And leaving it up to you to decide how to implement This user integration
Is really the most powerful way of doing it
At least we are adding the the class with which you can create the user
And again even there you can go look at that class
If you feel my implementation is a little you know needs some
Inprovement
You can either shoot me a mail or you could
Take
For this component Builder on GitHub
Pull down to your own repository
Make the changes push it back
And
The place inside
Of component builder where this class is constructed
is obviously
Within
The compilers files. Now the compiler
Has
Has quite a few files and you need to do do a search
So you basically go to component Builder
go to helper
and then Use the compiler
And here is all its files
So do a search in here
For
the function
Create user you could
you know just search for that
and I'm sure you're fine it
and it is in that area where you need to make the adaptation and the changes because it's dynamically added
It is not
it can't be edited like right
in the script it needs to be edit in the function where we add it
Just go search those functions
Thank you for watching
That's how you create users and connect them to your components
Obviously there is much more to say but I'm afraid this will get way too long like most of my tutorials get to long
I want to keep it this this way and trying to make it shorter hope you enjoyed that