Hi
I want to show you how to use the emailing helper class in your component
The email helper class is a class that gets added to your components helper area
And therefore available on every page
And with which you can then send emails
We could look at the helper Class by going to a component that has it
Included
And then into helpers and
The filename is usually the component name
Email
If've opened it already here
As you can see it's in just the basic abstract class
That
That takes Joomlas emailer
Which is this Jmail
And it gets an instance of it
And adds it to mail and then loads in
the variables that's required
Now
We'll come back to this in a moment
If you look at a component
What you need to do first
If you are gonna use this feature in any of your components
Let us open this
Learning manager
And then go to libraries and helpers
And you'll see that there add email helpers been set to on and that only
Places the helper class in your component that's all it does
It doesn't implemented anywhere else
So
At the moment that means that if you click yes here
You need to still create fields
That you are gonna load to your
config area
Now if you don't know about the config yet it means you've skipped some tutorials
But it's basically this area here
Which gives you the option to the ability to add
Configuration options to your components option area
So if we click here I scroll down you'll see that there is
Mail configuration and a whole lot of fields there
Now these Fields correspond to the Joomlas default Fields if you didn't know
So if you would like to create these Fields and you need some info on what there should be in what should be their names and
Everything
Then go look at the Joomla Global configuration XML
And you'll see all the settings in that file
For our purposes I'm simply gonna show you how the fields look like
We also have the dkim
implementation available
And even those Fields you will need to look at the code to know what their names should be
So there's a difference of course between name and label and description
When we refer to named and that is the
The value that will be used in the code
Ok I'll show you what I mean
I just close out here
Go back to the code
So for example that word mailer
Actually means
That the name of the field is called Mailer
The name of the field is called that and that
and so it goes on
So these are all the fields that needs to be set
If if if your component
If we go back to the component let me just
Close this
You would see  there is a options area so I'm gonna open that
once it open your see there is a mail configuration and a dkim area
Dkim
So let's open a mail
You see that it has the mailer status
So it's either set to off then no emails will go out
or to on
If it set to on you can decide whether you want to override the global function
The global
Variables
now the global variables are set in your Joomlas components
Global area
So you would go to Global configurations
And then
You'd go to
System
No sorry
It's server
And then there's this mail settings here
Ok
Now these are the main or the the global settings that will be used in the in any component that
Does not add
These settings in their config
So if you didn't create
Those Fields and added it to your component but you ticked the the button to sort of add the helper
Class to your component
Then
That means that it will basically fall back to these settings in your Joomla default
Area
So
Just that you know
And these are the values that you need to overwrite if you want your
Component into some way to use other PHP mail or other send mail or
Other
What's the other one SMTP
Values than that of the global you need to set it here
And
That is basically what this area can do
So you use Global it falls back to the Joomla Global
Otherwise you can overwrite it on this level
And send it out
In a way that is
What you would like
The DKIM area
Is there more advanced area which basically allows you to overwrite
Overwrite sorry not overwrite to encrypt
And secure email sent out from you to authenticate that it was really you that send it
This is very helpful to sort of show your the people that receive these emails that it's not
Spam and it's really comes from you it's more advanced I would encourage you to read up on it these are the values
Usually would be required to be added private key a public key
And obviously these type of areas here
If this is set to no obviously it will not be used if it set to yes please ensure to add the values
Otherwise it still will not be used
Ok
So that's basically the values that you needs to still create
Component does not do this for you
You need to do it
I could possibly foresee that
In the future we might add this
If you tick the helper class it adds these values for you
But even then if you have done it manually
We'll make sure that it doesn't add in twice
So as long as
These values obviously be the same
Names we will know actually a
Somehow identify that
And then not
Add them dynamically
So to avoid clashes
But for the meantime it's not automatically being added and so you need to do that manually if you want it
To be there if you don't like I've said before
It will fall back to the Joomla Global
So to explain that you on the code level
Basically it gets from the configuration
The mailer function
And then it checks whether it's global
If it is global
Then
It
Implements Joomlas
Values
If it's not Global it implements your components values
And
That is basically what it will do
Now you can read through the code
But the most important area really is this area
To know what is all the various
Options that you have in the signature
To send out Mail
So it's able to really send out a lot of mail but
Nonetheless
You're also need to consider
You know
Your servers own limitations
Since we obviously don't want you to spam people
We do not
Overwrite those values. We are simply using the Joomla default
Helper Joomla sorry jmailer
And it is been extended from another class
And so there are a lot of features and here
And if you wanna know more about them
you can read up on on obviously the jmailer
Class from Joomla
As well as read through this code here and see how we implemented
These are the dkim values that you would need
And in your
In your component
To be able to use the dkim encryption
But you could also read up on this and check out this function here
up till there
In its way that it's implementing these features
It obviously is adding it to the mailer and most of the work is done in the mailer
So it's basically adding the data to the mailer and the mailer takes care of the rest
Ok and so here it sends it off
And if there is an error
So let's say for some reason it didn't
you know work out well
Then it shakes whether
Your
Component
Helper class
So your component has a helper class it's just this file here
Even has a storemessage
Variable
or method
So if we were to go check this
You see that there is the storemessage method
In the helper class this is a custom method that I wrote now you can write it anywhere you like
But this signature should be the same
Ok so
here
Is the same signature you'll see it
So basically this area that
And that is dynamically updated to your component
So it uses your component name here and your component name there
But this store message
Is basically
Not
You cannot change that but it takes to send email the recipient the subject the body to text only in the mode and it's says
That it's email
So you can have different types so if you look at the the method
The type can be anything
We are obviously wanting to do different things on different type so if we send an SMS and we didn't
Fail
You wanna store the message if we did this or that
So this this kind of feature
Is it only used when something didn't work
But also if it worked
If it was sent
It's gonna store it
So it's a way to store the message
So that you can
Maybe let your user go
If they login
They can see messages sent to them and this kind of stuff
So this is what the store message does and as you see it's whole huge custom
Method that I wrote
And it does different things for different
You can update it in change it pause the video copy it down don't really matter
Just if you realize this is actually something you write up yourself you just need to make sure that that part is the same
The rest is up to you
Now you deal with it ok so that is really implementing the learning manager emailer
In your component
Maybe I should show you where I implemented at least
In one area ok let me do that
Ok so I have this component called job tracking system if I open it up
You'll see that it actually has that function
Adding the helper email it's got it selected you see there add helper
Set it to on
Then the view in which we are using the email method is the job or the view
Basically we want to email the client
I did job order
When when it's created
So let me show you how I implemented it there
So here is the job order
And
I would basically then
Click on
This area here email now I can update that
to whatever email I like
Testing
@
vdm.io or something
Just send it in to
Nothing
And
Then once the email has been sent
It actually let's me know
See there in the it says email was sent successfully
So
That's basically what the emailer does it just this button it sends this
Document
To my
Client
And also if I want to send it to my store
The people that does the job
I could also do that here
I'm not gonna explain to you
The reality of taking this content adding it to the email and sending it
That I would suspect you need to know and you need to learn or study to do that yourself
I'm I'm simply explaining to you how to use the email helper class
So we will go to the code and I'll show you how I do it and
Mostly
Maybe I'll give you some pointers but I won't go into detail
About how that is done
Ok so let's go to the to the code
So here we are in the job order
So first thing here is obviously some JavaScript
So there's the send email function
and Gets a set of values
And then it basically gives it over to the send
Email server function which sends it as a J object
Sorry  a json request to the server
The send
Email is the
Task
And when it gets a response that's when you get the notification
Ok so that's Simply the JavaScript of it
So now if we go to PHP
Previous
Tutorials we explain how to use the Ajax class
I'm gonna just touched on it briefly
You basically have your input here
This is where you put set up your controller
Let me show you that
So you'll see in your controller
There is this send email
Class that's what basically was defined
And this field here
And you see that there is
Basically three variables
And they are
Should be filtered in this way and they are fast over to these methods
And you should be logged in user
So if you look at the code again it basically this is the task down here it triggers the task
It checks for those values and then passes it over to
This method which is in the
Model is a model
So we go to models
Ajax
So here is the the model let's just scroll down to the send email
So here is the send email and this again
Is a custom
Script
So if I was to go back here
I Close this
You'd see there's the in this
Ajax method is a lot I mean look at that you can see that scroll down way down is a lot of other custom methods here
But this is another custom method I've written
Call send mail gets the mail the HTML to type
It it does the necessary
Cleansing and whatever
And then
It
Basically
Over
Here
We're calling the email helper
We using the send method
we Passing the valuables and we
Set the result in here
And if the results is obviously true
We will let the user know otherwise we give him the error
ok so that
That is the
The short end of it
I'm also using this email body to help me build the the email because I want to
Make sure that it's got all the necessary HTML and stuff so you can
Pause this video and type that out if you like
But this is the email body that I usually use and you can see you passing the HTML on the subject to it
And it simply adds the the subject to the
Email
The necessary places as well as the body
In the necessary place
Right there
So that it gets send in a way that's more appropriate
And then
That's all happening right here
Ok and that is what I'm passing in here
So a custom method which gets the data from
the Ajax
And then sends it off
So that's a quick tutorial on how to implement sending emails through your component
Using the email helper class
Obviously the email helper class
Is
Available on GitHub in in the component Builder
And if you feel that our implementation lacks some professional
Help then please do make a commit to Quest or send me an email
And we'll gladly update an improved this class
Although I think we are followed
All the necessary standard and requirements to make it useful to everyone
Ok thanks for watching
Until next time