Hi
I've already done a tutorial how to use the email helper in your components
And in that tutorial I actually do touch upon
The storing of messages
Or emails for that matter
Once it's been sent
Now I would like to just look at that again
For those of you that may just be wanting to know that
So
Obviously at this stage you should know
That the email helper class
it basically added to the helper folder
Of your components backend
So and it's usually called your components name and then email
That's that's the email helper class so to use it
In the custom script you could use the 3 braces brackets
Is that ok and then component like that
And then just email
And sent
And
That is how you would basically construct
Your
Your script I show that as well in the tutorial
We we going to more depths
of how to use the email helper
But
At the very bottom of this class in the send
Method
There is a little snippet
quite its significant as it may seem
Actually gives you a very great
Ability
Because
The result
Of the email that was sent
Is placed in send email
This result is passed to the method as well
The first it looks in your helper class
Which is usually a component name
Helper
That's the helper class
And whether this method exists in that class
And this method will not exist unless you
Write it
So
The area where you would have to write this method
Is in the component there is an area
Called
Admin helper
Let's look at that
So we open a component
We go to libraries and helpers
we scroll down
And we see there is
Email helper
And then underneath it helper admin class
And it's in this area that you need to add that method
Now I realized I've chosen the wrong components so this component actually does not use that storage concept
But there is another one that does let's open that one instead then
So again we are in
Helper admin class
And we have a function called
Store message and this is in the components
That where you edit your component
So this store message has what we call a signature
Values that it is passing to the method
And in the
The
Email helper class
You see that it
Also has
A signature
But wherever it gives this = with a value
That means that that's the default value so if you do not add
A value for this position there is one two three four fifth position
Then it will default to 0 if we do not add this it will default to null
So
From there all the way to the end all of those values haves basically the
Null value
So
In reality you only need to add you know these values the first four
But
Those values are all used in this method
So if you wanna understand exactly how these value should look look inside of the method
Read through the method
And you will see
So
Making a long story short
We end up here at this little script
Basically ask whether you created the method or not
If you didn't it simple skips it and returns the value of send mail if it sees
That you have created it
It'll pass these variables that correspond to the signature
And then inside of that method that is in your helper class
That is now this method
You need to do the necessary checks and balances
And discovering
For example since you've got the email address
You can
Search
with the getVar
In the user class
It must equal
Email
Recipient
= email
And then returns to us the ID
So
That is basically how the getVar works
And
Then when we have the user ID
We can obviously make sure it's
The number and we set it to our message as user
And we set it as the email and now we can store
The message in whatever table or do whatever we wanna do
Beyond
The normal
So even if you wanna do other things except
Storing the message
This is the method inside of which you can do it so store message
Is the method inside which you can do some more custom scripting
On top of your email integration
Ok so that's just quickly giving a little bit more depth on that specific aspect
Of using
The email class in your component
Thank you for watching