Hi
Sometimes one would like to add extra styling like this
Or like that
To a listview
The problem though is that by Default
All of the fields all of these field values are being escaped
And so
If you would like to add let's say this this kind of styling
to a field view
Let me show you how I did it
In the job order admin View area
If you go to PHP
There is a method called add PHP getitems method before translation fix and decryption
So this happens before
The translation or The Fixer or the decryption
Sorry the translation fix or the decryption of any field
This is not the ideal place you usually would add it after that was done but in this case I did it before
So basically I am setting up
A value
That when I wanna use danger when I wanna use warning
Simply using
The
The getDate and modifying it
By the danger time and the warning time from the
Job tracking
Configuration values so this is a configuration field that I've added to the component and it
It's names are warning time and danger time
And the default is 3 weeks 1 week
And basically this is the date
The dates that I would then use
I then look through the data
And when I identify
data that is actually
Part of the target
I add
This
Value to it
That then intern turns this red
Ok
And then the next one
Is I check the dates
And then depending on its values I again add some HTML value
To the the date and I use a custom
A method in a helper class call fancyDate
Where I convert the
Default
Sequel date
to a better date or a better looking date
2nd of April or something
Ok
So
The problem is though
If you do this
And you
Compile your component add items go look at it you'd see that it actually escapes those values and it prints it
Out
Like a
You know like you see it over here
It actually prints out
That
Around
The value
And that's obviously not what you'd like and the reason why it does that
Because all values are being escaped
Now there is a way to to stop that from being
from happening
And that that is really what this tutorial is about
To show you how to prevent
That escaping
So the value we have here is to create date
As well as the job status
So I'm gonna go in I'm still in the
The back end of the component
Job order
And I'm going to go to the fields
And then I'm gonna scroll down to that that value
Let 's see where is it now Job status
Ok I'm gonna open it
And if I then
Having a it open and I can scroll down and even here
You see that there
It doesn't show up here sorry I should actually had it but the reality is
way at the bottom you see I added this little line
I set escape
Equals
False
So you would simply add this line
And then when component Builder compiles
It will actually in the body
Of the component where that field is loaded
It will tell the
Escape method not to escape it
So that it would then
Display the html instead of printing it out
So that is really what it's all about maybe it's
Got a lot of explanation for such a simple thing
But I can tell you what if you can't do that it's quite frustrating because
Sometimes you would like to give some indication with some HTML
upon the value and then this
Feature actually allows that like you could see here
We were able to add a nice button around these dates
And as well as adding some colour to to these words here and yeah
So that is a quick demonstration of how to make use of the not escape
Method or concept
When it comes to list views around the field values
Hope that makes sense
You have any questions please don't hesitate to let me know
And
Until next time take care thanks for watching