I would like to show you
How to change the values that are being exported
And how to then
Have custom import option
With an import of the data
At the moment
Component builder actually allows you
To have
Import and export by Default in all the list views
Of the components you build
So let's look at what I mean
Here I have a component called IP data
Basically used to take
IP address and
Translate it to what country it was from and then
To update the pricing on your website based on that IP data
So
Obviously
You might want to export or import stuff
Into this component
So I'm gonna have us look at for example let's say
Let's take the IP tables
So here we have the IP tables
And as you can see
We are able to see the
The CNTRY value
And that is basically the country and the
The REGISTRY
Who this IP table belongs to
And The Range
That is being reflected
And all this values are here. Now if you click export without selecting any
Values  will give you this warning
So
Obviously you can only export the values that are selected so if you want to export them all you need
Change this value to all
And in some cases if the table is too big
That means you might not be able to export them all at once
Any anyway exporting the data that such big quantities is not really ideal
I would say anything Beyond 3000 items
Rather go to MySQL
Get a dump file it's not ideal to use that kind of quantity with in Joomla anyway
Although we have often seen the listview being used for up to
10000 registered sorry items and quite complex
Inheritance in structure
We're talking about the import export now and that's quite different
Ok so for our purpose
Let's say we wanna exporter this but let's say for some reason
Instead of us
Wanting to see if this zzz or AUS
Value
We want to instead see the country name
Ok so that would be a simple implementation of what I'm trying to explain
So if you would clik export now
Let's do that
And then let's just save this
Ok so we've exported it
And instead it put these AUS values here
And some other values from the database all nicely exported
And that's what you would expect
But if you wanted this to be a different value when you export it
Then you can do the following
The way component builder works
Is its
Got this
Get export data
Method in the model
And
This
Get export data method has this extra value set to True called export
or _export
A reason why we added this is because it is actually
Using the same structure
Of getting the data
As you would
When
Let me rephrase this
You're able to
Target
This method with custom scripting
But the difficulty is that you see this part that's custom scripting
And it's also been added
Into the actual
Get list query right there you see
It's the same custom scripting
So basically
In our compiler we are adding the same custom script into the get list query
As we are adding
Into the get export data
It's the same custom scripting
Now the way that you would
Know where is it executing is based on this value
This value is not set
In the list query of course
It is only set
In the export data
So let's see where this custom scripting is done
So if you got your
Admin view open you go to PHP and then you scroll down
Until you see the method where is it now maybe I should scroll slower is it that one yeah I think it is this one here
Right
Until you see the method it says get list query J model list
That's the the
The one and you'd said yes
The the code you put in here
Is added both to the
Get list query
As well
as to the export query so if you want to change the values
that are being exported
But not the values that's being shown in your component you be doing it in the same area
So going back here you'd see that it's that's the same code over here that is
Also added over here  you see that's the same code
So if you were for example
In here you wanted to change some value you could do that
by simply
Adding another lookup or something and you add this
export is true
Now to see where all this export = true is appearing
We would go to
Any
Model which is obviously a list model
And we would search and see there it is
And there it is again
So where are we now we are now in the get export data
And we are in the area where is looking remember we showed you in the previous tutorial
How to add some customisation
to your values in the listview
Some HTML well here we are asking is the export set or is it true
Then
Don't do this
You know
Don't don't add this feature here
So we are avoiding adding this
Customisation of coloring because we don't wanted to run when we are exporting exporting we only wanted
The values so then again you can see where using the export values
And
Then again there
So those are there
The places where the export
Function is coming in
To play and how we can
By using this
Underscore export
We are able to identify whether it's an export or not if it is we can make the changes to the values as we like
Ok
Then going back to our back end
Just to show you
This is the place where we did the query
And this is the place
Before the translation fix, decryption again
We are checking whether we are doing an export
And so you could literally take that
And say
Instead of the exclamation that if it's export is set
Come on and export
And export is true
Then over here you know
Do you think in that area there so that is if you want to change the values
Before translation or before decryption or if you want to you can do it after
After that
So after all was done
You wanna change the values
On an export
Then you can add it there
And that is really as simple as it is
Adding a
Change to your exported values
Now
If you want to then
Have a different import
Type as usual
Usually to import values you just
Update these right and if you leave the ID in it updates if you take the ID out
It creates
So without an ID it will create
With an ID it will update
Now let's say you say we you know what
I actually don't wanna use the IDs
I want to use these values instead
And then you need to create a custom import concept now we have tried to make that
Easy as possible and yet
I'm sorry to say that it's still quite complex
So
You basically go to custom import
And then obviously there is a little warning here
Because it is quite daunting
You that there yes
And it will load
Into these areas
The actual script
That are used by Default
In these various concepts
Now if you do not understand what you seeing here
Then I suppose you should rather not be trying to do this
Or you should
Then seek some
Classes maybe from lynda.com or elsewhere
I think Udome it's also a good place
Sort of sharpen up some of your PHP skills
And
Then you could make changes to this for example maybe just take out that chunk
Then
Do a search
You know so put something in you can find like
Your name or whatever
And then save this and compile it
And then go and search where does this come up
Where does this come out what what is happening
And then
Obviously
You'd realize that
We don't completely remove the default
Import method
When you do this kind of
Changes
There is a way that you could make these changes
And have two import methods next to each other
It's not that easy but it's possible and it all depends on really
What you doing and where is it now
not save area
But
This area the HTML and PHP View area
So it depends on what you do in the view so currently this is set up to do your normal
Import as you would usually do
So changing this will also change your normal import concept
Ok so
That is how you would
In this area you would
Change your custom import concept
Please read through the code
Maybe compile it
Go look at what it's done
Look around see how the default import and
Concepts work
And then make your changes accordingly
I have used this area quite a lot for various applications
Because sometimes you have a user that says to you or client
I want to import these sets of
Csv files
and they are like 4000 or
40000 lines and it needs to select only specific values
Well in that case this area is definitely what you looking for
And you'll be able to actually adapt your import concept to accommodate those kind of complexity
Well that is how to
Change export values and create custom import values
For any field
View in the backend of your component
So literally changing how that button behaves and how that one behaves is what I have just shown you. Thank you for watching.