It often happens that you would like to use some of the default fields
Differently than how component builder is actually implementing it
Now what is the default fields
If you go to
Add a new admin view or if you go to an admin view that already exists like I've open one here
You'd see that there is this little note
Just above adding fields
It says that the ID
The asset ID the state
The access the ordering the created by the date created modified by
Date modified Checkout
Check out time version
Hits metakey
Meta description and metadata
Is already added to the view so these are your default
Fields
That always gets added to the view even if you don't create them in fact you don't need to create them
But I have seen that sometimes you might want to display some of these fields in a different
Area
Of the application
You see currently
The ID field and  the published
Where is it
I think that is State
Yeah
State field
Is the only field that is been shown by Default
In the listview
So here you can see there is the ID field and there is the states field
and the ordering field but the ordering field
Obviously
Doesn't show the order number you basically click on that button there
And then you can move them
You know order them so all that is done by Default and so as you can see
The sorry
The other
Values are not displayed in the listview
And so I had a client once saying to me that they would like to actually see the date that something was created
And also by whom it was created
And so I had to adapt component builder so that those things can also be overwritten
And this is exactly what we've done
What is done is if you create a field
In component builder as you would normally create a field and you give it
Any of these names you see created by or created date but obviously exactly
the same name then it actually will overwrite
The default so in this specific view the job order View
Excuse me
There is a field
Created by
So
I can open that
in a new tab there is also a field
Created
That's basically the date let me just
See where it is
Oh there it is create a date
I'll also open that one
So in the
Field
You see that I basically used
The name created by
it's obviously a user is the type of field
And the label is created by the user that created this is the description
And that's all that's needed
For a user type
Then
In the created date
Basically it's a calendar type
And I used created
The date it was created
The label and some of its defaults now these values if you don't know them
You can actually go and look
At the compiled
Field
Let me show you that
So in the backend of your component that is administrator components
Then the relevant component
You would open models and then there is a place called forms
And you would basically open that
And you'd see a list
Of forms that correspond to the backend views that you've created so now in our case
This job order
Is the one
You're obviously open the XML
So you double click on it
And then scrolling down
You can look at modified by
And some of its default
So you gonna overwritten
I'm sorry overwrite this value
Then you need to update or basically use these values here
Make sure this is the only part that is
You shouldn't change it if you change it
We won't know
that you're trying to
Overwrite
one of Default fields because it basically uses the name
As the identifier
Ok so back here
We basically created the fields that was the first part
I'll just close them again
And then
We would like any normal any other field
We simply went to fields
And we added those
Fields
So here you would see
you scroll down
There's the created date and there is the created by
We add both to be shown and also the position
and how it should be treated
And we said it was be in the left tab
Of the 15th
Oh yeah that's the other thing
If you would like the fields to again display in the same place as before in the edit view
Then you would add it to the 15th tab I reckoned that its
Very unlikely that somebody would create so many tabs
Now what is a tab?
If you would to go to the view
Then this is tab 1 this tab 2 3 4
5 and 6
So
Since publishing can really vary
It wasn't
Making any sense to me that I would
Targeted in any way
Directly as the 5th of the 4th
So I took a very high number 15
It's not very obvious and this is why I had to make this tutorial
If you select the number 15
It will basically add these two fields in the same place it would if it had to build it for you
But if for some reason you say no I want to also display the field in a different tab
You could actually click and say let's say put in in the 3rd tab you click save
And and then you would compile
The components install it
And then
You see 1, 2,
3 it's in the third tab
It's showing up
So
That's All You Had to Do as they had to say and what tab you would like it now to display if go here you would see
It no longer shows in the publish tab the create date
Its only created by that shows up here so it literally moves the field to a different tab
As well as
Now displays the field
In the listview
And that
Simply because you added the value the fields here you said that you wanted to display and you added to the third tab
I'm gonna move it back to 15
Which is the tab number if you wanted to be in its default place
So I click save
and then save there
compile this install it
Basically updating the component
Refresh the page and now
If we go to where it was it's no longer showing there it's not showing there
It is not showing there it's back in published in the correct place that's where it
Will usually anyway be set if you don't overwrite it so using the 15th tab
As the the target
Puts it's in default place
And if you use another tab number it removes it from its default place and puts it where you have
assigned it to be placed well that is how you can overwrite the custom
Added fields Fields of a backend View
I hope that will be very helpful
Thank you for watching