Hi
I don't know some of you also encountered
The reality of having to
Sort off limit the drop Downs
Of a list field
Based on
It's association with another table
A very common place where we find this
Is for example
When you want to load the regions of only one country
And so I'm gonna show you how I have achieved this
I realize there are many ways to do this and yet
This is how I've done it
Ok so to start off
I have a component
I could use as a illustration
or job tracking
Now in this component
Obviously I have a client area
And then I have
Already loaded
I go to admin views you would see there is country and regions
Now
I'm gonna illustrate it on the basis of country and regions but
You obviously can
Change the
Field Concepts and
Replace it with other tables
But
none the less this is what I'll be using
And I'm gonna show you how I implemented it in inside the the client's
View because that's basically where most of the work is done
Ok so I'm gonna open the client View
And then I'm gonna look in the two places we wanna look at
JavaScript
As well as the PHP area
Now I have in various previous tutorials explain some of the
Ajax functionality
In component Builder
But I realized not all of you
Might have watched all the tutorial so I'll explain some of that again
Briefly
But having said that
We first gonna look at
What we really wanna achieve
Like I have said
When you load
So let me go show you that
So when you
Start with a client
You would like to choose a country
And then
Have it load only that country's regions
That is basically what you want to do
Furthermore
You want to make sure
when it does that
And you unselect
the country it also unselects
The region
And so there are
Various things we wanna achieve here
So in JavaScript
I'm goining to show you how I've done that
I'm just illustrating at the moment one country
Maybe I should go put on a few more so just hold on for a second there ok
So now if I look it says Australia
If I click on Australia
You see that it doesn't load any regions in fact that says create a region
If I choose Namibia
It says select a region and so there's three regions two regions already created
Now as you know by now there is this button
In some of the
Dropdowns which are being added by saying true to the button
And so it's very helpful
For either
Creating or editing existing regions
So if you could sort of selecting a country where there isn't any regions set yet
It basically tells you to create one
And you can then create a region for this country
And what's nice if you click on this
Create
You can then simply create your region
Save and close so I don't know
any of Australia regions so I'm just gonna call it
Region for now
And save and close
Go back to creating a client
If I now
Select Australia you see that it's got regions
So there we go
Problem solved
And that's really what I'm gonna demonstrate how I did that
So let's get started
On a JavaScript side of things
I first have
Two variables I actually could call them both of var
Doesn't matter
One is an object
And one is simply where we are gonna Store if there is a value already set
We're gonna store that value
Then on document ready
I simply
Oh yes
Before I continue
Creating the fields
I obviously make it bring all the regions to the page
I don't want it to
Leave some regions on
Unloaded how can I say
Instead what I rather do
Is I parse those regions
Into this variable
And then only put those regions that are actually
Part of this country back
Into the list of dropdown options that's really what I'm doing so that's
What you also see happening here
Is first thing I'm doing is I am
Doing it for each
On the regions options
And then I'm getting the value
I putting it in key
I'm getting the text
I'm putting it in text
And then I'm adding it to Regions
Simply as you would load it in any
Any array there
And then I am also
Getting the value of the set region
And I'm adding that to Region
And then I'm setting the
The function getregion
The getregion function is down here
This area
The first thing we do is we load a little loading show
now the loading show or
Rather this class
ID
Is loaded on the page by Default
When you
Set
This fade effect
On ad
Then it by Default loads that class
With a nice spinner
And so I'm basically
If the loading process takes long I'm sort of stopping the user from doing anything
Waiting for that spinner
Don't need to add that
Then I am
Finding
Options
for the region
And I'm removing them
All of them
Then I'm triggering
An update now this is
This update that we are triggering here list zt is a Joomla function
And it's actually
Possibly gonna change in the future
So keep that in the back of your mind
It things break it possible is happening right here
Because this as you know the list the of is dynamically generated by Joomla
And so we literally telling it
Draw that list again
But after having removed everything
Now
We are looking at the country
So up to here we only touched the region
Now we get the country value the one that is selected
And we add it to country
We then call the server at this point
And the only thing we are giving the server is the country ID
up here
We have a country ID
We have our
Get URL
Our case is get region
Is the task
We checking that the token is on the page
Checking that a country ID is not zero
And
We then basically loading the request
Shooting of an Ajax
We doing it this way because obviously
You wanna do some things after we've got
The result which is this done
And then we
Set region
now We throw the result into setregion
We hide the load
And
Then
We do some house cleaning on the button
So that button also gets
Tampered with
And I'll show you the region button correct
Correction that we are doing down here
And you can copy this code
Test that out obviously you would update this to whatever field you trying to limit
only do that
After set region
Now we going to setregion
setregion is quite simple
Mainly because we already done most of the work
With the result being returned and so I'll show you the PHP that returns this result in the moment
so in setregion would get an array
we Check if the array is there
And then we append
Simply as you would
With any list selection
We append the value
But now
Since we are
Oh yes
another thing
I'm almost skipping it
This select region
Is a
JavaScript
Variable
That I'm setting through PHP
Which I'll show you in a later
Stage
And basically it's just a string
That says that you should select the region
And if there is no array returned
We basically just use the other variable
Create a region which is also just a string
So now over here
we are going to each over the array
And we are using the ID
And we checking whether the ID
In regions
If it's in regions
We append the ID as a value
And as you remember in regions we saved the text
As well as the ID
And so that is how we get the text
Simply adding it in there
I know we could have done that in the PHP but I felt a  let's let the
The browser help us with some of the lifting
So
We got the regions there if it's a huge table you might want it should approach this differently
Eventually we are checking whether the ID and the region =
Since if it does your mother ensure to set
Region
Value so as your member previously
We found the region value
And which store did into region
Just in case
The value was set before and saved
Now the person is looking through different countries
But when you can select the country that previously was saved
We want to make sure that his previous region is also shown as the selected value
That's simply what we doing here
Then after everything is done we again trigger this
List
Update
Which is the same as what was triggered there
And that basically sets the regions list again afresh
Then only
Do we run this little bit of housekeeping
Which does the Region button
Now the region button
It's actually
A
JavaScript
That is added
Because of the list
Field so if your specific list field was said to have no button
You could simply leave this out
If it was said to have a button
Then this is the usually the name of the button would be the
This area before the J form
Underscore
This part of the name
Would be the first part of the name of the button function and then the last part would be button
So that's how you know and you can obviously on the page
Let it execute and search for this function if you aren't sure
But that's how you would
Run
The button correction
And that's basically
How did JavaScript looks to achieve this
Ok
there is a little bit more housework necessary in that's what I said before
This area of JavaScript can actually include
PHP
that area can not because that's just pure JavaScript file
Where's this is JavaScript added to a PHP file
So here we can add some PHP and that's where we get the select region and create region
Now I know there is another way to do this in Javascript itself so forgive me for being so sloppy
Anyway
There's this function
Which basically when the admin form on change of the country field is
When that event occurs
We want to execute get region
so That
Every time
That is changed
What is the extra bit of
Script that you need to add these two
If you are gonna
Copy this down exactly the same
Just another note
We see then execute this function which is the same function
That we are executing
On the page load
We don't need to read execute this
Simply because that is already been done on the page load
that is all the JavaScript
But you need to add
Now let's go look at the PHP
Should know by now you do not need to add the PHP to the same admin View
Since all the ajax methods are all added to one file
In the component called Ajax the the model
As well as the controller is the Ajax model in controller so if you compile the component
You can unzip it and go to the model
To the controller
either in the backend or in the front end
Where is now it will be in the back end
And it's under models
Auc there's an Ajax model and
All of the backend
Ajax
Methods gets added to this one model
And so this area is what takes care of the model
And
And this area here takes care of the
Controller
So basically saying the values name is country
the task is get region if no values passed it's Null
And it must be an integer that is past
And the method name is get region
And it must be a logged in user that's a simple as that is
That takes care of the whole controller setup
Then here
we have The method
Called get region it gets the ID
It doesn't need to sanitize it again since the controller already did that
You can go look at the controller to see the implementation
So we simply getting the
factory
the data base factories passes us the database
We set up a query we say that we are looking for the IDs
in the region
That are published
I'm basically where the country
Now this is again where you need to sort of
Make your changes
We want the names of the regions or the IDs instead sorry of the regions
on Their association with the country
so Obviously then in the region
Table
We have a a a field a column
That is called country
And it has an ID in it
So that each region
Is linked to a country so whatever
Table you're targeting
this association would be than this country
And it's obviously
me being paranoid we just add the interger there again
Set the query executed check if you have a value
And if we do we simply return the load
Load column
Function
Which returns the ID is in an array
There we go done finished
And
There we return false if no value was found and it's simple as that that's all the PHP you
Need
And that returns
The the PHP to our
JavaScript
And the JavaScript does the rest
Ok well
I hope this will be very helpful
And help you to sort of sort your dropdowns I didn't spend
much time on explaining that maybe I should so let me
Give a Quik
Run over of that
The field that we are
Focusing on is this country in the region field and they are both custom right
So I've already done tutorials on how to set up a custom field I'm not gonna spend too much on this
But just for reminder let's open region
we Simply saying the button is true
And
We select the region you can obviously update the view name dynamically in the description
And here we doing some
PHP
you could Put all of this PHP
in just
PHP one
Without adding it to the 19th
placement
But like I've done I've actually used every area
I like making the code look
It was written
and not computer-generated
And
Then I'm adding the options and so this is just a simple basic
simple custom field
there is'nt even any Java script in here
I've Done Everything basically in the model
Did the PHP as well as the Javascript sorry not in the model in the back end admin View
And I think that is because I wanna use this field maybe in other views with different
Different Association
So I don't tend to use the script area
Maybe as one might expect
So that's quickly looking
At
Filtering a dropdown list selection custom list selection
Via JavaScript
And Ajax therefore
If you are targeting a table of another
Component which you're not having the control over
The actual field names it will it should work the same way as long as there is
A field of
Association within the table that you'd like to filter
you could write that PHP
Find the values and filter it
Thanks for watching