Hi welcome to component Builder
We've just added a very
Smart new feature
To component Builder
That's
Is called
Custom code
You can find it here next to Dynamic get
It's basically where it's stored
You'd hardly never need to go in here
Unless you wanna look at what is already been stored and make changes to that in the UI
Most of the time you will be doing the changes in your editor
So your editor will be
Basically where you will work
So what is the purpose of this new feature
The feature is really there
For those who are used to actually coding in another editor
So what we can then say is let's say they create a component in component Builder
Then once they've created it
They basically do it compile
and install it onto the same website
As component Builder
To test it
And then during testing they are adding code into that
Compiled version
That are installed onto this website right
Well the new feature could then
On compilation extract that custom code
Store it in this custom code area
And add it back into the component on the fly
So
I'm sure that is quite exciting
Anyway let me do some demonstration give you some of the rules guidelines since there are some
Limitations
And then obviously this is still in beta there's quite a few things still to do
But I would like to get it out there have you guys tested and get some feedback
Ok I'm gonna compile the demo component
Since most of you might already have this component installed
And you can then use this is so the test area so we will compile a demo component
Ok then I'm gonna install it on to this current site
Great
Now
I'm gonna go and give you
An explanation of how to add
Custom scripting to that component
By going to an editor
Ok so here in the editor you can see this is the root directory
Of the website
I'm gonna do something on the back end of the components I'll open administrator components
And then there is the demo component
And let's just go to it's main page
Ok so its main index page
And then let's see I'm gonna add some custom scripting here
Just for the demonstration
Now the way to add custom scripting there are some conventions and some
Sort of regulations
Let me first show you the conventions
To insert custom scripting you will use a tag like so
So obviously
You will use asterisks instead of The X s that are in the code so the code has the X s in it but the actual
They would be with the Asterix
So that will be to insert new code you use that that place holder and the beginning of the
Area then after a new line
You will insert your code and then at the end of the code you will insert this one to close the code
Ok
Then there are obviously two ways
Of adding code, one is to insert code and one is to replace existing code
So inserting code would simply at the same line insert that code into the existing code
Where is replacing code will literally remove the old code and add the new code in its place
So these are the two conventions
Once component builder adds the code back
The tag will change inserted
Insert will change to inserted
And will have this new number at the end this number is actually referencing the ID of the
Code in the system
Now don't ever change this number or component Builder with think that it doesn't have one
And it needs to be created
So it will be an error it won't work so don't take this
Number out
Then
It will add this at the end
Now on other after compiling it and adding this string in it won't
Compile it again because of these
Opening and closing
Brackets not being there
Greater and
Lesser than signs
They they are the ones that activate it and makes makes it
Basically be parsed again
So when component builder places the code back it looks like this
When you then later come and want to change it again you would add this diamond in there
And it will then update the existing
Code in the database
With the changes that you've made
That's basically it. There are a few limitations you cannot add
Code
Closer to each other than I would say 6 lines
So if there are gonna be code
Close to each other and it ends and starts within the parameter of 6 lines
You end up with a problem
So especially at the end I will demonstrate that somehow in our
Actual doing of of this but the reason is Component Builder doesn't only use the line
In which this is found to remember where to place it
But actually creates a sort of a fingerprint of the code above the insertion and the code
Below this insertion to
Accurately insert it in the future
So that code changes
and then Component Builder will give you a notice and will not insert the code
This is because of the nature of JCB
It actually is constantly improving
it's constantly being improved and that therefore it's code is obviously moving
Around quite a lot
Now
There was no other way for us to try and automate this
Because if we use the line it could possibly cause an accident by overwriting code you
You never intended it to overwrite
So the only way we could solve this was creating what we call a fingerprint
Few lines above the insertion or the replacement and a few lines below there that replacement
Now
I'll demonstrate this in our in our demonstration in a moment
Just a heads up about that
So just quickly a recap
To insert new code you will use this
To replace new code or for the first time you would use that
Obviously at the end of the code you would add these
Corresponding placeholders
I'll put these this little block
Into the comments of this tutorial
So that if any of you need to copy it down you could just copy it from there
Ok and so when Component builder adds it back
It will look like this for the inserted and this for the replaced
and if you then come back
Obviously all you need to do is just add that diamond in there
For it to be updated in the database
So let's see this in action
So here we have that demo components Main
Document
Open
So I'm gonna add some replacement tags here
So there we go
I'm basically not making any changes but I could I could add a few lines here
Maybe another comment hi it worked
And
No space there
Let's do Echo
Hi it
Worked
And that should do it so now this is just gonna replace this area
So let's go to the compiler and compile the component
See what happens
So in the compiler I'm simply gonna compile a component again
Ok it successfully compiled
Now before I install it
I could do a check to see whether it actually did get the code from the component
The way I'll do that is I'm just gonna open custom codes in a new tab
And low and behold there is says component demo and the path in which the change was made
And did it was it was a replacement so we can open that
And there is the code that we want replaced
Right
And there is the hashtag
For the start
The fingerprint and the hashtag for the end
The lines it's in a replacement and everything seems quite great so I will we need to do on this
Area is actually click install
Then that'll be the compiled version
Now let's go back
To the code
So as you can see
It actually inserted the code in the correct place it moved the other code down enough lines
And it changed it from replace to replaced
And it added the ID
After it
That sort of targets it so I could go and say ok I don't actually want this in here like that
Click save
And then go back to the compiler compile it again
Here we go
Install it again
Go back here refresh this
Oeps it didn't change let me quickly go see why
I forgot to add in the diamond right
You want to change the code you need to ensure that you add this back in
Otherwise it will not even look for it
So we at that back in
Let's try again
Ok now it worked it updated the code in the database
So let's install it
And it updated in the code
So that's how easy it is to replace a certain section now let's look at inserting
Now remember as I said
Don't put code close to each other within at least eight lines
So 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
I could actually from this line insert another set of either insert or replace
Another section of code
The reason is because the fingerprint that it creates
Above the insertion
It's sometimes up to 8 lines long
Now
It could happen that it actually uses from there
And that could
Possibly be an error when you make a change here
It will think that this code is also been affected and it won't find it
So that is one of the limitations that these code insertions that you do either by replacing or inserting as
Chunk of text script can only be inserted up to eight lines apart
From each other
So let's do an insertion over here
Ok so we got that inserted there
I did put a comment
And let's save that
And now let's compile
Ok before we install it we can just again go check
Whether everything was done as expected and yes the insertion was grabbed it was
Added to the database and it is there
Ok
It has hash target obviously with insertion we only need where it starts not where it ends
And so
We can close that
Now simply install that component
Let's go look at the code
Ok so this added the replacement
Script
Change it from replace to replaced
It's added the inserted script
From insert to inserted it
Now if you want to make a change to it we're again Just add these diamonds here
Make our change
Save the file of course and then
Then let's compile
Let's check whether the work was updated
Great it's updated the work in the database
So let's install the component
Ok let's go look at the code again
Wonderful it's added it back
All seems well
Now
We are working on another part of this implementation that for if so for some reason this code above it
Changes
It will give you a notice
On compilation
That there is been a change to the fingerprint and it could not find the insertion area
It will still add the code on the line number
But it will be escaped
So that it doesn't change or hurt any of the code that still there
The same goes with replacement code
Since it is replacing code
It is a little bit more tricky
So we'll still add it into the line but we will not remove the old code
Anyway I'm still going to be working a bit on that it needs some fine tuning I would like your feedback if you think
There's a better way I'm always open for ideas
Reality is
We are very happy to announce that component builder can now
Automatically extract custom code from your
Component while
In development
Will add a switch that when your ready to distribute your component
You could simply say you know that it's no longer in production
And then when you compile it will actually not add these placeholders
Anymore
Ok well thanks for watching
Please give me your comments at Github
There is actually an issue open there
Called
Automatic import of custom code during compilation
And
You'll see that
Yeah there's quite a few been said you can simply add your your comments and feedback to this ticket
Or to this issue it's issue 37
Since the tutorial be on YouTube possibly by the time you view it closed but
You're still welcome to go and make any comments on the closed issue if you like
Anyway thanks for watching goodbye