Automatic import of custom code during compilation
This is one of our latest features that's been added to the
JCB
component
And I'm happy to demonstrate it to you now since all it's functionality is in place
Also explain to you some of the limitations that currently still exist
And hope that it will become
A very useful tool
To all of you out there
Ok so
First what does it do
Well
Is actually a little mutated from what it's original intent was
And it's become two things really so the first thing is And this is obviously what was initially
Intended
Is that you would be able
To add
Code
To your component once it's been compiled and installed
into that same Joomla website
That you be able to
Go into that code
And with a few placeholders
Actually add code
That once you compile the component again
JCB with dynamically grab that code extracted into
It's database store it there
And from there on forward
Continue to add it back in
Into the component every time
Now
The way we've done that
As we have not used the line numbers
As the main
Way of determining where that code must be added because of the reality that line numbers
Always will change
You know you might have let's say
let's say the custom code that you're adding
You said line
105 or something
And if you make it change at line
Then that
Means all the code moves down of course and now we don't know where to add your code
Without either writing over or placing it before and
You know there's all kinds of complications
So the only way we could resolve that
Is to create
What we initially called the fingerprint
But later became a
Hash
Reference of the code a few lines of code above the
The the custom script
And a few lines of code below the customs
Now
It varies from how many lines it
Uses
And there is a reason for it I'm not gonna
Bore you with the
The detail
If you want to see how we do it there is actually
The code is open source so you can actually go look at it
So there is a function
In the A get file which is part of the
Compiler a set of
Files
So
The functions name is
Search file content
And it's in this function that it really goes through every line of the code
That is already on
The Joomla website and then when it finds it it's adds it
to in array which eventually gets safe to do they device
So this is the lines that actually does the work
Obviously there's lots of things that works
With this this function
But this is the
Yeah this is the centre of
Of everything
Obviously I'm very sure there are better ways to do this
And so we will constantly improve this as others makes suggestions
And
Make sure that it remains stable
But to to explain why it sometimes
Uses more or less of the lines above it should never use more than
8 lines
Because basically
Here it is packing the fingerprint
Taking the line content putting it into an array
And every time
It passes it shakes where that array
You know if it's greater than 10
We cut it down to 6
Ok
And this continues to happen over and over and over because we don't want this fingerprint array to become bigger
Then let's say 10 lines
And at some point when we find
A placeholder we actually take that
Fingerprint
Array
And we we create
A a hash
From it
And then we store that hash into the database
So that means
That amount of lines are changing
Because it could be or we have just cleared the array and we are at 6 lines
And then we add a 7th and now we find a place holder and everything happens
Obviously there are two ways in which the code is added
Ok and I think I have
Explain that in the
Previous tutorial but I can do that again here
Quickly
Let's see where is it
Oh here we go
In that same file there is a comment
Way at the top
Which gives their explanation
Of the place holders
Now obviously the place holders these these
These X s here
Must be Asterixs
There like that one
And they get
This is the one with which you would start either to insert or to replace
There is also note on GitHub about this which may be
Would
See more logical
Let's go there
So here we are
at Github
It's on issue 37 if you want to go look at it
Under the Joomlal component
On GitHub
The component Builder on GitHub so
Basically to start
Inserting code you would use this as a placeholder
And then your code
Obviously on a new line
And then when you're finished this would close that code block but sometimes you don't want it insert code
You wanna actually Place code that was generated by JCB
And then you'd use the replace code placeholder
And then again
Use this one to end the code block
Now when component Builder
On compilation discovers these tags
They get converted to from insert to inserted and from replaced from
Replace to be replaced
And
It adds it back with out this diamond
In between those
You know dollar signs
And inserted
Text or replaced text
It removes them because basically by doing that it means that this
code doesn't need to be updated
The moment to add those
two back
In there between those
Values
Then the next time component Builder compiles
It actually knows ok this piece of code I need to check again and update
Whatever is in the database because it's been changed
This diamond here tells it
There is a change you need to update
Now
You will see that now there is this new number being added next to the
The code
That number
Is actually the ID
Of the data Database
Column sorry
Row the database row
That JCB
Is
Actually stored the code in
So if you change this number
You gonna
Yeah you gonna have a problem
So don't change this number JCB put this number in
So that he can
Basically know where to go update the code in the database so
Once you've made any changes to the code you would simply at this diamond back in that's quite important otherwise it will not be
Be parsed and it will be overwritten by what's in the
Database
So
That's really it that was the initial purpose of this new feature was to be able to in the
Editor create code and then on the fly have it become part of the JCB
Infrastructure
For your component
And then in the future it will continue adding that code back in
Without you having to write it
Or
Remembered
or in anyway
And if you wanna change the code you just add these
Diamonds either for the insert or for the replace depending on what you did
And it will automatically then know there's been a change and it will first update what is in the data
Base and then store it back
Into the new compiled version
So
That is exciting in itself
I realize
It's a It's a real stunning new feature
We have been doing some teething on some of its implementation if you even read down here
There's some comments and things we are at the moment at version 2.3.2
which is not yet released
I'm busy working on it
Because this new version
3.
Sorry 2.3.2
Will include
The extra feature which wasn't Ever Really discussed here on the Forum
Because it was a feature that I've been
Hoping for
Quite some time
You know I've actually build quite a number of components with
JCB by now
And I've always had this issue that I would develop a very smart
Function
A custom script obviously inside of some view or some field or somewhere
In JCB and then I would like to use it again elsewhere
But then I have to copy it
And go pasted there
And it will happen that I would improve it there you know it
Add this little thing there and I
Sort of debug this
Improve the whole function the whole maybe just pieces script or whatever I just improves it
And then it where I took it from does I need to know copy again back there and it
It's always this
Copy and move and then obviously there's variables inside that needs
To be different names
And
This always been a
Yeah
Very unpleasant
Experience
And so since I know of object orientated concepts I've always wondered
Is there a way for me to with JCB create the
Same kind of
In a small way of course
But give that some kind of functionality
And so when this new improvement came along
Immediately thought Well yes there is actually there is a
Way for us to make this work for both both of these aspects so what did we do
Well
I
Let me see where we
I created
The option for you to
Either I used the hash automation
Which is the one I've just explained or to use the JCB manual
Now JCB manual if you setup custom code
The JCB manual
Will do exactly that
It will literally create
The option
For you
To take
This place holder
For example
And I have a field let me open it
Ok sorry about that
Where Have a few jumps there
I had to open the field
So basically I have a field here with which I upload images so that will drag and drop
Field is actually and note as you can see but I'm using some HTML in the
Description and I've added some
JavaScript
To this footer of wherever does field is being used
So
Basically this code
Is used to upload
Or to it's part of the process this much more code but this is what I need to
Reuse quite often
And so
Improve this in many areas and then I would always have to come back here and there are certain
Ask a sorry text
The differs from each
Place for example that word teaser
It's a bit different
Everywhere else and the word image sometimes it must be
Images and not just image
And so what I've done now is I've actually taken
This code
I've added it to a custom code
Obviously I have set this is JCB manual
And I everywhere where I want
Dynamic
Script updates I've added the Arg values If You Wanna understand and more about the Arg values
Just read this note above here for basically in
To make to say it simply
Arg
These arg areas is like placeholders
And I can pass strings or
Values
Via this custom
Code placeholder and it gets updated on the fly during
Compliation everywhere where I used this
Code snippet else in elsewhere in in
JCB
So this
This gives me a little bit of that
Object orientated
Feeling where I write a function or a piece of script once
And then I can reuse it everywhere else
And simply update the values being passed to it so it's it's by far
not
Not error proof there if you
Obviously you can't use any commas in these values and you can't use any plus signs
In these values
It needs to be
One word
It can have a dollar sign if you wanna actually have it
Place A Dollar Sign symbol in the code but it obviously doesn't
Execute the string that you pass so it will literally just pasted in
Wherever you've placed this arg place holder
So you have got you can add as many
Values to this custom code
I'm in arg values
As you want but always make sure that they're mounted values that is in the code must
Correspond to the amount of values that you are passing to it
Otherwise you would end up having a certain
Area of the code the arg
Placeholder will not be replaced
With anything it will stay
Like that
If there doesn't have a value for it
Ok so now what I'm doing is back into the field I basically
Add the place holder here
Since it is
Id1 obviously it's that one number one and I am passing three values to it
Image image and teaser
Which will then correspond to the replacing arg values here
So that 01 would be image
This one value here would be image and this one would be teaser
So it will actually replace it on compilation and now I'm able
To reuse this code anywhere else
In
in JCB
So far I obviously have saved this previously
I'm gonna just close it now and just open another one
I've got one here called poster
Which is basically doing the same thing
And so now I'm also passing image image and then poster so
That means now on this
Area
It will actually
Change that second Arg value which is actually the third one
It will update it
to poster instead
And so I have
Somehow the ability to now
have dynamic
Code in custom code which can be reused all over JCB
The only negative thing currently
Is that
This kind of code that actually has
Dynamic values past
To it
Will not be updated
By any changes you make in the editor outside of JCB so if you think about the
Two functions you'd realize that they do not fully merge at this stage
But
Let me say this if you
Have a snippet of code which has None of these Arg
For example if you only used
It like this
Without any place holders like that
Sorry without any extra values now that code will be actually
Replaced
If you make any changes to it in the editor
So it will
Start behaving like the initial implementation it it will place it back into the component
With that inserted tag above it and if you put the diamond in like we explained you know it will
get this inserted tag sorry not that one this one
So if you if you have a custom code
To which you not passing any values
Then it will add this inserted around it and you can then in the editor
Add a diamond in there so that looks like this
And then on compilation it will update that code in JCB and then place it back into
The new compiled component
So
That still works
And I think it's amazing that it does but
Unfortunately the moment you pass any arguments to it
Like so then we know that there are Arg placeholders in the
Script like that
And since the script is now being used at multiple areas with multiple values
Now let's say you change one of them
You don't really want it to replace the the database script because
How will we know where these arg placeholders should be placed
The code at that stage has nothing, no reference whatsoever to these arg values
Now there is an idea busy formulating
Which we would
Ideally
Move
All the arg values
Up
Above your script
Like this
Maybe put some
Convention of
arg's you know, wait
Like that and then arg and then equal
And then wait sorry
Then change this to
Value
Bar in this case because it's
JavaScript
And
That could possibly start resolving the issue
I'm still working on it which then we would only really not update this area
In the data in the database
But update the whole rest so you would then in that case use value
Where ever arg0 is to be found
Like that
Then we need only take care of this area and this area can be done
dynamically updated
I haven't actually
Find a complete
Satisfaction with this solution
I'm still working on it
But I can guarantee you
That it is something I would like to be able to do is to make a change to it in the editor and it
Also updates it here in the database I think that would be excellent
But for now
Any code with args
As long as this note remains here I think we said here that if there is any change to these limitations
These notes will change
So the next time you open it and you see the note is different you would be as happy as we are with the
Advance and so that that is really the other
Feature that we've now add
Basically creating custom code and then reusing it across
Multiple areas of your component
Without
Without the
The old complexity of
needing to update it every where again obviously you need to know your PHP
and whatever language you are
Targeting with this custom
Code well enough
So that you
By this place holders and by everything else
that it actually works
If it does not work that debugging and everything unfortunately is is your responsibility
there is another thing that is still functional though I think I didn't mention it
Yet and that's the component placeholder
And the view placeholder if if this specific script
Is gonna end up somewhere under a specific View
This one actually doesn't
Wait it does actually because your field script this field script it gets added
to the view footer right so
Then you have a view placeholder which basically is just also three brackets
View
Like that
and three brackets
So that's how you could then do a view Dynamic update
Of anything you know if you if you need to use to view a string name any where
in the script okay so that means you have component
Obviously with the uppercase
And the all uppercase and all that
Variations
And you have the view unfortunately only
That current view that is being targeted
Will be added to that place holder
In lowercase so that that is
Demonstrating the
Well I've demonstrated actually actually demonstrated
So we have got these there I'm just gonna not save it because
None of the changes here is relevant
And then I will compile this now
And then
In the code show you where it's been added
Ok
A component that it's
Using
That at the moment
is registry
Ok so I'm gonna install it now
So let's go look at the code where it should have been added
So in the code we see there the image is being updated with image
Teasers have been placed there images been placed
There
As well as in all the other areas where we had those arg placeholders they've all been updated
And the code itself has been inserted
in the correct area
Well
That is custom code in a little different implementation of it
We've called that
The
JCB manual option
If you wanna know more about the hash automation option
Then please watch the previous
Tutorial
On YouTube
Thank you for watching