Greetings
We're happy to announce a new feature
That's been added
To the advanced component builder for Joomla
This feature
Is a feature I suppose can
Can become very
Useful
In the future of JCB
It allows you to export
A component
Out of JCB
And not only
The component's information but everything attached to it
So
If the component has
Admin views linked to it and those admin views have Fields link to it and those Fields have field types linked
And
those
Component has site views and custom admin views
And those site views and custom admin views has templates and layouts
And dynamic gets
And all these various linked concepts to a component
Is exported
Now
The way that you will export a component
is you'd simply click on
this export component
And obviously you need to select
The component or components that you would like to export
Now
There's a few things to say when
When we want to export a component
There are two ways in which we export a component one is
An encrypted way
And the other is non encrypted
Let me show you that in the code
So I like you to understand exactly how it works
So we have a method here called smart export Builder
Now
Smart export builder gets fired at the very end
Of the
Compilation or rather the built
Where all the data has now been extracted from the database
And it's now one
Big array
Of objects
Now
Basically in this function
Called
Get Smart export
Is where this data extrusion takes place
During this process
We actually
Take
A
we take a Count of a specific value
And that value's name is export key
So in this for each
We are looping
Through the components that you've selected so if you selected more than one
Then it will check whether there is an export key
For that component now let me show you where that is a set in the user interface
When you open a component
It has a tab called settings
And
At the bottom of the right-hand column it has a new
A field called export key
How you can put any value in here
If you leave this value empty
And you export only this component
Then the component will not be encrypted
If you add
A value to this field
And you export this component it will encrypt
That component's
Data
The database values
It will not encrypt
Attached files or folders or images
That are part of this component it will only encrypt
The data from the database
Now
Having said that
If you select multiple components
And any one of them has a key
Then it will encrypt
All the components
Ok
And I'll explain again in the code how this
Is done
So we go back to the code
now in the code
Basically we are asking does this component have an export key
If it's true and it is a string
We actually
this key is encrypted in a database
So we first check
That it is able to be decrypted
And then we decrypt the key
And then we add it
To the key array
With the component's ID
So basically we are building up an array
Of each component's key
now if a component does not have a key
It simply ignores this little script and it continues building its data set
Then
Once all the data set of all components are finished
We basically get to the Smart export builder I set spoke of you know
When we started looking at the code
Now in this
Smart export builder we are simply asking have we found any keys
If we have found any keys
We are gonna explode
sorry, Implode
The array
And convert it to MD5 string
Very simple
We will then use this MD5 string
With
An AES
Encryption Cypher
To lock the data
So there is the data
Now above here we already changed the whole dataset
To a serialised string
So we have a string in this variable
And here we are basically encrypting the whole string
And now
In this variable we have the encrypted value If we don't have any keys
Even if that means if none of the components that was selected
Had any keys set
Then it will default to Simply
Do a base64 encode
And that is swell then gets written to the file
That's part of the package
So that is how
It exports the data I'm too much about the actual mechanics that's happening here
In the bottom of the file
You're welcome to obviously look through it
And if you see any room for improvements
You're welcome to make a pull request
This this is obviously the first try
Ok so it exports the data and then checks whether we have any keys
So if you have
For example exporting five
Components
And all five components have keys
In all five keys will
Basically create a very long
String
And then that whole string will be changed into an MD5 string which is 32 characters
And that 32 characters is then used to encrypt the data
Now not to worry
This actual key
Which we then end up using to do the encryption
Will be shown to you in the interface after the you know after the the data is being exported
Ok so let's go back to
To the to the user interface and let's export a component
Ok so I have this component
And it has a key
And I have other components that has no keys at this stage
So I'll select this one as a demonstration
And then I'll click export component
And as you can see
A generated a key for me
Which I can then use
To import
This package into another JCB
I can import it into the same JCB
But it's obviously not necessary
So I could use it as a backup
Now
It is storing the compiled package in
The temporary folder at this stage
I am
Working to
Determine whether we should actually make this placement of the file the dynamic
So that you could change it
Because I think it will be ideal if it automatically becomes a kind of backup method
So we're even thinking of setting up a timer that could run backups
Of your components using this method
Anyway that's future planning that's not
gonna be happening Soon though
Ok so
You have an exported component
At the moment if you if your data sets on not too big and your memory
Settings on your PHP and so forth is allowing this kind of compilation
You could select all components
And
Export them
The same will be the result
Since I have only one component set with a key
They all will be
Basically encrypted
With the same key
And they all be stored in this package so I have just now
While talking to you
Exported all my components
Into this one package
Now to demonstrate the importing of this data set
I have a
Blank website ready
So let's go there
So here's my blank website
Basically it has no special JCB components
The first thing I'll do is I'm gonna install
JCB
I'm gonna install it from
From github
So I'm going to git Hub
And then I will
Open the releases
And I'll just copy the link
To this latest release
And go back here
Paste that in here
And basically install it
Okay the installation was successful
Now I'm gonna go to
Component Builder
Then I'll open the components
And as you can see
I have only the demo component here
And I would like to basically
Move all these components that I have
Over to this new install
Ok
So I'm gonna click on import components
Then I'm gonna browse to that
That package that we've just exported
And then I'm gonna upload it
Now
We have two features here
This Force local update
Basically what it will do
Is on normal circumstances if you do a import
The
The import function looks at the data that are currently in this
In this current
JCB install
So for example
We're talking about field types we're talking about Fields we're talking about admin views and site views
If it finds a side view that is being installed
That it is already in the current Database
It looks at the last modified date
And then by that determines whether
The current installed version is newer
If it's newer
It will by Default ignore the new data and not install it
Now sometimes you might get a package where you would like to force that it updates
The current data even though it may be all the data
So this is why we have to switch you can then click yes to force the update
Now
We have a key for this package so we'll leave this to yes
I'll basically just come over here and copy that key
This key will then always be necessary if you're importing this package
And that will be it and we'll click continue
It might take a time since this is quite a huge dataset
So you could just patiently wait
And it last it is installed it tells us that the install is being successful
You might get these warnings
Now what these warnings is really telling you
Is that
During the install
Obviously you realise that Lots of IDs
Will change
I mean
We are working with a database that creates IDs as the new item is added
And since these are the IDs used to link into the various components and views and places
All these IDc must be remapped
Now
We have been able to actually
Find a very well formulated algorithm to
To resolve this problem
So it remaps all the IDs
But sometimes
There are certain IDs that hasn't you know it's not possible to remap
And so we are basically telling you here about them
And so you could see that the target field in the admin views
Has a mismatch in the field
With ID 244 now you can go back to the old install
And try and find out what happened there
And most the time when I have reviewed this usually it is because that specific field
Is no longer published or is no longer available or some reason
So this is just giving you a heads up of any changes that may have occurred
And then you can actually go to these various places and manually
Fix them
Most of the time these warnings will not show and everything will just say
All is ok
But if there is warnings and errors just Simply read the messages slowly and close
Closely
And I'm sure you'll be able to resolve it
Quite easily
Well that is a demonstration of the new feature
Now just to show you that it actually does work I'm didn't mention before but it actually
Removes all the customer files as well as custom folders
As well as all the images per admin view site view and
Wherever
To the new install so it move it into its right place
So if that is true we should be able to go to the compiler
Select any of the components
And
It should load that components image here
I should be able to just click
Ok compile
And it should be able to Simply compile that component
After compilation I could simply click installing the component
Obviously if this component was correctly mapped
Previously
And I were to go to that component now
I would see that
Everything about the component is right and it works well
And
That is really
This new feature in action
I really hope that it will be as useful to you as it's gonna be to me
And that you will have fun with it
I must tell you I suppose that at some point
We could even start looking at selling mapped components
I have a number of components that was made for specific
Purposes
But could be easily adapted for others
And so I'm starting to look at the idea of selling mapped components
Obviously
It's a little difficult because it's basically selling
The rights to it in a way that you could resell it
So I'm not sure what would be the price tag of that
Anyway
We'll see
Thank you for watching