Hi
I wanna demonstrate to you
How to add a button
To your components admin View
Either in the list area
Or in the edit area of the
View
Now I possibly have touched on this
In previous tutorials but I thought Well let's make one tutorial it just deals with that
Ok so I have a
Blank install of JCB here I just got this demo component
Installed
Or mapped and I've been installed it into this website
So if I go to Looks it just looks as it should
and we can create an item
And the
Just the
Give it some details
Say
Now we click save and close and we have an item now you see there's
a whole bunch of buttons here and if you go into the test
There's also a bunch of buttons here
All of them are usually there those are the default buttons
So what do you wanna do if you want to
Actually create buttons in these areas without custom coding
You can of course do it with custom coding but there is a JCB way to do it
You know in JCB
quite easily
So let's go back to our
Admin views
And then we open the admin view called look
And you'll see there's a custom buttons area here I click on that
We say yes you wanna add custom button
They would see that it opens control methods
And also list view controller methods
Now that will
Obviously
You need to understand the MVC
Your controller your model again your controller and your model
Each view has two controllers two models
Because it has a listview
And it has a edit View
The list view has its own controller and model
And the edit view has his own controller and model so depending on where you placing the button
It will affect
Which model and which controller
You need to use
I'm not gonna explain much about the PHP being placed in these blocks
Because
That should be something you know how to do
If you don't you need to learn you need to study
to work with Joomla API
I'd not able to also you know educate you on that now at this stage
So you do a custom button you'd click on adding a button here's your icon you can
Select any of the icons these are the default Joomla icons that they use also called
Icon
Icomoon or something
So you can use that
Then the name of the button
What you wanna call it so I'm just gonna call it a test for now then the
Name of the controller method
So I'm gonna just call that get
Tested and
Then
We'll decide is this gonna be an edit view a Single View Target
A list view or both
You know where Where must this button show up
So I'm gonna do
Just one for
First list
And then
If it's a listview
See that says list Target
Then
We could decide whether this is only a function
Now when it is a selection
It means that you need to select some items
And then click the button
For it to actually submit those ids of the selected items
If it is a only a function you don't need to select anything
When you click the button a function
Will obviously be triggered
Which doesn't require you to give it any information
So it's basically just gonna
Do something
And that obviously
You need to be able to code that
Ok so I'm just gonna
Use the default
The default is actually
Very much like selection but it
behave differently if you
Yeah I think the best way to do this is select one of the options
Compile the component and go look at the code
And I'll show you where the code ends up
And then you can decide what you wanna do
Ok so I'm gonna just save this
As a selection in a listview and
Save
Ok
At this stage if we do not add
Values to these blocks for some reason it will scream at us so we just had to
Ford slashes
Which basically
Satisfies it's
Requirement of having information
I'm gonna add a little method here that simply gonna redirect us
To the dashboard
And I'm I'm gonna call it
Get tested
That that is simply a
A controller method it must be public
Here we simply checking whether it was submitted from the current website and
Then we just gonna redirect
To the components dashboard
here
We not gonna need a method now because we just redirecting
But if you
I will show you that in a minute let me just do this for now
And then let's save and close
And let's go compile this component
So we will just select
The demo component compile it
And then re-install it
To see the changes
We gonna go to the component
And then to Looks and now we will see there is a new button called test
And if we click it
It's empty redirect us to the dashboard
So that's all it does just redirects us
And you can then obviously redirect to anything
So that's just a first way of implementing a button in the listview
Now let us go back to to editing that the functionality there for the showing you some more
Options
So just open this again
Go to custom buttons
Now maybe just add another button
We call it single
And we again call it something like a
And
The controller method
And will leave this to default and then
Save
So now in the controller method we said we gonna have a function called get done and
So here will just put a
Public function
So this time we will actually get the model and then
Do something with it in the model we can also get the
Item values
Since the moment you click this button you're inside of the item and it automatically submit the
Form
So we can actually grab those items values obviously it could be different values
from what's in the database just keep that in mind because
You could change the values then click that button and it will actually submit these new changed values
And yet those values have not been saved
To the database
And so if you want those values to actually now be in the database you'll need to actually
Put it there
And
That's again I'm not gonna demonstrate how to do that but the model has a save method
And you should actually just
Do the necessary sanitation and then
Trigger the save message
The save method and it should store the data
So for our purposes I'm just gonna grab the data and
Not go through all that I'm just gonna do a little you know verification maybe and
And then return back either an error or or success so
First we going get the values
So now that we have the data we can check
Whether the values that we want to use is actually
There and available so let's say we wanna make sure that this is already a saved
Item
Then we at least check whether the ID is more than 0
We need to have a name and
Then we can check for that
And so we can do some checking within the controller
Before we trigger the model
And you know run the function we intend
Then we triggered the model we decide what we wanna call a method in the model so I just chose
Something random and then we can just create that method in the model area
And then do whatever we wanna do
So we
Start doing some Logic in the model
Set out of above method however
Controller
Now we busy with the model area
Now
Do keep in mind that
If the model is unsuccessful you wanna do something
It's a data set
But the model is not being successful
You wanna do something
And if you data isn't said we also wanna do something
So those are the areas where in which can we can add some messages that we wanna give back to the user
Tell them what's happening
And so
In the model we basically just gonna perform our task and when they we have achieved our goal we give back
True whether we have failed we give back false and then that would
Trigger on messages in the controller
So this is just
Giving a basic overview of setting up some model controller connected with a button
So I'm gonna add some of this code in here you are welcome to pause the movie and then drop down whatever
You'd like to reuse but the reality is
You should actually be able to do this without my help
And therefore if you don't know what I'm doing here then please go Google a little more
Go find out some more tutorials elsewhere
How to create model
And controller relationships
In Joomla
Using it's API
The other reality is you can obviously open this model and controller
Of the specific View
In your IDE and in there you can see whether you know how the code is actually added
In what is happening in how is it done
And you can educate yourself
That way  as well
Ok I'm just gonna add to code in then
Ok so here I've just added some code that you can also reuse
And this basically if the work has been done will let the user know it's done
If work wasn't done we also let him know
If we couldn't even detect
The required values then we just throw a major error and
Just quit out
So
That is really
The
The controller I didn't populate much of the model because
you should design your own logic but I do return true so to
Give this first message
Then we'll go to the IDE change it to Falls again to demonstrate
You know the response
And just play around with the code in the IDE
To give you a sort of a feel of how to approach it from that
Direction ok so we gonna just save this
Then go and compile that again
Backup
Just compile it
And then
Install the new compiled version
And open the component
Go to Looks
So we can see how our test button still here if we click it still takes us to the dashboard
Now let's open the test
Now we have a new button here Worked
If you click it now it'll basically give us
The work was done because our method returns true
Now let me open the IDE
Ok looking at our
Controller
We see that
Down here
Somewhere
This is the front end I should go to the back end
Ok there it is
Controller
First we gonna open the list one which is the plural
Version
And
here we see get tested was added
And there is a little method
Then if we go to the
Edit singular one
Then getdone here is our method
And all our functions
And
JCB  has
Added The Script to the translation text
so everything here looks fine
If you now go to the model
And we open
The the look model
We'll see that
It has a new method added here somewhere
Scroll down till we see it
Sorry it was way up here I scrolled to
Fast
And so I missed it
So just here after get table
Here it added our little method
So now
Add this to false
And save
Go back to Joomla
And then click our
Button again
And now it says work was not done
Because the method returned false
So if we
Change that to True again
And save then it should work
Now let's test out another one
Let's also make this
you know
Not execute
Save this so we can get this error
Go back to Joomla
Click a button
And now it even kicks us out of the item
And it says a major error has occurred
The reason why it kicked us
Completely out of the item didn't check it in
Which is actually not ideal but
You could fix that
By looking at some of the other
Controllers
And seeing what they do
When they want to kick you out
You know educate yourself by
Looking at some of how Joomla implements
Some of these features
Now
Ok so
We
Basically got what we expected we are going to change this back safe
Go back to the view
Open that you again
Click
our button
And now we get all is done and good
Ok so
That is a quick demonstration of adding a list button
As well as adding a button inside of the edit View
Like I said you could
Actually add one button both as a list and inside
If you were to go to
That specific
Button
let's demonstrate that quickly
And we can open it and
Then instead of saying list here we say both and we click
Save
Now
We'll obviously have to
Add
This method
Get tested
Also to the
Single View like that
And then
Save
And
then
Close out of this
Compile
But they keep on clicking that
Backup
So used to doing that
And won't work now because I haven't set up to correct paths
Ok
Install it
Now let's first go look at the code
now to help you see where the button is being added I mean I shown you the controller I showed you
the model
But if you go to the view and you open look and you open this
view HTML. PHP
And you open you go to add toolbar
You'll see that here
It actually
Has added a custom
Button
Get done and get tested
To the view
And
It is
Basically that is the method
That is gonna be called
By this specific button so it's gonna look in
In the look controller
And get
This method
That's really how it works
It also adds a switch a permissional switch
To the button if this specific user doesn't have the right to do the work
Button
Then it won't show the button
And it will also
If you
carry those permission structures through to your controller
It'll stop it even from being executed
You know
Manually via URL
But this that kind of security and implementation you'll need to know how to do that
Look at Joomla way of implementing it
because you need to in the controller check whether this user has the permission
And so you need to know how to check that permission as well ok so
That's your showing you how the button gets added into the view
And where that code is and you can go look at it
Now I'm going back to to Joomla
And basically opening our component
And we go to Looks we still have our tested here
But now if we open the edit we will see have a got tested here as well
And if we click it
It will also just take us to the dashboard
And perform the same function as it would have
If we click
There
Oh so that is just showing you that you can add one button to both the listview as well
The edit view of the backend admin area
I hope this will be useful
And thank you for watching