Hi everyone
We again have a great announcement to make
JCB has again been expanded
To now include a language translation
Feature
We are very grateful one of the contributors have
Extended the code base for this
We obviously
Working together to
insure that it remains stable
Those of you that been following
The process on GitHub
Will know that
As much time and effort
Put into this
So I would like to give you a quick explanation
Of how this will work
those of you that are already using JCB
or ACB depends on
We are asking ACB Advanced Component Builder JCB Joomla component Builder
It is
Actually a English component
And
It builds the English
Language file for you
So every where in your fields
When you create a field
There  are areas in the in the field
That says that it's translatable
Translatable not translatable translatable
And if you enter those values here
JCB on the fly would take this description for example
and will convert it into a language placeholder
and will add it to the language file
The English language file
The British one
Now
This is all being done automatically
For every area of the JCB
Compiler
Even in templates and views
That's now your front end
If you create
you know site views
And even templates and layouts
You can
Just adding
These placeholders these Jtext with the actual English language string in it
Then the passer will automatically grab that text and add it to the language file
So
So currently JCB is building
A complete English
Language
File for you
And that means it's
Already able to
translate it
But it has not had the feature for you to add
Multiple other languages
And so that is really what has been the request
The request is
Isn't there a way we could
Actually Translate
This language strings
And then when JCB compiles the component it will automatically add these other languages
And so
The
The suggestion was
That we basically
Add an area where you can
Create as many languages as you like
Obviously in accordance with the conventions
Your language tags
Need to be in in accordance with the correct prefixes used in Joomla
So
I think we could add a link here
Maybe on this page some point just to take you somewhere where you can find all the information to
To use the correct
Tagging
For your language file
And here you could obviously add the language name
So you can create as many languages as you like
Then
When you compile a component
JCB obviously like I have explained
Grabs all the strings from everywhere
And
Adds to the British English translation file now let me show you some of that
Happening in the code
So here in the Get
Class
We have a function called setLangStrings
It basically gets the content from wherever JCB is handing it
And it parses it
To see whether it has
Either this language string or that one
Then it does some gymnastics here to grab all the actual strings into an array
then it parses this array
Once it has it
And it converts it
To a language string
And it adds it back
Into the content and returns the content and then
With this
We call it an object array
It is adding the language string
And the language key
To the langContent array
So that's a first thing we have this langContent array
It's all over the place and it just gets
bulkier and bulkier
Now the lang is basically the target
It's the area
Which this lang strings belong to either the site
or the
Cite system or the admin or the admin system area
So there are four areas where the site this language string all there is also such a thing as both
While JCP compiles
Some strings he knows must go to both
And this is the actual language string be capitalised string
Which is generated up here
And
This is then
I trimmed and placed in it's
place
Now
this array
Gets
Placed into the files at a certain Point
That point is very much at the very end of the compilation of course when everything is being sort of
Done
We actually get to the place where
We gonna now add two strings to the files
So first we are basically
Calling a function called setLangAdmin setLangSys basically
This is in the interpreter
You can see these these methods are here setLangSite
Here is setLangAdmin
Basically adds a bunch of strings that are default always being added
And then
Also all the other strings have been built
Moves them over to a string called language
And obviously the British English and it's for the admin area
And so it does for all the various areas
And in the infusion class it brings it together
And then we grab the values of this strings
We added to our value array
And we basically
Have the old multi language implementation running down
From here from line
We start running into the multi language string implementation
Now what does this do
Basically
It queries the database
To see whether there is such a English language string in the database
And whether there is been any translations made for it
So doesn't really use the place holders
Because the place holders are so ambiguous between various components and our idea was
To prevent a very bloated oversized database we must try to share strings amongst
Components
And so currently when you compile a component it
Gathers it's English strings like I have explained
And then it checks the database whether these English strings already exist in the database
And if they do it then checks whether they have
Translations already linked to them
And if they do
Then it starts grabbing that translation strings and adds them
To this
Language object array
Also by tag and by area and then here we are basically parsing this array so by this time
Time we ready have all the languages
In place and we are now able to put them into the component
So
It's basically these functions get multiple strings
A multi language strings
setLangPlaceholders ,purgeLanguageStrings
These are the functions
That actually does the work
So you could go look at these they are all found in the get
class the one where everything really starts
They are found there and you can look at them they are
All their doings are are
Obviously open source so you can see
Now so that means by the point we get to this line 1109
We already have all the language strings
In their various
Areas and various languages
And we can now start adding them back into the component
And that's really what this
Part is doing
It just adding it into the component
So
Now let's go back to the user interface to see this in action
So I'm gonna compile a component
Just any component
Let's say this document manager
And while I'm compiling it
So keep in mind it will be running through
And grabbing all the English strings then eventually will check
This
Language translation table
Weather no strings
Actually exist
And if I do if they've been translated
Ok so that's basically as simple as that
It compiles it
And
It does most of the work for you
Now the question has been asked
What if
You've changed some
Fields name or some description
And now
That other description that Old English
String
Is no longer being used
What what then
Well at the moment
It will basically be purged
Now the purging works as follow
When it
Discovers that is string is no longer being used by a component
We can go in the cone and I can show you that
Then
It basically asks the question
Is another component still using it
Ok
so if more components are using it
and if another component is using it
It simply removes the current component from the string
And then it it goes on , it doesn't
Remove it
If no other component is using it so let's say
No all the component is any longer
Linked to the string
Then it checks whether there has been any work done in it
Has there been translation done
I mean it's quite a
Huge job to do translation
So we figured if you've done it you wouldn't want to just delete it
So what we will do then
As we basically archive
The string
We move it from the published State
Do it archived State so you can go to archives and then there see all the strings that no longer
Are actively linked to a component
But has translations in it
And if it does not have any translation
So you've seen it's not link to a component
And it does not have translation
Then we remove the string from the database
So these are the two functions to remove the string completely
And so it's like it never it was there in the first place
And so that is really how The Purge works at the moment it only purges That which really is no longer linked
Neither has any work done in it
And
So
That is what's happening at the moment
Ok so now if we were to go to this component in JCB
So the document manager
You see there is a new tab called translation
And in this tab it shows you all the English strings
Whether it's been having any work done in it so it will say no translation when the work has been done to it
And in how many components it's been used
So currently
Most of these strings as you see are used in quite a few other components
And now you can from here
Click on any of these strings
And
It will give you the list of all the components where it's used
it show you the string but you cannot edit the string here
But you can add translations so here you'll select the language and you will add the translation
And you can add as many as you like to the string
And
Then every one of these components this translation will be Active
So
That is really how
The translation manager works
There are two ways to get to the strings the one is like a show you via the component
And we are planning
To add a button here
Whereby you can import
these and export these strings quite easily so that you could give them to other team members
who can then make translations give back to you and you just import them here and then it gets linked automatically
So that is still under development
It should come out soon within the next.........
Let me not give any promises
Soon as we have the time
And
So to make it easier to do these translations
The other way to get to these translations
Is to Simply go to language translations
And here you'll find all the components strings together
So this could become a database
With over 8000 lines I'm suppose
But like you see it's working quite well I've already got a lot of components
Mapped
The ones that you see usually are the ones that are active
Which I'm working on
I've got quite a few in archive is well
So the reality is
I've been testing this against
you know
say 8 or 9 components at the same time sharing strings among each other
And I expect this feature to become quite powerful
Soon as we are able to you know speed up the translation method
There is been suggestions that we also
Add this feature to a sort of a community area somewhere
Where we you can push your English strings there and you can pull
Already translated strings from it
I know this is a great idea but how to manage that so that we don't find people abusing the system
are Still under the debate
So anyone have any good suggestions please go to GitHub and open a issue and let's start talking
Well
I hope this is enough explanation
On how to do
Multiple language implementation on your components in Joomla component Builder
I'm quite happy about this new feature I really think it will
In the long run
Become a very valuable asset
Anyway
Thank you
Very much for watching
Goodbye