Hi
I would like to show you how to set the site view permission
the Site view permission is really related to the front end of any site view
Since it usually by Default set not allowed
And that is basically because
We have
The problem where
That data is controlled
By the
Global settings of the component
And unless you write some custom script to add that Global settings to the database for permission
It actually doesn't have those permissions set and because it's not set it's by Default always said to not allowed
Now let me explain that on a code level to you
Ok we will use sermon distributor which is
One of the demo components that is available
and if you are
Interested in buying access to this demo component
It obviously has site views
So
If we open the options tab
You see there's a permissional or tab
And if we search for sight
You see there is category site access
Plural and category
Site Access singular there's also preacher site access and preachers
And series and series list
And sermon
And all these various site accesses
Literally saying whether the public
Will have access Now by Default as I said
It is said to inherit
And inherit will actually say not allowed
Now they are there's something that I've done to try and accommodate this problem
In JCB
So Let's close out here and look at some of the code I have done there
so I will have to go to component Builder
And then to components
And I'll open sermon distributor
Then I will go to settings
And then sight views
I will click add
And
Now you will see that we have here
A value called default View
Now what the default view really is
Is that the view
That
The component will
Direct you to
If you are accessing a view
That you as a user don't have access to
So
Usually we would set the default View to not have an access
Control
So
Will say ok the default View
Doesn't have access control
That means it's actually open and public to all
And then we could
Explain on this view
How to get access for example to the rest of the component
.
For because you could see in what user group the user is and you can by that determines some messages
Ok
So that means whenever you have obviously there can only be one default view even if you select more than
One the first one the compiler gets to will become the default view the next one will be ignored
So they can only be one at the moment it says that here select the only one and so if you have an
Access for categories and it's not yet set
It will throw the user back to for example here preachers
Now
What is the advantage of this it Simply negates the error page
So did you don't get a loop where the
The permission just never gets resolved so just goes into a loop and then crash the site
This prevents that but it obviously doesn't solve our permission structure of completely
But it is at least a first step towards trying to resolve it so you would say it
This is your default page don't give the default page permissional structure so if any of the other pages is Accessed
it will divert to the default page
And now the next step that we have to try and address this problem
Is some custom scripting
That you can add
Which will show
After installation so let me show you some of that
The component where we actually have this shown is the demo component
So you can just open the PHP tab
And in the PHP tab you see
That it has a enqueue message
In the post flight in stalled blocks basically gets the factory
Get application first set the component Global setting and the permissions in the option
Area
or the front end of the component will not work as expected
Please note that each view on the front end has access and permissions
So if you would like the public to access those views
They must be given the access and
Permission
And then this is just an info
Message that comes up
Basically after install
So that is another way that we've tried to help the user realise that he needs to
Add some now you can obviously
Change this into a link
Become very fancy
Or
You could
Even add
Custom script here
That updates
The
This components promotional structure
And actually adds the public to to have access to the site views
These are some of the ways that we are trying to resolve the permissional restraints
Of Site views
Now
let's look at this, I was saying earlier at the code level so forgive me for taking so long to get
So here we have the access file open of sermon distributor
And if we do a search here
Site
You see that it has the site access values set for the component
Now
When we look at
The front end of the component
Open categories
You see that here it is asking whether the user
Has that access
And then if it doesn't
It does a redirect and then redirects to the default page you see that
Now let's open the default page
And
The ideal of the default page
Is that if the default page is not the site route
It will If It cannot access the default page it will actually add this error
And then redirect to the site root
Which being the websites homepage
And so that's kind of how we trying to
Prevent the
This permissional structure from interfering with your user experience
Now if we go back to the component
The Sermon Distributer component
And we again open the site views
This time I change it that is doesn't have access
I actually save it that way
Go to the compiler
Compile Sermon distributor
and install
Ok now let's go back to the code
Now you'll see
That it doesn't have any of that checks in the preachers file
Only in the category
File
And it still redirects to preachers
Which in effect means that this one will no longer give any errors
But it will show these errors
Which relates to the fact that they cannot see
The the categories
Now I think some of the advancements that we might still think on doing is maybe
Add a field to the component
Where the user can change these errors
To show
Maybe a message of how to purchase access or something
Yeah we could still look at that you do realise that this stage
JCB does have the the option to actually customise any section of code
So by using what is known as the custom code implementation
Now I'm not gonna demonstrate that please go look and review those videos they are on YouTube
Where you can literally
Change this whole code block here
And then
Use use your own implementation upon these measures
Well that is a a quick demonstration or explanation on how to manage
The different
permissional structures for JCB regarding the site front-end
So if you do not want that
Control you can simply obviously just put it off
But I realize that most of you
Might want to add some custom scripting that adds permissions to the database for that component
That's little bit Beyond the scope of where JCB is at the moment
Aldo that is a nice to have there are more pressing things that we'll focus on
First