Hi
I would like to demonstrate to you one of the latest features that's been added to JCB
If it's a request was made about 11 days ago
Auto generate my update SQL
After a lengthy discussion
the decision was made to add the
The future and I am basically done doing so first let me give you some
Background so you can understand where we coming from
When you create a component in Joomla
Then usually you have a set of views and the views and the backend are linked to a set of tables
I'm so on the installation of the component
For example if we do so here with JCB
It actually
Builds the tables for those views on installation
So then if you go to the back end of the component
And
You create a new item
it actually stores the value in the database
So that it can be retrieved that's very basic
The reality is
If you as a developer make a change
To this component
Which involves new tables
Then
Obviously you would need to add
Extra script to your components package
So did upon installation
If it finds that there is already an existing component it will actually update the database accordingly to the
New settings the new tables or any Fields added or so forth
So we gonna demonstrate this
In JCB there used to be a way to do that which still works by the way it was
manual way a way for you to manually add the new SQL statements
That are needed to make the update, it was done under this version updates tab so you would click on a version
Updates tab and here you would add your specific sequel
Query script and upon installation
If the existing version is below
This update it will grab this and install it into the database creating the new tables and so forth
So
What I'm gonna do now is you'll see that at the moment
This admin view has only 1 2 3 4 5 6
Views
I'm gonna add another View to this component
You can see it doesn't have these buttons ticked
I don't not know how to resolve this it seems like
This is a Joomla problem
Because there are multiple
Columns in this view
Because if you close it and click it again
And actually fixes that anyway that's just by the way so now here I'm gonna add a new
View
Called help documents and just make some minor changes to the defaults
Add it to the 7th position
And then click save and click save again
So now we basically add a new view which means a new table to the database
But we haven't written any of the SQL
Because with the new changes this is gonna be done for you automatically on the moment to compile this
Component
So let's do that
So now here we are, we are going again compile this component you see it's version is it still
1.4.1
So
We are compiling it
Now what the system is doing is, it is checking the history and it's making a lot of calculation
To dynamically realise that there is been a new table increment
The version number
And
If I now
Install this component
And I go and open that component
I'll see that the new view is here if I open the view there is no errors
if I create new
it'll automatically start behaving the way that is expected
And
That is really
Let say,
text
And then, hi
So we are targeting
The
External sources
So forgot
Few other things here
as you can see
The database already stores the values
And the new table is actually therefore in the database and working as expected now
you realize that
This means that our
JCB component
Has been updated so if I refresh this page
You'll see that the version number has been incremented
And if you open the version updates and scroll down you would see that one point
.......
1.4 .1
Got this new
creating of a help document
Table
And a new version got allocated here
Obviously we do not know what is this link and so we add this demo link here which you need to manually update
still
But that is by far a tremendous improvement
Ok this also works not only with
The adding of a new view but also if you were to add a field
To an existing view so let me demonstrate that quickly
So I'm gonna be adding a new field to the preacher View
I'm simply gonna select any Fields since I will removed again
Let's call it
Image
And I'm gonna add this to left
One
That must be then two
And save
And save and close
So now I've added a new field to preachers
And again I'll be going to the compiler
And I'll select the component and just compile
And again since it detected there's been a field change it incremented the version number
And if I install the component
And we go to the component
To the preachers View
We'll now see
That new field actually there
Image
And if I was to select an image
And save
You'll see that it
Really
Oops I see I actually missed it
The reason was that
This component didn't have any history so I had to go and make a few changes take into
account that your building a component from the ground up it will have history
So this is only gonna be happening when you have install a component
via the import function in the components or maybe using the demo component
So what I would advise it just open all the views and save them at least once so that there is history recorded for
For that View
That is one of the drawbacks there is really no way for me to my negate that issue
Since the history
Of each of these different items
Being at the admin view and the fields actually needs to be created the moment that you saved the item
And it's really can't be done before then
Ok
So taking that an account
I'll recompile it again and fix
That so it should increment it to 1.4.3
I will just install that
Again
Going back to refreshing the preacher will see that
Image field is back
now select an image
Click save and now you'll see
That it actually does store the data for this image
Because if we refresh the
The component will see that it is again
Incremented the version
If I open the
Update area
You see that it actually
Added this new
Altering of the preacher table adding the image
Field
And it is also added the new
Version to this list
Ok so that is a quick demonstration of this new feature automated feature
It is in its very beta
Phase we obviously still gonna
Be working at it to make sure that it's completely stable
So please
Take a go at it if you find any bugs open look for other open issues which may be
Someone already reported
And start commenting on that what you think should be done
And if you don't find any then please open an issue and let us let us fix this issue
I think this will be a tremendous improvement to JCB
Making it
Again with the one of the best
Joomla component
Developing tools
Out there today
Where it is even writing your update sequel for you
Just by you being busy working and improving your component
Without being concerned about that
Thank you for watching