Hi I'd like to quickly give you a tutorial
On how to
Basically add
An admin View
To the front end of your site
So
There can be editing and submission
Of the front end
of this specific admin View now
Illustrate this
I'm gonna use the public version of JCB
And it has this demo
Version in it so basically first I'll just compile it
and install it to the local Joomla website
So we can see what happens
And then install it
And then basically open it
So here we have the
The demo version
That is publicly available and it basically has a admin view called "Looks"
So if you go to the list you of the admin View
I call Looks you see there is none, we will create new
And then
There is basically a description box
A more item where you can click
And see some
Custom Fields and fields
Being built sorry email mobile birth
Image website
And your normal publish and permission structure for the view
And the name field
Now that's basically what I referred to as the admin View
It's this combination of fields working together in one View
Now what I will show you is how to add this
Editing area, basically the these three tabs
To the front end of your site
So that it will function like a form
Now who you would allowed to access the form will depend upon the permissions structure
You see the permission structure
Is what
Actually controls who can edit
And who can add
Items to a specific admin View
So currently as you can see your public cannot actually edit this
If we created an item
They cannot edit it so there's an item level on permissions
and if I Close out of this
Then you'll see here in options there is also a global control on
Permissions
So the global control of permissions
Is also if you want public to be able to submit
To to this form you need to
Allow them to be able to create so you would say allow
And now the public is allowed to create
And
You see that usually
Most components has more than one View
This one only has one it's called look
So you'll also have to
Over here
Say allow
And if you want them to edit existing submissions
Then there is the edit State edit own created by
All these things in the Global Spec as well as in the local edit of The View
So there is basically two switches here one is a Global switch and one that is
specifically focusing on the view so if you cannot access the view on the front end
After we've created it it is actually would need to come back to to this area and
And sort out the permissions for the specific group
Who should have access to the specific View
On a front end
so this permissional structure is quite intense and
Extendable so that you can target specific groups with specific permissions and so forth
For every View
The JCB bolts in the admin
As well as site
Ok let me cancel out of here
I'm not gonna
Make any further changes here
So we basically in the demo component now I'm gonna go back to JCB and basically
I'm gonna flip one switch and then JCB will actually develop or write the code
For the site end of this component
So I'm going back to JCB
Going to components
And I'm opening the component
And now in the component there is an area called settings where obviously all your admin views
Are linked right so I'm gonna open that
Are usually there is a little bug in
Joomla which if you open it the first time it doesn't
Reflect the original setting
So I usually just open it cancel it and then open it again and you'll see that the original setting is
Is back
And
You see here that
Edit create site view
Must be set to "Yes"
If it is set to "Yes" then it means that it's gonna create a site view
Off this look as so that you can edit it on the site end and not only in the admin
Area
And it also means create items
So I'm just gonna save this
And then also save and close
And then go back to compiler
Compile
Demo
I see that off
Go
Install it
Now let's go look at the code
So looking at the demo websites folder structure we are going to components
And then we'll see that there is a com underscore demo folder
And we will see there is the modules as well as the controllers
As well as the views
So there is basically
This is the view that was dynamically generated
By
JCB review called look
And then the model also called look
And the controller
Are you can open that
To actually see what was the code that was written
And so as you can see it's basically looks very similar to the admin area except that it's been slightly
Modified
For your front end
And it's requirements
As you can see we were adding
Some CSS classes and JavaScript
From the back end
And
Then
Here is the model
Basically get item get form
And then here is the controller
Ok so we
just showing at the code just basically what was created
Now
The fact that this was created
Doesn't mean that there is actually Now set of links
That you can click and edit the forms which was submitted
or that there is a link to create any
So these these things is what you need to do manually
Now so
Let's show you some of that
as you can see there is two views here
In called on the site views
And one is called looks and other one is called looking
As you can remember the one we looked at here
Which I said was automatically generate is called look so that one isn't actually showing because it was just
a tick box that created this whole view model and controller
So you don't need to build
The look view again
But you need to get links to it
Ok so
In looks we are using a dynamic get
And in looking as well so let's let's go to the dynamic get page
So there is one called looks and looking so good let's go to the looks dynamic get
So as you can see here is the dynamic get for the look
Looks and it got a custom script area
Were basically we're asking whether the items are set whether there are items and then we looping through them
And during the looping process we basically determine
By this ScanDo script here
You see in the helper class there's a get action function
The get action function asks whether look item
With the current user has the edit option
To the specific look item
And if it does it actually in this little script here
It builds an edit look button
And dynamically adds that to the edit link
Which is coupled to the item
And then just continues on
So it basically dynamically generates the button for edit here in the dynamic get
Are you could have done that anywhere I just decided to do it here because then it actually
gets added to the model which is more
Where your logic
For lots of your data structure should be placed
And ok so now if you go back to this to the views the site views
And we open the looks site view
You see that we got the main get set as looks
And here
If you scroll down
Well basically
In this area here we are looping
Through the look items
And
Echoing the edit link
After the description
And that means now the link that we built here in the dynamic Get
Which is the button
Will either be empty and therefore show nothing if the user doesn't have the permission to edit it
Or it will actually show a button
You also see
There is currently as I look at this I haven't actually added
A a link
For creating new
Looks and
The same would be required to do that
So
You could use the same button script just copy that
And
Here at the head before the table
You could
Add a button to create new looks
Now
All you would need to change is basically
This link here
That it will have an ID to zero
And then it will actually create a new
Look
So that's a quick tutorial
On how to add
An editable
Admin View to the site
End of your component
And then link it into your side view so that you can basically click on a button and edit
A specific ID View
Or create more
And then control that with this get action helper class
Method
Which gives you
Basically whether it can be edited
You can go look at this helper class in the code
So let me just quickly open that for you
So here in the code
And helpers
We open
Demo PHP
And we scroll down
Until we get the method called
getaction
Where is it now
Ok here it is
getaction
Around 540 depends on how much the customer scripting there is been added
And
You can go through this logic
To see that we are dealing with a number of
Concepts and trying to determine the permissional
To edit own
And to create and so forth
And it all gets stored
And given back to you
Basically in the result set
Ok
So
You could also just echo out the result var dump or something
In the look
to see
Exactly what is the result that you get from that structure
So
If we go back to
The looks here View
Let's just open that model
You see that the custom scripting we looked at
Basically gets added here
From JCB
That custom scripting that creates the button
So you could come in here
And you can just add a var
Dump
Exit and
Take this can do
And
Login as any kind of user on the site
And then
When you basically load the page it should show you
The can do
List
Of that specific User Group
Also keep in mind that here's the authorities setting
That is applicable to the looks site View
And it also controlled in the permission structure
So there's a lot of permissions automatically being added to components build in JCB
And you need to always keep that in mind
It might look like things don't work while it actually works very well you just Haven't kept in mind that there is a permissional
Structure
And that you need to adapt that permissional on structure as it's fitting to your project
Ok well thank you for watching
Hope this helps