Hi
I would like to demonstrate to you the new automated backup feature that's been added to JCB
It is part of a
Extension
Which I called the API
Which really gives you the option of
Querying JCB
Via a URL
To perform certain functions
First of which would be to actually generate a backup
We not sure exactly
What kind of features we should be adding to this API
And we started to discussion
About this on GitHub and
You're welcome to
Give me a shout
Just send me an email you can
Just check here
My email address is
Behind this link here
Features we want to add to the API
Currently the first one like I said is the backup feature
Now
JCB already
Has in its
Component area
An export component feature which we basically just extended
To automate
But we've left it as well
Here is a button called backup and it actually is the same feature except
You can now manually also trigger that feature
Now what this backup feature does
Either being triggered by a
A CronJob or being triggered by this button
Is it actually
Takes all your components
And
Exports them
Encrypts stem
Stores them on a local folder
And emails the key to a
Trusted email address
Would you have set up
Now
The
Components that are in your trash will not be
Actually part of this backup
So only components that are published
Or unpublished or archived
Will be in the backup every everything else will be ignored
And
Basically when the backup runs either manually or automated via
A CronJob
It will take those components
Use the specific keys as it would with an exporting of a components
An encrypted
And
Store them in that folder as I said
Now
There are some things you need to set up
For all  this to work
As expected
The first of these being in the options area of JCB there are some new
Feature so let's just open that
So we see there is now a mail configuration
at DKIM
And a CronJob
Tab it added and also this field here called API user
Maybe let me start with this field
The API user
Primarily be used
for
The ID that is used
In the permission structure
You see
When you are in the components area
And you trigger this feature manually
It actually uses this current login user
To determine whether that
The components being you know encrypted and backed up
Whether he has the permission to actually
Do that
Now
This a way
As we increase the permission structure of JCB
You might end up having components that certain individuals who are in certain groups may not have access
to them
And then there might be components and Fields and views that they may have access to
Or some that they may not have access to
And so we're already now
Laying some of the foundation to make sure that there isn't some loophole
Where are there by
Triggering a bash sorry a batch
Update or export of components or backup
They can't extrude certain components which they actually by Default don't have access to
I know that's a long explanation but
It's that's just to give you a background to why we still need an API user
We still need a user
Which now if it's automated the backup
That this user ID actually
Allows him to make the backup
So that means that the IP sorry
The API user should be a user
Which has the permission
To all the actual components Fields and
Well everything actually
In the JCB component
Now
It is secure because like I said the component
Gets
Compiled
And stored locally
We might
Consider adding
The option to push the component backup to an FTP
Server
But that part is not fully functional yet
We we have had
the
The proposals made to do that so that the backup is actually not even on the same system
But did it secure on another system so if this system
Collapses
You you still safe
You still got you your data out
So that sounds to me as a good
Idea and so we will be adding an FTP
Option as well
Which will very much for the work similar as your components
When you compile a component and it sends it off to a sale server or
Or such
That is really the same features will make use of anyway so
That's just talking about
Selecting an API user
And why that is important
Now
When we go to the CronJob
Tab
We will see that there is some is basic instructions here
For those of you familiar with CronJobs I suppose there everything is self explanatory
Those who are not I would suggest you Google around
Find some tutorials
Read up
Make sure you know what you're doing
And that you're a very comfortable and setting up a CronJob
There are various ways for you to trigger this URL
The system currently detects whether your system actually can run curl request
And if it can't it will fall back on the getoption
Assuming that JCB is installed
In an environment that allows these two functions to work
If not you can simply take
Only the URL
And run it in a CronJob
In in the manner that is
You know applicable to your system
And know that
This URL actually just triggers
The backup to start
And when the backups finished
It actually just tells you
The same message that you will get
If you run the backup by clicking backup here
You see there is a green message that pops up
Saying yes the backup was done the email was sent
Those are the only messages
That also actually
Gets returned upon this URL
So they they are the same
Now
We currently throwing that responds away
But you could
Add it to a log
Depending on how regularly this CronJobs running
There isn't the date currently I think
It might make sense for us to add a date
But at this stage there isn't one
Ok so now we if you're running in a firewall your Joomla website has a firewall installed
like RS firewall
Then you you might need to adapt your
Your curl request
To behave like a real browser
And here is a a a a post on stackoverflow that could actually help you
Understand more about that
So now currently the
Cron backup folder path is set
Here
And so it currently only backups to a local folder
As I said we will add an FTP option here
We will still work out how we can do that and still have it secure
Joomla doesn't by Default actually
Encrypt fields in the
You know Global configuration of your component
And
So that's might be part of what makes it difficult for us to implement This
Here but
But we will work on that
The point is currently It stores it into a local folder
And it
Emails the backup key to the email address that you set in here
Now make sure that email address is secure
And that it is safe
Obviously because the keys are being sent to it
Now here is a naming structure for your file
By Default it actually adds only up till the day so it will
Make backups all through the day but overwrite the file every time
Unless you add an hour then it'll only per hour overwrite it
And if you add a minute
It will actually never overwrite it because it will be a different minute every time
So that is
To rename your package and to see how much of the backups you want to
Keep
And
If we go to the mail configuration area you see that it currently set to use the global Mail
Configuration which is your Joomla default
Now
I would advise that you use a very secure method of sending
the emails
So either SMTP
overwriting the SMTP settings here
Or if you use the global ones then overwrite or insured at your Global
Email settings in Joomla is also using SMTP
That it actually runs through an SSL and is secure
Ok the DKIM is also a added feature
Which can increase
Trust
And security
Off your emails
Then there is the folder sorry the company
Details
Which
At this stage
Is important
To add since it will also become part of the backup package
And we will look at that again when we restore a backup to show you where this information comes up
Ok so that some of the settings you need to first set
Within your Global configuration
Now once you've set those settings
Company settings your CronJob settings
Your local path the email the name
And your
User
API user
You can save and close this area
And we can start looking at a component
See this feature in action
Now since this is a default Joomla website
Sorry Joomla
Install and JCB install
There's only one component here
And it's the demo component
Now usually the demo component doesn't have
Encryption key
So I'll open it
And
I've already set it because I've done this video
A few times
So
You basically come and set an export key
In at least one of the components
That will be part of the backup
If any one of the components
That are being backup have an export key
It will actually encrypt all the components with that export key
If multiple one's have an export key it will Combine those keys
To use as the encryption key
It hashes those keys so the actual key is not what is actually being used
And the actual key that's being used is the one that will be emailed out
To do that trusted email address
So we'll save and close the the demo component
And
Then
We will just run a manual backup here
Which like I explained before is really similar to the CronJob except that it's triggered by clicking
This button
Ok so we just click it there
And
The moment since it's a very
Just one component
It's not a very big
Process it should
be finished quite quickly
And it will basically say ok
The backup has been
Done successfully
The owner details was set so if for some reason you forgot
To set the owner details in the options area it will actually tell you that here
And the email
With the new key was sent
So now
To make sure that your backup actually works
You should now go check the folder
In which you set The Backup should be placed
And see whether the backup is there
And also
Check the email address and see whether that they receive the key
So I'll be doing that quickly
Ok I see I have a backup actually here in the folder
As expected
So the backups been done
I can double click into the backup
And make sure that it has all the
Expected files
And at this stage it looks It Like It does if you have a lot of custom
Files
That you've added into the component
There will also be an extra custom
Folder in the zip
Document
And I not only in image one
Ok so we will test this backup by actually importing it
But first let's see if we received the email as well
So here we can see that it also send the email as expected
With the corresponding key
Will be using this key to test the backup
Be sure again like I said that it actually sends the key
to a secure
Website email address
And that
That
That even the email that sense
The
Email from Joomla
Is using a secure SSL by SMPT
Now let's test this backup
A backup will only makes sense if we actually lost our data so I'm gonna take
the component
And basically
Wipe this one just delete it
Throw that in trash
Then go to trash
and
Empty the trash
So know
There is no components
Click on import components
Now we need to browse to the directory
Where that component was backed up so we'll click on the directory tab
So there we have the components
The path to the actual backup
package
And we click on Get File
Now we will take that key that was sent to us via the email
And we will force the update
And will add that key here
And we'll click continue
Sorry I just step back for a moment again
Because I realized I didn't explain what you'd seeing here and like I said before your
Package data of the owner of the package is displayed here
And the package details are displayed here
So if you have more than one component backed up all of those components will show
Here on the components being imported
And here
You will see the
The package owner
Details
And get the key from this link here
So I will
Again do this import I just wanna to quickly
Get back to that
Let's Let's click continue
Wonderful so we have the component back
It's all being restored
And that's really what the purposes of the backup
Is it when something goes wrong
You can actually come back to where it was when the backup was made
We can test with a backup has been successfully restored by going to the compiler
And then selecting the component
And clicking on compile
And as you can see is been completely successfully built
And we can now click on install the demo component
And then we can even go
To the demo component
And see that
Everything is actually working
Adding a new look
There's a  all the various fields
As it usually
are
Available in the demo component
Well thank you for watching that is automated settings for JCB
And setting them up and you making use of them