Hi
Recent question came up that was asking about help menu integration
For JCB components
You will see the JCB itself
Has this
Help document area
Now I have not actually had the time to
Expand upon this help document area as much as I would like to and maybe in the future
We would
Still expand on it but it is a feature
That actually is very easily added to any other JCB component
If you have purchased
The Sermon distributor package
Let me show you what I mean
There is a place
One of the repositories on the VDM data I called JCB packages
So you go to VDM - io
And then JCB -Packages on GitHub
And one of the package is here is Sermon distributor
You can
Download this package
But
Before you haven't purchased a key for it you can't really use it
So to get a key you would basically click on this link here
Which is vdm.bz
/jcb
-packages
This will take you to a
Place on our website
Where you can purchase
The purchase the Sermon distributor package
Here is the
Link that you would need to get to
You can also go to VDM dot IO
Which is
Our website
Some just open that and then under services
You can also find
Joomla
Sorry JCB packages
You just click on that it will take you to the same place
So there are a few packages already available
Which basically is a fully mapped component
Inside of JCB
So if you purchase this you would get information and a code and everything which will help
you install the Sermon Distributor package
So
I'm gonna quickly install the Sermon Distributor package
On this demo website that I am using
I'm not gonna demonstrate how I did that because if you purchase the package you would have all the instructions
And how to do this once you have installed the Sermon Distributor package you can go to the admin
views
And you will find that the admin views now has this
New admin view called
Help document
It's just As one admin view called help document
Now you by Default
With JCB have this demo component
So let's open the demo component and let's add the helper structure to it to demonstrate
To you how it works
Now
At the moment it doesn't have any helper structure at all it is just a demo
Component with only a few
Structures actually I think it only has that see admin view it has one view called look
And got no custom views but it got a site view called looks and looking
So what we'll do first is we gonna go to the admin views
I'm gonna click here to add another row
And we are gonna add the help documents
The support icon
Oh yes we can have this unticked problem I'm sorry about this while we are
Busy phasing out the repeatable fields so you'll end up working with Sub fields in the future sub forms
But to fix this in the meanwhile you just closed that and open it again and now you'll have all those
Tick boxes in place so I'm just gonna add that
view again
We gonna use the support icon and we gonna leave
Most of this to defaults except it doesn't have meta we don't
Don't use access
We can do the import but it doesn't have a front end editing
We don't want it to have one and
We would have it in the 2nd position
And maybe not part of the main menu
I think that's good enough now
We'll play
Save this
And we'll save and close that's really all it takes
So you've just install the Sermon distributor package into your JCB that
Added the helper document menu sorry the admin view and I've just linked
That view to the demo component then I'll go to the compiler
And I'm basically just gonna compile that demo component
And as you can see here it isn't here yet installed on my website this is quite important
Not to have it in installed on the website
Then I'm gonna compile it
Then I'm just gonna install it
Now if I go to demo
We will see
That it has this new helper documents area
Now at the moment it doesn't have any helper documents
What we can do to change that is we can then go to the helper documents click new
And when it's opened we'll select which group you want to Target
So I'm just gonna select all
Then I'm gonna select the I wanna target a view in the admin area
The demo will be basically the desk dashboard
Then there is help documents
This import I'm gonna take looks I'm on a target looks area
Then I can give it a title
And I can say what type of help do I want, I want a link to an Joomla article
Want to put in my own custom text
Or I want a link to an external URL This is usually what we will use when we ship a component
Since this will then give us the opportunity to link it to an external URL which
We can update an edit without sending an update or you know and upgrade
To the component we can just change the help menu itself sorry the the help pages which
We linked them to and this is how JCB is been setup JCB is linking to an external
Help structure but you can decide whatever you wanna do with this component you could say text for
Example
And you could say
This
Is the help
You need
And whatever
And save and close
Now if we go to looks
We'll see that then automatically there is a new button here called help and if we click on it
It actually opens that help
And so you can now even going back to
If you now click on new then that help menu won't show anymore
But you can close out here
And you can then go back to the help documents
create another one
Again select or you could target a specific group
Or you can just target all groups
Again admin area you can also target the site area and be able to actually
Link it to any of the front end
Areas then we can say now we are wanna not
Target the list but the edit area which is singular
And again we can say
Give it a title
And again this time let me link it to an URL
And then
Save and close
And then let's go to that area
And new
And now we'd see that area also has a help button if we click on it
It opens that URL
In a pop-up and as you see I just selected
A video
And so
That is how you can actually
Link
To other external sources to be giving the help
To the specific page in the instructions that is necessary
And you can then
Having set up a few help menus for the component you can go back to component Builder
And to the admin View
Area
And
Let's say you have a help document linked to component
Demo but it is
You want to ship it with the information that you've Now created as help
Inside of the component then what I would usually do is I would actually
Open this component
Sorry this admin View
And I'll give it a system name of demo
And I'll go to the MySQL
Say yes I wanted to link it I'll select
Table
And then I would go to the demo table
Help document you see demo help document click on that
And I'll just remove some of the
Values that I know
Is not necessary
Ok I think that's fine
Created modified can stay
I wouldn't even take the version out but
Doesn't even matter
We can most certainly take that one out
And there we go those seems to be fine
And save and close
Now
I can save this
Or save as copy
And if I have another component I'll just copy this one
And link it to that components data base
The only thing to remember when you've done this
Is it you must first compile the component before you uninstall the local component
So you would first come here and compile that component
Now let me quickly show you in the code what is happened
Basically I've
Opened this zipped package of a component gone to admin area then to
sql
And then if I go to the install MySQL
Document
I'm just double clicked on that
And it's open this document I'll now see that they obviously has this
Insert table
But it also has
Insert
Data
That we created see there is
This is the help
You need there's a URL I added
And it will basically insert this data
Into the database
When this component is installed
So
Having done those changes and linking the table to the component
It actually goes to the database in the extract these values and places it
Into the dump file of the
Component
It does not place it into the update file just that you know and that means that
If users already have your component installed and they install this
It will not add these helper structures you'll have to use
Custom scripting in the Joomla component area in the PHP tab there is
a place for update and uninstalled and installed
To add custom PHP script where why you can insert this data into the
Database
Ok now I'm gonna show you what happens if the component is no longer installed
And you try to compile it
The first thing is I'm gonna quickly uninstalled the demo component
Now I'm gonna go to the compiler
And I'm gonna try and compile this component
It will give me this error
And basically it's telling you that it couldn't find
This table
It couldn't find that table and it's because you uninstalled it
And the only way then to compile this component
Would be to go back to the admin view
And deLink the component from the table
So like I said make sure to compile the component
Before you uninstall
The component which you are linking to
So we linked
To the installed components table
The other way to try and avoid this
Is to actually instead of linking to the table
Like we did here is to instead use a dump file
So I would say you click on dump
You open your sql
File that it created
And you copy
The the values from that file
or cut whatever
And paste as values in here
Like that
You could leave the comment or even leave a comment out
And this way if we save and close
We will now
Even if the component is uninstalled be able to compile
And still have this demo
Or
Shipping values
Of the component in place
So let's try compiling it again
This time it compiled without any errors
And if we go open the ZIP package
And then open this install MySQL
.utf8.sql file
We will see that it added that dump
Values right back into the file and that's exactly what you would like it to do
Anyway
This was just to demonstrate actually
How to add
A help menu structure
To any JCB component
Basically you could do that without purchasing the Sermon distributor component
The only part that really is necessary
Is for you to create a helper document
And of course
This helper document
That we are using from the Sermon distributor package has custom scripting in it
And it's this custom scripting that makes it a adaptable to any other component
I can
Quickly
Show you which areas this custom scripting must go
But obviously I would rather wanted to buy the components package
It's really only in a relation
To the articles
And to the site views
And the admin View
That we have custom
Fields
That are a little tricky
As well as the user group
You need to
Have a little perspective on how to setup user groups
So these are the two areas that are difficult the articles one as well
Because JCB when it has
When it detects that this is a help helper document and it detects those specific field
Values that are set up correctly then it automatically
Build some of the front-end necessary concepts as well as adding
This dynamic behaviour in the backend
I hope this helps
to
To at least show you that it is very doable the adding and help
Structure to a component
What I think makes this quite unique
Is that
The component then ships with this
Pre built in help structure but the user that uses your component
He might want to give extra help or little different kind of help to the front end users of his
Website
And he will be having access to this helper area and editing it and changing it to
To the correct wording and expectations that he might have
Or she
Might have
And so that is the way that you could add helper structures
To your JCB components
Thank you for watching