Hi
I've got Joomla
Installed here with
JCB
Joomla component Builder
2.5.6
I've got quite a lot of components
That I have
Imported
From another day JCB
And
Basically all of it is working
If we were to look
Inside of them
It really looks the way that it should
And it's expected
Now
Joomla has
Conveniently
Decided to
Get rid of this repeatable
Field
Which pops up into a little
Model
And
So we have systemically been removing this field
From JCB
Just to show you
We've already done that
in other areas of JCB
Like in the language area
If we would to
Open
Any of these
Language strings
You see that we already have the repeatable field
Set up here
Now
This would have been a simple as changing the field type
Within JCB to achieve
Only
Reality is that the compiler
As well as one other feature which is the Joomla components
Can be exported in JCB packages and imported
And so
These features are mapping into these component concepts
You know the
Field structures really how data stored
In a json
By the repeatable fields
Are different from how it's being stored in the subform fields
Are gonna go into explaining what the difference is
There is actually
Few tickets been open on GitHub about this
And so
We have
Taken on the task of just Sporting all of this
With this next release which is JCB 2.5.8
The whole admin View area
Will now be moved over to this new form
Subform layout
So if I was to open an admin View now
It basically has
The old
Repeatable field concept
As you would have learned with all the tutorials we've done
So your permissions is one of those taps the fields
The conditions the linked fields
And then you have a list of the fields that are linked to the admin View
And you've got some custom buttons you could
Setup and it's also
A
Repeatable field
As well as linking a sequel
Clicking on table this is also repeatable field
In a model
So all of these different fields are now gonna be moved to subfields
Because of space and statistics
We will
Move some of these Fields into taps
I will try and do it in a way that seems obvious and that he wouldn't feel lost
So just up front
The fields
This Fields button
Are going to be moved
To the fields tab
And so does
The conditions move there
There will be in new tab called settings so basically this tab will stay there
And will call that details and a new tab with settings
And the rest of the repeatable fields that are remaining
On this side will be placed there
Ok so that's just a heads up on what's gonna happen
But this is gonna happen really without you doing much
Basically all you need to do is upgrade
And
We have added a number of scripts
That you can actually go and look at
On GitHub if you like
As I'm doing this recording
The staging branch
Is where you will see these changes
So
Basically if we would to go to the script
This is the script that will
Convert
The Fields and all the tables and everything
So let me just go down to that area
So here we have a function
Inside of a method
More like an anonymous function
And
Basically this is what converts the repeatable fields
So I'll be using this function over and over
As you can see we've done
It with a upgrade to version 2.5.5
And
Then there is another upgrade 2.7 which was not really released because having made this
This change
We still need to to convert the repeatable fields
And that will continue to run until 2.5.9
Now
The way it does this
Is it really
Targets
The various
Up here
There's to convert repeatable function it Target all these fields
as you can see
Inside the admin View
And it passes it over to this
Convert repeatable
Which is really going to do the work and this function
Like I said you can look at it
Over here
If you are uncertain of doing this
You can come and look at this function here
And
I will now also demonstrate that it actually does work well
The only thing that I have actually noticed
It's like with this website that we are working on here
We talking about thousands of values
Well
Even more than thousands
And
I have found that
It sometimes does not convert every single value
And so because of that
We actually did another fix
Which
Goes beyond and ensures that this upgrade will not cause any
Internal conflicts
And that is within the
Backend
And within the model
There are a few places where these New fields will now exist
One of them is conditions
Field conditions and the other one is admin Fields so I'll open that one
Open this one
And obviously
in a
Oh not
Not that one
It's this admin View
These are the models in which these field changes will take place
And you'll see that within the
Get item
Method at the very end
Of this method
In the admin View
We added a function
Which would basically check
If this
These Fields were updated during the upgrade
And if it were not updated
That is while the field is busy loading and you're opening the page
It'll check whether it's been updated
If it's not updated it will actually make
Do the update
And add it to the update object
And then basically check every field
All the way down
Till here
And then if it sees that there is been any one of those fields
Found to be
You know ready to update
Then we will run the update
And after that it will never
Do it again
Because you see the way the
A the array is constructed
This
Will no longer exist once it's been moved to a subform
Storage
The subform array structure is different
So
Once you open any of the items it will automatically convert it and make sure that it's
Converted
The other thing that we've done
Because you most probably will not all open every view or every
Admin View
Is
Even when the new admins Fields we've done the same
So you can see here
In the Admin Fields we are also making sure that that update is there
And the same with the Admin field conditions
It's also there
But then there is one more place where we also add these
Checks and that's actually in the compiler
So even if you didn't go and open any of these views and you just went straight to the compiler
And try to compile any of your components
The compiler obviously now been adapted
to instead
Actually
Use the new subform structure
Within it's compilation
To within the get file where most of these subforms are now needed
We have
In the get admin
Function let me just get there
So here is the get admin View
Method of function class method
And you see we are checking
Whether it's still in a repeatable field
And if it is
We convert it
And we again store it to the update object
That
While it's getting this one Admin view at the very end
So every where it's doing it check
If it's not being converted converts it's sets it back to the data set
And also to ensure that we store it back into the database
Little String
And So It Goes On
Doing it everywhere
Where we
You know expect
To find values that still
You know me I've been missed
And then here it very end of this function
Which is a little
big I supposed
If we found that there are any updates we run the update
And after that that view is been updated and it will never need to be updated again so these are the
Kind of
Switches
How can I put it
Fixes really
That we put in place when you already have a JCB with horrendous amount of
Data and it is just too big to do just with the normal install
Then all these admin views will
Be
Updated and adapted
As you start using JCB
And you should not really anywhere at any time experience
Any conflicts
In fact if you do the reason for me making this tutorial
Is it you can actually get into the code
And that you can
You know
Open an issue on GitHub
And give me heads up so I can
You know Patch whatever you find
And push it out the rest the community
Ok so that was just a code side of things now getting back to
to our install here
I think what I'll do is I'll
just open
Maybe this Admin view
And then
I'm gonna go
And
Basically
Install
The
The upgrade
I'm just gonna selected it's not been released yet
So this is a pre-demostration
Just to ensure everything works
So if it doesn't you even see that
So let's just select this file from my computer
Ok there it goes busy installing it
It should take a while it's quite a big dataset
And you can just wait it out
I'd wouldn't shout at you if it missed certain values
I don't know why doesn't but
there it goes
Your upgrade is been successful
And you are now on version 2.5.8
And if we were to open that Admin view
Which
Basically looked
Like this
And now just refresh it
It should now look like that
So you see it's moved
These Fields to the side
There's now a settings field
And as you can see all the data is just been updated and moved to subform
values
Same with the taps
And if we go to field and conditions
There we go
That's how the new field and conditions view looks like
Now
Because of many reasons we couldn't keep the subform fields within the admin View
Especially when you
Start having
More than
50 admin Fields which in my case I have quite a few of those it's not advisable
Because it actually causes the tremendous
Slow down on page load I mean imagine each of these lines are actually 1 2 3 4
5 6 7
8 9 10 11 12 13 fields
And if you start having a huge a lot of those fields
Which you could have up to 800
By the limit we've set it really takes a long time to load that into the page
Ok
Enough about that how does it work now
Well you could either click on this edit button here
Or this edit button here to actually go and edit these and change their values
If you would like to just edit one specific field
You could click on any of these
you know pencil editing
Links
So for example if I click on name
It will ask me whether I've saved all my values in this current View
And yes I just click ok
And it will now open the name field
And I can now come in here do any edits that I'd like
And then save and close or just close out again if you wanna only wanna get some information
Now
Back into
This area
The same goes with the custom Fields I could click on any of those to edit them
Or I could click on this edit here
And it will
again ask me if I saved all my work
And then if I did
click ok
And opens
Those values right here
A nice new tweak with added is that it only loads the fields
That are actually linked to this Admin view
So that you can only Target
The specific fields
Which really makes sense
That
Those are the fields that needs to be targeted
With this conditional option
Then you could also create a field but creating a field will not
Necessarily add it to the admin View
It will just make it available to you
If you were to have
You know add it
By going to admin fields
Oh yes let me just say this this button here
And this one here is the same button
Just this is a shortcut
Because sometimes you might have a lot of fields
And it's a way down there to get to conditions
So we added some shortcuts up here
There's also the tutorial
On how to use this but the tutorial still was made when we had the old Fields layout
It should still make sense I mean you just need to keep in mind that things change a little
So you could click here
On any of these links
To actually open
That area where the fields are now found
And make the changes
So that's really the new admin Fields and
moving away from repeatable fields
To start using subforms for all our
Repeatable concepts
It's really what
This upgrade is all about
There is 1 heads up which I know is little different to how things were done previously
Let me just close out of this
Admin View
Oh yes
I could just mention this
Here is a shortcut to get to the admin Fields without opening the admin view and then opening the admin fields
You can click on this right here
and it will automatically take you
to the admin fields
And you can make changes here
And obviously it's link to the look
Area
or the look admin view
And the same is true when looking at
The conditions there the second button here is for conditions
The thing that has changed is if you create a new admin View
Now
You would obviously add the single record name the list record name the short description
And the system name
And that's really all you need to add
To save the admin view for the first time because
The admin view at this stage
It cannot be linked
to any Fields until it has an ID
Now I might still work on this and try and
You know
Tune it in a way that
When you click the button and if the
Admin view is not saved it saves it for you
But
I haven't done that yet so at this stage
Since the admin field doesn't have an ID it's still new because we haven't clicked save
Even once
You can't link any Fields to them
To it so what you would
Natural do is just add some
Add some name here
And
And then just save it once
And having done that if you now go to Fields and conditions
It basically says create
To this button here and that one here is the same button
You can click on any of them to create fields
So if you would create a field
So yes I did save everything
And then
I
You can just click on this plus over here
And there's a first field and you can start you know adding fields
And tweak them as you would before
And
Yep so there you go
That's the new subform
Fields for admin views
And that's what this upgrade is really all about
I trust that it all benefit all of us in the future
And make it more easier for us to transition into Joomla 4
And thank you for watching.