Hi I would like to quickly give you a tutorial on how to now do the tabs
I realise there's been a little change and how tabs are made
So you go to admin view and you then open the admin View
An in the admin View
You actually have
A place called settings
And if you scroll down a little there you can create tabs so you could create any
Any amount of tabs here
Let's say anymore or many ok and if you click save then you
Basically have 4 tabs
And the change we've made
Is if you go I'll go to the
The fields
Obvious gonna ask that your first save those tabs because if you don't save them they're not in the database
But now in the tabs menu you would have all those tabs as a drop down
The other side is also true and that is if you have no tabs setup so
Let me quickly remove those
Just
Take them all away
and click save it now there's no tabs if I now go and
Open the fields
It actually doesn't have any tabs it only shows details
Because every
Thing will now show only in the Details tab
So to have more than details as a option for tabs you need to add in the settings area
There is a place which says tab setup
Options
And you just click on this plus sign here
And an add your settings right here
Ok
I hope that will help