Hi
I would like to demonstrate to you
How to upgrade to version 2.6 of JCB
The upgrade is quite a major upgrade
Because we are removing all repeatable fields in the Joomla component area
Joomla component area
Has quite a lot of
repeatable fields
If you were to open
A component
You'll see that
Repeatable fields
are basically
Little models that pop-up
With values
And as been used quite excessively in this view
The reason why we did that is because it's really a very smart field
Because it combines these values into one value
Basically the JavaScript on the page
Grabs these values and converts it into one value
Which on submission
The form
Only submits one string
And not actually
Several fields
So to me it's
Feels like we going a few steps back
But I suppose there are some conventional
Reasons which
Makes
The repeatable field
On a subform level
More
desirable because of its
Ability to actually validate the data more
Correctly
None the less
We have to remove these Fields because in Joomla 4 they no longer are supported
In doing so
I had to decouple a number of these fields
Into their own tables
Because of the size that we would
Of values that will have on the page
The page becomes immensely heavy
And so they're about 9 new tables
Being added to JCB
To accommodate this
So the real
Change Is Gonna effect only the components area
But because JCB is very Dynamic component
That actually integrates with various levels of this data structures
I had to also upgrade the compiler
As well as the import and export of JCB packages
We have tested this and it's for the most part those involved into testing
Have found
That
This transition is actually
Major improvement to JCB
And should be very
easy and you shouldn't have any issues
Those of you that might run into
Little
Glitches that doesn't work as you expect
We would suggest that you clean your browsers cache as well as memory
We found it
Traces of the old repeatable field structure and
JavaScript surrounding that
Might clash with the new changes in JavaScript
Within the new update
So to clear your browser memory not just the cache is quite important only after you've
On the upgrade
And you started working in different views
You should see that
Everything
Works as expected
Now
An area which even at this stage has been
Been reported in giving some conflicts
Is the dynamic get area
The dynamic get area
Basically returns values
From
The admin area
Where if we target let's say backend View
And we grab
You know
Some information
These values are returned from the admin area
Where it basically goes to this Admin View
And
Builds this structure
Now as you can see with my demonstration here
Everything is really working
As expected
If if you at this stage
Would test this area before the upgrade
You should find that it works
Without any problems
If it doesn't
I would suggest clearing your browser memory and trying again
Until you can find that this is working
As you see mine working here
And
The reality is the only thing I've done is I've cleared my browser memory
So that there's no all traces of JavaScript
And what I say clear I mean literally going here to to history and just wiping everything
For this domain if you don't wanna clear
You know all of your history and it specifically targeting this domain
That you are loading your
JCB component in
Ok so that is just few heads up for
The current
2.5.8
The upgrade should be quite simple
The release I've just released it like 8 minutes ago
So you should just be able to go to you know updates in your managing area
See that the upgrade is there and ready
Click
on it and click update
There we go
The upgrade is been done
If we now go back to
Joomla component Builder
We should see
That
It's up-to-date
And everything is
Been done without any errors
If we now go to the
Joomla components area
You should see
A view similar to this
With a lot of new shortcuts
To these different decoupled
Areas that I mentioned
And if you open the component
Not much has changed in regards to where what is located
But how to interact with it is actually been moved so for example the component updates
If you see it as what as a button here if
you click its gonna
Ask you first save everything before you continue
If you've done so
Then click ok and it opens the area where you then would do your updates
Usually it was in a you know in a module
Sorry a model that popped up
And you could change it right there on the same page
Now you simply go to another view and is basically doing the same
So
You just do that the same goes with your admin view custom view site view
And basically everything else
The contributor is we've moved down here so you could
Do them on the page
But for most of the other repeatable Fields we've moved them to their own tables
The Fields and the folders we've moved
To a joint table
So if you were to click on that
You should be able to
Easily add
Some files to your
Component or folders
All found within this
Structure
As it's explained here in the
Note
The same is true of all the other
Areas it's basically
We've moved
The
Admin views to
It's Town tab
So you could access them via this button or via this one
And so here you would see your changes you could also actually from here directly edit
The admin View
That you've linked
So
It will be able to
Edit the admin view directly out of your component area
And
So
That That's a nice new feature
Which
I suppose will come in very handy
Ok so that is really the new upgrade
As really targets
The majority of the changes is in the Joomla component area
We do
Have a lot of data checks all around JCB at this stage
That if during the upgrade we might have missed a
Field in not converting it to the new subform layout
Then even when just opening a view it actually runs through all those fields
And make sure that it's been
You know changed and converted
If by any means you didn't get around to opening the views and you just go here
To the compiler
And would click compile
It actually
Does that again it runs through all the fields
And it makes sure that it's in the right format
And therefore you're compiling should work just as before
Now
What are the new features we've added is this
Translation checker
Which basically checks how many strings there is within your component
And how many you've translated for this specific version
New language available
For both the front
You know sorry the admin view the admin system view the site view
And again for the another language Admin view admin system view in the site view
So basically giving you
A little feedback on your progress
Because we realised that this area of JCB is not
May be utilised as much as it
Can be
So we bakes
Making some awareness here
But this area is available
It only comes and becomes Active if you've actually got some language translation as sorry some languages
set up
So you need to have some languages in your
Languages area
And you need to have have compiled that component at least once before
Because like you know by now that the
The the language string stored in JCB found on the language translations
Is only generated once you've compiled at least your component once
Then it links the component language strings to JCB
And you can translate them into those languages that you created
The other problem which you now saw their with which regarding to The Back-up folder
Because I haven't setup a backup folder for this JCB install
It'll tell me if I leave the set to yes and I compile he'll tell me that it couldn't move that
Backup file
Because the temporary folder and the backup
Folder is now the same place
So basically it's saying it couldn't move
The file to the same location
And that means this is not really an error
It's just a mis configuration
Because we haven't setup The Back-up folder to be a separate folder from the temporary folder
And then if you need some more help regarding the translation manager
And please go watch this tutorial
Here we do give you a notice the
that you can even in the options area of JCB
You can change the percentage of translation required
Before a translation is added
Currently it's set to 50%
Which is actually not
You know set in stone you can change that to any percentage that you like
Ok so that is creating a component now with the new upgraded JCB
And having just compiled that
We can go back here
We can see that the component was built
And everything is working as expected
Yeah so thank you for watching this tutorial
If you run into any issues that you think is related to this upgrade
And you have already cleared your browser memory
Also note that I'm I'm using
Firefox here
Let see
Firefox
64-bit
Here we go
Then please
Open an issue on GitHub and we'll try to get back to you and see if we can get this resolved
So far my experience is that this upgrade
Is taken JCB into
A very
Powerful position
Where it is now having No repeatable Fields anywhere
In the in the component
All is repeatable Fields have been converted
And is now only subforms
And
We've added some nice shortcuts like you seen
To these decoupled areas which means you can actually access them directly without going through
The component view itself
If you wanted to
Work on for example
The component dashboard
You know you wanna make some changes to the dashboard
Or you wanna just work on the admin views
You can click on that link right here
And work on the admin views without going to the component directly
Which I think is
Very nice Convenience shortcut
Which I suppose we'll make our life a little easier
Ok
Well
Again thank you for watching