I would like to give you a tutorial on how to build a hello world
Component
With Joomla component Builder
Joomla component Builder
Is a
Joomla component
Which
Helps you to develop
Joomla components
Quite easily
I originally developed this application or extension
For myself just so that I can
Maintain the code
In a very consistent
And
Shareable way
For example since there are lot of
Concepts in any components that build that you build for Joomla
Which we could call conventions or
Boilerplate
Implementation
These things are usually always the same
And so I wanted something like a wire frame
That could just take care of all that for me all the time and even if Joomla was to change
I could just make a change in one place
And then compile it into all my components that I have developed
And then just have them Run
Again stable on Joomla
instead of having to go to every one of those components and that means
We've gone Beyond
Just developing
The most basic parts of a component with actually gone and ventured into some of its complexities
And that is why
Even showing you an hello world
Component
Being built by JCB Joomla component Builder
It is still gonna end up being quite an advanced
Component
Now
Since I've really mentioned to you that I really build
JCB for myself
And it wasn't originally intended as a community project just something that I was wanted to use
It has since become a community project and the code is open on GitHub
And most of you might already know that
But it also means that
I didn't think about the complexity
When I was developing the component
I just had
Desired functionality in mind
And I didn't really care that it is complicated to achieve those things
Because I set the conventions in place
and I obviously know how to use them
And so
That's why JCB
On the surface might look just like any other of those component Builders out there
But when you start
Using it and
Knowing some of its secrets
It actually is amazing how conventions
Even
Conventions that you would
Use when you develop components yourself
would
Actually make JCB do things that are quite amazing
So you will end up realising that JCB has actually a ton of functions
Most of them will most of the basic ones of those we have tried or I have tried
to
Explain in the tutorials that you can find on YouTube
You can actually access the tutorials from this link here
Looking at the tutorials
Would be
The most
Easiest way
For you to discover some of JCB's
Hidden secrets
but at the same time
It really is only the basics although it's quite a lot of
Tutorials and
I know that I usually
Yeah I elaborate more than might maybe is necessary
And yet
That's because I wanna make sure that you are able to not only
Do basic things but even advanced things
If you come to JCB and you do not have PHP
As a as a language
But you don't know it well
And you do not know Joomla's API
Then
You shouldn't expect to build complex components with JCB
Complexity is only possible with JCB the more you know yourself
Because the more you know the more you would have a perspective on how to
How this implementation should function
And most of the time if you do have that perspective
You would start knocking and opening the correct doors
And set up the correct relationships
To have those conventions dynamically
You know be built for you
By JCB
If you are very good at PHP programming and you do know the
Joomla API
You should be very happy to simply go into the compiler
And really start reading the code
The compilers codes files are actually
Alphabetically ordered ABCD
And so you can start with a and work your way down
So the first one is a underscore get the PHP and so forth
Reading this code and understanding how JCB's compiler
Constructs the code would send you on a treasure hunt where you would discover amazing features
That work just out of the box
And yet having this under the hood
I realise we all need to start with the basics
And that is
Just to build a hello world tutorial
Just to know how to
Actually
Combine
The different
Concepts
That is required for a component
To be fully functional
And portable
And useful
And that's really what I want to actually
Give you a tutorial of
In this video
There are two concepts which I want to mention before we start
One of it is patience the other one is perseverance
I know within any programming career
These are invaluable
Aspects
Which if you have them
will make the whole difference whether you are only a normal programmer
Or an extremely good programmer
You see because those of us who have stuck around
and have just been going at it
We have realised that many
might consider us being genius
And yet
It's only because it's disguised by perseverance
Because we continually try and try and try
Until we resolve or succeed
This is what has made JCB be possible
And this is also what would make you successful
In using JCB
It is not a component which I can claim has no
you know, internal conflicts or has no
Inconsistencies
But it is most certainly a component with which I am myself
Have developed countless
Mini
Programs components itself from it
Which I am maintaining
And I am planning to
Start
Pushing some of these components into the community
It's just that I have not seen the need for doing so yet
For the initial development were mostly
For clients who has directly
Approached me
Now
Having said all this
Let me take you through the basic steps
Building one piece one another
So that you would
Fully understand
How to build
A component
In JCB
I think it's self explanatory
That you would need a Joomla website
This Joomla website would preferably be
On a developing environment which is
either offline
Or on a server
Which isn't necessarily
you know used in production
This is not because JCB itself is unsave
Any of that it is simply just it's more convenient
If you have it offline
You can open the code in your IDE
And since JCB has the feature to extract this customised code out of your component
And put it back into your component on compilation
A feature which will not be discussed during this tutorial
What does exist
A local developing environment is most ideal for this
I know that you could with
Certain
Yeah protocol
Set up a
Tunnel between your desktop and
Your live server
And still have this kind of interaction of editing code live
And then compiling and
seeing changes
And that's all good because if you're able to manage that kind of complexity
I don't need to tell you anything about how to setup an environment
But what I would suggest though
Is that when you are busy trying to install JCB
And there is
Some limitations in a shared hosting environment
then I would
Encourage you to try and first resolve that
or move development offline
So
When you go to Joomla website ready obviously you would login
Having logged in
you would first need to install JCB
So I'm simply gonna go to manage and install
There are many ways for you to install JCB you could download the package you can grab the URL
From GitHub
You could also
Install it
From the web
It is listed with Joomla
Now if you type in JCB and search
It actually
Brings up JCB here
But
It would not necessarily always do that
I've recently discovered
If I type in
Component builder which is actually it's name in the listing
It doesn't even come up
Which to me was wow
couldn't understand how that happens
If you do not find a component in the search
This is the component
Then you could go down to
An area
called tools
And then
Developing tools
JCB is one of the listed developing tools
Here it is only listed as a component Builder
So you can click on that
And simply click
Install
This will then grab a URL from GitHub
This is the same URL
You could have just used here
As you can see
That would have done the same thing
But we can use the Joomla
Installer
And simply click install
This would depend on your own network
on how fast this takes it could take a while
This is quite a big file
And it's part of the places where there might be
a limitation
If used
Outside of a local developing environment
Ok we've got JCB installed
Now let's open it
There's just a few small things that we need to lay down
as foundation stones
In understanding how a component
Basically most Joomla components
Are constructed
We're Gonna Build A component called hello world
The way to setup a component
Is you need to first understand field types
Then you need to set up the fields you'll need
And then you need to set up the views
That you want in your component
These views also map
Back to the database
These are what we call admin views
So your admin views
have fields and these are usually your Database
columns
So these are your database tables
these are your database columns
And these
are your field types so you got a text field radio
List
Multiple selection
Checkbox a date field
You got many types of fields
But each field independently
Is linked to a type
But also there are some database settings within each field
As it gets linked into the admin View
Since the fields
Form the columns of the tables of the admin views
This is how you set up a component
Once you set up a component
Then
You basically are done with
what we would call the back end
The back end of the component is what always needed to be done First
Well you could
Argue differently
But the point is within JCB you'd first build the back end
And then only add in the front end
And the front-end usually
Doesn't have its own database it actually pulls it's data
From the backend Database
Now
Having explained some of that
Let's show you this in action
So in JCB
It already ships with quite a lot of field types
So we open the field types area
You'll see that there are many field types already setup
JCB is built in a way that it can be extended
Like subform
Is a new field type which was recently introduced into Joomla community
It also replaces an old field type
Called repeatable fields
Repeatable fields is a field type I would encourage you not to use anymore
Since most of you might know JCB be used repeatable feels quite excessively
And yet due to the fact that Joomla is now discontinuing this field type
We had to
Migrate all of our repeatable Fields to subform Fields and it was an amazing
Huge
Process
But yes part of the reason why I'm redoing the hello world tutorial
It's because of the fact that subforms are now being used all across JCB
And there's been a little few changes
And how things are implemented
So here you can see all the sub this field types that I've been
Set up in JCB already
You could always add new field types
So as JCB
you know continues and Joomla continues to
Evolve and become better at what it does
So we will be adding more field types
And whenever we would be
Confronted by field type
That needs a little bit of extra tweaking within the compiler
I would hope to be ahead of all of you most of the time in adding that field
type in there if it needs that
Most of the time field types do not need
Extra help
It's only field types like subform that actually does
But field types like URL and
Text and tel and
Sequel tag it needed some extra help
But most of these don't
Because basically the way a field type works
Is that it really helps you set up what we know as the properties
So
The property has a name
It has a default value
It is either adjustable not adjustable
It's mandatory or mandatory translatable and then you can give it a little description
So that when you use the field type
You can always come back to this
This information can be gathered from going through the
Joomla core
Libraries
Because these field types really are only mapping Joomla's own
Implementation of these field types
So if we were to open a field type that's already been created like the text field
You see that these properties already there and in place so the field
Type
Is text
The name is any text
When we say that the type is text
Then this is not adjustable
So
We need this unticked if it is adjustable we can tick it
It is most certainly
Mandatory
And so
That is how you set up field types I'm not gonna go into this too deep
Since there is extra tutorials on how to do field types I just wanted to give you a brief overview
Or the fact that the most of the field types already are created and ready for you to use
So you'd most of the time simply start with fields
There are quite a few Fields already here
But I'm gonna go on as they are not there
And I'm gonna create
Basically two or three Fields that we can use in our hello world component
So
First field I'm gonna create
Click on new
Then I'm gonna select
Text as my field type and you see
That information in the field type
You know
Mandatory in everything all this information here
It is actually brought in by Ajax
From the field type
So if I was to click on this button here
Just to it give you a quick demonstration
And I was to
Just say change this to TT
Like three of them and save and close
And then go back to fields
And click new
Then select
Text field again
You'll see that now it added
three t's in there
Because this whole structure is being built
From the field types default settings
Which we just looked at
So I'm gonna go change that back quickly
I maybe just put a little
Something in here the description
For you to see
What I mean
So creating a field we haven't really started with it I've just been demonstrating the field type but okay
Ok I'm gonna take text again
And I you see those o's are showing up here
So this means that this whole area
Is actually dynamically populated from the values that are put up in the field type
And so is this XML structure here
Usually
Populates with the demo
Or default values that you add it
When you created the field type
The JCB ships with most field types or ready in place it appears like this is something we have done
But really it's something that you can extend and even change
So for example if you know that the text field type has more properties than we have setup
You can go in and add more to it
You can simply click on this you know edit here or before creating a field
You can go to the field types
And open the text area
Sorry the
Text field type
And
Here just click
The green button and add more Properties
And then those properties will dynamically also appear
Within
The area where you create the fields
So this again is just
Wanting to show you
The JCB is tried it's very best
To be scalable
And basically customizable
To your
Own desires
So that it isn't just
Blocked in
To what we have set hard into code
But it is movable and therefore scalable
So having
Looked at Field types
I think enough
Let's create our first field
So it's gonna be a text field we gonna call it greetings
So I'm gonna update the label with greetings
This is what
Will be visible
In the database
Greetings
Singular is gonna be the database name
I'm gonna leave most of the others just default
Let's see
Autocomplete is on
Validation
You know
We can leave all of those
It doesn't really matter let's just maybe change the hint
Ok
And then I also gonna just remove the description
Definitely take out the default text otherwise it will always
appear
And now in regards to the database
That is what these features are all about
Since text Fields can differ
We didn't come
Out and say well all of them gonna be this size
We left it up to you to decide
What kind of text field of this is gonna be
And really it's all up to you
Obviously that would mean that you would need to know a little bit more about
MySQL and databases
To really effectively use this
Most of the time it is available on Google so if you do not know
What would be the best for
A text field or a date field
You can Google that
Or you could simply go and look at Joomla's own implementation
It's got an article manager
And you can go into its XML
Database
And look at
What
Database
Values was used and just use the same
Whatever be the case
You should be able to actually navigate through this
Without much problems
Since that is what is would be required
You need to
have perseverance you need to
You know
Be curious
dig through things
And doing that you will eventually succeed
Because these values are all movable
That means that setting them wrong
could break things
And
That's why I always encourage those who gonna use JCB
To really do a little bit of homework
And to prepare themselves
To get involved in programming
More effectively
That would only
Be beneficial to all of us I suppose
Because good programmers makes good programs
And makes the web a safer place
So
Having created our first field
I think I'm gonna just reuse name
And maybe
Also description
Those are part of the demo
Component but since Fields can be linked into any admin view and therefore belong
To any component
It doesn't bother the fact that it is linked to the demo component already
What is though true
is that if you change it It'll actually affect both
Components
Okay so
Having created
our field types
And also now a field
Let's create an admin View
admin views as I already explained
Is really the back end of your component
And So you'd need to do some thinking and maybe draw some up
there's a whole
A lot of tutorials around the web about object orientated development
Which talks about use cases and
All kinds of discussions and trying to sort of
Come up with a
Perspective of what do you wanna build how should it work what should be where what should have its own classes
What should have it own tables where we gonna put what
And really that kind of work you need to do before coming to JCB
JCB
Isn't really gonna help you with that
And so
Once you've got all that planned
Then you would come here create your Fields create your admin views which basically is your tables
And then link them to a component
And once you've done that
You've basically laid the foundation of your application
And you can start working on what will make it unique
And special which is the front end
So first
Admin View
This is the name is really just for you to identify
The View
If there be more than one view with the name greetings
So let's say you've
Built quite a few components that deals with hello world
And now you got three or four different
Variations of greetings
Now you might want to just say ok this is the first
One
And
By doing that
It's identifiable within the drop down list across your application of JCB
You'll see that when we would later select the greeting that the system name is used in the drop down list
So we're gonna have a single record and a list record
Single record is also what we understand as the edit View
So that's when you are looking at one record
And you are editing that record
In the admin area that's the single record
That's also
What will be used when you
Actually tweak JCB
To add an edit option
To the site area of your
Website
Since JCB can do that for you
On the fly
This single record
Would also affect
The front end of your component in that case
Which we will show and demonstrate
As we go along
So for now I'm just gonna call this
Greeting
and the list record
greetings
Obviously we want to have the ability to read and write to this table
Now when we say this is a read only
It means that the data is in this actual admin area is not gonna be able to be changed
Via Joomla
Unless obviously you've added some JavaScript and some
Other nice
Conventions around your component that sort of creates data for that area
Dynamically as people use the component
Which that case you might use this feature but I must tell you I have hardly ever used it
I'm not even sure why I added it but it's there and I know maybe some of you might find it useful
This basically turns all the fields in the area as read only
And when you try and change them they never get
But you know submitted to the database
So we would by Default always leave it to read and write
Then you give it a short description
We'll go to settings and we'll see
That
Sorry Fields and conditions
We'll see that this button to create admin field conditions will show once the admin view
is saved for the first time
So you cannot add Fields to this admin view if you haven't saved it
That is one of the changes that now came in from us moving away from repeatable Fields to subform fields
the admin view
Is it table on its own
And it's relationship with the fields is also a table on its own
So at this stage
Unfortunately you need to first not click save and close but just save once
So that it basically creates this admin view in the database
And now
If you go to fields
And conditions you'll be able to link Fields and create conditions
We are not gonna be creating conditions since we are basically illustrating or demonstrating a very basic component
We're just gonna create
A linked fields
Linked fields are basically the fields that we created previously
So we will click on create
It's gonna ask us to be sure that all our work has been saved in the admin View
Because if it isn't and we click okay
It will be lost
So make sure your work is saved before you clicking okay
This will now open an area where you can link Fields to your admin View
This looks very similar to the pop-up we had with repeatable Fields except
That it's basically it's own View now
So if we click on this green
Button here
It opens
An area where when I select
The fields we wanna use
So we gonna have a name field
And
That's a text field
We want it to show in the admin list view
We want it to show first we gonna have it behave as a title
we want it sortable searchable
Not filterable because then every name would be a filter that's too much
But definitely linkable this means if someone Clicks on the name it will open the greeting so
You can edit it
Now
We only have two tabs at this stage
I'm not gonna go into great detail about the tabs
This Time Round
If you want to know more please go through the tutorials and look up
Tabs to to see more on this subject
I'm gonna let it be
In the left
In the tab
And in the tab I want it to be the first item
I'm not gonna add any permissions to this
But there is an editing permission available at this stage
If you want it to
That would create permissions around this
Field
Which you can tweak who can edit it and who can't
You can also control this from a global view perspective
Or on a field level
These are some of the hidden advantages the JCB has
In
Handling permissions across your component quite easily
Now The Next Field you wanna add is greetings
We want the greetings to also be in the listview
And we want it to be second
Want it to be searchable
Sortable and searchable
And it doesn't need to be a link
We want it to be on the right
Hand in the tab and we wanted to be first
And sure that's basically All We Need
And they will click save and close
This will now basically link those Fields to this admin view
We now again open the fields and conditions
We will see that those fields are here
And with all the variations that we have selected
Ready-to-use
Ok so having our admin view setup
We can actually now go and create our component
So we can
either click save and close
Or we can simply click close
We haven't made any changes in this view since we've come back
This area is already been saved
So we could click close
But clicking save and close it's always the safe choice I suppose
So
Now that are admin view is in place
Let's go create the component
Click new
We're gonna give our component a system name
Since this is the second hello world tutorial we'll call it version 2
Now we also gonna give it a name which
Is the same as the first one
Hello world
We're gonna give it a code Name of hello world
And is it's version 2
Am I gonna explain too much about all these other switches
Basically just that we will need to add company names
Author name email website
And a short description
Now that we have those in place
The next thing to do would be to add an admin View
Now since the admin view can only be added once the component's been saved
For the first time
Let's save it
Great our component has been saved
Opening the admin view we now can link
Admin views to this component
There are two places to do this
Under settings
You can click on component admin View
you can click on this one here
Or you could in the admin views click on create
Both these buttons take you to the same place
This used to be The Old Way
In how people would add admin views to their component
And that's why we left it here
But within the new JCB after our transition away from repeatable fields
We actually can handle all of it within the admin tab admin view tab
Just click create
We are sure we have saved all our work so we can click ok
Again we are faced with something that looks very similar to when we were linking the fields
except that now
We are dealing with the admin view
Linking admin views to this component
So I'm gonna click on this plus button here
To open our first line
We basically just wanna
Link The greeting
We gonna leave the default icon
Of
Joomla
But there are a whole list of icons available
These icons
Are icon moons which are the Joomla default icon
That are part of the Joomla backend
And front-end I suppose
And you can search this
Just
Search that phrase I suppose
And you will find on
Joomla's website
A whole
Picture map of all these icons
Then I most certainly want this view to be
Part of the main menu
I want an add record
On the dashboard I want a list
That means clicking on something and it shows us the list of greetings
I want it in the submenu
The auto checking feature
Basically
Components get checked out when somebody
Not components items
So when you
Create a record
That are stored in the database and someone else comes and wants to edit that record
You wanna prevent people from working on the same record at the same time
Since one of them is gonna lose their work
So Joomla has this feature by which
You can check out an item
And then when someone else tries to open it it tells them hey sorry it's not been it's not available it's
Checked out
The problem with seeing though is that this check out
Can be problematic
Because people don't save
They just open it maybe to have a look at it
And then instead of clicking cancel or close
They just click back
And the item doesn't get checked back into the database
So the auto check in feature is a nice add-on that JCB has
set place
Which basically you can set that an item
Which are checked out longer than a day
Is obviously one that was missed
And should be checked in automatically
This
Is one of the reasons why
I developed JCB because I have all these
little tweaks that I
Want in all my views but I
Know that
If Joomla changes something and I need to change this little tweak
Going to every single view is like so cumbersome
So here it simply click whether you would like this
And if Joomla makes a change that we need to know adapt this feature we just change it in the compiler and it
Immediately you know compiles correctly for all the components mapped in it
The other feature which I think is also great is this keeping of History
If I want to keep track of all the changes made to any item of greeting
Then I just need to tick this
Keep history
And JCB will dynamically add all the needed structures so the Joomla's
Integrated history component will work alongside your third-party component
And keep track of every item and it's changes
So that is just a tick box and JCB does the work
The has metadata basically adds
The metadata Fields to the view
So you don't need to add them it gets added just by ticking this box
Then also does this field view have access public
Special or
you know registered
All these access levels
Do you want to implement these levels of access on this view usually you would use this
If you want the view to be actually be editable on the front end of the site
Because then you will use the access
To control some of these
I'll show you more of that as we go along
So I'll just take this as yes
I wanted to have an import function
And like we said
We want to add a site edit and create view for this admin View
Yes
And then
We want it to be first
So this admin view basically is gonna have all the features that an admin view can have
By Default in JCB
And as you would realise when we start demonstrating it although it's as easy as ticking this box
The code that JCB is gonna write to do this implementation
Is quite stable
And yet
Dynamic that as Joomla evolves and changes
We can tweak these codes
In the compiler and make sure that it remains stable this way
Good now save and close
Now that we have linked this admin view to the component
We can all go to admin views and we'll see this admin view
We'll even see the icon we can click on this
little pencil here and this will actually take us to the admin View
Obviously again making sure that all your work is being saved in this area
Click okay if it is
And you'll see that it opens the admin view where we linked
The fields
And we can actually how work in the admin view
From the component
Now there are areas in the admin view I didn't demonstrate like the permissions the tabs the link to views
And I'm not going to going to do much of that
I'm just gonna add
Some permissions
Because I want to demonstrate
The permissionable structure
Regarding the front in management of editing these items
I'm just gonna use the core there is the option of using what is known as the view edit
Instead of core edit then it means it's relationship is just for this view
I want it to be related to the Core
Which means that it's not gonna be only related to this view
But whatever I change in the Core will affect this view
For more explanation on the permissions there is this tutorial
Which is available in the description
And you can go watch this tutorial
And also
Maybe do some changes compile the component
And look at the code
Look at the code and look at the code that's all I can say for most questions being asked because the code
Really tells you what has been done
There is many ways for you to learn
How JCB does things
By making changes
And then compiling your component and looking at what changed
Usually using something like git will be very useful in Discovering the changes
There's also a way for you to know where in the compiler specific code is being created
Which I will show you as we continue
So since we've made changes I'll simply click on save and close
And this will take us back to the component
So being back in the component
We'll see that
Everything is still the way we left it
And
quite a few things around
The admin view which I'm not gonna go into depth
During this tutorial
I would encourage you to watch the tutorials that are already online
For actual explanation on all these features
But to demonstrating a hello world component we have done quite enough
Regarding the back end
So all that now remains
It's basically to compile so we'll click save and close
And we'll go to the compiler
Select our component
And compile
Great
That means we've just written
9000 lines of code
created 51 folders in 122
Files
And if we were to have manually
Written this without any boilerplate tool or
You know wire script
That could help us write all the classes and tables and stuff
And it took us 5 seconds to write one line
It would have taken us
25 Hours
Or about three 8 hour days
That's a long it would have taken you to do this manually
So just right there JCB's  already saved you quite a lot of time
Now the component can be installed by Simply clicking this button
Or
Grabbing
The URL and going to the
Normal installer
Because it has actually
Compiled a
Shippable
Joomla component package
Which can be installed on any Joomla component
Sorry any Joomla website
Now one thing I didn't do
Is I didn't actually select
A
Component image so when we selected you see there is no image showing as there is with this one
So
I think I wanna quickly go back
I'm gonna clear the temporary folder and just go select
At least the demo components image as our hello world component
So in the component there is this area to select an image I'm gonna click select
And I've selected
The demo components package
It says that we have something so I'm gonna save and close again
And now go back to the compiler
And compile it again
Now I'm gonna click on install
If I now go here we'll see that there is now a new component in this Joomla website
And I'm gonna open in a new tab
And there we go we got our component installed
It has a greetings tab and a add greetings tab
We also have not selected images for those
So let's quickly do that
Gonna go back to the admin views
And then the greetings
I'm gonna click
On greetings First
As an admin View
And here you see there is a place for icons and the add icon
I'm gonna select
So I've selected
This little bucket as the icon for greetings
I'm gonna just add one for
For adding a greeting with a little
Green Plus
Now we got it to icons
I'm gonna click save and close
so now
I've got greetings
Set up
And
I'm gonna go and compile this again
That's usually how things go we go make a change
We come back to the compiler to compile it install it
And go look at the component
And
Also
When it getsa  little bit more advanced
We not only go and look at the component in Joomla
But we also go and look at the code
So there we got it the two icons are in place if I click add on greeting
We see that there's the name there's the greeting
And there's also all these other Fields added by Default
So the created and the metadata and the permissions
Are all in place
That is
How you would set up a basic
Hello world component
Go to the options
Will see that it has this
Check in timer
And you can change it to 5 hours
What I explained you know the checks in the items
We also have
The history version enabled
And set to remember 10 versions of any item created
As a greeting
We also have the permissional structure in place
Which includes the greeting
Access greetings batch dashboard and so forth
Which are all
The switches related to the greetings area
So now that we have the admin area basically done Let's continue to
The front-end I'm gonna illustrate to you on the front-end how to view greetings
That were created how to edit greetings that were created and how to add more
Greetings from the front end to this component
Let's close out of the components edit area the first thing we need to do
We need to create what is known as a dynamic get there 2 ways to get to the dynamic get
Area one is to click on this add Dynamic get
The others would be basically in the sub menu to go to Dynamic get and then
Click new we're gonna need two Dynamic gets we gonna need
one to basically return a list of greetings
And then we'll need one to return one greeting because one the one Dynamic get is gonna
Return for us all the greetings that are available and published the second
one is when we click on one of those greetings it should open only that greeting
So we gonna use the name as who is being greeted and then the greeting will
Will only show when we actually click on the name and then show that individual's
Greeting so that's part of how we think about this at this stage then
In this area where we can see the full greeting we are gonna add and edit button
And in the list area we are gonna add a create button but these create and
Edit buttons are gonna be controlled by the permissional structure which JCB
Puts into your component by you just saying that it should be there so setting up a
Dynamic get is quite easy you first know that ok I'm gonna use a back end view
Which is related to my component and then I'm gonna select that back end view
You see it says greetings first so like I said before with a system name
What is used in the dropdowns so here we select greetings (First)
This one is going to bring back a list query we don't want any pagination
And
I really don't need all of this we don't need
The asset ID
We can leave the created by
And the created
We can take out the modified the version we can also leave
The hits
And the ordering that's fine now
The greeting we most certainly don't need in a list we only need the name now
Ok let's give it a name that we can sort of identify when we start setting up the site view
We call this
List
Greetings
And then in brackets
Name only
So we know ok this is what it is going to save that
You didn't need to save it we could have just gone right into tweaking the data without saving
What the data tweak gives us is it gives us a little bit of control on the writing
The JCB will do regarding this query so for example we want it to be
Before did
Now the ordering is called ordering
a.ordering
So we want to order it
Ascending by the order set in the database
The other filter we want to add
Is we wanna make sure
That it only returns published items
So in the
"Where" area replace published
And we say equal 1
so only published values be returned there are some other features
Around the tweak area which I suppose goes beyond just in the normal Hello World Component
But there are tutorials about this on Joomla sorry on YouTube in that playlist
That I've already referred to quite a few times, then there's a joint area which we not gonna use
But
It is a very nice way of linking to other
component tables that I've got any kind of relationship that needs to be in a
relationship between the main table and the join table but like I said
When I'm gonna go into this we are simply going to do the most basic which is what we've got here
And we gonna say save a new so we can do and another one
The next one is this gonna be a greeting
Just simple greeting we wanted to be one item again we gonna do a back end view
Again from the greetings list
This time we really
Want the name and a greeting we can still use the published we don't need to modify
By
We can leave those we don't need ordering we could have left out the head
In the previous one we set up now let's do a little tweak to make sure that it
Doesn't allow someone to grab
An unpublished value
By just adding an ID in the URL or something ok so that's ok
Got this
Oh yes
Now we need to add a filter
We gonna use the ID
Basically passing the ID via the URL
So the state will be ID and
It is gonna be a.id equals so that's really what makes the item load
Is this filter type and there are many ways to load items
And yes this is a little bit more complex than you might wanted to be but believe me
It gives you freedom
And ability to build quite amazing things
And so
Please go and watch the tutorial on Dynamic get on GitHub
There is actually a place
I just show you
Called Wiki
And in the Wiki there is links to all the different tutorials
And here is the dynamicGet
And you should really watch all of that
Even the second one
And yeah well my encouragement is to really watch everything I have often seen people ask question
In the issue area
Which are dealt with in the tutorials
I'm sorry
We all have a lot of things to do and so if I don't answer this questions but simply point you to the tutorial
I hope you understand
Ok so we've got in the dynamicGet all the value selected that we want and
Also how to limit it
The tweak is in place
And the limiting factors
We don't need to join it to any other tables,we simply going to
Return these values
Let me see
We could add the username values if we wanted
So we wanted to show who created this we could say created by
go to joint
Click on the joint a database tables not view because we want to use
The user
Table
And we basically want
A single
Item returned
And here it will be
Created by
And
In the joint field it will be
b.id
And we basically want, let's see
The username that's it
We don't need the ID, we already got that so just the username
And we could just say
Let's call it
Creator
Or
Greeted
Greeted by, ok so he's the one sending the greeting
save and close
So now we've got two
Dynamic gets a list greeting and a greeting this is what you need to build first basically
Again starting at the database looking at what is the data I want
On the page
What do I want to show the people looking at the page
And by that determining really what the data is you going to grab from the database
And giving it system names
That are
Identifiable because now
The next thing to do is to create a site View
now there is such a thing as layouts and templates
That all can work together with site views
I'm not gonna illustrate that now
or demonstrate it, basically if you want to know more about that look at the tutorials
On YouTube I'm just simply going to build
Two site views
And yeah let's go ahead and do that
Ok, the first site view we gonna call
Greetings
And we gonna give it a name called
And a code name
Greetings
Now the code name is significant because you don't want to Clash with admin views that you've already created
That are gonna be
Edit views on the front
So since the listview is not being
Placed on the front of your component only the edit view that means edit views name
Name is greeting
So we can't set a code Name
For the front called greeting otherwise they will actually
you know conflict
So I'm just gonna use greeting and for the Single I'm gonna use greet
Ok so
Just give you a little explination on why I'm doing things the way I'm doing it
So a little description here
I'm gonna just
Place a little
Heading
And adding it like that will actually mean
That this little string will get added to your language file
So that's how you create language strings it's just adding the snippet
Oh or even just this anywhere in JCB will actually create a language string
Ok, now over here
We are going to select the list greeting and the reason why there are two of these
Is it the one is what we will act upon in the compilation the other one is just for you to look
So if you end up
Let's say in here and click save
It will not be playing any role whatsoever in the compilation
It will play a role when you export a JCB package but that's a whole different subject and not going to deal with
that, so good practice would be that these two actually are the same
The main and the Dynamic Get but since you can add Custom Gets
We don't have any Custom Gets setup so you can't select any, but you can add more than just
Your normal main gate to a site View
You can add the main Get and then a bunch of custom gets which brings a whole ton of data to the
Page from different variations from relationships which I know it's a little bit
Beyond the Hello World Component
But it is there and it actually does work very well it's just that you will need to do some
home work in tutorials and so forth but we want the list greeting and so
This list greeting gives us a few Snippets now
Do know that the Snippets are really not always accurate because it's very difficult for me to always
know exactly how the implementation is gonna work out so I'm giving you a snippet which is how
I expect you to use the data but you can adjust that and this is where your knowledge of PHP will really
come into play you should know that this and that little arrow
Items is because we are working with an object and the you know what is it
Mean and how to use an object and how to interact with an object
How to parse over it, how to grab its values, how to update its values, all this is part of your
own background that you need to bring to JCB.  JCB is not gonna
At this stage crank out customized site views the way
it does the admin views because my idea was it when it comes to site views I always wanna do
Something different and I just want to have the ease of getting all the data on the page and then be creative
And so I haven't spent much time to make this as automatic as I want to set up of
the back end and the admin views because this is really what makes your component different from every other
Component out there and here we want to encourage you to really
Yes do you do a lot of preparation and thinking about data
Structures in relationships because your Dynamic get can grab from so many data places
And bring all that data to you in a nice object which you can then parse and display
With a lot of permissional switches as I will show you in a moment so that is giving you little backdrop
on why the dynamic get and the site view even the custom admin view , it's relationship
and why it is like that ok so
Basically looping through those items is this these two strings is all we need and then
I could grab a listview let's see
We are busy working on adding the
Bootstrap library to JCB
At the moment with basically got
UI kit version 2
Linked to JCB
And I've selected the list option for this
Uikit is a library developed by YOOtheme
If you do not know UiKit I would encourage you to actually go
Google that
And
Then
You'll see it's quite a nice library to use we have voted that Bootstrap is the better one
And so we are migrating to Bootstrap
But will still support UiKit as much as we can so for now just to get things going
We simply gonna loop over the items show the name nothing is yet
Clickable nothing is editable is just to get you know you introduced to using
site Views
Save and close
Now we gonna go back to our component
And we are gonna add the site view to it
You might ask why don't we just add the component to the site view when we create the site view
And that was a idea that
You know I did play with but because of database relationships and all kinds of
Reasons I felt that the better approach would be to link site views
At admin
At the component area instead of at the site area
This gives us the option to use site views quite easily with in other components
That was really the idea behind it
We might rethink this and we might reshuffle this in the future I mean this is the first time I build
Such a component called JCB and who knows what happens if we start refactoring it and a far more
Advancement program is get involved it might become even far better than it is now
Now but this is how it works at the moment
So you go to site views
And you click create link site views
And then you basically select that greeting site view you say yes
I want to have an admin menu sorry be able to add a menu to the front of my website with this view
I want this view to use Metadata this is going to be this component default
View I wanted to control Access will look at
That again but I want that access to that it's default be public so this is
Basically again making use of all the options and save and close
So now if we go back to compiling our component
There's no changes being done to the database I need to maybe just give you a heads up here if you're
Adding new tables JCB is
Build to actually know that and add the tables to a
Sequel update which when you update the component it automatically updates the data base
But it's still important for you to actually check that it does this
For there could be a reason that it thinks that it's not necessary
Yet
I tried to
Most
I've tried to build enough places things in place so that it will actually pick up that you've add it
either a field or a new View to the component and that the component now needs to increment a version
And Release a table update but sometimes that is not happening and
And then even if you update your component the database is not being updated
Necessarily
So that's just something you need to keep your finger on make sure that that happens
for most part
JCB will take care of that
And since now and this upgrade we have only added a front end we haven't touch the data base
Everything about that is just the way it was before so we can without any concerns just compile
And
Re-install the component
And then go and add it
To the front
So we can sort a look at what has happened
Ok
Now just a heads up
When you add a front end site view and you said that it's default should be public
But if it's not the first time you installed the component then that default cannot be set to the database because
It's a default that only gets set the first time the component gets installed, I don't wanna go into all
All the technical reasons for that but you could go into the app the components script file and you can search through it
To see what I mean because it's actually a function that gets added to the script file and only gets implemented
with on the first installation of the component now that's important then if you do not
Even follow what I was saying now and why I said it then I hope you'll get to
To understand it as I try and demonstrate these things
Before you can add the greetings to a site admin sorry to a site menu let's
just at least add a few greetings
Ok
So we've got at least four greetings in place and now we can actually add
That list View to an
Front and site view
So we go to menus
And
Go to main menu
Select menu type click Hello World greetings
that was the previous component
Ok
Everything else looks good
So we've got Greeting set as the home
Of this website
And we gonna click save and close
There we go
But got home and Hello World greetings
That should mean that if we click on
This
Preview
The front end of the site
We should see the greetings
It's gotta say the page isn't redirecting properly
And the reason is like I explained
We set the front side view
That it should have access control
Which means
You can control who sees this page not that it's just open to everyone but
But you can say only this group can see it all only that group can see it
But since we haven't set that
And by Default
Doesn't allow anyone
Now we said that it's by Default should be public but like I explained
But I
Gave you that heads Up
It only sets that default the first time the component is installed so it is the way you should ship the
Component
If you only add that feature later
You need to do custom scripting in the script area
Which is the beyond Hello World component tutorial
To update a database and ensure that this view is actually public
The manual way to do this is basically to go to the Hello World component
Click on options
Then go to permissions
Scroll down
To the area where you see greetings site access
Select the public group
And change
This site access
To allow
This will now ensure that the site area is actually
Available
To the public
So having refreshed the
Public area we know see James Williams Sarah and Koos
All of them loading
As expected
Ok now
Let's
Add a
Link to James so that when you click it you actually see the greeting that James should receive
So we go back to the site views and we open the greetings
Now we wanna add a link here
But there is a better way of doing a link in JCB
Which really takes care of all the
Controller issues
When I go to the front end of the component then we open
The model for greetings
Will see that there is the get items method
And in it we are basically checking
Whether this item has an alias
If it does have an alias and an ID
It actually creates what is known as a slug
And this alias
And id gets combined
Into The Slug
Since we know that our greetings area does not have an alias
In fact it only has an ID
It will only end up with an ID in The Slug
So
Let's go add an alias
to hour greeting
There is a shortcut to the site
Sorry the fields linked to an admin area it's this little icon here
And we basically wanna add another field called alias
And if you go to the fields
We'll see that there
Is already a field called alias
So we can simply use that field
So go back to the admin views
And we'll click on this shortcut for
Adding fields
And
We gonna
Basically
Click here and add an alias
We gonna tell the system that this isn't alias
And
Now we are moving
Both of these above the tabs
And we are creating the alias to be second in line
And the greeting
We are going to
Let's see
Make it a full width
The greeting
We also gonna go edit the greeting
In a moment
So that it's no longer a text field but a text area
Ok so we got name alias all of that is in place save and close
Going back to fields
I'm going to open the greeting
And since there are some values I want to stay the same
I am going to select
That
XML
Definition
And I'm going to copy it
Then I'm gonna select
Textarea
Then I'm gonna paste
That first
XML in here
We obviously have to remove it again
But just so I can copy paste
Cut the name
I want to keep the same name
You can't just change the type because the type up here
Needs to actually correspond with the type here
So just changing the type in there will not work
So the label you want to keep that the same
We want to add
Let's see
Add greetings as a description
We don't want to default text
And let's add the hint back again
We Don't really need any of these other Fields so we can just remove them
We don't want the filter to be set to raw
Would rather use the word string
Since we don't want any HTML at this stage in our greeting
If you want HTML now in the greeting you can use
The
Save HTML I see it's not in this list but it actually does exist
Usually we would use the editor instead of just a text area
Anyway
So here we go
We got
Our textarea replace
And I'm gonna add just here
Span 12 I don't know how long that's gonna still be there as a class
But I think it is still there
And now I think that should do it
Yeah let's change this
No you know what we don't need to change that
Save and close
Ok since we didn't change any of the database values with this text field
We shouldn't have any issues
But we did add a new text field
So if we go to the comp I
Compiler
And we compile the components
You see that a dynamically incremented the version and
If we go without installing we go to the component you see that it hasn't
Actually updated view because this was open so before doing anything I would
Suggest reopening the view basically refresh the page
So that the changes we also basically show
So now we can go back in simply install the new changes
And if we go to a Hello World we should be able to
Open the Hello World and we should see the alias there and if we click save
It should dynamically add a new alias now we'll have
To do this for every item because the aliases are saved or created only once you saved the
Item so I'm just opening all of them quickly now usually a user using your component
You only gonna ship this component when you've got everything in place I hope and so they wouldn't
have to do all this gymnastics to make sure that all the values are in place and if by some reason
They have to you will have to help them along with some custom scripting I suppose
Anyway
So now that we got all our items set
And it actually has an alias
We can start working on those links
There's one more place we need to make a change
And that is in the dynamic Get
If you remember when we set it up
We didn't actually
Include
The alias
So I'm gonna copy this
I then just change to just another
View quickly and then back to this one
So that we can get the alias there
So here is the alias that we want
We don't need all these
And we can just add that over there
There we go we got the alias now also selected
Save and close
So
We can check with this alias is actually being
Brought to the page
By
Adding a little
I call it
production tricks
So
Would we'll do a little PHP dump here
var
dump
And
We just take all the items
Copy
Paste it in there
and save
Now we go back to the compiler
I'm just quickly compile this again
And
Install
Go to the homepage
Refresh
And now you will see that it dumps all the values on the page and then displace them
So now we can look and see ok well fine
There's the alias and actually created that Slug we spoke about
So we got the slug for every item and that is the first step in setting up
Hey
Well-formed
Link
for
Opening one of these items
I don't know what Some of you might think
Wow that's got a lot of things to do to get this to work
But I can tell you if you wanna build components for Joomla
And you wanna go outside of the box
And build things that are actually unique and completely different from what other
People are doing
And this is really just the basics
Ok so we gonna
Set up a href here
Around
This name
But we are gonna use PHP to basically take care of creating a link for us
So here we are simply gonna say
Echo
And I'm gonna go show you where we get the name
The class name for what we wanna do here
I guess back in the code
You see that there is
In the helper class
A
File called router so you can open that
And you'll see that you have what is know now called Hello World helper route
And
If you scroll down
We don't have this stage have how yes we haven't added the the site view for the single record
So there are some values missing here oh man I should have first done that
Anyway I'll go do that now but we'll come back to this file
And there is another file
Or I should say class
that works together with this class
And it's basically these two classes with their methods
That we were gonna use to actually build our link
Ok so let's
Create
That display site view
So
I've removed the
var dump from this view
I'm just gonna save and close this
I could have set save a new
Just gonna create
Another site View
And we gonna call this
Greet
We can't call it greeting because like we said
There is already a greeting in the front
All greeted that one might be better
We gonna
Make a nice display here
I'm using
Panel
I'm gonna copy the panel snippet
and paste it in here
And the title
I'm gonna make
The name
And the content
Will obviously be the greeting
Now I don't want two of those
So I'm gonna take out this one
So I basically
Got one greeting setup here
It's not yet gonna be oh you know there's no buttons here yet to edit it
But he will basically view One
Greeting
And it will also show you who set up the greeting
And ok now we can close this
So we got this greeted
Site view
We can help go to the admin area
Of the
Good because sorry to Joomla component area
And I'm gonna click on here
And
Actually add a site view
To the component
Same way we did before
Can I say I want greet
I don't want it to have an add menu
It must have meta
It's not a default view I also want access there
And by Default it's not public
So
Save and close
Now we'll compile the component again
Ok I've compiled and installed it
If we now go back to the that file I just
Opened previously this Hello World
Helper route
And we scroll down
Will see that now has a method called greet route
And you basically pass it and ID
And it constructs
The
The URL for you
Now
This component view doesn't have category
So it will skip this area
But it's
A function that I
Wrote that should
Be able to
Basically
Work for any View
So
You want to use this
Method
And this abstract class
Now
Those of you that are
A little bit interested in how this works
You'll see in the main
File of the site View
You'll see that the router
Is actually also added as a helper class
And
This is basically the name of this helper class Hello World
Helper route
And so
That's the abstract class name
Going back to our site view of greetings
To add our link
We now know
The method name
So that's the method name
And that's abstract class
Sorry that's the class name now let's get the method name
So we go back to
Scroll down
That's the method name so we can
Just copy it
It obviously
Needs to
Be corresponding to the view we want to open
And we wanna give it
The
Slug so it's gonna be a item
Slug
But that's not the only function
That we want to call here there is another one I mentioned
Which works alongside this and it's called the JRoute
Function
Actually class I should say
So we would add the JRoute around this
First
method class
And
That would basically
Add the
Other values to the URL
That is required
Ok so we've got our own helper class of a component
We give it The Slug
Which then gives it to the
JRouter
Which then
Echos out
The link
To open this item
Great
Now let's save this and compile again
To see it in action
We go to the front and
Reload the page
And when we click on one of these says not authorised
To view greet
That means
This specific group
Are not allowed to look at this
What are ways to prevent the link from showing up in the first place
But this is you for some reason you didn't actually put that custom script
in place
You see
You can actually see how the backend generates some of this
So if I go into the code
And we go to the admin area
Of
The
Hello World component
And we open the model
And we opened greetings
No no no it sorry not the model
Actually the view and then greetings
And we open the body
And we open the view data HTML
You'll see that it is grabbing
Some permissions to know whether it should show certain buttons
And then here
Is again setting up some permissions
To see whether
You are allowed
To actually
Edit
Here it is
To actually edited the The greeting
And if you're not allowed to edit it
It just Echoes the name
You see it doesn't show you the link
So this area here
Is really a demonstration of what you wanna do in the front
You don't wanna always show the link
To the item unless
The person
Who is actually viewing the site
Is in the correct group
Of the site
To be able to actually View
The item
Now I'm not gonna spend more time on this
Part because we wanna also do an editing concept
Which is really
More interesting and what I would rather spend time on
So here I'm just gonna go back into the admin View
In the admin area
And just change the permissions that the actual public could still open this view for now
So in the backend I go to options of the
Hello World component
Permissions
Scroll down
Again I'll see there is a new one called greet
Change this to allowed for the public group
And save and close out of there
Now I forgot back to the front
And click on
This link
It actually opens it
And it gives us the name James gives us the welcome welcome to JCB
And the greetings were set by the Superuser
OK so it actually loads it as we expected
You can also see in the
URL this demo site of mine isn't fully
Search engine friendly setup
But it already generates that this is a greet
To James
And so
And the name James appears here because of the Slug
The Slug is used to generate the search engine optimisation here
If we didn't have an alias it would have given you one or two
Depending on the item ID
Ok so
That just gives you a quick demonstration
Of how to set up
A front-end
That actually can open specific items
Now The Next Step
Is to actually make these items editable
Now like I explain to you
In the admin area we're ready doing some of this
So I'm gonna just basically copy and paste most of the code
From the admin area
And I would encourage you to do the same
Unless you know enough that you can just do it without looking at how JCB did it
So I'm gonna copy
The string
And then I'm going to also
Copy this one
These few lines
And then I'm also gonna use some of these
I realize by looking at this first area that the Checkout
And
This Checkout value
Needs to be set on the page
I also need to make sure about this value
Because
We need to check the users authority
On the page so we need to check whether the user is set
On the page
So
We can go and do that and look at some code
I'm gonna move some of this code
And then we'll go to the front end of the code area
I want to add the option to edit the item
In both the list as well as the Single View
So I'm gonna do it in the list view first and that I'll demonstrate step-by-step
And then when we go to the Single View I'm just gonna place the code in place
I'm not gonna explain to much because it's basically the same
So here in the site view
Of the list area I'm going to PHP and I'm going to
Custom view script
It says add PHP script to the head of the file
So I'm gonna paste
This link in here and we see that it basically
Has this view
Greetings
And the task is greeting
Edit
So that is the task
And it's gonna be available in the edit
Variable
Ok so that's the first part of the code we want up on the page
Now for the rest of it
We go back to the Admin view again
The backend
And we see wither we need to grab
These as well
So
Before grabbing them
Let's open the corresponding site view so we can look at some of the code
Ok so
Here is the greetings
I'm gonna open this view HTML
And we'll see that the user is already being loaded onto the page so we've really got the user
That's great
This is the items
Ok let's look at this
It is always is good for you to actually go and look at the code
The JCB is writing seeing the code
Is what makes you familiar with how things work
And also helps you to detect when something doesn't work
Why
And how to fix it
Since we know that the user is on the page and we go to the site
the admin area
This area
We see that it's accessing the user in the same way
Using this
As an object
User
And ask him whether it has authority
On the core
managed
To check in
And then also it
Basically checks
And gets the check out user
Details
And
We'll see why in a moment
But we don't have the check out user on the page
So
What we gonna do it's we gonna quickly
Also get those values by going to the Dynamic Get
And making sure that those values get brought to the page as well
So we go to list greetings
And again like before we just copy all those values
And just tweak away and then back
And the values we now want to make sure also comes along
Is basically
I see it's a value that it doesn't by itself add
To the selection
But you can add it in because you know it is in the database
It's just that
This table selection
Only shows at this stage the actual values that
That it knows belongs to the view
I think I need to update this in JCB
It is a little tweak which I haven't done
So it's not showing the Checkout and Checkout by values
But you can type it in by just going
And then
Those values will also be brought to the front
Of this view
So
Basically the Checkout and
The check out time
Actually we don't need the check out time
Only the check out
Basically who checked it out
We could add the time
But I'm not gonna demonstrate that during this tutorial we'll really it was over an hour and so few minutes
So I'm just gonna use the check out for now saving clothes
So we've updated our Dynamic get
And that means our values are on the page and we can move our code into place
We'll need to add it inside of this for each loop
Since this code
Is actually working with the item
Itself
Ok so we've got the code in there
Recalling the user
We also checking the item check out to the user ID
Making sure it's
We checking whether to check out user
Now let's go get the rest of the code we need
So again in the admin view we gonna go with
This area here
And just copy that
We wanna make a few adaptations because in the end of the day
The front end is a little different from the back end
In that
It is only
The backend only displays an edit view the front-end also displays a read view
So
We wanna make it a little different
You can pause the video to see some of the things I've done here
But in simple terms I basically got the edit here I'm editing echoing the edit
Link
And I'm adding the item and I'm putting in a little icon which then you can click
And here I'm checking whether you have permission
To actually edit
This item so if we were save this and refresh the homepage
It should actually not change anything because the public doesn't have permission to edit it at this stage
Ok that icon should be pencil not edit
Ok so let's save this and compile it
to see it in action
install it
And we reload the home page
and as you can see it doesn't show those little
Buttons
Now if we go to the back end
And we go to options
And we change
That
The public is allowed to edit
And
Let's say Let me not change state
Yeah Let's just do that they aloud to edit
And
Let's open the front again
We know see that it shows the edit
Pencil
Let's click on that
And we see it opens
The edit area
Where it can actually now
Add the exclamation
And click on save
Save and close
It tells us that the message was saved successfully
If we now
Open that greeting
We see that has the exclamation
so our
Attempt to integrate
Or to make our items editable
On the front end
Within the control of permission groups
Has actually worked very effectively if we again
Revoke the permissions
And
Refresh the page
And then suddenly those links are gone
And even if somebody
Were to try and
Circumvent the system
By having
In the URL paste in the link
To edit that specific item and
It will actually
Say that it's not permitted
So the
The the permissional structure is actually armed and will protect the item from being edited by
By that group
So
Again we gave the
Public
Permission to edit
But now the question is
Can we also give it permission to create
So going back to greetings
Let's add an option to create
An item
If I go and add this button here
With
a link
To create an item
But I'm not adding any checks around it
But you basically need the same kind of
Check as you've using here
Except that there are some
Shortcut let me
Let me show you
So basically around the button we added this PHP
That checks the users authority to create
For the core
Of this component
If yes
Then it will show the button if no the button will not show
So that is to control the visibility of the button
So let's save this and then compile and install
To see it in action
So we see the button doesn't show
And that is because currently
Who got a component set
That
the public
Cannot
Actually create
If we allow creating
For the public
And we
Refresh the page
You see that now it actually shows
Sorry that's the different view
It is this one
Refresh this page
There we go
Now if we click on it
It will open an area where we can create an item
So here we can set a new name
And then
Save and close
We get this save not permitted
This must mean that we haven't granted enough permissions
For the
Public user
To actually create an item
See giving it the option to create an item
Is not enough because there are fields
That
You know you need also access to
Before you can create an item
So let's let's try again
But first giving it more permissions
So we've granted it
Basically all the permissions
That it needs
and go to the front
Now we click create greeting
Save and close
And there we go
With saved the item
We can again edit the item
We can close
And we can View
As you can see it's all working
As expected
So
Our Hello World tutorial
Is nearly at it's end
We have within this tutorial demonstrated to you
How to create
A Hello World Component
List its items
Open individual items
And edit those items
As well as creating new items
All based
On the permissional of structures
Of the component
So if we
Where to change these permissions back
To not allowed
And we now refresh the front
We'll see that
Now we can only view the items
And even more
If we go back
And we wanna control the actual viewing of the greet items
Not be visible to the public but maybe only to let's say managers we could do that
So you can manage
That kind of control over your items
You know without actually
A lot of custom code
If you click on it now it will tell you don't have authority to view it
Now you can add
Basically custom
Scripting
To remove the link so that it doesn't even look clickable
If the person doesn't have access to view it
But that's already
We gone so far over the time
Trying to demonstrate to you
Some of the basic principles of setting up a Hello component
In JCB
I trust you've enjoyed this tutorial
By far it doesn't usually take this long to actually build a Hello World component
In fact there is a older tutorial
Where we managed to build a Hello World component and very
Shorter time
But I illustrated and demostrate it and explain it a little more here
To help you guys along
To actually build components with JCB
And that you'd realize that JCB
Is really actually a very powerful application
I mean I haven't even gone to the code this time
And shown you all that it's written
But I mean just from the compiler
We ready got 13000 lines of code
Which would have taken you 5 8 hour days to write
Which is about
39 hours
And I think for a basic component that's quite a lot of code
And it's because that it's already integrating a lot of permissional structures and
you know version control
I mean if I was to
Open
The greetings
And
Just open James
remember we added that
little
Exclamation mark We could check the version
We can see the changes and when it was made
We can actually review
Some of the previous versions
And we can even go back to those versions
That kind of integration
With your history component is done automatically by just adding history
And so is many of the other features
The JCB is adding to your component like export of data import of data
Bash sorry Batch
Changes that you can make
As well as
You know a whole lot of other concepts
Which
It's just Beyond the scope of what we had time for today
Well enjoy coding and yes
If you have any issues
Please go to GitHub
First check out the wiki page
Check the tutorials
And if you just think you've discovered a bug
You're most welcome to open an issue
And we'll see what we can do in trying to resolve that for you
We would like to invite other
PHP
Programmers
To really get involved on the JCB
GitHub
Community
And help us improve
JCB
So that
It can become a home
For us to manage
The troubled waters of open-source
Development
Thank you