I would like to demonstrate to you
How to add rules to your
Model
Basically to a field
Adding rules to a field
Uses your custom rules to
Test the value
Before actually
You know submitting it to the database so this is a quite good feature
to actually have in your component
Now
I'm just gonna use this Hello World Component the one we we actually
Did a Hello World tutorial on and I'm gonna add a rule to one of its Fields and then
Then quickly type it up
And show you how to include it
Ok so I've gone to admin views I'm gonna open this greeting
First
As the admin view we want to change the field in it
I think that's used his greetings
And let's add a rule
That we can call something like
Now we see at this time
That the field attributes don't have the validation
Option switch in place
So
We might start shipping JCB with this new validation property well not new it's
Just not being added yet but if you have a version of JCB that doesn't have it set
Then whatever field type you've selected you can edit the field type going here
Or
You could edit the field type
By going to field types
So this have to close out of this again
And then here field types
And you can select the field type that you want to add this validation to we want to do it for now just
to the Text area
This one
And it has a filter in place I think I'm gonna add validation just underneath it
So just gonna click
here a plus
It is adjustable
It's not required it's not translatable and let's give it a little
Description ok so I think we got it all set
I wouldn't add a value here because
If if you don't want to use it you just leave it empty
And ok that's basically it let's save and closed so we've done the text area
Now
Let's go back to our
Admin view greetings
and again open that field
And now we have this validate a property available to us
So we can now copy it
And add it in here
Now we want to have a custom validation here
There are built in Joomla validations as well
But you can also set up a custom validation rule and this is what of form
rule as its known
This is what we want to demonstrate
So we gonna say
Let's call our rule strlen
Ten
So my string must be longer than 10 characters
Ok I think that should do
So I'm just gonna copy this again
And save and close
So now that we've got our validation set JCB is not yet able to well
We don't have an area for you to write the rule and have it be included
So the way you do this and I think it's it's efficient
Is it you right up the file yourself you put it in the custom folder of JCB
And you include it into the component
So that it places it in the correct place
You see the one thing that JCB already does for you
Is that it creates a folder called rules and in the forms
Every XML
If we open it
already has a field path
And a rule path
So you you can just add your rule to this
Basically to this folder
Which I will demostrate to you in the moment
But first let's create our rule
So I had it this room here so in the folder structure
I'm basically in the admin area components component builder and there is this folder called custom
An inside of this folder
I've Now created this strlenTen file
strlenTen file and then it I placed this this code here
Basic
J form rule nothing too fancy about it
Ok let's see now that we've got our file in place
We need to add it into our component
So we go to the components and we open that component
And we go to
Settings and there adding custom files and folders
We click on this component files and folders create component files and folders
For this Joomla component
We just click on that it's ok
And here we want to add
1 file
Since we've added it to that custom folder everything in at custom folder will come up as a file that you can
Select
So there it is that file
Now the path to where we want it to place the file
So in the backend of the component we go to
Models
Forms
And we are targeting this greeting form so we opened that and we see
That it has models rules
So
Let's copy that
Now we need to remember that it is admin the admin area
And then
Models rules
So
This admin is basically the way the package is built so the target Place should be the place in
Inside the package this be always the case for both folders and fields
So in the
Folder
You want it to add it to the admin models rules folder
And then you need to decide whether you want this file to be updated
Now at this stage that files doesn't need any updating
But hey we can change that
So you can see I've just added this
New licence tag to it
And I've added this BOM
Basically when the file gets taken
It will
Take this part away and replace this with your components licence and so the file
will basically be
Become
Branded like every other file in your
In your component
And that
Even if you use it in areas or components
Other than the one you originally made it for it will just dynamically looked like it was made for it because it
Add that components
Data at the header of the file and even if you had the components name somewhere else in this
You can actually replace it with the well-known
Hash hash hash component hash hash hash and it will be placed with the component name
Ok enough of that we've got our file in place
You wanted to be updated
And now let's compile the component and see it in action
So here just tick this as yes it's the file should be updated
And then save and close
Also close out of a component again
There's no shortcut to that file area over here that you can use
We go to the compiler
And we compile our component
Ok it's done now let's install our component
Now let's go look at the code to see what happen
Ok so here is our components admin area If we open the rules we see ha there is a file it was
Placed into this folder
If we open that file we see ha
It added our
Copy notice to the header of the file
And now let's also look at our
XML
Scroll down
We see the validation is there strlen.Ten so
Everything so far so good
Now let's go test this
So we open this component in the backend
We go to greetings
We click new
Now as you remember
We said that greetings now needs to have a length
Of at least 10
Characters
So let's test this
So we add greeting which isn't enough and we click save
And it tells us
Invalid field greetings
Problem
There's one little change I had to make to get this to work and I realize I'll need to tell you ok let's go look at this
For some reason they want this file all lowercase so I had to change strlen.Ten to the T
Also in lower so let's go do this
Also with the file in our custom folder
Then
Inside of the actual file they also want the T here to be lowercase
I suppose because they are using the upper case camel rule
To sort of break-up the the name
Let's see ok so that was what I had to do to get it to work
Now
I also need to just update the component to include this file since the name is changed it will no longer know where it is
So we open the component
You know what
Let's not open the components go directly to that file
Area
With the shortcut
And we see it is no longer selected to a scroll down selected again and save and close
That should do it
Ok so now that we've fixed the little glitch which I created myself
Let's go back to see this again in action
And save
And invalid field greetings
Ok that isn't very helpful
Maybe you would like to also show a custom message
So that the user word least know more about what is going on here
But now before we do that let's add enough values and see if that it actually saves
And now it's saved excessively close
So our greetings been saved and how value here is more than 10 characters
So it was valid
Now let's go add a custom message to our
Validation
Now remember whatever you do to the live version of this file
Will not necessarily become part of the next compilation
So adding a custom message you need to actually go back
to component builder custom
And to that actual file
And add it in there then recompile your component and it will automatically
Update the live demonstration
So the other way just a test before doing it live or be you know before
Adding it to the core of your component is to actually go to the live file which as we saw is
here in Hello World
Models
Rules strlen.ten
Good
Now let's add our custom message in here just to test
Ok
We using the element and adding an attribute to the element message
Field must have more than 10 characters
That is one way of doing this of course there is another way
Again this takes us back to JCB
And we go to the field
We open greetings
And we look for the attribute message
It doesn't have message
So we need to add this attribute we'd click on field type
And we scroll down
I think let's place this under description
So we say
Message
It's changeable
It is translatable
And it's optional so
We don't make it compulsory
Ok we got all set
So
Just save and close
Now
Let's add this validation sorry the message
To our field
Now before we save this and actually go this path let's first test our live
Change we made to the file and see if that also works
So in the File we added this attribute
To the element
And basically return false
Good now let's go test this
So we again open that item
And we take away a few characters
And click save
And there we get a message that it needs more than 10 characters
Ok great so that option also works very well
Now lets use the other one which I suppose is more convenient
Unless you are checking multiple things and you would like to give multiple error messages based on those
results then this implementation is the better option but if you just got one message and it just needs to
really explain to the user one issue
Then using the XML path I suppose is more convenient
So in our custom file we haven't added that change so
Let's go and compiler component and install
First we need to save and close out of this
Field so that the changes be captured
Then go to the compiler
And compile
our component
Install
Lets go look at the code
So here in the code we see our custom message is again not showing up
The XML greeting we now have this translated message here
As you can see
Lets go test this
So again we open that field
And first lets just save it the way it is
Ok good it works lets take away 2 characters and save again
And we get the expected message this time around that message can be translated
And as well it is actually in the XML file it's not part of the actual function
Ok well so I think this covers it
We have now successfully added
Our own validation rule to one Field within a view
And we were able to include that rule into our component on compilation are using adding custom
Files
Thank you for watching