I would like to give you a tutorial on the new snippet manager and how it works
We are very excited to announce that
We have added a community concept
To the Snippets
In JCB
Previously
You could create your own Snippets
And then
If you would to create a custom admin View
A site view a template
Or a layout
You could access the snippets
Through a drop down
Let me demonstrate that quickly
So now in a site view
If I were to click on one of these Snippets
You see it loads
The snippet here
You can copy it from here
And
You can then place it in your code
And so
It is possible to actually load many Snippets
Now currently
We already looking here at the new Snippets
Area
You see that now
We have the type of the snippet
First
Then the name of the snippet
And then the library
The snippet belongs to
Once you've selected the snippet again and updates here
The name of the snippet
The type of snippet
And the library it belongs to
And usually this library is a link
It'll open you to the actual documentation on that library's website of the specific snippet
So that's all as it used to be nothing fancy nothing much different
Yet
There is a major change
Taken place
Because now
We have what is known as local Snippets
And then community snippets
We have
Actually enlarge the Snippets area
So that you can contribute to the community Snippets
And also import
From those Snippets that is been added to the community
By others
Now how does that exactly work
Well
Snippets that already exist
Are usually Snippets that either I made or
Someone else and
They already have
What is known as a contributor
The name of the contributor it's email address
web adress and so forth
So when you create a snippet
We will use your details
To actually create this contribution
So if we open an existing snippet
And you go to the contribution area you'd see that there is names in these
Fields
If there aren't any names
Then
Well that means the update didn't do exactly what it should have done
And when you
Go to the Snippets area
Where you get Snippets I'll show you that in a moment
There is a place for you to actually update all the contributor names
And so be sure to have their names actually in the database
The reality is these details should actually be in there already
If they are not
Well it's not a snippet you made so you don't need to really worry about it
These details only really apply when you wanna share a snippet
And all when you wanna improve a snippet and then we will add the correct details in any way
So really it's not to be worried about
But here you'll see how the contributed details
Are
Dealt with
We are using your company details that is set in the global options you could click this button to get there
Under the company tab of the JCB for the new Snippets you create
You cannot change the contributed details after snippet
That already exist
At this time via this area
So that is a simple heads Up
This area is really only for
The management of the community Snippets
If you're not gonna be contributing then this doesn't even matter at all
What is important though
Is that your snippet
be
Mapped the same way
As the Snippets in the community
For example if the grid
UI kit version 2 is called layout
Then don't change it
Because it will then behave like a new snippet and not like an existing one
You see because the community
Uses the name
The library and the type
To build
The filename
The file names
Well we'll look at that also as we go along
What I mean by file name
For now all you really need to know
Is it there are a bunch of Snippets already in your component
These snippets were shipped with Joomla
Component Builder
You know
So it
It means that
Really this is how it was
By Default
But we now have an area called Get Snippets
Now
If you are one of those who like to get your name out there and want to
Become you know involved in the JCB community and have others
know about you and so forth
Well this is the ideal time to do that
If you share a snippet
So let say you created this snippet for example
Then you would click on Share Snippets or you could take more than one doesn't need to be only one
You take and you Clicks share Snippets
This will then create a package let me show you
So we see that it's created a package it's placed it
In this folder
And you got a few helper tutorials here to actually get you going
So if you wanna learn well this tutorial I'm making now will be
This link here
And if you wanna learn
More about Git
It's this one here
And if you
Want to know how the forking is gonna work then it's this
And if you wanna know how to do pull request it
It will be this one
And if there's any issues you can open an issue on GitHub
So this really gives you a sort of a few links and shortcuts
To actually get
Involved in sharing
Snippets
What happens when you've share the snippet
If someone Clicks on Get Snippets
Then they will see your name
If that
That specific snippet
Comes up
So let me illustrate that
If we click on Get
Snippets
It might take a moment
Depending on how many Snippets are in the repository at this stage
Because it buy Ajax it's getting all the Snippets
From GitHub
And it's building a little page for you
There we go
It's just loaded the whole bunch of Snippets
The first view shows you all the current Snippets
In the JCB community Snippets
Repository
You can go to this repository by Simply clicking on this GitHub link here
It will take you there
You can see which of these Snippets are ready in sync
It's called EQUAL
You click on this here
It show you what EQUAL means
In sync with your local Snippets so it has little Mark here saying it's a local snippet
And it is in sync
If you don't want to know more about when is a snippet
Considered equal
Then click on this little button here
And also you that like I've said
Then if there is a snippet out of date let's say someone
Contributed to the community on a specific snippet let's say it this snippet here
Someone saw ok if we If we open the snippet
They they saw this little snippet and they thought you know we could do better and they improved on it
And then shared it with the community
Then that snippet will end up in the out-of-date tab
If there is no out of date Snippets then all be blank like now
But if there is
Snippets that are out of date
They all show up here
Then there is the new tab
Now the new tab
Well that could be
a little bit misleading
Because in this example that I'm giving you I went and I deleted a snippet from my Database
And since that snippet already exists in the community
It realize the system
Then detects ok well that snippet isn't here so it must be new
That's how it basically worked out that little
Some
Now you could click on this
Get snippet
And it will automatically
It says here
Are you sure would like to add this new JCB community snippet to your local Snippets you says yeah ok
And then it goes to GitHub
Gets the snippet and moves it to your Database
And Boom
You done
So now this snippet is no longer new if you click here you'll see its oh no new snippets
It is now also been added locally
Then diverged Snippets is where
There is a discrepancy in both the creation date as well as the
Modified date
And then those snippets will show up here and they can be updated in the same way
If you have made a change to a snippet in your local environment
And then
You've realized oh that changes hasn't been good there's been a better
You know
Just to return back to the old
Community version
Then you would come here to the head
I made a little change to this
Pacific snippet
And they'll tell you that the snippet is ahead and if you click on it
They'll show you
What that would mean
You can then click on get snippet
To really revert
Back to the old one and that's what it will tell you
Oh sure you would like to update your local snippet with the older
JCB community snippet
So you can say no I like my new snippet I don't want to update in just ignore it
But if you wanna go back then that there is this option
To do so
If this is a good snippet
You might wanna consider sharing it with the rest of us
An and that would be to actually
Be to actually do the sharing snippet
And go through those tutorials in knowing how that works
There is sometimes a situation where a specific
one of
The community
Might be very enthusiastic
And he contributes let's say 300 new Snippets to the community Snippets
Repository
Now that would mean that you know you wanna click on every one of those snippets get snippet get snippet that might be very
Tedious
So we added this little bulk tool
Now the bulk tool is able to
Detect whether there are new Snippets
And whether they are ahead Snippets
Or whether you just wanted
Just update all of them with this this just get all Snippets
And so
If there isn't any diverged or any outdated Snippets it will also not be able to do that
So here instead of clicking it one at a time you could just click on this and I'll just update all of them for you
And you're done
But if you like me and you wanna know exactly what's going on
You could go here you could read the description Ok there's no
description
See the usage
See how the snippet itself looks like
And if you really like what you see
You might even want to look at who contributed the snippet
That brings up an important and yet interesting
Concept
We have decided that when you contribute a new snippet your name and details will end up here
Like I explained earlier when we looked at the contributor area
Yet when someone makes minor contributions to the snippet
We will not necessarily change or you know place this contribution
Contributor's name
Instead
We will let them show up in the blame view so there is a view
Which is called the blame View
The blame view shows you who changed what part of the code
And when
So whenever there is an improvement on any of the Snippets
The GitHub repository tools will help us sort of show you
Who made those changes
So that's how they will be recognised for their contributions is via the blame
Where is if you contribute new Snippets to the JCB community
You will actually end up having your details show up here
And have people be able to click on this link
And actually go to the website you put up as your website
So it's an ideal way of getting yourself out there in the JCB community
And at the same time sharing good snippets with the rest of us and make make our life easier I suppose
Anyway and so
That is the really looking at the Get Snippets
Community area
And we're excited about this we hope that this will really faster a lot of
Participation
And that it will
Improve JCB constantly because as you know
Snippets are used in these
Four key areas custom admin views
Site view templates layouts
And
These areas
Are what really the customer sees right the one that uses the component
So we wanna always be sure to have the latest and
Most
Stable Snippets ready in available
For everyone using JCB
So once you have actually
Imported
The new snippet you were able to see it at the end of your Snippets
So this one is now the latest one we've actually
Imported
If you open the snippet
You see that contributed details are already in place
And so these contributed details will be updated as you add new Snippets
If for some reason these
Details are not
In place it will say Dynamic value let me show you there
Please create a new one
Like this
So
It says Dynamic field
When you have created your snippet I'm just gonna do a
Simple
Test here
to illustrate this
Ok so it's obviously
A test
And you click save
oh missed a value
It will first
Search the
JCB snippet repository to see if there really is a snippet with this kind of a relationship
Between the name the type and the library
If it doesn't exist
It will go to your Global area like explained
And they will get your details
And dynamically added in
to
The the snippet
So there we go
Its obviously found my details
and put it in there
So that is how this details get set
When you create a snippet a new one
It will fall back to your details
If that snippets name
Type and library relationship doesn't already exist in the JCB
Community
Now if for some reason
It does exist
It will actually
Take the initial contributors details and add that in there
That's how it works at this stage maybe there is better ways but
For now this is how we will start at least
And I'm sure it will evolve and change as we go along until we are able to actually
satisfy all and everyone's needs
I think that's enough of an overview
Of how everything works
So you've
Seen how to use the Snippets in your components
You've seen how to
Start initial steps of sharing a snippet
You simply select them like I showed you
Obviously
Only when you have improved on it or whether you've created new ones will you ever wanna do that
And then you click on Share snippet and gives you a package
And
Then on that it
Let me just show you again
On that it has a
Few tutorials like
Tutorials I'm forking the JCB Snippets
And
Tutorial making a pull request
These two tutorials would be quite key
For you to understand what would be this next steps
And getting your Snippets
Into the JCB community
Well thank you for watching
And
Yeah Until next time