I'm very excited to announce the
Actual
Library manager implementation
We're busy with a pull request we should have it released within the next hour or so
I'm very excited about this, this new improvement
Is really gonna make
Libraries very Dynamic in JCB
Not it has not been dynamic
It's just
Not everybody realizes how easy it is to add new libraries
So
What I wanna do is quickly
Not to elaborate , show you how it used to be done
And then
I want to jump into how it work now and you'll see why the new implementation is so much easier
So much better and
I think everybody's gonna enjoy it
Ok so let's get started on how it used to work
So if we go to a component and we open a component
There are three libraries that are already built into JCB that just works out of the box
And those three libraries can be selected
With the add UI kit add food table
Ok
Let me see
The other libraries that are being added
Is when detects
Basically some code in the certain areas of the script
I'm not gonna elaborate on that, it's going to take too long
Point is this two you could select here simply
By selecting
You know now there's a new feature called dynamic
And that is part of what we will need to look at
Dynamic
Basically means
That it is added in on the basis of the views
That are linked to the component
So The Old Way You had to come to the component and sort of tell it here ok , I want UiKit and I want food
table added
And you could tell him you know what version you would like
Or if you want it with the UiKit you could actually set that it adds both versions
Now with improvements you'd set this to Dynamic which basically turns off
The
Global adding of the Uikit component
And then Falls back
Onto the new implementation which I will demonstrate with in a moment
So let's leave it on this the way it was
That was the first way of actually implementing some library
The second way
Which was the way that you could now scale it
Is if you want to go to settings
There is component files and folders that you could add
So you could click here and say you know what I want to add a
library that isn't already part of JCB
Ok so let's say you wanted to add Bootstrap
So
You would say ok there is a folder in your component on the administrator components
Component Builder custom
And inside that folder you would place the folder
For Bootstrap so I don't have it here
Let me quickly do that
Just now I'm gonna refresh this page I
I quickly went and added a folder to this custom folder
Called Bootstrap
So let me just refresh this
So I'm gonna get in click here
And then there we have it, select Bootstrap
I want Bootstrap to be added to the media folder
And since we do not do any
Changing of the folder name will just leave that as it is
So basically I move this folder into the media folder
That's the way you would have done that in the past
So close
Now
Having added the files to the component
You will then
Actually have to go to the view
So if we go to site view
And this looks View
You will have to in the looks view
you know set
That it actually now uses
Now this is the new implementations I'm gonna undo that
And just say Ok in the custom document script area
You would add this snippet in here so you add a script now you know
that you add the the Bootstrap 4
Folder to media
But when it gets installed to Joomla
It actually a creates a component folder and put the
A files in there
If you do not know how that will work out add the folder install it onto Joomla website and go look in the media folder
To get the correct path here
And save and close and that's how you would in the past have extended JCB
To actually use
Other libraries then what's built into JCP
And ok I Illustrated that simply so you'll know that we could have done this before
But it was a little bit more complicated
As the way it's going to work now
So now
With the new changes we've made
You can actually
Remove
The
The files
If you have done this this manual way
You can actually remove these files
So close
You don't need to add them any this way anymore
They will be added in another way now
I'm gonna demonstrate the other way
By actually starting at the libraries area
Some closing out of the component
I'm going to libraries
And you see that with the upgrade
There's now a Bootstrap 4 library ,Uikit 3
2,
Food table 2 and 3 and a No Library
Which is really only necessary when you create a snippet which doesn't belong to any library
Just your own snippet that you want to use
So
The Snippets are now directly linked to these libraries
These libraries
These six which been
shipped with JCB
Should not be changed
In relation to its name
Or it's type
But you can change its behavior
now the behavior is the file behavior
There are an a various file behaviors
Let's open Bootstrap to show you some of those
The moment Bootstrap is set on always add
And it is linking in basically a
Content distributed
Network link
And it says that it it should add it as a link
Now you can change that you can say no I don't want to add it as a link
And you can edit this
And
Without
Making any changes to the link you can change this to
A local
And that what JCP will then do
Is during compilation he will download these files
And add them into the component as local files
Which would then be used instead as the link
Which I think is quite nice
You could also do the same thing here as we did previously you could add
Files from the same custom folder
And also folders
Those are
The same kind of implementation except
It's now done on a library level
So that even library gets added to a view as I will show you in the moment
You automatically use this
Files
So that means
You don't need to do it per component
You basically do it per library and as you link the libraries to Views
It'll automatically incorporate these files into your component which makes it a little bit
Less effort you just set it up once
And thereafter you could just reuse, reuse
Do I'm gonna change this to local
So now it will says local get
There is an a few behaviours year there is a conditional custom script and do not add
Now the conditional
Is still under development
All its functionality is already here so you'll see all the links are showing up here
But as related to its implementation in the compiler
It's not ready yet
So for now
Skip the conditionals option until you see that when you compile that it doesn't give you a warning at
This moment
If you compile JCB
Your give you a warning that the conditional options are not available yet
I'm in fact we're planning to have them released with the next release
Which would be 2.6 point 7
So any any version if you looking at this tutorial after 2.6 - 7
Then the conditional options already working
So I'm gonna just demonstrate it briefly
The conditional options works in two ways
the one is you first need to add some configuration fields
now configuration fields
Is basically Fields that will be added to the global
Options of the component
And if those fields are tripped
It will have an effect on whatever way you set it
So to show you that
If you look here you'd see there is an options area
If we click on the options area
That's now in a component you would see there is Uikit2 settings
And it has a bunch of
Buttons here
That's basically the kind of buttons
That you can build
So you first go and create the fields in JCB as you would normally create any other field
And then in the library come here and click on getting the configuration fields
So
Here I'm just gonna select the anything so I'm just gonna say
Add more maybe as an option
And I want to
Created under the tab called
Boot....
strap
Just like that
So that's gonna be the tab name
That's gonna be the the the radio button
Save and close just as a demonstration
So now if I change this to configuration
And I click on adding a configuration and then I say
I want to add the local
These two local files
I want them to be included
When add more is said to
Yes
That's basically
How this configuration of conditions will work
In a relationship so
You won't see any option Fields if you haven't created
Option fields
In the configuration
So if you wanna use this area when it is eventually ready
You will have an include and exclude option
Based on buttons
And then you select the files you that you want to
Be added or
Not not be added
Based on these selections
Now these buttons obviously as part of your component parameters
And so within your code when you start developing your templates and your layouts
You can draw upon
These parameters
In your PHP
And say ok if it's the switch is that then I want this
HTML to load
Otherwise I want that HTML to load
So you could have Bootstrap alongside Uikit
With the same implementation
So that is giving a idea of where this conditional
Area is supposed to come into play
The area that I have really like more is actually the custom scripting area
Which really
Is giving us the same behaviour as what we did in the site view right
So we basically just add the same
Files here
And
The only thing will change it will add
Component
Like that
Wherever we have the component name
Because we want this to be Dynamic or that needs to be
Three of those
So that if it gets added to any component
You'll dynamically update those names
As related to
The fact that it will use Bootstrap version 4
It really is using this name here
And it's putting a little - between them and making it lowercase
And
These two files
Are based upon those names there so you basically need to use that name
And
That name
And it will dynamically detect that this is a CSS file
I put it in a CSS folder and same the same goes with the JS a file
So basically this is how you do a custom scripting for Bootstrap 4
And that will be very similar to Always Add
Because Always Add would basically write that script for you
And so you just Add the files you always want to add
And the behaviour is like this so
Really I'm trying to give you as much Liberty as possible
So that you can use libraries in any way you're like
Write your own conditions
Or your own custom script or just let JCB add it always
Now
I'm gonna demonstrate how this adding always is gonna work in a moment
Can I save and close out of here
So we have basically Bootstrap Always Add and Uikit Always Add
And Uikit
Version 2 we using a built-in option as same for the food table and the food table Version 3
So the Build-in options are only available for these
1 2 3 4 libraries
Not for Bootstrap but for those 4 libraries
And any other libraries that you add will not have a Built-in option unless we build one and then it will become available
Ok so that is showing all around the libraries now
Let's link the library to a view so I'm gonna go to site view
I'm gonna go and open looks
As the site view
And basically I'm just gonna select Bootstrap 4
That's all the moment I select Bootstrap 4 the Snippets
That will show up here will then be the Bootstrap 4 Snippets
Since we do not anymore ship
Snippets with JCB
You'll have to install some Snippets
So let me show you that quickly
You go to Snippets
you don't really need to go to snippets. Ok, so the Uikit Snippets are still being shipped
But not the Bootstrap 4 Snippets
You then click on get Snippets
Select Bootstrap 4
And it will then load all the Bootstrap 4 Snippets that are available to the community
You can deny the user bulk import
Or you could import individual Snippets
for Bootstrap 4
Once it's ready it will show you which ones are new
So let's I'm gonna add
That snippet
Say yes I wanna do that
So it's basically installing it
And then I'm also gonna take that one
It says would you like to add it too? say yes ok
so I've install to Bootstrap Snippets
The way to install all of them since there's so many
Is the use the bulk option
So you could actually come here to bulk
And you see that it has the new and you can click on this and it will install all of the the Bootstrap snippets
Ok
So that is the quick way of getting libraries
Snippets into your system
And installing them
Just by clicking on
On get snippet
And it will basically do that for you
Now let's go back to site views
And again open the looks area
So now if I select
Bootstrap
Then you'll see those two Snippets that I've installed
And I can
Click between them and really that's just for you to get the snippet
And to be able to add it into your
You know into your code
Where ever you would like it to be like that
Ok so
I'm gonna do that
I'm just gonna demonstrate
Adding the library so selecting the library here
Is what will add the library to the component and actually to this view
So you can select
Multiple libraries for one View
But there could be a problem with that if you for example want Uikit version 2 and Uikit
Version 3 on this page but you want to have it
Only use the one or the other based on certain switches in the global options of the component
Now
Uikit version 2 was set to fall back to
the internal
Build-in option
And Uikit Version 3 was said to fall back
to
Always add
So if we just look at that
Ok so that's Always Add and Built-in
Now you want to
Actually have both libraries under the page
But you wanted to work within some custom implementation the way to do that
is to click on new
And use the bundle option
Select
Those two libraries
Like that
Decide how you want to do it so it will be possibly a custom script
Or it will be a conditional one
Which you will then have to create
Obviously let me just say this
So we could call those Uikit
Bundle
Let's call it Uikit like that
And save
Now
Once you've saved it once
You should now add the actual files
So
You would go to folders
And then
At Uikit 3.... wrong button
Uikit
3 and Uikit 2
.........
And you wanna add them to the media folder
So
You'll have to still link the files remember selecting those libraries
Doesn't inherently
clone it's
Files
You'll need to still manually add the files so now we've got version 3......
Why is this so difficult
here we go
The screens not working along here
Ok you like it Version 3 and version 2
And save and close
So now
We have
The files
And here they are as folders
And it shows you all the files and folders
That are found inside of those two folders that you've added
So
Yeah I think it's little difficult you cannot see which version is which here
This might be a
A good option to add
Maybe the folder the name here
I think that will be
In the next release we will make that change
But I think the other option which is also ideal for this kind of implementation is a custom scripting
Which you could still create
The the the configed files
Fields excuse me
So when it when it's this Uikit version 2 is selected
it will load the Uikit version 2 files
But you must understand if you create the buttons
it will be added to the component
But if you use custom script
And in here in the behaviour you write the custom script
You need to
Let me just show you in the file
So in the file
You see that it actually puts the parameters
In params this params
So
You will need to down here
Get
The Uikit
The switch the the button name
That you now
Have created to the configed fields
You then get the value put it into a variable
And then based on that variable
You would either
Add the file or not add the file
So you'll basically write this script
If I was to
Just copy this is an example
All the way up there
And go here paste
This is basically what the custom script should look like
But that means that you created
In the library config you created buttons
With those names right
And that the values are related to these values here
The HeaderCheck option
Is something that if you
go into the file you go look at the PHP you might understand how to
Use this
And so the HeaderCheck at this stage always being loaded
If you don't wanna use the edit check then you just you know just don't use it
But you could go and and try and figure out how the HeaderCheck works
And then use it
anyway so that is
Making a bundle
Now let me save this as an example
And so now we got this Uikit
And it's a bundle
If we go back to the site View
And we open that up again
We will now instead of creating this one and that one we will just create
Select that bundle instead
And that bundle will give me
Uikit version 2 snippets it and if we have any version 3 snippets installed
it will also load that for me
So I will be able to work with both libraries
Why selecting is bundled
Library option and JCB when it compiles
He will basically use the custom script that you wrote in the Bundler
To add it to the view so let me
Show you that so I'll save and close here
And let's go back to the library quickly
And just do something silly to the code
So that you will actually see it's implementation
I am just gonna add
These bunch of lines here
Save and close
And then let's compile this
and install
Ok let's look at the code
So now you see that it's added in this library files
Obviously it's also added in
The
Originals because
We haven't set that button to show let me just show you
What I mean
In the component
You need to change the version
Of the old library implementation
You need to change that
So now
You need to change this from adding Uikit version 2
To basically to dynamic
Save and close
No if we compile it now you will see it will not add the
That
Code
To the file twice
You're basically just add that Uikit bundled
Code that we wrote
Ok let's look at the code
So now
We see that it only added the code that we wrote
And then
Remember in the file we added this as custom script
So we need to go remove this
In the
View
Where we added this in
So in the view we added these custom script
We actually didn't need to add the spaces
And we do have a little bit of a
A discrepancy there
Ok I'm gonna escape this just that you can see
We don't need to add this in this way anymore
We can go here
And
Basically
do that
we still want that
Bundler in there as well
Ok so we don't need to do this anymore
We can just
Basically select Bootstrap
Save and close
And then I'm gonna run the compiler again
There we go
If you look at it hear we see that there is that escaped code that we removed
And here is this code that JCB added
remember I said to you that
We basically in JCB
We are Linked in
If we look at the library might not here
Let's go here
The Bootstrap 4 library we set Always Add
And we basically linking it from a link right and we just said local get
Now if we look at the code
We see that it
wrote
For us this
Path
So now let's check if it actually did add the path correctly
So we wanna go to the media area of the
Program
And go to
.........
Demo
And so
We see it created the Bootstrap folder
And added the files
According to the path
That it also set here so that it is really implementing the get
Option
For the libraries
And all you really did is you just linked it to this view
This does give another situation where
To every view that you want is pacifically library to be available
You need to link it
To that View
Which wouldn't be a problem
If you created a view now and just add your library and then add the Snippets
Then I mean then you're starting a fresh and you will actually select the right views you want to use
But if you since you haven't done this before all the components
If you wanna use a library in the view
You have to go and add it
Or you just have to
Basically in the components area fall back
On the old way of implementing
The the libraries that are built into JCB so that means the old implementation still work
If you
If you basically set it here
to
Add both Uikit version 1 and 2 and 3
And also
Maybe to add food table version 2
those
Implementations still work
And doing that will add it to every custom and admin view where it's used
Sorry
Custom insite view custom admin view site view template layouts
So that that's the old way and that still works it's just that when you want to start using like
Bootstrap 4
You'll have to actually link it to the custom admin view or site view or template layout
Where you want
That specific
library to be available
So
View link in Bootstrap over here
Then it will be available to this layout and to every view where this layout is
Used
Ok so that's the quick and demonstration of the new
Libraries implementation
We call it a library manager
Because of The Diverse ways of you linking in the files and so forth
We really hope that you
Understood then are able to enjoy this new implementation
We want to
Make it possible for you to add libraries
And then basically share that snippets
With the rest the community
So those of you that interested in doing that
Please watch some of the previous tutorials about Snippets and the snippet manager
Because
I think doing this will not only help everyone else in the community but also get your name
I'm out there
I get people connected with with each other
Anyway
Thank you for watching