I"d like to give you a
Quick overview of the new implementation that we've added
To JCB
That allows you to do translation
via a
Excel spreadsheet
It is really just to
Make it easy for you to
Build your component
Extract your language strings
And give it to someone else
Have them do the translation in whichever language you like
Have them give the spreadsheet back to you
And imported into JCB without
The necessity of struggling with INI files any of that
So that was what we wanted to achieve
The other thing that you need to know
Is that JCB
Doesn't really work with placeholders
When it comes to these translation strings
It actually works directly with the English
String
And the reason we did that
Is because the place holders
Which in the INI file is the
Let me just show you
Quickly
If you look at these
For example may be back
This
Word
This English word here
Might be ended up being used in multiple views the same English word
But with a different
you know a placeholder
So
What we did instead as we said to Ourselves ok
To ensure that you always translate this specific English string only once
We will only add the string and wherever it is reoccurs will replace it
The string itself
This should be an advantage
I can understand that
That you might want to have a differently
But this is how we've gone about doing this
And so when you think about create new
Create new comes you know is used
Many places over in
In the you know in the files
sorry
In relation to these placeholders
But you only need to translate it this create new ones
And we will add it
The compiler will add it
Correctly
In every other place where it belongs
So that's really
The first thing you need to keep in mind
The second thing which is
Almost as important
Is that you often have strings that are across multiple components
So the string back for example again or cancel
or close
It is not only used in one component is used in many components
And so we also said to Ourselves we want to still just translate close
Once
And then in every other component where it's used
It will automatically be used
And so when we go to JCB if you have a fresh install of JCB
And you scroll down and your open language translations
You see that there is no values there
A same as if you opened languages there's also no values there
If you want to have JCB
Populate the translation the English strings
So where does it get them well it gets them from your fields
And from your site views
And from
Any other place either
Your admin view or
you know
Any other place where you use
Translation strings
In then it populates dynamically the language translation so you don't really ever need to click
New
To create any it creates it
For you so the way to do that if you would go to the compiler
You select the component that you would like to compile
And you simply click compile and you need that do that only once now you can just clear that out again
You don't need to use it
Now if we go back to language translations
Suddenly
There's a whole bunch of strings here and also tells you that it hasn't been translated and all
So just that's quickly and we got
Almost
249 strings here
And like I said close will only be shown up once
So
It is with every other strain
If we then open one of these
You see that you cannot edit the English string now we've had request
The people would like to edit the string but it doesn't really make sense because if the string is
Is being used
In a
Field
How would we be able to know
That their relationship here needs to change
For example if you update a string here
Now JCB needs to know
In that field in needs to update the label for example
There's no way for us to it
you know to determine that
So you'd basically change the string and it won't be useful
Because it JCB on compilation
Will deter will detect that this string doesn't exist
And it will just create it again
So the way that you would change a string which is found here
Is you need to go and change it in this either
The field where it was created
Or the site view or the admin View
And I mean in this case we know that this word demo
Is the components name right so if you wanna translate that string
Oh sorry change that string
So for example I'll quickly demonstrate that
I'm gonna change this demo to two o
Like that
And then save and close
Now I'll compile it again
And just cleared out and then go back to our language translation
And now
You see the demo is gone because
Demo is no longer being used anywhere
Another component either so the system will automatically remove it
If you go to the end of the string will see the new ones
Have been added
See there
So that's how you would
Change a English string is you'd go back to where you set it
And then from there have it been changed
I'm gonna just changed it back quickly
And then compile it again
Clear it out again
Go back to language translations
And you see that it's removed the other one and it's added to correct one back
Now
I'm gonna translate or I would like to translate only this one string
And if I wanna do that
You see that there's no language is available
We decided to allow the languages to be set dynamically meaning
That you would manually create them
And use them as you like
So there is an area called languages
You'd click new here
And then you'd give the language name and it's tag now the tag
We've given you an example here
But if you do not know how this should look
There are ways for you to find out one of the easiest ways
Is there actually just go to Joomlas translation area
So if you go to community
.Joomla.Org/translations.HTML
And then you select
I would say just selective
This one that's the newest
And then you'll see there's a whole bunch of languages here
Clicking on any of these
Will take you down to that language
And basically this is
The little tag that you would look be looking for
So if you want to do for example Dutch
Then this is the the one
The the tag that you would use
You would use the
Dutch as the name
And then that as the tag
I'm gonna set up just for example I'm gonna setup Afrikaans
Is my native language
So
I'm just gonna use Afrikaans
As the language we wanna create
And obviously then this is the
The tag
And you can create any of the languages you want to use
We might at some point at a few major languages here
And ship it like that but
Just that you know you could just create a language
You Cannot create a translation for that language unless you've done this
You must first create the language
It is just the way it works
Now we can go back and
Let's take a string that
Would look different in Afrikaans
So let's take author
So now here if there's more components which the word author is used in
It'll all be linked in here and it all be done automatically you wouldn't need to do any of that
You will only really need to focus on this translation area so author in Afrikaans is
skrywer
or outeur
So will use the outeur which is actually more correct
And then
Will you select the language for which that string belongs
And then save and close
And that is as simple as that
From now on in any component
Where the word author is used
If
The Afrikaans translation with relation to the other strings
Is enough
It'll dynamically add this language
To the component
And you would not need to translate it again
Now this is all been the way it's been working up till now so this is none of this is new
The area that is new
Is that you can actually export
these strings
To a spreadsheet
And then
You can import them
From the spreadsheet and it will dynamically be added so
I'm gonna just select a few strings here you don't need to select any of the already translated
strings
But if you do it will also be used if it doesn't really matter
I'm just gonna select a few
And
Click export data
This will create a
Excel
Spreadsheet
Which you can then save
I have now open that spreadsheet and you see that it has a bunch IDs
And then it has English
It's got the
The tag of the language
And it's got the value that we already set
So now I'm gonna set
The value for these others in the spreadsheet
So now you got your
Language
File back from your translators
And they basically translated it
This column
Now you can have multiple language every every language will have its own column
And
All you need to ensure that this top header
Is the language tag
That's really what's important and that this language
Is created and published in your system
Do not let them change to English string
When you import this file
The system will look for the ID and the string
To identify that this value exists
If it doesn't exist it will simply ignore it
So if you change author
Even though the ID Remains the Same
It will not find it and it will simply ignore this line
On the way I'll demonstrate this is I'm just gonna change back to having to k's
And
Save this document
And then let's go back and import it
Now the imported is simple we just click on import data
Then we select the file from our system
Click upload file
And it should dynamically mapped the columns in your spreadsheet
To the
Table columns so you would have
Your language strings if you got multiple language
It should automatically mapped in
If you are having multiple languages and you only one import for the one language
Then all you need do is add this ignore the column next to the language as you do not want to
import
Ok and then you click continue
And that is it you will now see
That it has added translations
Except for back
Now
At first it didn't actually add these so I had to quickly go and add a little fixed to the
import
I didn't realize that
At the moment
It actually would stop at the first failure
And not import further
But I've just fix that and should
Within the next update this should be resolved
Anyway
the point is
Once you've imported it you'll see that it is added
The translations to
Those
Strings
And it's also mapped it to the correct language
But back was not imported because the English string didn't actually correspond
If we go back to our spreadsheet
And fix this little error
And in fact make a little tweak to
What are the other strings
Just for example sake
And then go back to importing this file after Saving it of course
Save
So again import data
Browse
Now you'll see that back is been done
And the other one that we also played with was disclosing new
We added to the double T there
So now you are able to export
This language strings
Translate them in a spreadsheet
And easily import that spreadsheet
Which word automatically update
Your values here if you
Have updated more than 50% of the English strings
To a specific language
It will automatically be added to your component
You can change this percentage
By going to options
In JCB
And then basically changing this
Select the percentage any language should be translated before the system
Should add the language to component during compilation
So that means
If more than 50% of your English strings have been translated
It starts adding it to the component
If not
It will just ignore it
Ok that is
Giving you a quick demostration of the new import export
Option in translating
The strings in your system
And knowing that if you have translated any of these strings will only
You need to do it once
And it will dynamically be available to every other component that uses that field or that View
And therefore these English strings
Thanks for watching