I would like to demonstrate to you the new implementation
Which isn't such a major thing but
Something we've done to try and
Help along some of the router complexity
So when you build a component
And you have a front end
For your component so you've got site views
Your site views usually are getting it's data from a dynamic get
Which you link up to the site View
and this dynamic get basically returns a
Resultset
and it is from this result set
That we should get information
By which we
Combined with the view name
Build what is called a
Search engine friendly URL
your search engine friendly URL is basically done with the router
So JCB also builds the router
And it sort of guesses what should be these values
So let me compile a component
And show you what it guessed
And then see how we would need to change it
the component that we're working with here is Sermon Distributer
So I'm gonna compile it
And install it to this website
as now the router doesn't really work I'm not gonna demonstrate
the
actual front-end
I'm just gonna show you the code
And
And let's take it from there
So when you look at the website you've got your root directory admin
And then components
And then in here we've got Sermon Distributer
And there's a file called router
I'm gonna open this
And you'll see there's got a function called build
I'm a class method
As well as a function called parse
and in this function
called parse
There is a switch
Which basically
Makes decisions based on the segment's
First value
And if that segment's value is
Because usually that would be the view name
In this first
Value
it determines
which view are we looking at is it preacher
And so we going through the list
Now by Default without us
You know making any changes
JCB Builders for us
All of it
So
If we look at preachers
Which is a
Basically a listview
Let's open the preacher model
So here is preachers
We can scroll down
And we'll see that
In its
Query
It basically has a get items and here it got a list query
And it really is just getting all the items from Database
With no input from the URL whatsoever
Let's see
Yeah it doesn't do any of that and then it just
Gives back
So it's a simple as that
It does not
Need a URL value
So that means it most probably will only
Set this verse
Value
And all of this will really be redundant, it won't be used
Because it's a listview
So there isn't an alias
We not looking at an individual item so there isn't an ID
So we could
Actually remove this here
This code
It's not doing anything
Now
It is also not gonna really
Slow your site down that
Dramatically it's fact it's it's hardly noticeable
It's it's just that this is default
Being generated
Where us if we look at for example
Preachers is the list view but then there is a view called preacher we see it here
And it is saying that
It needs to get the ID from
Discernment table
Which is actually in error
So if I open the preacher
And I look at the list query
Then I see that in the list query about here
It is getting an ID
From the URL
And it is asking that it should be equal to preacher
So
It is the main table is
Is the Sermon table
But it's not looking for the Sermon ID
It is looking for the preacher
Value in the Sermon table and that's why
JCB be fell back onto the table name
And yet
It should actually go to the preacher
Table and
See weather
That preacher value is equal to this ID
So it is actually
Making an error
Now you wrote the code or you set up the get so you should understand the logic of what you see in the code here
If you do not
Then
This is a feature with JCB has with you possibly won't be able to you know make use of
Like we've said many times
JCB is for those who know PHP
And can actually write their own components
Now
I know that this is an error because we want to actually get the value the ID
Of the preacher
Is the one we need to check
And it is is doing it wrong it should
This value here should be preacher not sermon
You can look at the getVar class here at the bottom
Here is the getVar class
And here you can see what it's going to do
And how it's going to actually get the values
So you can also use the getVar class
for your own purposes
So
At this point we see at least one of the
Router case
Within the parse method
In the case loop there's at least one
router area that needs to be changed
I know by having looked at this before
That there is actually more than one it's also this categories
Down here
This one
Should also change
This should also become
Well actually it should just get a true
Here
there should be true because this is a category
Look up
Now the other place it also need to change is this one
There should also be serious
So this is where the guessing which JCB does
Dynamically
Did not match the complexity of our Dynamic get
And I'm sure that as time goes on we might
Improve it's
Guessing Ok we might get better ways of guessing correctly
And
Within the dynamics of the dynamic get
Be able to actually build this case more effectively but
Since we have not done that yet
The quickest way for us to resolve this and which most probably be the most Dynamic option
Is actually adding a way that you can replace the snippet of code
Targeting the specific
View
So you will never need to really know what is the view
When you do this because they are placeholders
And you need only remember where you at your dynamic
Get
So let me go and illustrate this within the JCB interface
So all I wanted to show you here is that we are actually targeting with this new Dynamic implementation
This little snippet
This area here
We not replacing the whole method
Because really it is it is standard there's not much to do in
Improving that and if we do it will be just improving it for everyone
And the built function it really works well I haven't seen any issues with that
So
At the end of the day it seems like only the parse method
Needed a bit of an improvement
So let's go back to the interface and let me let me show you
Where we can make the changes
To have the the category render correctly
As well as the preacher
This one here as well as the series
...........
............
Basically make the changes so that this will say
Series
And
That this one will say true
And this one
This preacher would also say
Preacher
That's basically all we need to do and then this router
Will work
Without any errors
Ok
So here in the interface you have site views
Now the site views the ones who wanna make changes to his this preacher
The series and the category now I'm gonna show this to you little bit
Long winded but
Bear with me
It's just make sure everybody is on the same page
If you open preacher
You would see that it has a dynamic
Get called
Sermons preacher ID and it say get list query
Ok so
This is the one
We want to change
The get
the dynamic get
As well as speaking about serieses
The same is true of that
We have this
List query get series ID
Sermons that we also want to change
And so we not changing it in the view
The idea was
That if we change it in the dynamic get it automatically
Right to correct code to whatever view you add it because we've added some custom
Scripting
Sorry placeholders within the script
So let's take the first one is this sermon
Where is it
Sermon series
So in custom script we scroll down to the bottom there is now a new
Tab here option here
Add PHP
Parse method in router little bit of explanation there
click yes
And it will Dynamically load
What is what I can consider the most basic implementation of that little snippet
So you see it looks very familiar it's got his place holders
And it has a specific
It has a specific
S View placeholder
That's because we're dealing with the site View
And it has to have this s in it
To replace it with the site view name
So wherever this is gonna be used this this Dynamic get
This
Would be replaced with that specific site view's  value
Ok that's just to give you a heads up
About the place holder and that's what makes it dynamic
So that you can use it in any site view and it will automatically write this
Because really the the display of the page is actually based on the database request
Which is built in the URL by the name of the view
As well as the ID of the element
And if there are multiple variables being passed
To the
URL
You can obviously update that and
Replace multiple values
So
Here we want to within this one
Did the default option here will actually resolve our issue because
Remember these two values were not the same
JCB's Dynamic build actually changed this value to
Sermon instead of
Leaving it
The same
And there is a very good reason
For that
Usually this would be the correct response but in this case because of complexity I'm not gonna explain
It isn't the correct response and so you want these two values to be the same
And it is basically the site view's name
So we could just save it close this
The next one we wanna do is this sermon preacher
And it was also
Having the same issue basically
So we
We gonna do the the same kind of
Just add the the custom
Option
To ensure that these two values remain the same
And then the last but not least was this category
It is also behaving
Incorrectly
And really it's only because it
Didn't detect
That this is actually category
And that is primarily because it is using the Sermon table
To to start instead
In the Sermon table
We have a joint here
too
category
If you can see there
And so it does load the category and
the tweak
You see that we are actually using
This ID
And this is a category ID
So it should actually go look for the category
And
build the parse method based on the category
And so
here
We also gonna Just Add
A true
To this getVar
Which tells the getVar
method that this is actually a category
This this name
In effect is actually gonna be ignored
Because it's gonna not be looking for this tables value is gonna go to the category table
And look for the value there
Ok so this will resolve this this issue
We can save and close this one
So now we have
Done some customisation to our router
Just by adding those
Values to the dynamic get
If we compile our components now
It will automatically fall back
Unto those
Values
Just
install again
And now let's go look at the code
So we see here
That it did exactly what he wanted it added preacher preacher there
And this is now
Categories is true
And
We see the series is series
And so now at least we know that this actual
The router will behave correctly
This is the first step of our improvement to the router
It seems to me that we already have a very workable
Situation and this is really gonna make it too much better
There was also the idea of adding some custom scripting into the built
Method
And we will look at that
And I invite
You and anyone else too
To get involved
On this on GitHub just if you know how to improve his even more
Then please
I get in contact with me and let's let's work together
This is so what we've done so far
But like an all iterative developing concepts
Will continue improving
this
To the point where it really serves as well
And holds up with changes also happening in Joomla itself
Ok well thanks for watching