I would like to give you a explanation
As well as demonstration
Of how JCB deals with Joomla's
Implementation
when regards to creating of
Database tables
As well as updating them or even adding more
Joomla's way of doing this through specific file convention
Within your components file structure
Package
JCB is also been
Designed to actually detect changes in your component development
And create with files for you
The best way to illustrate this is well just let's compile a component
So we have
sermon distributer here
that's gonna compile that for us
And then we'll go to the zip file
Unzip it
Have a look at it
And see those files
extracted here
And inside of this we have an admin folder and inside admin ,a SQL folder
And here is the first file of interest
that's what Joomla uses to actually build a database upon the first install of the component
Do take note that it runs this file only on a fresh install of the component
Thereafter it will not run it again even if that's file gets updated
Even if more values get added and usually it does JCB updates this file as you create new
views which in
Then it means a new table
And if you add Fields which means a new column or field in the database
And so
This file update but it is for those
Clients of yours that it couldn't install the component for the first time all those who already have the component installed
This file will mean nothing to them
All the files in this update folder
Is what would actually be relevant
If you have a client
Which has version
1.3.2 installed
on his system
Any gets this package from you this 2.0.0
Package
It will Actually
Start with
This file
Then that one and so forth
It will start with a
File which is the same
Version as the version that is currently installed on
The Joomla website
So
That means
JCB builds these files
In that expected way
Ok
Now let's go make a change to the component and see how JCB updates these files
Just gonna install the component
So we have it in the database
We can look at the database in the moment
To see how things change
Now I'm gonna open the admin views and I'm gonna add
A field
To the admin View called sermon
Is it gonna be any generic field
So that we can at least see it in action
I'm gonna call it mobile telephone
And
Just put in the fourth position
The left tab that's not really important but
Ok so there we go
We added a field
Now you could it disappoint also add a new view and JCB will detect both of them
And will add both of them to the update file
But
You could even do that
You know
Make this change run the compiler
Have this new update
Then make another change ,run the compiler and it'll follow along
Incrementally
Incrementing the the version
Value of the component
As you go
Just for our sake
Maybe let me add a view
Already in another View
And then you'll see how JCB combines to these values
in one update
So I'm going to grab a
view that isn't already part of this component
And just for illustration
Save and close
There we go we gotta view and it a new field
If we compile the component now
It will
Do all those things that I've explained
There you see it's incremented into 2.0.1
And if we go to the zip file
again extracted open it up admin
Sequel
Updates
we now see there is actually a new file. Let's open this file just
Investigate a little
So we see here's the
Command to actually add that new field
And here is another one
To create
That new table
And all of that is been placed into this
....
2.0.0
File
Which like I said is the current version
Of this installed
Component
If we look at the database at this point
You see there is no
Look table
And if we look at the Sermon table and structure
Then we see that there is you know
No
Mobile field here
Ok so that's install it now and see the change
Ok it's been successful go back to the table
Let's just refresh this
I know you have it
Got field added
if we go back to the new table that it had to create
Scroll down
And there is the new table
So it's done both of those as expected
Secondly let me show you where it made some changes in JCB
To relation to this component
so you'll see that the component has automatically incremented it's version number
If we open this component updates area
You'll see that it has dynamically
Stored that same values that we saw on the file here next to the correct version
And it is actually created a new
Version entry
You have to manually update this URL
As there are too many variations here we couldn't actually implement this dynamically
this URL is what is being used in your updates server file
If your component is set to have an update server file
And so
At this point
You can now continue even adding another view or even another field
and it'll just the same it'll increment it and it will update your database upon installation
And really that is as simple as it is
There are some places where that behaviour may not function as expected
The only one I'm very much aware of is the one that happens when you
Actually import
Or
Export a component from one JCB to another
Those of you that have used this you can export a component and then Import it Again
That effectively creates all the data in the relation to JCB but it does'nt
Recreate the history and the asset IDs and everything else which is related to its
Integration
Within the Joomla
Interface or Database
So that means for example your
There is no history
Regarding the admin views
And the only way to start any history for that View
Would be to open it
And to save and close it
That's the only way
Now that specific area will have a history track
Same goes with the admin views
You have to open them and save them
This one not the admin
view itself but the actual Fields of the admin view
Open them save them again
This will create its first entry and serve as a reference point
To last time to the which those values were changed
If you compile the component at that point it will actually
Add two component ID to that specific entries
And use it as a reference point like I've said
Then having after having compiled it so you first saved them then compile the component
And then only start making your changes
So that you'll basically
Bring the component into the motion of What would be the natural
Flow of development
This natural flow that you would
Create a component add views then add Fields to it all along saving closing saving
And that generates the history values that we actually need
To detect changes
If you import a component none of those values exist and so
It won't behave as expected
Well that's just a heads up I supposed many of you might not even have this issue but
If you do
You will know at least where to look and what to do to fix it
Anyway that is a
Quick overview of JCB's
Implementation
To correspond to Joomla's conventions
In creating tables
And updating them
Dynamically
Through The SQL Files
In the updates folder
And yes I hope that
This is gonna be helpful to to those who may not have understood this before
Thanks for watching