I recently had this
Request on the Forum
By Marco
Regarding some help with Sub forms
How to generate a subform itself writing in JCB
Where to find the XML details in relation to repeated subform fields in View
How the data of the subform is populated
How posted data of a subform is validated
How data of a subform is processed and
Persisted
My assumption is it above is done as part of JCB and would not require manual construction
Of XML files
Googled but found an answer to no avail
Yes
At the moment
We have
Only made tutorials about
I think repeatable fields
And repeatable Fields as such has been discontinued
I don't think I've actually made a tutorial about subforms as yet
So here it goes let's do it
Ok first thing First
Subforums have fields in them that much we know right
So if we gonna go to component for example let's say we open this admin view
We are actually looking at a subform right this is a subform
And each of these little
Fields here is a field in the subform
And actually is only an ID which you need to add to create
the subform so what do you do if your first create what this is a
Custom field
That basically grabs values out of the admin view so this is a custom field this one
You create that one this is a list field
You create list field this is a checkbox so you basically create these Fields First
That's the first thing you do you create a field you wanna use in the subform
So for our purposes I'm gonna use existing fields
I just to sort of demonstrate
Ok so we've got what we have the description mobile number name we got a few Fields here
Ok so
First we wanna create a new field
So I'm gonna
First create
Open that we have both open so I can get the IDs
So then here click new
And basically select subform right
Subform there we go
and it actually populates your XML for you
Now something tells me
That
If you haven't actually looked at all the tutorials
That is available on Google
Sorry on YouTube
Then a lot of this world maybe you not even make sense of what I'm doing where I'm doing it and all that and
So
For those that maybe just seeing this video and not watched any of the other tutorials
Please go to YouTube and type in Joomla component Builder
And try to find the playlist there's old playlist full of tutorials
Start at the top working through way down it so many tutorials many hours that I have spent trying to
Teach
And guide people in using this component and I know those tutorials will make you
You quite able to build amazing things
Ok so I'm gonna just leave this options the option list
This form source if you read here you can add a path to an XML file containing the field
So you can add a custom
A XML file to your component how to add custom files to component hold not a topic it's
It's also possible within your Joomla component to add files and folders all those kind of things
But that means this specific source can still be used but you don't need to
If you
Use the fields
Option then you basically need to remove the source option right only one of them so only the fields
or the field form source
So these are the two options I see it's currently set to mandatory the fields
But
I think you can change that
Going to the field types change that to optional
And then that you can select other Fields or field source form source
I think the compiler will in any case if it detects there is a form source it will behave correctly
here we need to add the IDs so we can come here and I want to have a name
So it's just 199
I just add 199 and a comma
And then let's add something else let's say
Website
So it's 280
And let's do an email as well
Where is it
There's no email here oh there's an email
And it's 100
Ok so we have
That in place we can add a description
We can add a maximum
A filter, a show on, I'm just gonna leave this the validation of these fields
I think
That is an area which I haven't actually looked into
But if I'm correct
And also the reason why they moved away from repeatable fields
Is that every field is validated
On its own merit
So for example
The name field
If you create a name field you're obviously
Saying ok I want this to be a string and it has this filter string
Value
And since this is part of the XML it will be validated on this
I can be mistaken here
And yeah I haven't actually looked at the code so mind that but that's
That's what I anticipate it will do most cases I would say
Anticipate that it doesn't and try and do some custom scripting
I'm not gonna illustrate that now
Are you need to
Actually know little bit more about JCB which there are tons of the tutorials to show you
How to do custom scripting all around it component and even to do custom scripting anywhere and
Any area of the component through the custom code area implementation
So I'm gonna talk more about that now
So
For now we want to
Just
Make sure it got all the spelling right here
Ok good
I'm gonna save this just give it a name
Options and test so I can see it
This obviously I would make
A text
The default means that JCB already
the Store method
.......
it will detect that this is a
Subform
And will add the needed
PHP in storing the file and in loading the file into the form again
So that takes care of that
So you don't need to actually say Json it will
On its own by its default to the correct implementation here so you need to make sure either to click
Text or medium text depending on what this value is gonna be
Anyway I think for 50 text is quite enough
And that's it saving close
Ok
Sorry about that
it will span there
Let's see we got that field here it is I'm gonna just add it to any view for now
Let's see I'm gonna add it to this look View
Just so we can see it in action
now the look view is part of the demo component
So I'm just gonna dump it in here let's see
Above tab full width details
description I think let's just add it there
Details also full width
make it the 2nd
And I say
Options
And then we got a test right
Ok save and close so we've added it to a view
Now I'm just gonna compile this component which the view belongs to
Which at this stage it is demo
and install it
Now let's go open that component
And let's open a look
And here we go name enter name here enter website address enter email
We click there
And our values are there
Let's just save one Hi
Children
We can do I think that's the only one that's
Oh yes you do have
Let's do that and why enter those values and then some
Value
Sorry
And I'm just gonna grab this
up here
paste it in there few times
Just gonna put here
Joomla@ VDM.io
Put that in here
To get sort of a feel for it
Ok save
Ok it's safe to values it loaded it back it's done all of that Hi
There
then save and close
and so
If we open it again
It shows it up again
And now we can shuffle it
Let me just put
Number for a Top
Save it close
And open again
And so it is loading it also correctly
Ok well that's a quick demonstration
Marco I hope this helps
And getting you able to use subforms
With JCB
It's as easy as that
Thanks for watching