Great news
I think the option that we've
Put in place especially for those of you that have really purchase some JCB packages
Like the demo
Advanced demo component or the Sermon distributor component
This will be excellent news so let me demonstrate what we've
Done
And also makes suggestions
Of future
Changes
On the import components area now
There is an extra tab
And with this tab you can now easily
Import
Paid or free
Components
That
We actually
distribute.
It's called the VDM packages so it took of moment to load it it does take a while because
it actually queries
At the moment it queries GitHub
And check and gets a list of all the latest packages
So if we
You know updated GitHub it will automatically
show then the new packages
Here
So
And we will be adding more free options
I, we are planning to to add some more free packages here the moment there is only 2
To really most of them are paid
So you could
You can buy any of these packages and use it
in anyway you like
So
The Hello World is free and the demo version
here is free but you could, yes you can actually get any of these and if you
You're ready purchased a sermon distributor version
you can just select
it here
Because you know JCB is constantly improving
And so Sermon Distributor
is also improving
And so we making changes to
To sermon distributor and if you wanna update yours or even if you have played with it and you wanna reset it
But know remember
If you got a reset it it will reset everything in
Including every field and even
Field types
So
Do
Keep that in mind
That if you
install this package
Over the existing
one
It will revert everything
Back what is great though
Is that Joomla obviously keeps
history right
If you put your history on for the JCB component so that means you could actually take a step back and some of those every
If you want it
Anyway that's just a little
Side note so you basically select the package you want to install and then click on get package
This will take a while as it's downloading it from GitHub please make sure to read all these things I didn't even now
Trough that but
you should read
All of these packages are fully you know all that
Is written there
So you end up at the page which
We usually would
Shows you who made the package
If you still didn't get the
key
you could click on this link here
To actually go buy the key
And get it
For any of the other packages
as well
Or before getting here there's a there's a link
That says By packages you could also click on those and then
select the package you like
Here it'll show you the component that is actually being in
Stalled
which is says here is sermon
Distributor
2.0 2.0.2
Which is the latest version
And
You then add your key here
Which I will do in a moment
And then click continue
Which then makes it
Install
We added this new switch here quiet
And some of your
Releases that might be a spelling mistake like
This one here which is Quite
But we fixed it and
We did push out
The the fix
For this
Which means in
JCB 7.8.1
Possibly
2.7.
O oh sorry 2.7.1
Come on
We'll have this typo fixed
Anyway what this does
Is it give the option to see exactly everything it does JCBs
Importing on the package
So the actually tells you what ID was changed to what ID
It doesn't give you the names just give you ID references so gives you a lot of more
Sort of insight of what happened
Which is obviously used for when something doesn't go right you could click on this so usually it's set to quiet
you don't really wanna see all that detail you just want to know it's done but if you wanna see the detail you basically
click yes
And here if you want to overwrite existing
Data
You see how the force location update works
Is if it finds an item
And that item is
Newer
Then the one
That is
Being imported then it
Drops the import option
And it keeps the newer version in your system
So if you click here that's how usually works with the force local update to
No if you change this to
Yes
Then it will ignore the time stamp completely
And update the item irrespective whether it is newer or older or whatever
Ok so that's that
So we're at the ID and then we click
Continue
I'm gonna pause the video from home as you want to see the ID
And there you have it
So it gave me a very detailed
Print out so when it didn't find when it founded
It says it founded and then it updated it
But if it didn't find it it will actually say that ID so and so in field
Was changed to ID so and so
And it's been
Imported so there is the list
Of everything he
Did
Yeah it's quite a long list
I'm Scrolling
Ok and then the bottom it says great if that's what you would usually see
Just that
So
All of The Rest
It actually just
Showed you because we ticked it
Not to be quiet so now was Sermon Distributor imported
Now you can open at look at it
Basically it's
Should have all the data here
The licensing might have changed so just add another licence here and then
Save and
Close
And then you can actually compile it as easy as that
So Sermon Distributor
click compile
And
Then once it's compiled obviously then you have the Joomla package so what this does
It also included the
The external script with
Is also the sort of a
Demonstration of actually
The adding external scripts
So it's grabbing it from GitHub.  You can go and look at that.
It is simply a script that checks
For mime types
And it tells you that first time very
Detailed in there after you only see
This
And only if it changes when will you see
Something like that again
Ok so you can click here on install
And now if you go to components there it is Sermon Distributor
Fully mapped
Well all functional
JCB
Has Built This by importing it first from our GitHub repository and
then you're able to adapt it and
Use it in
Anywhere you like
Anyway yeah that is the
The new feature I wanted to sort of demonstrate
I hope you like it
What the suggestion is at the moment we can
Just go back there for a moment
Importing components
The suggestion is to have even a 5th tab
So there will be
This tab VDM packages and then a
Community tab
like over here
Which
Those of you in the community
Good one to share
Free
Components
We could add that in here
And we still thinking about the paid
You know share sharing paid components
Yeah we still think about how that could
Work
Of course at the moment it shouldn't become
Too complicated because if you if you
click on anything
And then click get package
That package
It's has it
Internal
The variables
Which actually
decides the
What this values going to
Be right
So if we would
Click this value
It takes you to my shop
Where you then purchase that
specific product
Ok
So
That is a valued
Determined by the package
Which means it shouldn't be that hard for us to actually include paid options paid components
What is a little bit of a challenge
Is whether JCB should actually ask for a little bit of a
Yeah contribution
To support a project in this
Way
so we still discussing that anyway anyone have a suggestions please post it here at the bottom of the
Video make comments
Tell me what you think
The end of day
We wanna make sure that the community
can use this
In long run that it becomes
a nice tool
I'm even thinking of moving this option this whole getting to
Importing of components
To an actual tab
On the desk
on the dashboard
So you can get to this page without having to first go to
Components and then
Click through here
So there is even that kind of discussion but just for now we wanted to demonstrate the new feature it's
It's actually been able to
do that already
We just didn't have that extra tab but you could have copied
The links to those packages on
GitHub and have imported them that way that's
Should basically what
what the ReadMe files would have shown you if you purchase any of these keys. Ok well thank for watching again. and speak to you again.