I would like to
Introduce you to a feature that we've been working on for quite some time now
And I'm very sure it will
Come as a surprise to some of you that actually can do this
Most of the features already existed
For quite a while
It's just that
I've been
Trying to make it
Stable so that
It will work well
And in doing so I had to extend it a bit
So I wanna
I wanna look at this feature
It actually has three
Two or three concepts which maybe is best if I explain that
So what is this all about
Ok
It's about adding
Dynamic
Files
Folders
Or even external
Files
Which maybe is on a website
Or
On GitHub
And you want to
Get the content from that file and add it
Maybe as code
Or even as a file
To your
system
So
Here's the thing
I'm working with components that is pulling data from all over the place
And so
Most of these features are really what what I've been needing to
Get projects going
And
Trying to save myself
Time
That I don't need to
Copy paste and move things around to ensure that it's a correct copy being used and on compilation
And JCB itself is maybe one of the best
Explanations
So let's look at this
You know that there is a feature
But you can add files
And folders
This feature is like I said it's always been there
But currently
I have expanded this
By adding an advanced tab to this feature
It's got this basic which is the normal one
Which if you watched some of the previous tutorials the older tutorials
I do actually explain
How this works
And how you get these files and I'm not gonna go into that
There is now a new area called advance
Sorry I had to just quickly update that note for us
Advance area now
Is able to
Grab
Files from anywhere in your system
An added to the component
Now
It can be files outside of the root
Directory of your Joomla website
Just being sure
That
The PHP
Which usually is a php has permission
Has the right to the file and can read it
So this is just the only thing
But for most cases
We won't need to grab files outside of the Joomla root directory because we actually
Maybe just editing a custom script
Custom file
Inside of our Joomla
Component which we've created
But this file or
This folders are not
Generated by JCB
So we want those files
Where they are actively running inside of our component
We want them to be
Basically taken and put into the package without us having to move it around
That's what this featuring will now do
So you can like a I'm doing here
I you can use constants
You'll see there's a little note here that tells you that
That you can use constant paths and the full path
Directly without quotes that means
You don't need to do
You know like in PHP you know you do something like that wait no not
And you put this part in quotes right like that
Well you don't need to do any of that
You put the constant directly
Like that and
The compiler will deal with this
And make it right
So
That you can do also with folders as well as with files
And then
You obviously need to still set the target path and relation
To the ZIP package
So you have folders
Called admin
But as you can see here I'm actually doing
A folder called libraries
And
That means I am targeting a
A folder which isn't actually
Usually part of a package
you know a component package
But because I want that folder to be installed with my component every time
And I don't want to do actually have a separate
A package for
For this library
I've actually
Improved JCB to include this
Package
Which is basically if you guys go look at this
You see that is It's basically a
Composer
file and I'm including some
Classes there which we are now using in JCB
And I'm moving it
Every time with each install
Into its place
Now
That might be
I'll sort of convention I suppose
But there is neither rules against it I think in
Yeah so
That's what we're doing
What's nice though is that when JCB detects that you are not targeting the normal Admin
Or
Media
Image folder or site
Those are the normal folders
Then
oh wait not
Image folder is neither is that normal
But did you got your three that is site admin and Media If If JCB detects you're
gonna be moving content
Into a folder that's not part of the
Expected package component package folders
It will actually add a little script
To the script install
So that it all move this folder into its correct place
On upon installation of the component
Or whether the component is updated
So you can go look at that
In fact I can show you just briefly
So here I got the component open
The Script file for component Builder
I'm gonna scroll down it's obviously a huge file
But here at the bottom we know have this new little script
It's named a little weird so it doesn't conflict with any other method in it at anytime
And basically
It gets the
The details from the above methods
And then it checks whether
The folders obviously it gets there the dynamic install folder
It checks whether there is more than one
And
Then
If it's
One of these it ignores it because those already being deal dealt with by Joomla
And if it isn't
It actually moves it into it's correct place
Now this is a dangerous featuring
As you can see here I'm saying you must use this with caution because you can literally
Grab
With this new function
Any
Thing anywhere from your Joomla website and overwrite
It anywhere
On the
Users installation website
Which could be problematic
And
Something you shouldn't do
Unless you are
You know unless it is your right to do so
Ok so this is the new feature in in doing dynamic
Movement of folders
And files
What's make this all so nice if you're using these constants in your naming of your paths
And you export and import this component into another Joomla website
Then
I mean as a JCB package right
If you export a JCB package and you imported at another JCB install
It actually remaps these files it actually export them
Remaps them and move them back into place on the other install
Which
Really makes it very comfortable in you know working in a team and you wanna have these
Is files always be the same everywhere
This is so gonna be very helpful for that
I can also
Obviously because of the feature
I give you the heads Up
But if you import a package
From anyone
And and you do not know or you do not trust them
they could actually move files
Through this method into your system
And is therefore part of first security which you need to consider
With whom you are sharing packages
Anyway
So this is so some of the
Feature regarding the new folder implementation folder and file implementation
The other aspect which I mentioned earlier
Were you actually able to get content from anywhere
Works as follow
So anywhere in any custom area of JCB
Where you can actually add custom script
You can also now used to this external code
Snippet
Now this could be a URL
Or it could be a folder inside of your system
This folder does not yet work with
With Constance I should actually make it that it does
And it actually needs to be the exact for the path of the stage
But the reality is that with this external code
Concept
You can take
For example
variable
From a
Gits snippet let me let me show you
So here I have what
I've called fancy date
Which is basically a few functions static functions
Which are not wrapped in the class yet so it's basically outside of a class
And why because I want to include it
Into my
Helper class
With the snippet
So
That I can have others work with me on this code on GitHub
And
If any changes be made to this code it automatically updates my system
Now I know that there is some question of security in doing so
But we've added a few little
Tricks in the compiler
They actually notify you
If there's been a change to the code
So what that means is the first time you use that snippet
To include this
Snippet that you've got here
You obviously do something like
Raw
And then here I have basically a text file
So you'd grab that URL
An add it like this
You can take away
The actual because currently
It is bound to a specific version
Which obviously
If anybody makes a change to the snippet
You won't get the new version
Well that's the way of locking it in
But if you wanted to have it be Dynamic you can actually remove a part of this
I think it's this part
Let me just check
Yeah that's right
Then you can use it like that
Now this specific piece of text that you see here
Will dynamically be added to my component
Let me demonstrate
So here I've opened component Builder
in it's back end
I'm gonna scroll I've gone to this libs and helpers tab I'm gonna scroll down
To this area which is called
Admin class so I just do in the admin area so that's easily
Detectable
I'm gonna add that snippet like that so it says external code
With the path of the URL
And
That's it I'm gonna save and close
Then let's go to the compiler
Now what should happen
Is that the moment you've compiled this it should tell you
That you've added
This kind of external code to your component
If it doesn't tell you that then something's wrong it should tell you the first time you've add the snippet
Because it actually creates a hash
Of that snippet
So that in the future if it changes
You get notified
So when we grab the snippet from
Github
An anybody in the middle you know tampers with it
It will notify you that the snippet was changed now if you know that it should have changed because
You made a change to the gits
you know snippet or someone else in your team did
That obviously you'll be expecting that
But you could still for safety sake go check in the code of the component
Where the snippet is being added to ensure that it is actually still accurate
So I'll show you that
Let's compile this
So we see two messages that are relevant to the issue at hand
This one is a new message which I'm not gonna go into now
But it's basically dealing with that
That is actually detected
That
Remember we said we have this folder we
Pulling inside of the
Library folders
And Everytime You'd compile
You actually tell you that
You tell you
That it is detected it and it's added The Script to the script
PHP
So
Yeah I wasn't gonna explain it I did
Anyway so that's what that is about but this first line here
Is showing you the snippet
And it's telling you there's been added for the first time
And that you should be investigate to insure the correct code string was used
So you should go
To the place where in JCB the sorry in the package
The compile package where this should have been added
Go and check that it is the correct
That what you see here on GitHub
The string here
Is also what you gonna see in the code
That's the first thing
Every time there after it should give you this little message here
And it should tell you how many code strings are being added to this component as an external code
And to avoid shipping your component with malicious code string always make sure that the correct code string values
Were used
Now I did tell you that if we did take the change it will also notify you so
First let's go do what it said here
Let's go check that it is to correct code
Because I'm in the ZIP package
So we see that this the library folder been added
we gonna go to the admin area helpers and then open
Component Builders helper
File which is where I added the snippet right
So let's just open that
And then
Here we have it
fancy date
And fancy datetime
So
Basically from here
To here
Was taken from GitHub and put inside of the component
Now I'm gonna go make it change to the snippet
on GitHub
I'm gonna just do something small
So that we can see what happens if it change is made
To this code
And how JCB response
I'm just adding this
New little string here saying change was made
And I'm updating this public
Gist
So it now tells us that it's been revised for a second time
And a change was made
Now let's compile the component without doing anything else just make the changes here on GitHub
Then go back to the component and compile it
So here we are
Selecting version
Compile
I can see I will have the maybe add some space in between the messages here
Doesn't always seem clear enough
That the messages are not related to each other like
Here it's showing that other message again like it said it would
But you might miss that
So
I think I'll have to look at that anyway
Here in the warnings area
We see this
We see that
It has changed
Since the last compilation
Please investigate
To ensure that changes safe
That means
JCB is automatically detected
That the snippet that you originally added has actually been updated
At this point we anticipated that so
If we go and look at the code
We see that it just added this little part here the change was made
And the rest of it is exactly the way we want that
And so everything is fine
It's a change we anticipated
So we know that nobody else has tampered with the script
And neither was there a man in the middle attack
An in any case
If there is someone tampering with the script
It will end up as a string here
So let's say they put something in here it will
it'll do
Something like that whatever they put in
And you will see this error
In your file
So that's
Basically how it will play out
But in the actual reality JCB will detect that
It will see that the hash for the script is changed
And it will notify you with that message
I'm gonna do my part and trying to make sure that it's more obvious you won't miss that message
But that anyway when you use this kind of implementation
It is not the most ideal implementation it's just that sometimes we want included an
external value in our component
Which is dynamically changing
And
And we wanna do it without really thinking about all the time
And this is what this feature is ideal for
I'm so use it with caution and
You know know what you doing
Or don't use it at all
So that was a quick overview
Of the new
Folder file
Inclusion
As well external code
Features which I really trust would be useful to you
It's powerful tools so I realize
There are the danger of it being abused
But at the same time
I think component development works upon reputation and if you wanna have a good
reputation in the community
You shouldn't do anything that will hurt others
Or damage their
Contribution
And their applications
but you should steer
Within the parameters of your own component
And your own implementation and any case because people are gonna look at your code they are gonna
unzip your package they are gonna see
If you're doing things that are not
You no good they're gonna notice that and your reputation will get hurt
And that's the last thing you would want
When you're developing components for Joomla
Anyway thank you for watching