Ok let's do this
We want to add a
File
Field
to a component
And upload a file
So
I
I'm gonna use this demo component
it got a few admin views who got the areas
Look
I got a site view looks
And looking
I'm gonna add this field to do look
Admin View
But I first need to create the field
And
We need to sort of look at
The steps that will need to implement
Currently JCB doesn't out of the box actually
Address this
We might think of doing this
Maybe in
The future but
Because of some of the security risks
It's actually best you do this yourself
Because then
At least you're under
Control
And the risk is
Really yours
And not
put anyone else at risk
Ok
So you're uploading a file
The field you wanna use already exists
In
field types
So if you go to field types
There is a field called
File
See where is it
Must be in the next one
Yeah we go
File
Now this
Obviously
Everything in here
Was taken
From
Joomla's documentation
So it shows you a whole lot of attributes their values some of the descriptions
But also shows you where to actually get more info on this
And so it's always good
To actually do that
Ok so here we are
Scroll down
And there is the file field
So
It actually now has this new except
Perimeter
Which is a nice little
Extra which wasn't available when I first set it up
So if yours doesn't have it
You see that I
Actually
Have
Since added it
It's not showing up here
Ok so
Might
As well add it now then
So you're under size let's add that new attributes
So it's accept
The value I'm gonna leave it to be in image and can be changed
let's give it some information
as regarding
description that
just copy that
and place in here ok so
We got this new attribute set
Those of you running the latest
Release of JCB
Might already have this there it only gets added if you do a fish install
It doesn't update the database with these values
Ok great
save and close
So we got a file types set
If we go to files now
And we can
Create a new file
Sorry field
Files I mean
Field
And we select the file
Come on
You see that it gives you the
Information
And there is that new
Attribute
Available to us
And you'll see that it's also showing up here
And so this is the beginning
Of actually setting up
The
File field type
to your component
I'm just gonna call this file
And
Then here we can just say
File
Well let's call it image
Here we say, Choose an image from computer with maximum 100Kb
And most of these other values we could actually take away
we will come back to this
Once we've added to the component and started looking
at
some of the other things that must be done because this is only step A they are actually
3 steps to take
Of which this is the easiest
So we have here
Image
don't need to say that just save and
Close ok now we go to our admin View
And that's this
Look I'm gonna go directly to it fields
So I could add that
File
Field type
I'm a little bit
chunt in here so I'm gonna
Zoom out a bit
Ok
Where will I place this
There are
Two tabs
I think let's do it in the more area
At the bottom here
More
And
Image and we'll see there are quite a few files here
Image
Think it should say
file ,here we go
And
That should do it
Let's make it full width
For now
And then one
there is just one and save and close so now
If we
should open the admin View
We should see the new
Field has been added
And it is said to being in the full view
Sorry full width of the
The tab
In the more tab
And
We could actually now compile the
Component
As a beginning to see ok how it will work out
compile it
And then
Install it
Then have a look at it
It say create a new demo
Go to more
So here we see
The file
So it's telling us
File one Ok we have a problem here
We've got two
Fields with the same name image
So I'll have to go change this
go back
I'm gonna uninstall this
Is gonna be the easiest way to do that
And then go back
To the fields
because it's the
Last one I'm created
End
Image
And lets change this
to
Banner
Think that'll be ok
Not the type
Ok so I think we'll use banner
and we'll call this also banner so it stays the field type is file but will use the
Label banner
and save and close
Now let's try again
You know if you have
Two of the same fields
Meaning exactly the same name
JCB automatically calls the one
image one the other one image two
And doing that is not good practice it usually doesn't come out right in
Events
especially with history
Because it is only tracking one field right
And
When it actually checks the history that field name doesn't match any field
So
So when it comes to the history and updating of the database
Automatically as you add new fields
Using the same field multiple times is not recommended ok
So let's try this again
And then install it
Now if we go and have a look
We should see a different
Reality here great
Banner
Its got all the necessary information
Obviously this is set
in your server
Tells you that
And now you can click here and select a
Image
So I'm gonna do that
So I got this autumn tree forest that I've selected
And
Need to add a name and some
That seems to be all I need to do and then save and we have a problem
Now as
A little glitch that
None of you should have I
Tampered with some of the
Validations
In a previous
tutorial
Anyway
Now I fixed it and
As you can see
When I saved the item
It actually
Didn't upload anything
So the file is not in my system
And that's where usually
All of you would sort of
End up ok so you've used file
you've
Selected the
Banner whatever you wanted to upload
And it just nothing happened and that's because
There needs to be a server side
Which needs to actually validate the file
Move the file and check the file and everything
Make sure that it's a correct file
Secure the file
And then place the files path back
Into this
Field
When it puts the value in the database
And it's that process which is to be custom coded
Ok so let's go back to our component and let's do it
One of the things I like to do before I actually start coding anything is really look
Under the hood look at what's going on especially if it's the first time I'm doing it so
So since many of you this might be your first time I'm gonna show you someone how this is done and it's
Like inspecting what's going on Under The Hood and how can I use it
So I'm gonna open this item again and I'm going to again select our
Image
And then having the image selected I'm gonna go to the code
So I know where the code is for this website right so I'm gonna go into my editor and I'm going to the
Admin area office component and of this
View
Model
Into where it actually saves the values so Follow Me Follow Me There
So here we have the component wait not this one that one the Joomla Mount
An administrator components demo
And then models and look
I wanna go there
Double click we gonna open and you could just go to almost the bottom of the file somewhere there
Look for the save
Method
Function really
That's where we wanna sort of poke because
It's at this point where all the data from the browser is available to us
And we should be able to access it now you could write the helper class and put it in your helper function
And use the same uploading sort of
Class if you want to reuse it but you could also scripted writing here and
I'll show you how to do it that way
Obviously I like reusing scripts so the helper class Idea is more appealing because I put it there and everywhere I
use this field
Type
for file uploading
I just also use this helper class to deal with moving the data and using it
Ok so for now
What we gonna do is we gonna var dump some values just to the screen
When we click save in the UI to see what happened so
Let's do that
So basically two
One is the actual data that is available here and the other is this we getting the
Input
And I'm gonna
Check in files what do we have there
In the input of the application and if so Ok we can save this changes then
Go back to the
The website
And basically just click save
Ok so now we got a a dump now if yours doesn't look like this it might be because you do not have
XdD bug install on your server
You would then want to add some sort of
Formatting
Something like this
Echo
pre some like that should do it
Just to sort of add some formatting that it doesn't bulge into one line
Ok I don't need that I've got XD bug so it does it for me
Ok so now we here we have the data and we see that our
Where is it
Banner B it's not even the data list but that's ok
Just crawled down you see we dumped a different set of data and it actually
if we scroll a little
We'll see that has a protected value called  jform name type temporary
Name error size
All that information then in the temporal name and has
The actual file name
Banner with its temporal occation so it creates a temporal
location for the file
It tells us type is image jpeg and also gives us the file name
And so this is the array would you want to actually get hold of and
With whom you would want to yes make changes
Move that image
Give it it correct name back after validating it and doing whatever sanitation is required
And then saving that value back into the banner data position
Which should be in this first array here but it is
It isn't there
But it should be here
So you should actually just create it
Ok so going back to the code let's do some of that
There is a nice
Get function here
We can just say  jform if you remember that was where the data is and if we want all the values back
as an array or that it should be null if there is none existing
So we gonna save that and then
Just upload the file again to see
You know how does it look now
Have to do it again because of previous values are actually gone
So we'll click save again and there we go we've get a little different array
But more useful
An easier to parse
And now we can take the next step to actually check the this array exist
There is a function already or a class in Joomla which already does
All of this for you
In fact I would say let's go look at that and let's just copy some of those functions
In fact that's copy the function and adapted to our needs and just put it into
Our our class so in components you go to the
The
Installer then the model and then uninstall
and scroll down till you see one that says get package from
upload
I think what it says yeah get package from upload
This is the function which is really ideal for the task
It takes care of a lot of sanitizing it has lot of error checks in it and it should
Should be
Yeah it should be useful for us in this case we'll obviously take some stuff
away and add our own little messages so we don't depend on the installer
Messages so we'll just copy this whole function all the way up there
just control copy it go to look our class
And for now I'm just gonna paste it in here above
So there are some key things I would like to change here for example
I'm thinking let's
Let's change a function name and we call it
My
Upload function
For now
And
We we gonna pass it the input
So we don't want that
To be done twice
And
We know the this is gonna to be jform and we definitely don't want to have raw
Because it's an image We want this to be array
So we can actually check the values
And then
This looks fine
We can say here
Upload
Sorry up
load
ing
of images
Not
Available no wait and set uploads are not enabled in PHP that seems fine
Ok we can actually take these messages and put them in here because JCB is gonna grab this
Once we put it into our component
and gonna add it to all language files for all component in this is really wanna make sure that that happens
We don't need the Zlib because we not gonna unzip anything
So we could actually move this part
Now there is gonna check where we actually got a file set of files here so
It's got a check wither that
User file is an array
And if it's not it want to say no file was selected or
a file was uploaded so we can just type that in
If at this point we detect any errors we basically want to
You know erase those errors and actually break out of this upload
So let's see
Upload error warning upload error
I suppose we need to go look at these language strings in the
Language file of the installer to correctly translate these
For now I'm not gonna do that so I'm just gonna say error
You can you know do that on your own
Ok now what we wanna check here is our
Upload size you want to make sure that our upload size is what we expected
Is the maximum upload size too small in the php.ini and that's really
What happening here and so again it will give an error saying
File too large
there we go the same here
It's checking again this time it's first checked whether it's in the INI files here it actually check the file size
that there is a file size
And so we can again say
Upload error again you should just check what is the actual file language string
And replace that with the English version here
Ok then
We build appropriate path
We take the filename create the path we used create this temporal
SRC which is source path
And then we
Move the file with the
Jfile upload
Now at this point the file is being uploaded to the server
And they are still validation still to do in our
Script what we actually
Just grabbed from the uploader class
We do this unpack now we don't need unpack we wanna do some other things here
Which are
More appropriate for our purpose
First thing I'm gonna
Actually move the get classes function up a few lines
And also make sure to have the folder class actually available in case
Then I'm going to clean the name
So that it is everything is fine and well it anywhere later we might not have any issues
Ok so then we still have what we did here before
This actually is going to be replaced with little function
Which I sort of started writing called
Check upload I'm gonna change this function as one of my own
Sort of functions which I've already adapted
For other projects and
The past
Like you've seen
we already move this one out
That one can stay like that
So
over here
We are going to just do a little check-up to actually make sure that the package
Which we are actually going to
Give back and which were used to store in a database and all the rest is actually you know
Ok
So here we just gonna grab the result of this which basically gonna be true or false and we gonna check
If it's False we gonna say
No some that I did upload
Failed ok
And
Then
If we still going
We going to actually do this check
So now we've got this check upload in place
And we first gonna get the format from the file
And then we going to use a little
Custom script here to validate our format
I've got a
In my component I usually set formats that I allow
So it's a global
thing
That means
In your component you would have to actually go in and add config
Drop down
With a list of
Allowed
Formats now
To sort of sidestep that in
Instead of trying to
Explain all that
I'm just going to go and remove this
Function here you could
You know pause this and copy that down if you know what I'm talking about but then in
That case
You don't need to pause this you know how to type it
I'm so I'm gonna remove that
And just add
You know some format was I think ok I'm ok with this JPG
I'm ok with that format and I'm also gonna be ok with
jpeg
Ok obviously
Add the dot there
And
Maybe gif let's see or wait
png
And then gif
So those are the formats that I'm
Gonna say yeah
Those are fine of course because it's really the file extension that we are checking here right
So we not gonna use a global value here we just going to use the file format
Allowed file formats
And then here would basically gonna check
Is this file format in this array
If it's not
We gonna say
Invalid file
Format
And there we go and is gonna error out but with this error out we will
Need to do some house cleaning
So
We will have to look at that at the moment
So what I think I'll do is I'm going there also passes the destination of where we've moved the file
And
Then
Because that's where the file currently is right
So here we got the temporal destination which is really
In the temporal path the temporal folder of the Joomla website it's not where we want to end up
It's just where we gonna keep the file until we happy that it's safe and so
Ok we got it in the temporal destination we moved it up there
And now we checked if something happened yet fine
Do check the upload
And
Here
If we now
Find
That this
Actual file
Is
Problematic we gonna have to remove it
So we gonna have a little new little class here
And then we gonna say remove
let's say file
I think that's right
And we gonna write this little remove file in a moment
Ok so let's say for our reason you'll see here I've got a lot of
Validation whether the user actually has permission to upload stuff
Now that again I'm I'm gonna remove that from now because
Yeah
It's gonna be a little bit Beyond the scope of what we're explaining
Now
I want to pass a package back
Which
We are happy with
Saying
This is actually where our file is
And what its name is
And
So we gonna just do that
So that's the directory
And that is the package name
And we gonna
Pass that back
As the package
We could
Since we've got the
Format
And maybe you wanna store that
We could also add that to the array
So
There we go everything is good
The package name directory path as well as the format and will return that back
As the package
And we give that back
To the model
The save function
Is going to call this so in the save function we gonna call
This
here oh yes and we said
We are going to
Has it
The input
Field
The input value since we're really getting it why get it again so we gonna pass that over here
See something like
That ok
That looks good
So
Now all that needs to be done is over here instead of this
Function
We can now do
The following
This
My upload function
And the input
there we got
So
I will actually end up with that package
information right in this variable
And we can then just exit out to see how that will look
And even if we've got some typo errors here
Oh yes we still need to create remove file if we have a problem
Ok so why do we need to remove the file
Well all the way up till here the files is actually not on the server
It is somewhere in memory
Somewhere in limbo
And
If something happens
And we returned False here we don't need to do anything it's not really anywhere it's just gonna
Disappear
Same with it
Happening here or there
Or any of these other areas before here
But the moment we do this
We are actually moving the file to the server
And it is now if that is true it is on the server
And so when we pass the destination and the filename here to check upload
We ready have the file on the server
And so if we then discover that this file is not legit we don't want it we must remove it
Or any other checks we do
Even if it's something more complicated than this
You must remove it
Because it's on the server
And so our little remove function I'm trying to save a some
Some
Unnecessary
things
I'm gonna also snipper it up a bit because we're ready up here
We got the classes for the file in a folder so we don't need to load that again
We going to pass it the destination
Which is the folder
And
We gonna
That's gonna be fine
So
All of us we are able to
Actually
clear out the name we don't need this we just need to package name
So here we gonna ask is it a file
Then delete then if there's something not right we gonna do clean path and just check
Again and delete in this should remove
The file
From
The server
You can test that if something's wrong just Google it
And
Tweak it but this should be ok
So we gonna basically pass it
The destination path
Which is the one to where we moved it
Remember
up here
So that's the same path we are passing all the way down to the remove
Function and then
It will clear it out for us
And if everything is fine and it doesn't need to
We gonna continue on and then pass it back here
to the package
Which will be returned
to our
Save
Method
So all of this code that I just wrote here now I'll take it and dump it on GitHub as a gist
So you could go there I'll give the
link to it but if this is Quickly coded I mean
I'm sure that you could improve it
We copy it and pasted stuff from other
You know other classes
To sort of get this working but there's nothing really to extravagant here the only thing
that we didn't go into his exactly what does clean do and what does apply do and
Those kind of things but you can obviously go through the Joomla libraries and
Check exactly what does it do
But for the most part it's just generic
php
Functionality
And so yes
That it would be enough
To actually upload the file
So let's give it a spin
So we back over here if we
Click on this it will actually take us out of the
Item so we can just click the back there then name
And we would have again to select the actual image so there we have the the image
And we can click save
And see what happens oops we gotta bounce of errors here
Ok let's see undefined index undefined index we've got trouble
Let me go see why
Ok so I didn't pay close
attention here I'm just gonna do another var dump
So I can get the exact way to sort of most possibly need to do a for each
It might want to upload more than one
But
Or we could force it to just use the first I think I wrote something about this
Already somewhere let me just check
Think this should do the trick
If it's an array we just wanna grab the first value out of the array
If you got multiple
Fields
That are uploading files
In the same view you gonna have to change this little chunk here
Because then you gonna have to deal with each of those
Files
In a for each loop inside of this function
Which basically would mean you could
Skip all these as they are Global to everyone of them and then from about
Yes from about here
You would add a for each loop
Because you would
Ok and then here you won't Echo well you won't break out you just grab the error into an array
Which you would have eventually then pass
More
Targeting each specific package
Really
And then return
Here
All the successes as well as the errors and handle it somewhere else
So since we just uploading one file I'm not gonna
You know
Do all that just gonna grab that
First
Value and we gonna work with that first value in that should do it
Ok let's go back and try again
Save
Again we have a problem
Not user files
User a file
Sorry
user a file
It become so
Little
Changes like that can
Throughout errors ok
And at last we actually have
The file on the server
What I had to do is had to take away these points here I had that one
part wrong so it won't need the actual point actually
be without it and you'll see that now there is our file in our temporal folder it is actually on
The server and and also we have the path
And we have the name
And all those things
In fact
Everything now is
Is good we can now move the
File
To its final location now we could deal with moving the file
To its final location
Here in our
Save class
Or we can again have another
Function
Which we passed this
Value to which then moves the file to where we would want every image
File to go
Ok let me quickly type that out. So here in our package
We've got the file name so that's
Really important
And we got the full path which is where the file currently is
And what
It's format is.
We could actually have more values in this if we wanted we could do something like this
Instead of just passing
That user a filename
And name
pass it the whole
The whole array
Like that and then here we change that to archive
And
Then here we do
that
Which actually means we've got this array
to our
You know it's available
So instead of doing check we can then do
Package name
And then
dir
And
Format
Return the archive package
Now we'll have all the information which we actually were using even up
Here will have all of that information to our disposal
Of coarse also need to
change this
to
that
Well you know what the name is already there
so instead of package name
We can just be satisfied with the name
Ok and then we could call this
full
Full
path
Yes
So that'll be there in any only information that we are adding which is really new with these two values
So we can just do that
And now our array looks full
It's got the type the temporal original temporal
obviously that's no longer there
Any errors that might have come up
The size of the
File the full path and the format
So we got all those information to to use now at the end of the day the only information we really gonna
Keep is up to us
We could decide to keep the size of the file
We could decide to keep it format it's really up to us
And really
I'm not gonna go into how to deal with all that we just have one
Name
Field
How will you say a column
In the database called Bana
In which we are to place our final
Information and that information should be a
You know the path in in relation to
The image folder
Where we have
Placed this
This file
So first
I'm going to get some constants to use I like
Using this route
As that is
Always going to be the root path
To our website
And then next actually add
Just the path to the images
It's where we going to place our image
So I'm gonna copy this
So we going to just
Add
The path the relation to the root folder to the banner
In the database
Now
You do realize that this is actually just for you it's so that you know where the file is later
You will then on the front end of the site where you gonna use this value
You have to
When you get the value from the database you'll still need to create
The
Actual image html tag
To actually load the image or whatever you gonna do with this file
You're gonna still have the code that nothing of that's gonna be done
you gonna just at least have the path to exactly where the file is because you're storing it that way in the
Banner
Column that's the field
Ok
And now here we taking the root path
And that exact value
And we are moving
The full path which we build-up here right which is the actual current destination
We are going to move it from the full path to the Final Destination
And that is really yet
At this point
We got the image on the server
And
We are moving it to the correct location
And we are storing the value
In the database
And we've done with saving and uploading the actual value
As
Yeah that would be all that's required
Now
In any of these steps
You might wanna be more
Do some more things be more secure be more validating
Because it's not only images your obviously going to be uploading if you uploading PDF
If you uploading other kind of content
You gonna have to do some Googling to anywhere in these steps
Especially in this check upload area
To do the correct validation because at this point the file is on your server
And you need to make sure that it's the right file
Now this isn't
Airtight
Because this really just
Checks that the files type
Is one of these
The extension
It doesn't actually valid data
File to really being an image
They are more
Secure ways to
To do that
But some of them are little bit more
Yeah if you do use them the server side
You know
If your application is gonna be running
And shared environments
Then it will cause problems because in some of those functions are not available in all
shared environments
But if you wanna be
Like very specific
You could actually help the user along to who uses your application to
Enable those functions on their server
And by that giving them extra
Security with uploading of files
This is obviously a very big topic
Which I don't think we have time to go into in that dept
But in general this sort of implementation is really how most are doing it
And yet
Yeah
Let me know
Get you too concerned
This should be ok
Now
We have moved everything in place let's give her a trial run
So it says that it's been saved to excessively
But
No file selected is shown here
Now we might want to
Show
The file that is now currently in the database
Instead of this upload or
Show the upload still but let's say someone decides to upload another one that it
Actually changes it
And remove the old one and adds the new one
And displays the little image here
As it is in the database now let's first see is it in the database
Ok so here in the database we see there is our file
And it is actually set to be in images autumn trees forest
Building grass
Dot JPG that is where it is
Ok now let's see if it actually was moved
To that
Place
So here in the folder structure we gonna open images we gonna click here on images then
Scroll down
and see
there it is autumn tree
You can see it there
Yip it is in its place
So the actual image does now
Exist in the image folder
It is been uploaded and it actually is in the database although
Our little snippet there says that it can't see it
Before we continue with that kind of custom scripting we need to take what we have done so far
And actually added to JCB
We've done and in the IDE
And if we compile in install
Store this component now
You actually overwrite everything you've written
And boom it's gone
So what to do
Let's go grab that custom scripting and added to the component
In JCB
Ok so we wanna grab everything
From
Upload my uploads function
You wanna do check upload
And remove file all of that we want to get
So we gonna say cut
And
Got that in the
The clipboard
Then go to JCB
And in the look Admin view which is where all this is happening we can open up
Then there is a place called custom buttons
You gonna say yes here
And then there is the controller method we are not adding anything there
But here is the
The model method
And so this is a place for us to actually add
some script to the model
And we gonna just paste what we've cut
Out
right in here
And overhearing the list controller we're not adding anything and
Also in this list
Controller we're not adding anything
So we basically just adding that
Which we written to the model method at your PHP here is gonna go into the model
As methods so
This is the methods
That's a method
That is obviously a method
So all of these are methods
We want it to be available to the class
from now on
We are not actually at this point dealing
With if you upload a new file that it removed the old one
That should still
Be further custom
Scripting
And so this point all Just add the new file it won't
Remove the old one
So could be that he's adding more files and more files and it just gets added to the image folder
But it's not being removed
You have the remove
file function already here
So you could actually yeah you could actually fix this quite easily
But I'm not gonna show you how to do that
I wanna encourage you to
Study up some of your
PHP as well
Now
Here we need to also add obviously
The Script that we are adding to the save method so here is the PHP save method
Before data modelling this is where we want to actually Jump In
And like it says there the value are in the data array
So we just gonna go back to the IDE
And scroll down to
Sorry this
time it's up
Just gonna scroll up
To this little snippet here
Because this is everything new
Right
I just copy that or let's just cut that as well
and go back to
The JCB interface
And paste it in there
Ok so now we have our
In the save
Method before modelling
We have this little snippet that will be executed
And the same goes with
In a custom buttons
we've got in the
Models we've got our classes that are being added
Now we said If we open the item
So that means after we've saved it
We want to actually take the value in this banner
And we want to display it in the page
Now there are many ways to do this
Since we already have this value
It shouldn't be that hard
So
JavaScript to the rescue
I'm gonna use JavaScript to do this
So we have hands our script to the view file
Or add JavaScript to the view footer so that means we can decide where to add the Javascript
Do we want to add to JavaScript in a file that gets included in the header of the document
Or do we wanna add it to the bottom of the view as a snippet ok that is really we were
want to do it
Because you wanna use PHP
So
We gonna actually do some PHP in this
Area here
Where as in this is file area we cannot do PHP
So to show you exactly where this is gonna come out he's gonna just add a comment here
Add
Java
Script
Here
And I'm gonna show you how we gonna do PHP
P
HP
Also
Works
And
We gonna save that
Now we actually can go out of here and go compile this component
And install and then go look at it code
So here and our save class
We have
Upload image
And that is all
Good and right
Now let's search for our function here
And there is our function also in the same class been added
Through JCB interface so it was not lost
It's not exactly the same place we were originally
Placed it but it is in the same class and it's what we want we want those
Classes to be available to us here
Ok so that part is still good
Now we wanna go look at the view
And see where that JavaScript going to be added
So we'll just close images here
Then go back up and open the view
Then wait what
Where are we
this is the installer
You wanna go to the demo that one
View look
And edit
So we are looking at that specific View
And you see here
Is
The JavaScript
Ok
So it's added it
to our script
Area
And I actually am able to
To do PHP Echo
In the script area
Which is what
We are going to do
We going to check whether that
Banner
Value is available to us on this page
And then we are going to
Use it to actually render the image
in its
Appropriate place
Now to know where the values are
We go back to its view HTML dot PHP
Area
And we see that here it gets the item and it places it in the item Global
Class value
So we have the value item we can therefore check if banner is in the item
So what I will do
Just
So that you can
Sort of see what's happening as well copy that
And then I'm gonna go back to the edit View
Where we put our html
I'm gonna say
I just var dump
That specific value
And save
And so we can see all of that so let's go to the interface Ok we actually
have to add the word
Exit jexit is actually the correct way of doing it
J exit
To this and go little up because we got a little fader here it's gonna hide this and just
Let's just take that out for now
So we can see
What's going on
And then let's
Refresh or page
Ok so we got it all broken that's fine
But here at the bottom
ah still not showing
Let's take it to the top
So we've added it here above everything it should actually show now. So let's go see.
Refresh
There we go that's what you wanna see
So we see that it is publicly accessible there's the banner value so we can check whether there
Is actually
A value in this whether it's a string and has a value because we know we controlling that value
the user cannot actually manually
Add that value there
It needs to do it through the upload field
So we can check whether that has a string
And if it does
We can just create a little
Show the image
Underneath it's appropriate placement
Ok so that's how I get to see the value
So if you are dealing with something similar
You can
Do these kind of poking into the result sets to exactly where is what
How does it look and how do I get to it and
Yeah that way
You're not dependent on the way sort of
Not knowing what's going on
So now here back in JCB we going to say
if
We gonna say if
It is
Set
And
If
It is a string
I'm using the helper class here we've got a function in the helper class called check string
To see whether it has a length
And that it is a string
Not an array or a Boolean or something like that
Now
This is the way you can
Sort of use the helper class to use the brackets brackets brackets
Component and then bracket bracket bracket helper colon colon
and there you go
And
If that is true
We want to
Obviously load the image
Because then it exists
Now we wanna see where do we wanna add this image and it's actually underneath the the upload
I'm just gonna have it show up like a normal image so we gonna just do some jQuery
to
To do that
Ok so we are doing
This image source and we are echoing the item banner
because we know it's a string
We can add a class here
Now you can target this class
And make it nice with CSS Just add your CSS is here
To view
Just here you can add your CSS so here you just add the the class name that you gonna target with your
CSS and you can do
All kind of nice things with it
you gonna have alt and banner
And we gonna insert it after the banner
Field so the
You know is the way we know what this value is
Is we open one of those views
like so
And we drill down
Until we find
That's so we use our inspector
grab maybe
The banner
Label
then drill until we find the ID J form banner
That's how I get it
ok
And
Then
We just add this after
It after the control group so that looks nice fits in with the layout and I think it's broken
Ok so
That should trigger it
So we saying See if we have a banner if we do add this JavaScript we done
Save
Now let's compile and in
Install
So
compile
And
install
Go back to our view
And
Obviously close this and refresh
Now go to more and Walla there is our image
Now to show you it in action we gotta change the image
It won't remove the old one
But it will immediately show you the new one once we click save
So let's do that
So I've selected to different image from my computer and then click save
And go back and wow there is the new image so that is how you could implement
The file
Field type in JCB so as you can see there is some custom scripting needed
I'm gonna quickly
I show you a URL where you can go and get this custom script
And use it in your own component
And of course
May be adapted to change it
At least use it as a place to start with
And
Start using the
Custom Joomla field type
For uploading files
Thanks for watching
Is any questions or even
Suggestions of how to do this easier or faster or safer
Leave the commons in the area below the video I'll be happy to look at it and
Make any necessary changes to our snippet ok
Or even at the snippet itself that might be a better place
And the gits where the URL I'm gonna show you now
Are you can go there and make comments there and we will just make pull request in the whatever and we'll fix it up so
So that works well for everyone thanks for watching