Ok if those of you who have
not already
Watch this
How to use the field type
To the file field type
To upload a
A file in JCB
If you haven't watched this
Then
I would suggest if your first come and watch this tutorial
Cause a lot of things
that I explain in here
Which I'm not gonna go into that depth
Again
Otherwise
It's gonna be 2 hours
But in this tutorial I'm going to the sort of the
Talk about a Drag and Drop
Automated
Crop
Functionality
Which could also be used instead of this
Implementation
So this implementation would be
I said much more limited
You could do a crop
With this one as well
But we haven't
Actually demonstrated that we going to demonstrate it now
In this tutorial
And
The library I'm going to use before I
go on let me just
I'll actually add a link to this video
Underneath
The one that you watching
Ok
So
The other thing you need to know about is UIKit
Of course I suppose by now
You're very aware of UIkit
UIkit has a very nice
File uploading front-end
Which I have used quite often
So
I am gonna demonstrate using
UI kits upload
But
If you know anything about
JavaScript and that kind of stuff
It wouldn't be hard to
Plug-in
Bootstraps or
Any other library which
You actually wanna use JCB
Can be scaled
To be using other libraries it is go to libraries in
Set up the new library and then in your
Include the files in your admin View
And there you go so
At this point
I'm just gonna use JCB sorry
UIkit now
I'm gonna use the older version to you UIkit in my
Presentation
And that's simply because that's the one I've already got going in some of my projects
I'm a little lazy or a little reluctant
To actually
Embrace the later release
Because of his lack of compatibility backward compatibility
Which is to me like
not good
Ok anyway let me
rant about that
So where you wanna go
You would like to go to get
UIkit
Version 2
And actually to components
This is where you would like to actually go
Then
You would see
Sorry
You'll see there is a
Upload at the very bottom
That actually explains to you
How to use this
This library
This is the JavaScript that will be using
So it's got a nice progress bar and everything
And
This is the HTML
that we'll be using
And it's got a nice
You know
Drag and drop area
And selecting area
So you can
give some
Information here to the user
As well as have them drop the file right there
And it works very well
I've used it for
Number of years now
It's got some some
Events here
And it's very similar to Version 3
So if you wanted to see version threes option you'd simply click on version 3
documentation
And scroll
Somewhere to the bottom it says download
And here it is
Select
there is the markup for the select
And then the Drag and Drop there is the markup for the
Drag and Drop so you'd use
This
And then this JavaScript
So it's look very much the same as the few changes of course
Little bit changes in the
those but
For the more part it's generally the same kind of approach so you would naturally just be able to plug-in this
If instead you wanna use UIkit
Or any other library
You gonna see me making for example this dynamic
And
The URL is going to be dynamic
And whether it's going to be allowing multiple or only one all those kind of
Let me I don't think the previous one and had the multiple option
But this one also has allowed
You know what what
What type of image of file do you want to permit to be uploaded
And the action is where the URL is right
And yeah so you'll see me actually make some of this dynamic
With the script that I'm using
And of course here we are talking Ajax
Oh so you are able to upload the
File without saving
The item
Whether for this area is available
And you simply can use a note
To actually
Add this
Script to your page
So that's what I usually do I use a note and just add this
Somebody drop something here it's gonna post to the server
And so if the item has ID I passed the ID
So that it gets stored in the database immediately
so even if you save it
or don't save the file actually gets added to that item
And if it's a new item which means no ID we actually add a hidden field
To the form
So we return the actual value that must go to the database
And we put it in that hidden field
So did when you then do save the item
It actually does
store it in the correct place
So that's sort of the approach
I'm gonna demonstrate that to you
Step-by-step
With an existing component which I really
I got out there and which
is using
And it is actually available
In JCB so you'll see there this new import JCB packages
You could either click on this
Or you can go to Joomla components and click on import components
Is the same is really the same thing
So I'm gonna go back to dashboard
And click on import JCB packages
There has been a release fix I think it was been in a
The previous release if you clicked on import JCB packages it actually didn't
Yeah I didn't give you this doesn't give you
This
Package tab here
It gave you only those
In fact it's a little broken
So best then go to Joomla components
And
Ensure to click on
Import components
Then to be sure that it gives you this
VDM packages tab
This VDM and packages tab is in new extension on the import of components
It's actually the only
Part of the import of the components that already does
Actual validation on the package integrity
So for each of these packages that I hear we actually do have a validation
so giving your example Hello World is not
Already
if we come here will
See Hello World isn't here
So
If I was to now
Select Hello World
Click get package
It actually fetches it from GitHub
And it has a method of actually
Getting a hash a checksum
Of the package
Now you can make sure that
It tells you here that the validation so now this point the package
is on your server
Now you can click cancel and that will delete the package from your server
But
This here tells you that the validation is pass so what is
The actual package that we are distributing is the one you've now got
And you can verify that
By click on this link so if you click on this link
It should open a simple
A text string it's taking a moment my network here
Ok and this text string
Should be the same
As the one
You see here
That is sort of just a heads up and its an area which we now
We started adding some
that checks on validation
And yeah it's not military grade but it's
Fair enough
I think I anyone trying to NOW stand in the middle of this
He's gonna have
Quite crazy gymnastics too
To take care of
Ok so at this point we
The package which is being imported is
Displayed here and you just click
Quiet means that
You don't see all of the things it's doing I would suggest you
Say no you wanna see everything
Force update
Means that if it finds a similar field type or a similar field or a similar admin
View anything that is similar
And the creation date
Is
Younger in your system
It actually
Overwrites it
Because you're forced it if it
If it finds it and the actual current date in your system
Is older
So that the one you importing is younger it automatically update it
With the latest
Newest version
This is how it works
And that's why we telling you to make backups
Because well the other advantages if you get to field type that was overwritten
And it's not really what you expected
You actually got history you can go back one step
Usually you would
Ok
So I'm gonna say yes force that and then continue
And that simply adds
a whole list of
What it's done
What is imported
And it also moved an image shows you that
Tells you done
Ok so there we go Hello World is
Is now in the system
Now
We are going to look at something completely different
And it is actually
The
Document manager is it paid
Is a paid package
which
We distribute
You can obviously buy this package
From us
It actually does have all this functionality that I'm going to demonstrate now
In it and so I'm just gonna use that can I add a key here and click
Continue
And then basically install this component
In JCB
And then from there we will start demonstrating it's functionality
Ok so we got document manager now installed here
Let me quickly show you how
it looks in action
So I'm gonna install it to this component Joomla website
And demonstrate it
Ok
Now
We have a here component manager
Sorry document manager
and we can create a document quite easily
By clicking a new document and you'll see that there is some allowed image formats are not set in the global settings please
Notify your system
administrator
So you can't at this point upload
Actually anything
Neither image neither documents neither any media
So we'll go out of this and in the options of the component there is actually
A media tab
That says what type of documents you wanna allow
So
For our purpose I'm just gonna say PDF for now with the media I'm just
MP3
and with the images just jpeg
Now with
The images
I know in my
This component I'm only having one image and I wanted to be a specific dimension
So
I'm gonna say I want the width
To be 200
And the heights
To be 300 so make it 350
So it's almost like a book
A four kind of
Dimensions
I'm so that's gonna
Be used
to crop my Image I'm using a library which l'll
Show you in a moment which gets these values
To decide upon how to
Actually go ahead
and crop the image
It's an image
Obviously if it's any of these it doesn't do anything only if it's an image
Does it actually use the crop mechanism
And it doesn't via on Ajax ok so we've done that save and close
If we now
Again click on new documents
We see this Drag and Drop area
Like
We are looked here I GitHub
Sorry on
UI kit
We see this thing in action really so we see it says that your
Upload your image and it tells you
That
This is the what the dimensions should be
And if not the doc will be cropped to this size
So that means if it's not this Dimension it will be cropped that either large or
you know downsize
By dropping the file here or selecting a file from your computer
And formats allowed
JPEG
So it tells you what formats are allowed
This is all
Done
Basically to dynamically through this
Script that I'll show you the moment
Then the same goes here with the document it tells your PDF is allowed and with the media tells you MP3
Now the image I'm only allowing one image
Where as with the documents I'm allowing multiple
documents and multiple media for one document
How this displays in works on the front end
Works lovely no problems
I'm going to demonstrate that that's not what this is all about I'm just
Just gonna demonstrate
this functionality of uploading a file
And you need to you know if you use this in your own
Component you will need to extend that and use it and make it more functional as a
As it should
Should be in your
Component
Ok
So now let's go and look at the code
There which we need to focus on first is basically the document
Area of course
We'll have to
Look at some of its fields that is attached here
Some of its JavaScript
And
The Ajax area which is really where everything
Things happening
As you'll see I'm using custom
code placeholders
Most everywhere
Because I'm re using a lot of the scripts
Everywhere under components
And
I've therefore
Adapted it so that it could be used multiple places
So you'll see you're also of God upload file remove file
Functions
And it's got target and
Type and field filename target Flush
Type
it got values
All these values play a role within the behaviour that we will eventually have
Or did we demonstrated
On a pay well I didn't
demonstrate it I just
Showed you how it is I will actually demonstrate it still
You also see here I've got this set a vastdevmod
Which is basically
A function
That generates
For us some variables
Which this case is called
VDM
Which gets placed in a
variable
Called vastDevMod
This formation
Is what is used to identify the view
From which the query is made
This is a long string which really is related to the cash
At that stage
Of The View ID and name
This is how I passed the view name and ID
So I do not really pass it via
The
Ajax query
I actually have it in
Session memory
And only if these keys validate does it
Actually work
..... sort of another layer
And another layer this many layers in this to
To try and make this secure
Then this adminKittwo is where I am actually loading
All the
Uikit
Files
So I am manually adding it to the
View the admin backend
Doesn't actually work as the site views where
We could select
A
Library and it dynamically
answer to the view on compilation you have to manually add it to the view and you'll do it basically
in the custom
Script of the document
Now
I can show you some of these Snippets
And then
Then we can take it further
There's obviously in the custom buttons area
This is the get VDM which I have
Explained
Again we have some custom script here
And that's basically all that we have there
And then in the JavaScript area we again have set file
which is part of the script that will have to look at
And you see I'm using set file here
Here and
I'm here because we have an image We have
Documents
And we have media
And they all
Using the set file
Method
Which is the JavaScript
Function
Which is declared in this custom
Script and here at the bottom of the footer
We got
What is known as get file
Snippet which again deals with actual some of the automated integration
Of the file when
Drag and drop
And that it actually immediately
displays
On the page this this takes care of that
Ok so
We'll go and look at those individual
Concepts
We also going to see like I said previously
Some notes
So here is the
Main media apploader note
There is the main document apploader the note and there is the document image apploader
note
And so this is where I've added the HTML
For the drag and drop that you see in the
Admin View
Then we have for each of those correspondingly a hidden
value
For the document image key
Main document
Documents
key and a
Main media key
All of these are hidden
Fields
Which
Basically is where we store
These values
and
That's what
We'll look at as well
Ok
So
Let's go and see the code that is used
maybe let's start in the interface
Right
So let's first look at one of these
Uploading
Concepts
But since I know what's happening there I am already aware that
The actual code is not there
So it's actually also custom
Placeholder snippet so before we actually dive in let me
Anyway
Open the custom code area and go back into documents
So that when we see the code
Snippet
We can actually go and
Look at the code snippet
Let's use this documents apploader
Note
And open that
So here we have the document apploader note
Basically we have a diff
All the way down there
Which has an ID
And then it has the
Class for the placeholder
Some icons
And you'll see
Try again have here upload your documents
There, here I've got a span tag
That says main documents formats so it's basically gone
Be the place we load the formats with JavaScript
And
Then select the file from your computer is
So this is all basically
It's this snippet
Just with a little bit of extra
Flavour
Yeah that's really all we looking at
And then obviously there are some conventions
Like main documents apploader
That again here
Upload drop main documents there are conventions which if we go over the code
Eventually you'll see that those conventions is what really makes this
reusable then in the scripts area I added a JavaScript to
View footer
And a JavaScript I'm using
Is this Uikit file apploader custom code so let's look at that then First
We can just search for it
There it is we can open that so this is the code that gets added
So it's got a little bit of PHP here
And it is saying ok great
Argument zero
Formats so we are asking we getting the global parameters
Of the formats reset
Which remember I showed you we said it in the global settings so here we are saying document is the First
Parameter passing
So we are basically saying document formats here
So we getting the document formats and then
Here we have arg 2 and arg 1 progress bar
So if you think about the ID here
It says progress bar
The 2nd
Which is the third argument
Is Main
Documents is the
Second argument sorry the first argument because we counting from
zero, so it's actually saying
Main documents
So if you look back at our thing here it says main documents
Formats
So this is all part
Of
Main
Documents
It is the way we
Identify the progress bar to progress bar ,let's see
where is the progress bar
Here it is
Progress bar main documents so it's an ID
There's only one of them on the page
So it's targeting it here saying ok that's the progress bar we gonna
And
Then
Is having some settings the settings obviously the action
We using J router now this J router is a little
JavaScript
Trick that I wrote because often times
You have this
Site view or are the admin View
You have it in the back end
And you have it in the front end
And so this is this just takes care of whether it's a backend or front-end call
So that it actually executes correctly
Now that is your component name
The argument one again would be the second argument
Which is in our case
Documents
So basically there it says documents the type and then this the third argument which is showing as a
Second one is Main
So it's passing the target is main
Raw is true it has the token and there is our key
Which is being used to identify the view ok so it's making a query
On this
This area here
And it is set dynamically
Then over here
We know that the formats must be
Added to this area with pipe between it
It's like you remember here
It adds the formats
With a pipe
So we're just basically exploding the array we got here from the global parameters
For documents
And it displays it
In here
Then again we have other
This actual snippet
I will add under this name on a
GitHub gist
So you could actually copy paste it from there and adapted for your purpose
Begin here
We are also
Imploding the formats because he wanted display it
I want to show the use of the formats
So we have here
Second argument or sorry
Third argument and
The second argument formats which would be
Documents and Main so if we look at our diff
We see there the formats as
Documents and main format so it's targeting this span tag
And basically adding it in there
Ok so that is
Adding the formats
HTML to this ID
Then if
We've detected up here
That you didn't have any formats set
We basically gonna update the whole
diff
Which is the upload drop area with allowed formats are not set in a global setting
Please notify system
administrator
So that's the final part of our JavaScript so we have JavaScript next in with
HTML
Taking care of
Some of the
displays behaviour on that page
Ok so that is the reusable snippet
So I'm reusing this same snippet file apploader
For various areas
So
If we were to close out here
And I was then to actually open the media
Note
You'll see that it's really just using the same snippet so if it goes the script it's the same snippet
I'm just changing the variables I'm passing here is saying media media Main
Where's the other one was saying document documents plural and
Main
This one is saying media media main
And then
The same goes with the image
The image we also have
That kind of behaviour
Say Uikit image apploader, this one is not using the file apploader
Is using the image apploader which is a little different
There is an image
apploader and there is images apploader in my custom Snippets
I'll show you
Why there are difference
One allows one image
And the other one allows
More
Wait him I'm over file one
Allows one
A more than one this one only allows one
So it has a little bit of a different flavour and behaviour
And yes I will also
Show place this out there and Git
For you to have a look at
Always remember these arguments are
Behaving the similar way as an array
Which means that the first argument will always be zero the second argument one and so forth
So I'm basically using arguments in
And this snippet everywhere where I declare it I am actually passing
The three arguments that is required use this plus there to pass
And the
diff obviously looks very similar except that it now would say images
And
Images
you see there it's using different placeholders
So you need to update those accordingly
As it's needed
So that's just to set up the field
Set up the field you need to have that JavaScript in place and you need to have that diff
Sort of in place
Regarding the hidden if I was to take one of the hidden Fields let's say the documents
Hidden field you'll see there is some naming conventions here that
you need to follow
So it says main documents it doesn't do say documents
And you'll see when we actually add the value back to the page
Were able to target it based on these naming conventions so yeah that's
Quite important and then for some security
Which
It's really just a little extra layer
I like the guy one guy said, that it's not that we can
Really stop them, we can just make it very hard
So there are different encryption options this medium encryption local file key
Is actually better than the basic the basic stores the the key in the database
Which in that case means that if somebody sweeped your database , they actually do have the key
But it could happen that they were able to get hold of your database but not actually all of your files
Specially those that are behind the public repository so the medium incription option can actually generate
File behind the public folder which therefore is not publicly accessible
And
That makes it just that little bit more difficult to actually get a key to open
The value
And the reason is let's say your documents are
You know not available to every group on your system maybe to some groups can access that document then
This is another layer of security that's already by default built into the field behaviour
Ok
So that is
Really just looking at the fields now the admin view documents have some
Custom script in it as well
So we got to here the set file which really is the JavaScript that
fires
when it
Gets the request back from the Ajax call
You'll see, let me show you if we go back
Here
on
all complete there is a function
And then
At some point when everything is satisfied it has here a set file key
And it passes a bunch of variables to it
this is really the function
That we're gonna have to look at
So
Let's say let's use that setFileJS
And insert it here
So here we go
So we'll see here there is a set file key function
In the
Document
And
so in your Ajax which you're using
Uikits
function here
It has an auto complete So even if you look here
at allcomplete which is a place where there when you know the server has told you
It's done everything is good then you can do some house cleaning in the browser
And that's really what we doing
We're checking if it's done
We take away the progress bar and if it has an error we actually
Pop out the errors and alert if it's successful because we decide what this response going
to be
So we decided to give a successful
Value in the array then we fire the set file key
Which is actually
looking at our
Admin View
Where adding this custom code in here and it is actually adding all this code that
you see here
Is being added
it's quite a lot of code
But it's all being added
To the admin view and it can be used for different admin views
If it's obviously dealing with either images documents or media so I'm gonna try
and explain all this,it looks almost as if I'm going to end up teaching you some JavaScript
altough I'm being accused of writing Javascript like PHP yeah sorry
the point is
The JavaScript here actually does some checking and validating and I'll put this
I'll just put it out there and
Really when it discovers that everything is fine the file actually was added
Then it
You know goes ahead
here it's checking the length of the filename see if the filename length is not
Not greater than 20
.
and if it's not an image or a document
Then it must be removed
So the return values are here quite key
To make sure that
We have this
remove file from server
Function in place
where I showed you in the admin
View that we've got these
Remove file tasks
And the methods well this basically is going to be as I
Scroll down a bit
Here
Here it is
It's basically
querying that, you see
Remove that
And it's passing all the necessary variables
To remove the correct file
Yeah it's also checking
That a person who is trying to remove the files actually logged in user and on the file
Where we will look at in a moment,at the actual PHP which will again
Validate that that user actually has permission to remove
The file
So there are all these checks and balances across every step of the this implementation
And as you by now I might realise this implementation is far more complicated than
the normal file upload, that's simple this really gets into the
Nitty gritty of some of these things because you wanna give a real easy sort of
Behaviour for your user
But that will mean that you need to do way more
To sort of thing for them and protect them
So they don't
Actually become vulnerable at any time
Ok so
Once we satisfied that the file is correct and it doesn't need to
To be removed
We actually
Trigger
A few
Things which actually puts the file
In the page
That's really what we wanna
Eventually end up doing
Set file
Is what
We are moving
Towards
Because we want to make sure
that
The file now after you've dragged and dropped it on the page
Boom it shows in the page once it's really on the server
And that's really what's
Being done here a little bit It's doing a little bit of checking just to make sure we're all good
Everything's fine
And we end up with what we now called
File name
And it get past here
And now
We are moving
Into set file
And the sent file is gonna take the the target
And it's going to
Determine
What kind of target it is and
Get the format get the this ,get the that
So we can build the file name correctly
And now I've got some functions here
Which maybe not what you need
But I mean
You look through this
And you decide what
Keeping what is
Throughout
But we end up building a notice
Which actually has
You know
You're so so have been
Set
And
Then
It Triggers
The get file
The get file is
the other function
Which if you look at the admin View
Let's go back here
to the JavaScript
We've got here the set file
And here we've gotta get file
The get file is it getting another layer of validation and also just like
just make sure that everything
Is really
Behaving as we would want and
expect it to behave
So the rest of the snippet here is just a remove file and is Json's
String we also have a little snippet
to check if
If it's a Json string
and if it's empty
it's all part of just
Sanitizing and validating
Making sure everything
Is the way we expect
Ok so
we
now wanna look at the get's file JS
Which
Has different
Implementation and as you can see
It is in the footer,the view footer so we have
PHP
In that area of the JavaScript
So is the set and this is
The get file
In the get file
We have a
Again a link
That was a echoed
Which we are now gonna use to actually load the file
To make it that it can be downloaded
Now that's really the issue
If it's a document or if it's a media
We obviously don't wanna display it but we wanna have you be able to
To download it
So we have different behaviours for image and
Images
As well as if you
Scroll down for
Documents at for media
So it has different behaviours it continues building Buttons and displays
And I'll
Pop this code also out there on the Gits
And you can look at it
And
See if you can make sense out of it
This thing here the document link
Or the document button
Is
The potential idea about this
If we go to actually
let me Close out here
And go to the actual document manager
In the document manager when you create a document
You have here what we call description
So if you add a document you can actually use those Place holders
In the description
And
It's the beginning of
Actually using these documents
Across the website
And not just in the component
So we'll eventually write a little plugin
And if you actually use
This place holder which
it generates
If you use that
Anywhere
The plugin will identify it
And will load either a link or a button
Depending on which one you're using
This is the bottom this is the link
That's really what it's doing
So
You might say I don't need placeholders and you
can grab that part and
Take it out
also then wherever
The bar placeholder
is being used and
You need to remove
For example over
There
Because we got a file box that
we are building
And it's basically getting the place holders
The download and a delete buttons
All of them get loaded into
the file box
And
If we are having more than one file
We are treating it differently than just having one file
And really that is what we do here being the document
and a little different
Behaviour but somewhat the same
And
That is what actually then does the final stretch
it's like a relay
race, one carries it this far and then the other one takes it over
Carries it a little further
And this one is at the very last end of the match
Where it is now finally putting the image
Back into the page
And
All of the nice little
thrills, bells and whistles happens here
And of course this is where you can really spice it up with some
JavaScript
And
And you can see I 'm using Uikit to actually deal with
most of the styling
Ok
So
Now you've seen
The
Front-end
As we would call it
Of the behaviour of our
Drag an Drop
So you've seen how I set up the field
You've seen
When the Ajax has finished it's request
It actually
Runs this set file key
And the set file key
Then Triggers a
Whole bunch of things
Which ends up
Adding the
The file to the page
Let me demonstrate here
In the
In our little
New document
Let me demonstrate some of these function
so you can see
That which I now explained and exactly what it does
So here I've got a bunch of images
Is Just generic open source
kind of
Images
So I'm just gonna grab one
And dump it in here
And
You didn't see that
let me scroll down
Get that image again
Put it down a little lower let me get another one
Let's use this house
And I'm gonna drag it there and highlights it
then for a moment it has this little apploader because we are
on Local network
It's very fast
But usually would see it
Uploads
And then when it started says your document images set
So that was built with
JavaScript
And there is the document
image on display
And there is now remove document image
I can Click that and it'll tell me are you sure you wanted to leave this document
Yes, and boom it gone
Ok so and we back at Square One
As if we had nothing
And it doesn't only deleted from the page it actually removed
from the server
As well
So let's drag another one just
Drag it there and drop
Uploads there is our nicely cropped image
Obviously crops in the centre of the Image because
How does it know the house is on
On the side
It not doing that kind of
Smart
Detection yet
We just cropping the image
in the most
Sensible way
Now with the uploading of a document
More less the same let me just get a document
Ok so we got a document here
And you can
Drag and
Drop it in there
And again it uploads it
And with the upload
It generates those links I told you would you could
Copy
And now put it in
In the
Description
If you want
Or you could test it
What is noteworthy here
Is that the name of the document doesn't
Actually get lost
While
The the place where documents are added
Is actually in the same
folder so
You could add multiple documents to
This document
I'll just keep on stacking them though they even have the same name
each one will be
uniquely tagged
to not be the same as the other
Which means that on the server we are storing this document with a
Long hash
Sort of added onto
The name
Which is an extra layer of security so people
If they could access the folder they at least
know what the name is
Same with the image if we were to
Actually inspect the
Image
You'll see
That that image
it got this
Huge name doc image Jpeg wrrllll&&&&&&& ext.
So it's no longer than same name as
the one you uploaded
It actually changes it if there is preserve the name for example in
the documents
Option here
So did you giving to someone the document they get what you expect
But we do actually
Adapt the names
For security
So that
You can't be actually allocated
On the server if for some reason not a good document
Ok and so you could test it by clicking here
And it should then just
Bring it up in
And be available as a download
Now how the download works here with the document
I'm actually using a controller so if we
Hovered over this
Link here
You see ok you can't see
See that
Showed you
Well
Maybe I'll just show you the
Ok I've copy the link here now
it's a little huge because we are using
Basically a very much of a
Encrypted
Path to the file
it could sometimes being encrypted or sometimes just be
basically
64 encrypted
But the point is we have what we see here as a task and download
Document so there is actually a controller called download
In my component
And I will show you how this download document
Concept works but
You'll need to write that
You need to
To figure that one out
That's sort of
Onto you
That's if you want people to download your
Your documents
If it's just to upload images
of course
You don't need any of this
But it is only when you gonna actually have a downloadable
File
Or media
So next one we wanted to show you here
It's just upload some media file
Ok so here I have a bunch of audio files
And I'm going to upload them
What I'm going to do is I'm going to select
Whole bunch of them
And then upload them all at once
Which is really what this apploader can actually do
So
let me see, there we go
Drop it there
And
Can't see it yet but it's actually uploading uploading uploading
Think I need to refresh the page
So let's give it a name
Let's say
The
Document
Let's say
More
Soon
And then save this
And then see ok it didn't
Actually upload all of them
Interesting
Let me try again
Ok now I've got 6 of them uploaded so I can see there are 6 documents and you can
Actually download them and test them
See if they are still fine
Why the home
The order of the home
Yes
We see that the
media is working
let's also do that with documents let's add some more documents
So I've got a few selected and
Drag and drop them there
And is uploaded I need to maybe check some of the JavaScript I see you didn't add the download button here
But without saving if we just refresh the page you'll see that it actually has
All those documents are there
Because it's really used Ajax to
Store them in the Database
And so at the end of day
That is the behaviour we wanted here in our component we wanted the option to upload multiple
Documents to one document and multiple media files
And
To be able to test them in the backend if you wanted to test any of them
And in even be able to remove
Any of them
At any time
Just click on remove and it will be removed and in the front
We'll be able to use the file names and
The user
Would be able to identify oh ok so this is what I want
And so the filenames actually get preserved
While it is actually being stored
in the server
With this
Hash behind it
And so
We are seeing the JavaScript we looked at earlier in action it is uploading it is deleting
This one is actually cropping which will look at it a little more
So
That is seeing our Drag and Drop
Options in action
Now let's go look at the server side of this
implementation
The server side we have in the documents admin View
we're opening the PHP tab
Got this Ajax area
And
Like I showed before
you would obviously need to set up the Ajax with this area targets the controller
So in the controller it creates all these necessary script
To make this
Method
Which is again we gonna look at inside of that
Custom code
Make this method available to the Ajax call
There are some values that we set because every
Component I used this stuff in is different and so for some we're using images
,documents and media
As the types
And for some
The target or Main and Doc and the allow view there's only one of you in this component that is allowed
To use the apploader and that is the document view and so they get view ID
Is the function
With which I get the actual view name
And ID
And it is basically using
The session to sort of throw that around
to insure
That nobody is able to tamper with
That value through the front in anyway
So little extra little gymnastics to make
Just add another layer there
Ok so we gonna look now at this PHP Ajax apploader in the custom codes area
So let's just go here and then
Search for it
So here in the custom codes area and why I'm using custom code because I'm
Reusing this
At the moment it doesn't look like I'm reusing it many places it only says it's used in component but this is not the
The area where I'm actually doing my work this is just for tutorials
I'm using a whole different developing environment
or rather a developing
System Joomla website than this one, so this one is just for
Explaining and
demonstrating ok so
I'm reusing
This code in many components
And here
We have formats, image formats that are allowed
In the system
Document formats that are allowed in the system
Media formats that is allowed in the system and this you can adapt to whatever you need
At the end of the day
Is up to you to decide what you want to
Allow and what you wouldn't, the reality is this is the available formats but as you remember
Here where was it again
in the options area of our component
It has a media area and there we have allowed documents allowed media formats and allowed image
Formats and
These is
Should be the same right it should be the same list having the same values But these are what is
a field we created in Joomla
a List field and so we manually added this
to the components configuration area so if you don't know what that is
Let me quickly show you
So in the component
Here is our component it has this
component config
If your component doesn't show one like this Hello World doesn't show a component config
You can go into the component
And then here in
Let's see think settings
There is this button here of create component config
For this Joomla component and it's in this I'm gonna close out here I don't want to do that one of
I could just show you with a document
Manager
Basically
we could use the same button in settings
There it is
We can actually edit or now if it hasn't have one you can
Create and here you select fields
With a custom values and the tabs in which they should
display and it's basically as you can see here I've selected allowed document formats list
Which is just a list of
The formats and I obviously said it to allow multiple selection
So that's how I'm doing this allowed media allowed image and allowed documents and
then here's the crop document image and if you do not know how to create a field and how to
Set radio buttons or list
Then go review the videos about that I'm gonna
explain that now
But that's really how we deal with that and that list that list that we looked at now
is the same list as what
To see here
It should be the same
Because
This is the allowed
And that list
Shows the
user what is allowed for the system
So how can I
Sorry notice
Sorry about that
Notice came up and messed up everything
But I hate to start over now
Anyway
So this is what you could say as available formats and then those
Dropdowns is what you as the owner of this website
Where this application will run is what you will allow
Ok and that this list should be the same as the one there but it also is sort of going
to be use so that people
Post a specific type
As if it is allowed we're gonna able to sort of bounce this and make sure that
Security wise we are safe
So here is the upload file function
And the upload file starts by first getting the view ID
checking it
And
Then making sure that there is a view set
of course
And that that view is actually part of the allowed views array so they allowed views array if you remember
In our
Where did I show you that
Ok it's in the admin
View document admin view Maybe this one no here it is
The allowed views is documents
So that's why I'm saying I'm setting that outside of the
Custom code because it
Depends on which component we are working in right
So if it is an allowed View
We then get the target
And the type and we set it to Global target and global target type
Then we check that this type
What is the format that we are talking about so
If we think about
The format
There is
Again we go back to this one, where is it?
Here let's move it closer so we
Close to each other
That is the
Formats that we allow the types because we want to
Sort of validate that the person and who is uploading
Is uploading the things we anticipate so it is setting the format with the type
So if it's image it will be images
If it's images it will be images
If it's document it will be document if it's documents it'll be document and media will be media so that's the
Types
And we setting that is the format type now then we using a function get package from
upload now if you watch the previous tutorial of using the file type uploader
Then it's more or less the same kind of function
So if I scroll down
We'll get to it where is it get package from upload so
the only differences we doing the application at get and the
input in the function
And we are targeting files because we are passing those values in the files place
Then
We are seeing what is the file we are checking whether these things are allowed warning import a file
Error
This kind of error you'll see I'm not throwing it
to Joomla
I'm adding it to the error messages
Error error message
Because we gonna have to give it back to the view
We're not able to this is Ajaxs call he did nobody will see it if we just
You know used the arrays warning or something
So we are actually grabbing the value in saying
We done here get out of here if we still going and so you see you could go through this and
Very much the same implementation than the one we've demonstrated the only difference though is our
Check method is actually
a little bit more
Taking that View
And again validating it
So we doing a 2nd layer of validation here
And then checking whether this specific user that is now logged in has the right to actually
Edit this item so it is doing some user validation
And if not it removes the archive
And it's really we still can have that remove method with little bit of the code that you saw me take out
Is still left in it here
In the previous
Tutorial I use some of these codes and yeah so that's really all the
Same I'm not gonna go into depth if you don't understand what I've just looked at here then please go back to the
The previous tutorial watch that
It gives you enough information so that we actually up here in our file upload
Upload file here we at this point have the package
And we passed the package to upload now
Now move the file into place so remember we had to do that in the
The previous here I'm using a function upload now and in the upload now function
We are returning and if
Any error now still remains
It's gonna be doubt here where is errors that might have a curred here if this was false
We would use that
See that's the error message put it in error
And Pass It out and if we were having
Any other issues we will do there it's been an error and will pass it out so this error handling there already
Now in upload now package
We are checking whether the package is actually there the package name and we're starting to
From that we are building the
Name. Now remember I showed you or explain to you
That we are using
This we're preserving the filename but we are sort of hiding the filename so we
Using the target the target type the file format and then this random key generator
Now
I'm not exactly sure I think all JCB helper classes comes out with this
Random key so you could just use it in your component and you can decide how long this string should
Be and then I'm using a little place holder which is little generic placeholder VDM
And
Then I'm adding the actual name of the file after this placeholder so that everything before
this placeholder
Is really internal my system uses this but the client uses everything this
Side
And so then if it's a document
We are gonna need the folder path for hidden file path so again
Get folder path is a function which I wrote
And I'm not gonna share that with you
But you can build your own helper class function
To get the path to where you wanna put the file this is up to you I'm using a hidden file path
But there is
A lot of
Discussion behind that
If I don't pass any values
like in this case
It most probably return a public path
And which would be where the images
So every documents go in a hidden area
Images go public
And usually because the image you wanted to load somewhere
So you don't want it to be behind
The root folder of your website
Ok now we end up here with the full path which is the file path
Sorry for this this one here
The filename and the file format
So that becomes the file name
And this becomes
The file format
Now I think you will notice that at this stage
The package
Name
Is
Is really what it's used to build this name here
And we stripping the file format from that package name
making sure
That it doesn't have a file format in it
Really to ensure that this
Yeah this file is stored in exactly the format we detected as and not as what do I say it is
Now
We move
The package
This is where
get interesting
To its Final Destination if something fails at this point
like it doesn't move
We actually remove the package and we say there was an error
So we just like we are done
We not gonna worry about it
If it succeeds then obviously if it's an image
At this stage
Image
We definitely want to resize it so I've got a resize
Image helper
Class
This is also something that you would need to write yourself
Which
Helps me to resize my image
I passing it some values
to actually target the image and resize it
And it really doesn't change anything with the image location
Or anything like that so I don't need any value back
I just need it to resize it and get it done and I don't need to know anything else
Then I'm doing some encryption here
To see whether the basic encryption is available in this program
And
Then to actually use that encryption
When I start storing the documents
To the database
So
Here is a local file
And
We are checking if it's a document or a media
We are going to encrypt it
And
Then again here we make sure that this ID value
Is greater than zero because if it's still a unsaved item
We don't have any place in the database to add this
So we could just skip this basically
So if we realize ok this
This file or this
Upload
Doesn't have an ID
Then we skip this function here and we rather do if it's an image
If it's a document or is it it
excuse me if it's a media
Then we load
The filename like that
And
We are going to pass it back
to
The View
Basically taking the results you
See here
Formats it's got a lock value
Then a token
Link
So it has different behavior for different things
And all builds this result array and this is what we
Give them back
We give them back to result array
And it gets started over here
So the File format is added
Success gets the file name which is this value here
And then we start building some other things
Switch are necessary
Like the token link
for the link
Because you want to have the downloadable if
Media document or if it's media
If it's an image no we don't need any of this we can just skip that
And then the key name
And there we go
We done
Where is it it is actually a safe item
We are going to update the database right now
With this new target type
And Target
So this is where the hidden field name
Remember I said to you there's
Some convention
In the hidden
Field name
Well this is where that Convention comes into
To play the hidden field name is build up from Target
And target type
and if these two are not correct we are going to not save this value
At all
And so we are building an object
Which then we take
And since we have validated this this is definitely
the allowed view
And this Object and this ID and then we update the database
And
Yes
We're done
We've got the
File name
And we are basically going to pass the filename
Here
Same way
And return to the browser
So that's the service side
Of this implementation
There are some things which I haven't explained
Like
This
Encryption
Sorry
Resizing of the image
I didn't give much explanation
Get the folder path didn't
You need to write all that up
But
You could make this work without knowing those things
You
You could
Put a
Hardcoded path
Here is the file path
And you could
You know not do any
cropping and let
Let the user
Make sure about
The cropping
That is really
How I upload many of my
Documents and
Things
Obviously this is constantly
improving
Because I'm using the snippet across multiple
Places
It's very easy for me to come in here
And say oh this is not
Ideal and
Fix it
And then it fix it
Everywhere for every every place it's
been used
And so there is sometimes the Need of decoupling some of these functions in some but I'm trying to
Yes try as much as I can to not
Do that
So set filename array that's another function that you saw
Here in in the upload where is it
Set filename array
This set file name array  is really
a key when you realize that the actual file
Already exists
So the ID is there
Because that means that there are other files possibly still already in the database
So with
The add and basic view we actually trigger the set filename array
Function
To check the database
For that specific
Target
Field get the values
I decrypt them and
Load new values to that
And then basically
Pass it back to us
Where if the item doesn't exist
That means it doesn't have an ID
I don't know if you remember when we
Did some demonstration I was
Actually adding multiple
Media files that only one ended up
Being remembered
And that sort of the downside
Of the current
Implementation
Is that if the ID doesn't
Exist
We're not able to actually keep track of that
So it's only when the ID exist
That we are able to
Actually do multiple uploads at
Once
So I should actually
Give a little bit heads up of the about that
That you want to save the item
You're actually ready to
To expand upon it
And to allow
Multiple upload at
Once
So the set filename array is
Is really dealing with multiple when you are having multiple so you'll see there is image
And document
Is when the file
I'm using the
The plural
to tell me
That it should allow multiple
So if it's singular
Image
And document then I don't allow multiple
I'm just gonna remove the old one
And add the new
Done
And when it is plural
And we are using the set filename array
And we basically building
It to
actually be
Multiple
And then
One thing I didn't
Emphasize
here
Is
That we actually remove the
files as well
There is a remove file right
There's remove file
And it also at some point does a validation
To check whether the user has the
Permission to remove files
And
And then will basically remove
the file
So that is
Also and it's
Also uses
Is this file name
But then it passes the remove
Variable to it
Which then means the action is not to add but to take
Away and
You will see that there
The action here
There is the
Add and there is the take away option
So behave still different
So we still basically get back the array we still build an object and we still updated Database
As well as
Actually removing the file here
Ok so all of this code I will dump on GitHub and the gits
For you to reuse as you see fit you'll obviously have to Adapt it
And
Keep it under an open source licence
That's
Only requirement
Ok well
That if all those things line-up and are in place
Going back to our
Admin View
Basically
That needs to be there
These things
Need to be here so you could
Pause the film
And
Video
And just make sure that you have the same kind of
Ajax
Query calls option
And then here I am actually
Doing some opening of the files
You see that I'm building but I'm called links
So this is going a little Beyond
Just showing you a little bit of my implementation and these links
Eventually
End up on the page
So we've go back
to
Our JavaScript
Here
Scroll down
We see this get filed JS
Now let's
Again look at that get file JS
Because
You'll see that those links
Actually come in
To play there
If I Remember correctly
let see here
Oh I see now is not in that JavaScript
Is actually down here
You see that here I got a
Load the links to the page document links
And I'm actually adding it to a variable called document
links you see
So in the
Custom script
Where is it it's not this one
It's this one you'll see if I
If I now search
So I'll take this copy
and here I'll search
You'll see that I'm actually using that array
And saying is this
property there
And then creating a link
And so that is how we deal with some of that
And it it works very well
To sort of pass value
from
JavaScript
to PHP
And have it available there
Ok well
I know this was a lot of
Things to sort of take in and I would expect you to realize that that previous implementation is
So much easier
But like you've seen
When someone actually does create a document
And they
Are able to so easily
Just drag and
Drop stuff
And it just crops and
It just gives your component so much an easier you know for you feel to it
Instead of
The olds you could still do the old select
But the Drag and Drop is
Becoming quite popular
And this implementation is
Really
Very
Yeah it's very nice to have
And I'm sure from what I've shown you you should be able to get this going in your component
I'm not really gonna give support on to this meaning that
If you get stuck you on your own
Because if
It is really the truth that you will need to know your JavaScript you'll need to
know
Your PHP
and you will need to know how to debug
And how to line-up these
Concepts
That they all
I work in
Synergy together
It's not gonna be
So easy for me to
Do that
Specially since I usually do not see the code
But if there isn't any of the code that I've share on
Gits
Which I will also put in the description below this video
Even have that code has issues in it
Or errors in it that the
That are like ok
a very big problem or something
Then please do feel free to
Give me a heads up over there
And we'll collaborate
Improve it as
Necessary
At the end of the day This feature is really way behind
What
What you really need
There is a media manager in
In Joomla
Which is actually ideal
The advantage about this way is that your user is
Is never gonna interfere with other users documents or images or
Stuff
So if you use this concept they not ever gonna actually look on your server at a list
And select stuff
This is why I think people would like this
Because they can upload stuff in
It doesn't affect other people it doesn't make
you more vulnerable as the owner of the system
Who uses the application
So it is I think we better approach
But like I said there is a media manager
So if you go to content
There is a media manager
And there is a media file type
Which
Works very well
And
And can also add
These kind of functionality to your component
If this is a little bit too challenge
To a big of a challenge for you
Anyway thanks for watching
I know this might again be so such a long
Tutorial
But I'm trying my very best
To sort of get you on your feet and you to go.OK.