Ok well recently I was asked whether
I'm seriously saying that Hella World
Tutorial should be an hour long and I had to laugh because of course
That tutorial is doing way more than what a Hello World tutorial should do right so
Here it goes we gonna do the real quick Hello World tutorial we go to extensions
Install
We searched for JCB
We open it
And we click install
And again install
On success we go to component Builder
And we click on
Import JCB packages
We go to VDM packages we select
The
Hello World
Component for free with click get package
We'd see that it has a checksum validation 413
We click this a link here
To check and make sure that it is the same key as on GitHub
So we can check that that key
Matches this one
And it does
So we know it's a package
Still
Authentic and
Then we we can say yes Force update and click continue
Great import was successful and we go back to Joomla components we see that our Hello World component has
Been installed
We go to compiler
And we click Hello World
And compile
It successfully compiled so we click install
And
We look at the back end
We create a greeting
Say
Hi James
Save and close
And so our first greeting is set
We go to menu
Main menu we change the main menu to be a selection
type
Hello World
Greetings
And
That should be it we save and close
And we click on Joomla Mount we see there is a page
Is not directing properly
So that might be a problem in the component we go back to hello world
And we click on the global options
And permissions
And we search for site
Because there are some site views that we need to allow
it to show
Public
That one and
That one
so those two will show and
yeah we save out of here we refresh to front
And there we have it
There is a greeting
Hi
James we can click on it
And it says hi James we can go back one
And then click on edit
It says I'm not allowed to edit I'm not in the edit group
We can go back to the backend click on options
And we could actually give me edit permissions as public but I think you get the point
Hello world in place functional and
It was really very quickly to do
And that is the quick or the real hello world how to set up a Hello world component in
Joomla
Component builder without
Waiting a whole hour thanks for watching