We've added a new function
To JCB which allows you to add a field
to a view
Without adding the field to the database
Now when will that be useful
Usually
When you have a field which maybe is getting data from another table
And
You want to actually change the behaviour on the page based on the data selected
But that selection itself isn't relevant
Or when you want to actually combine two fields
As one in the database
Then you could have both fields on the page
And on submission in your save area in the admin View
You can add some custom PHP script
To take the value from that other field
And actually
Save it in to this
Field that you intend to
Combine the two values
And so you don't want both values to be stored in the database
Or the other option is you have fields on a page which
Actually only get used to generate data in another table
So when you save that item it takes those values put it into
The other table
And basically
Leave just one value in this table
Which next time you open it up all those fields are hidden based on that value selection
Something like that
So it's really got multiple implementations and sort of helps you to get
A subform on the page
Or any kind of other field type
To be able to you know use it
Once
You know what use it within your custom scripting either in JavaScript
Or in PHP
A previously this wasn't possible if you add a field to view it always gonna get
Stored into the database
But now
If you go to admin views
And
You well
Let's take one
That has this function going
We use the admin view
Fields
So you'll see that this new
Feature is
Replaced your admin view list option
Because now you got show in list
And then you have the default which was the previous
Check or uncheck option
Which basically is 1 and 0
But now you got a third one
Which is called No DB
I have a field called not required which basically is what you would usually add
If you are using
Conditional JCBs
Internal conditional option
And you have Fields that actually are required
But within certain criteria those fields are hidden
And obviously then not required
Then I'm using this not required field
To basically Store Some values with JavaScript that upon submission
It did adapts the validation on the server side
Now
I don't really want that value in the database so I'm using this
Non DB option
If you changed any other Fields I'm just gonna do demonstration
Obviously I do want this field in the database but just to sort of show you
If you select no DB
It will automatically give you this notice
Basically these two notices
The one saying the non DB option
Will remove this field from being saved in the database
And then this one
Only use the non DB option if you're planning on targeting this field
With JavaScript or custom PHP
To move it's value into another field that does get saved
to the database
In one form or another basically saying to you
But if you use this value we not gonna store whatever is placed
In it
In the database for you
You will need to manually
Do that
So that's really why it's there it's really for custom
customization to your components behaviour
And so you'll see that also clears out
All your selections because None of these features
Will be
Of you know be used well a vailable to this field
Because this field
After saving
Dumps is value and it doesn't exist
Unless you grab it and
you know
Use it into your script
Ok so
If you use the list option
We now have this automated
Counter adding
So
Every time you do that if counts all the fields that are available
Already in your script
And then it adds the next
Logic number
But anyway that's Beyond of what I'm actually explaining or demonstrating
So for now
Our
Purpose here
Is to show you that there is a new
No DB
Field behaviour
Which Some of you have been requesting
And I also needed it in the past
So it's available now
You can try it out play with it
And of course if it doesn't make sense to you just don't use it
Ok well thanks for watching