The option to now add your own custom dashboard
To your component has actually finally come
I might have mentioned this in some previous tutorials but it's somewhat hidden
So I thought Well let's do it quick tutorial just about this
So in the past all components basically it's layout ended up as the dashboard looking like this
Obviously with your own icons
But you could do only about what you see here
And this is still the default dashboard
So if you don't add your own
You're basically Build this for you
Based on your Fields based on it's icons and layout selection
So you could add tabs like we have here
And these tabs are quite powerful
You can really
Add
A lot of
Functionality within that
But for some of you this might be boring and not really what you would like in fact you wanna look different
You don't want your component to look like it was built with JCB
And I don't blame you because that is what makes components
Valuable
Is that they are actually unique
And that is really why JCB exists it exist because I didn't want a cookie cutter component
I wanted to build my own components that actually look different from
Each other in yet have similar
Behaviour because of my company's approach
But
None of the others out there actually
Could do that for me
They all
We ended up looking
Just like
The one
We were using
So now with JCB
We constantly
Trying to make sure that this is not the case in fact that's why the site view area is it a bit more difficult
Because you wanna give you
The opportunity to express your components functionality
In a way that's unique to you
This might be a challenge but in the long run believe me it is the advantage
If you could do it without knowing
Any Javascript with CSS or HTML
Then anyone else can do it as well
So there is like a little bit of a
Yeah incentive to sort of
Get your head around some of these Technologies
And any case to be a good component developer and not knowing PHP
And those
Front-end languages
Is most certainly a risk ok
Well
So without any further ado if we were to go
We'll have your this common known
Hello World
Component
and if we would to
Open it in the website now
This is it dashboard
Now it doesn't have a custom dashboard
And
I'm not gonna add one at this point but I am gonna
Take-away
The dashboard it has and
So then it's sort of behaves
Like the article manager for example
If we would go here there's an in the components area there is a new tab or rather
a tab called
Dash&Install
You see here it has the default
And then here
It has some description of what that means
If you click on dynamic
It actually gives you a list of all the available
Sites
Views that are linked to the component
And that would be custom admin views
As well as
Normal admin views it will show you a list of them all
And you can then select
Any of those
And that will become the new dashboard for your component
So basically save and close
And go to the compiler and compile the
Hello World
Component
And basically just reinstall
So to demonstrate how that changed our components behaviour
So
we're going to install
Then we will
Basically go to components and click on
This hello world link
To see what it does now as its default dashboard
And so it loads the listview and the dashboard is gone
So from this point forward
Your Hello World Component
Actually
Looks like this
And it doesn't have a dashboard
Now you could use a custom dashboard
Which and In our case
If you
If you're using
A component
That has custom admin views
So JCB has
The compiler and the gets Snippets area as custom admin views
So if we were to do the similar
thing with JCB
We could just as well
Select
One of those
Obviously say dynamic
And select
One of those views
So scroll down a bit
Where is it
There
The compiler we could make the compiler
JCB's
Dashboard
Now
I know it's gonna break a lot of things somehow I suppose but let's try it out
So we got JCB now we switched it to have another dashboard
Instead of the normal dashboard
The compile it here
And then install
Before install it I just want to tell you what I meant by things may break
We got a bunch of times here
And all these tabs are getting information and making it available
To you so you could just get
information from us
And we got the version here in the last build date and
Yeah so you are basically gonna remove this whole area
So or we just did
If I click on this
install
we see first
It tells us that this language string is no longer here
And at first it seems like it's a broken issue but if we refreshed it
You see that actually removed it
And so it's just a cash thing there
So basically the dashboard is gone
And if I was to
Go here and click on
Component builder, it will from now on open right at the compiler
And that will now be it's default page
Which is what we told it
And so the behaviour is correct
We don't see any issues
And actually if you were to gonna go to the code
Dashboard is completely removed all is files everything
And so no trace of it is left
Obviously to undo this
you could
Simply say default again
And save and close
And then compile it again
And it will place the dashboard back
So
That's not really any harm done to the component
But for those of you wanna take the custom admin views
And design a much more
Impressive maybe not a boring
Dashboard
Can now do so
By Simply using this new feature
And I'm sure it's gonna be a lot of fun
So there we refresh now
Are dashboards back and if you click on it
There we go everything is fine again
Shoo away thanks for watching