I would like to demonstrate you the new feature of removing and adding a prefix to your
Component name in the Joomla menu
Take a look at the menu there's this little arrow
in front of Component Builder
And that's the prefix we talking about
in the past it would add that automatically
Now it will still do that but you can actually change it so
Go to the global options of a component
And under the global tab
You see a new area called Add Menu Prefix
And there's a little description there
And you can say no
And then it won't have any prefix
Or you can change this to any
Other prefix you want
Are there you don't need to add a space here and the space is automatically done so you can check out
This list here. There is a link to a list
of HTML character entities that you need to use here
This will obviously translate to that arrow
And
You need to make sure to use something that can be it just placed inside of an XML file
So
That means that if you wanna use strange characters like that arrow
You need to use the HTML you could also use your company name or
You can use anything it'll basically just add that
As a prefix to the component name
So just of illustrate this
Let me change this a little bit
So I am grabbing the the value here
The one without the x is the one we looking for so this the & hash
Value this one here
I'm gonna grab that little circle with a dot. Well let's take the one with the
Circle in a circle that looks nice
Ok I'm gonna take that one
I'm gonna add it in here
And I'm going to click save
Ok it's asking me to add some other info as well
Ok try again save and close
Now let's go and compile
one of the
demo components here
So you can say demo
And compile
And install it
Now you'll see it has this little circle
Next to the demo name
That's the way we can
Change that little
Prefix
And then obviously the option to just remove it altogether
It's also there
Basically
Saying no prefix save and close
And let's do it again
Compile and
install
And now you'll see it's just the way usual components will look there is the demo
So this little
Prefix can be added or removed now thanks to this new feature