I want to
Demonstrate
The way to add JCB packages to the community
Directory
The moment if you go to import JCB packages this now in new tab called community
Packages
Where we would like to encourage all of you to start sharing packages
Main focus or purpose for it would become
To be quick start
For developing
Components
it could serve
As a back up for yourself too easily
Pull on old
Packages that you've developed
To maybe have a specific feature for example
Linking your Joomla users
into your component
I know apps or componants that does that
And I often want to reuse that
So
You can now with this new
Idea
Be able to import that component over and over
I without merging it with
The old version
But actually creating a new
Component including Fields and everything else
And so that way
You are able to quickly start a new project
And you don't need to really do all that over again and again
It's sort of similar as the Clone feature that now has become available so they JCB components now
Clone feature
You could select a component
And you can clone it
And in cloning it
It basically creates
A Exact Copy of the component
But not linked
To the components so even did admin views
You see it actually create a new admin View
And the same goes for the fields
You actually created
a whole new
set of fields
Specifically
For this component you see it's got the same
Suffix
(EO)
Ok so
That is the Clone feature and now the import feature has the same functionality
So if I was to go and say let's import
The demo component
Then
Once it has
gotten the component from GitHub
We will see
That it has this merge option or no don't merge now
Remember we
Already have the demo component here and it is exactly the same component
But I don't want it to update this one
I want it to really
Bring it in as a new component and then I will
detect this to No and it does give you a little explanation here and also tells you that the paradation rules
Field types snippet languages and language strings
These things will still be merged
And that simply is unavoidable
Ok and then if you wanna see
You know what happens on the hood
And then you click on continue
And what it will do now
Obviously give you a whole lot of information of the import
And also whatever files it moved
But it actually created a new component
It didn't update the old one
And that is a very nice option because now
You can quickly start with this component without affecting this one
Now you'll see that
Even the admin view is
Dislocated it's not the same admin View
The same again with the fields so if we look at the fields you'll see it also has the (Ra)
Suffix
to it (Ra)  (Ra)
This name doesn't anywhere appear
In the compiled version of the components it's all system names
So this (Ra) will just be for your own
to know that this
Field belongs to this component and so on
So that's sort of what the new JCB package import option is sort of been improved to to manage
Now with the community option
You can actually do what we wanna call
What is a share
Like I've been doing
Sharing
So many in a lot of information with all of you
Components tools
And so the idea that all of you would have this attitude of
Giving back to the community
And the other option is that if you want to distribute a package
And at the same time maybe get some marketing
This is also gonna be doing that
Ok, so let me illustrate to you the process of getting a package into the community
Packages
We are going to use
GitHub
Basically this repository JCB community packages
This is the URL
VDM -
IO
/
JCB - community - packages
You will need to fork this package
I'm not gonna teach you how to use GitHub
neither how to use Git
I'm gonna illustrate it just by doing it
Doing what you need to do
Demonstrating it to you
But I'm not gonna teach you how to do this in a
More thorough away
So you need to
Go and study up GitHub
And Git
Specifically to be able to manage this
And what will happen is anyone who wants to add a package must start by forking
The repository
And then once it's been forced
They need to clone it down to their the developing environment
Where they have JCB
Or to where they can move a JCB package
Because at the end of the day they need to add their package which they want to contribute
To their forked version
Of
This
JCB community packages
And then once they done all that and pushed up the changes to their repository
Then they'll make a pull request
To add the change
Into the community
Version of this repository now
Hope that all makes sense to you
You'll get the URL here
On your own repository
Copy that
And then you'll go to your
Developing environment
Hopefully
It will be Linux
Because you need to
Run a bash script, so
Needs to be a bash environment
And
Yeah so you could run it in a VM where ever you want
Just get it going so I'm gonna open a terminal now
And then the terminal I'm simply gonna clone
this repository
And then once it's finished cloning it we gonna change to that directory
Now if we list out
The items
You will see that it is exactly the same as what we have here on GitHub
It is in literally the same
Information
So it is actually a folder a folder on your computer
And we will then now need to go to JCB
Extract the package you want to share
And simply place it into this folder
And then Run
This hash.sh script
Ok
So let me do that
So here we are in our
JCB program
And I want to share this question and answers
component and I would ask that you won't share things that do not work
If you still busy developing the thing then it is not time to share it yet
But when it's ready
And you know that it works that means you've compiled it and tested it and you know it stable
Then anyone share it
Does need to be a big component it could have just one View
Doesn't matter
But it needs to be something other than already what exist
So no more new demo components
it need to be something else
So
Always please check that if you wanna contribute something
Be something that's already there
If there is already one
And you want to improve it sure then you can do that you can
pull it in make it better and make it pull request to improve it
But just know that we will have to be able to test it
So if you're using a key
Then the person that you get it from
You can't
Contributed without a key
Back in fact
If someone places
A package in the
Community
And has a key
Then
it sort of lockout everybody else
Because then only they can improve it
But as soon as I take the key away
Then everybody else can improve it because there is no key
And doesn't matter we all can check it out
Ok
So
I'm not exactly sure how all this is gonna workout
I am very open to all of you to just give me feedback input how you think this should be done
The idea is not to
Infringe on each other's projects
But to help each other get projects going quite quickly
That's really the agenda
The idea is if you wanna build a project let's get something that can sort of serve as a base
From which to start so this question and answers
Program is there is a very nice base it's got just
Few views a few fields
It's got a very simple straight forward implementation of
Q&A for your front in of your website
And so I thought well this is a nice thing to
to sort of use
As a demonstration
So I'm gonna export this
Wait a minute let me just show you something else before we do that
Is going to the component
And
those of you who want to maybe give away the component
But you want to sort of
have people first visit
Maybe a video that you've made
The way you could do this
Is by this Buy Link here you'll basically make that link
Direct to your video
So that when they click on the Buy Link they go to the video
Were you gonna give them the key for free
And they can
Watch the video get the key come back and open the package
we're not currently
Already implementing package link
The package link should be
Where the package is
Which most of the time will be the repository
Which is why we not fully implementing this because it's sort of yeah we don't need it
So we left it here maybe for future purposes
But at the moment we don't need it the way we've set up things
You can sort of just use the repo URL
So it is only the Buy link that's really important
If it's not a free package or if it's a free package but you're giving the key away
So the other idea is not add a key at all
So
If you don't add a key here
Then it will be a free package
This is how you make something a free package it's just
Leaving the key out
That's simple as that
And
Then it will be a free package
Where as if you leave the key in
then people will have to get the key from you
And if you've got a contributor to the community
Then
you'll need to share the key with the admin of the repository
So they can validate the component and check that it's safe for distribution
We'll stop with some things in place maybe a forum
Procedure on how to do this
Inside of JCB or maybe just
In the read more of the repository
We'll give you a heads up when that happens
For now the explanation is simple if you want to have people get the key from you
Where ever they need to get it weather it's free or paid
Needs to be this link here
And
The key
This here is what we used to build the key it's not the actual key
It's just used to build a key so you can put in anything here really
Ok
Now once you got all that in place
You will compile your component
Or export the JCB package really that's the right name
once you got the component
Exported
Then the package is available
in a specific
Directory called "temporal directory" in your
Developing environment
And this is the package
That you wanna add to the repository
This is the key that you now need to give to everybody
That wants to use the package
So this key
can nowhere to be found
unless on this page
where you compiled it
store this key in a safe place
Or use it in your video
and give it to the people in the right playtime
Whatever you like to to do this
The Next Step would be to now move this package into
The
Repository which we cloned down to your local developing environment
Here I got the folder open where the package is so you see there
Is following that path which we found
When we look at this it's same path
So basically we gonna just drag
And drop
The file into the other folder which is where that
Clone repository is at the moment
In my home folder
So here we have
The package been added
And
We basically done
And we can close this one out
And go back to the terminal
Once in a terminal if you say get
Status
You see that it tells you that is one file
That isn't
been tracked
Now before you add the file
You first need to run
The hash.sha
...
program
Which is a bash little script
So you need bash to run it and a few other two other programs actually
I'm pretty sure you that
It's this
JQ and sha1sum
These two programs is also required
And that the script will actually shout at you that
if it doesn't exist will say hey , you need to get these
So if you
You can just
Google JQ
Bash
Install and it will
Give you information
And adding these two programs to your
Developing environment
And then run that script
What that script will do
is very simple
it'll go through the files in the repository that are zip files that's what it does here
it will create a sum
And then will place the sum
In a file with the same name except
Added the sha to the file name
So there it adds it
Then it will
get a shop file name and then unzip
The file to get the info.
VDM file from the zip package
Then change that to the shop filename
Which should be the same as your package name just with info as the prerogative
Which is what we need to show the people what your package name is and who owns it and these things
So that's where that info come from
Then it takes that information and
It adds it to an array
Which
Then later gets written to the checksum.json
That's all this does
Nothing
Not not no not smart really it's just straight forward
Some Little Bash
Do to get the information from the file
For you without your having any issues
And that it
Just follow convention
So I'm gonna go run the file now and you can see what it does
So basically you add the the Dot here make sure in the repository then the Dot
And then
The hash.sh
And enter and it should just do that simple as that
Shouldn't take long and if it did
Then something is wrong
This is all it should do
Now if you again do the git status
You'll see that now there are actually 3 files
That of not be tracked and tricks some file
Has been modified
And why because there is now a new line been added
To check some so if we do
Git
diff
You'll see that your component the one that you are adding
This one
Is being added
And so that line was changed because it got a comma
But this is the new line that it is added
So basically just added your component
To the check some
And that is all that should change
You shouldn't change any other files
In the repository
Only the ones that you are contributing
Are the ones that you must change
Ok so
There we go
The next thing is to git
Add
Those files
So if you do git
Status
They are now green
now the comment
The comment
I think
We there's like Convention out there
I'm not so keyed up all that
So the moment I think we can do
Git
Then
Add it
Questions and answers package I think that's simple enough
And then
Press enter
Oops I left out something and it's to commit word
So she say git commit
Then a m
The m is for the message in the a is for pushing it all into the branch
So there we go and then you have if you have a pass phrase
and you
Which I should actually have
Then there you have your commit signed
If you don't know how to sign commits in git then please Google that and get your keys in place
We would expect that all commits to this repo
Be signed
Specially since we need to be sure
That it is you
That am you know making the commit
Now when you've done all that you do git
And your push it up
To your repository on GitHub
At this point you are still not affecting the community repository
It is just affecting
The the repository that you forked
And
That is
This is a very secure way of dealing with this
So if we now go back to Git
Hub
And you know were fetch the page
You see that I'll say this branch is one commit ahead of VDM
And then there is this make a pull request
So you make a pull request there
And it will basically take you
To the main repository
And all explain to you which one is being pulled where and it will tell you that it is able to be merged
And
Did this is the information that's being added
For the info
For the sha
And obviously for the package which it doesn't show because it's too big
So you see Binary file not shown
there it is
And so there is also the changes to the checksum
Now at this point
You need to
Create a pull request to click on create pull request
And
This
Comment that you made in your repository when you you know
Contributed the package would usually be added as the title
You wanna give a little explanation of things that we as the admin team need to have dissipate
Because we got obviously have to test this now
We can't add packages to the community packets branch without being able to test it
So if you have a key for the package
Then
Yes
I think we will create a form
Eventually
Where you will be able to submit that
And we'll put that in the information because at the moment this area doesn't even have a pull request template
So we will add a pull request template
So that when you create a pull request that tells you where to send the key
Set the moment if there's a pull request maybe just keep the packages coming that are free at the moment
as soon as the templates in place then then you can use it
And then make a pull request
And
Then
I'm at the moment the only one that
Manage this but I hope that others would get involved
There are some other developers already
Quite involved on the JCB
Repository
But I would like to also encourage them to get involved here
And be able to sort of help me
Test these packages
Make sure that only valid in
Stable packages gets
Added
And so
That's really it here you now click create pull request now I'm gonna do this
Because it's all premature
I I want to
I don't wanna pull this into this
The repository at the stage
I'm gonna do so later
But the point is
This is the procedure that you need to follow
To actually get a package into the community packages
Because once it's get merged into the master branch
It will also become available on this page
Automatically
So automatically it'll show up in this dropdown
In fact
That is a simple as it is
Well thanks for watching and if you have any questions please open a issue
At the correct place
So if you wanna talk about the packages for the community
Open issue here
Please don't make a open issues at JCBs repository regarding this issue
So that we'll have you know clear
Separation
Between these two concepts. Ok thanks for watching.