I would like to give you a quick tutorial on how to install
A JCB package
Or import
Is the right word really
Now
At the end of day
You already have JCB on your
System
So I'm not gonna explain how we got to this point
But from here on further
There are two ways to
To get to the in
Installing
View
One is by clicking on this icon
It'll take you there
The other one is going to Joomla components
And there is a button
Up here this is import JCB
Packages
And that will take you to the same place
You'll see that there is a number of tabs here
And you can actually
If you don't If you're not interested in these
Two tabs
There's action option in the global options
Where at this point we are controlling those tabs
Through this
Global switch that says manage JCB package the directories
You can say show all
Show none
Or manually select
The repositories that you want the show at the moment they are the least two
But they are
Reasons to expect that they might become more
as
We see
You know
This area becoming more active
Ok so
Once you're on this page
And you have yourself exported a JCB package then this is where you can select it from your
Computer
Or from a directory
Or from a URL
And with these import methods
There is not a checksum validation feature in place
So you need to be sure of the Integrity of that package
We cannot validate that package integrity
And since if it's being
Selected from your desktop and you are in a your local development environment
There should be no reasons for concern
If you're pulling it from an external source
Then possibly
You need to be more cautious
Where is it when it comes to the VDM packages and the JCB community packages
These are the areas where we are trying to add some layer of
Security
To try and protect you
And to ensure that
The package area remains as stable as possible
And so there is ways for you to add your own JCB package
To the community repository
Here is a tutorial to show you how to do that
And
Also
Explaining
Why
We will do things
The way we do them
Because of
The fact that everybody will then have access to that package
In this area
You can then also also
Now get free keys
For the VDM packages
In the past you have to pay for them
And we have decided in
In a initiative to
Sort of
Show all of you exactly how JCB can work and function
We have decided to give these packages way
Asking you to follow few steps
In supporting Us by
Forking starring or
watching
These packages in their specific repositories on GitHub
needing more guidance about this
You can just click on that link
And they'll show you exactly what you need to
Do
and once you've
Got the key for that
specific package
You can come and select that package here
Obviously
It's only related to some of the packages at this point
Which the first being
Most prominent
Component builder itself
And so I would
Suspect that would
Would be your First Choice as
Well
and once you've selected the package you simply can click on
Get
to
Have the package be
Taken
From GitHub
And Brought
To your
Developing environment
And in doing so
It will actually run a validation on the Integrity of the package
Because they are checksums
In place
But
You need to validate the check some
Manually
And the way you do that
Is it'll show you the checksum that was used
to evaluate
The
Package integrity
And since it's past the validation
You know this checksum is the one that you need to see
If you're open
This link
So opening this link will also reveal a checksum
But at this time you will be seeing a verification
By
Digi
Cert
And
It must be at least
This part of the URL
Must be correct
Up There
This will vary from package to package
But it should have the package name here
And this should correspond
To the value you to
See here
And that little bit of manual effort
Is all you need to do
To be sure that the package that you have now got
In your position
Is the original authentic package that we have
distributed
So at this point you're all good to go all you need now
Is to take the key that we have sent you
And to add it here
To the key area
like so
Now you need to make a choice
Whether you want to if the JCB already is installed on your system maybe it's the second time you doing this
Then you might not want to merge you might want to have it be like a clone
I like a second instance of JCB it will literally
Then create all the fields and all the views
And all the linked
Concepts
Again
Where is if you choose merge
And
There is a change in the package which is newer
Then the version you have it will
Actually update
That version
If you wanna force it
To update it
You will say yes up here
The force local update really Only Works
If you selected merge
Then there's also show all import information
Which if it is the first time that you're importing package
It might be ideal to to check this yes
Because it'll show you literally everything that it does every field it adds
But it will not show your names or shows your IDs a lot of it will be like ok that doesn't make sense
To see anyway
But at the very bottom of the list
It shows you that
Files that is moved and this is what you need to see
You need to see the files that is moved
Into your system
Specially if it's not a package that we are providing
Or someone else that is being
Sort of validated through the community
But it's someone that you've
Imported through a URL
Or through a package from you
Distributor package you received
Or from a directory
Then you most certainly wanna
see all import info
Because you wanna make sure that what they told you is what you get and that's what that little feature is all there
About
Then there is also the component that is being imported should show
Here the same as the one you saw before we got the package
Now those of you that have used this area multiple times
You will know
That you're actually able to add
Multiple components into one package
It's just because we at VBM
Are distributing one component at a time
That's why there's only one component in the package
But in in
Integrated perspective
You can actually import a backup package
Right here
And that would be
Then everything
That you have done
So in my case all the components I've build are actually zipped in a backup patch package
And I can import all of those into JCB at once at the moment
I've tested it up to at least 20 components which is
It takes a while but it and actually gets there
Ok so at this point
Everything looks fine
And you can click continue
This depending on the size of the component
All the size of package
Might take longer and shorter
And I would just suggest that you wait it out
Take a sip
Coffee or something
It it does take a while because literally at this point
It is updating the IDs
Everyone
One at a time
So with every field the IDs are being updated with
Every view and everywhere that ID in any other ID is being used anywhere across the component
Everything is dynamically being updated
During this process
And
So as you can expect it is a lot of
Compilation
Lot of algorithm
Lot of things happening under the hood
And therefore does take a little bit longer than
You might expect
Because the ID is changed
And the way we in export the package
Is literally
Just taking a photocopy of the package as it is in the JCB where it was
Develop
Or when it resides
And when you imported we now recreate and remap every ID
To ensure that it remains functional although basically all it's identifiers
have changed
Ok so just wait and in the moment it will show you that it's been successful
But it does take a while
Once it's done
You get this
Longest especially if it was JCB
Which you've imported
I mean it's a long list
It has over 1000 field so
You can anticipate a long scroll
I'm gonna grab this
thing here
and drag it
And it goes and goes and goes
And it's
Huge
But they're very much at the bottom you start seeing different things
Like the files every little file that has been
Imported
And that's really helpful
If you are importing a package
From a developer which you do not
No or
You're not absolutely sure you can
Trust
The now you must check
Every one of these Fields that they are legitimately related to this component
And that it is actually what you
anticipated
Or expected
And you can also Therefore go look at these folders
They are all related
The custom folder
At the moment as we scroll and now here
Are some
Folders that are related to the administrator
VDM compiler
Yes
This is in the compiler so there's a lot of files for the
compiler
Joomla 3
Then for the helper this
This little thing here is just like a
Spacer really
By which we sort of
Create the string
And so there you get all the files that have been moved into place and low and behold
There is component builder the fully mapped
Package
In your system
And that's really as simple as it is to get
The component that
You need
Fully mapped
Into your system
And as you can see
All it's
Views are correctly mapped in here
And if you open any of those views
you'll again see that all it's fields
Are also
Correctly
Mapped
And
You do realize that every one of these Fields their IDs have changed
And even
The fields
They again
Have field types
And even those
Might have changed
The field types
Itself
And so
Down to the very
Smallest detail we've tried
To make sure that every little thing
All across the board
is remapped
And
You know
Fixed so that your component is again
Fully Active and stable ready for further development
Ok so that is the quick tutorial on how to import a JCB package into JCB. Ok thanks for watching.