Person could use in trying to create extensions
My name is Marco Dings you can interact on social media with any of these
items since I've got a lot sites.  I'm not going to read them out
Interact here
So I'm gonna tell a bit of what's out there because there's more solutions out there than Joomla Component
Builder why use a tool and then I'm focusing on the Joomla component builder itself and
We'll have a nice giveaway at the end of the session
So why use a tool at all
What's out there?
We have Component Creator I think that's a about it well-known extension by RST Joomla
sermon it's SAAS solution it's closed source
It's free for one table you have to pay subscription
Well you do get provisional support.  This is a wonderful too that's been
Presented on JAP since 2015 or even earlier JoomDD
Which is actually a model driven
Tools or it actually abstracts your ideas and then generates a code out of it meaning you could
A theory create a Joomla a Drupal or a WordPress website go
forward if that's nice plugins for please in store many clips if you gave it a stuff and
Now I also has a web editor it has some basic reverse engineering starts
Theoretically you theoretically you can feed it any extension and it should be able to make model of them
I emphasize the theoretical part because I think that's quite some limitations for that to actually work
What is open source so the instinct developers are the back of the room and
You can't travel back in time but you could have seen their session
And is this Joomla component Builder a very unknown
Tool
What it has its own characteristics Joomla component builder is a component that you logged
Into your website
It actually is on your platform it builds the component for your
You in your plat form so you don't you're not dependent on any SAAS Solution whatsoever
And the tools was actually used to build itself
So the model that is used as they refer to themselves as the mapped
Joomla component that's where the you have the gooey interaction and stuff that
Used to generate its own coat
The compiled source is open source
So the mapped Component isn't but it's gonna change however
Even at this point in time there is no licence costs and are no limitations
So as component creator allows you to create a component based on one table yeah you can't do
very much with that
There still doesn't have any
Any limitations
So
Let me start by
Asking you what are the challenges that you see when you
Let we for start with the question who creates components or has created their own components in the past
Ok that's quite a lot of
People so what are the challenges that you'd see
In
That's so let me start with my esteemed colleagues Eve and Victor who I specially want to thank
For attending for the promise to do that so Eve what challenges
do you see when you create a new component
Well nothing
Yeah
And you're not lazy you want to
get
Rid of that of that repetition.  Let's say yes.
Ok
Everybody as a remark that people thank you very much thank you thank you
Anybody else want to add something. If sometimes if you change a name or something
Where it is their and their and their you have to correct them yeah
and does it that changes because of things that you do yourself ours changes that it's done by Joomla. no the change you do by yourself
Whatever it does
I should Change to this and then have to change it everywhere
Anybody want to add something. Rene. It is big the way components actually hold together
Yes.  You can get lost you know.
Yeah
you can really quickly create a basic component
but if you want to do something special and you can't do it with these component creators. You can't load it back to your component field.
Ok ok have summarize some of the
Things that I think annoy me and doing that stuff that's a boilerplating
that is Specially what Eve was referring to setting up the directory structure creating all the crop files now
there is tools that will help you with that beach be storm but still it's tedious work and you have to watch the
Capitalisation of the names and the slots of naming conventions
And really I'm lazy
And you think that a tool can do for me I'm very happy with
I also like
to reuse stuff
Obviously if you've already create a lot of extensions then you can reuse previous word back copy pasting
But
Yeah you want to rename it so there's some work involved you might want to reuse
Other people's work
Maybe somebody created something nice and we use that and obviously use libraries in general
that contain
abstract stuff
There's a lot of stuff in Joomla that we all
Love I think
But you still have to do some stuff
By yourself and your own component if you want to have away make that work being multilingual
Support
Having from of groups
Access control structure
Adding history to your
Components use just as with article so that you can see you who changed what and what time
Custom fields
And not all tools support that and obviously the tools out there have their limitations either be it cost
Be it the licensing scheme
Or be it the skills required
And
Advanced items I would say ok can you extend that tool
Easily to
Accommodate new features
So should that be a
Workflow extension to Joomla
How is it can you add up to your own component
Tools should in theory be able to
Add that without bothering you with
all the
nitty gritty details
Can you do reverse engineering JoomDD is a tool that can do that
Impart so that's ok
But
To me more importantly is the roundtrip development which Rene mentioned
Typically in the tool when you start you have their school while you can easily click together a table and view and stuff like that
You exported to got your component then you start working on it
As soon as you realize that you missed a field or what else something you're screwed
because you can't go back to that nice graphical model then you have to delve into it
Round trip development is something
That I value
Collaborative development
Working together on a single component with multiple people and that say model
Those were things that I would like to see
In a tool that supports my workflow
Hans income
Joomla component Builder
And specifically
Version 297 that's the
Latest and current version
So anything I'm telling will projected this version not the earlier version so
If you want to check it out check this version out that's the latest
basically gather a little more
So there is this
Link Joomla component builder on www.vdm.io well
Since this presentation will be available you will not need to copy it all
It's only extensions directory
Unfortunately in this talk
We can but scratch
The surface so what I ought to
Convey in the stork is
that I thatch on the ideas. He say oh yeah if you could do that that will be fine still you would need to delve in
To this
yourself
To get into the details
fortunately there's
Quite some
Documentation in the form of videos
Dozen
Dozen and dozen of hours of video
Which doesn't make for the easiest in
Looking up stuff but it does makes easy viewing just sitting in your own couch and streaming YouTube
Videos to your TV on
Suck it in
Yeah we can but scratch the surface so you would really need to have a deeper look afterwards to see
How to do stuff but if resonate with you in what you can do because
Hope to convey that at least
Then you're in for a real treat
Let me go back
Because
Contact why I started this is because my son wanted to have a website
And children are like any customers
It's really easy
Nothing complex I just want
And this case he wants to wanted to create a website with Disney characters and the autographs and stuff like that
That's all he wanted
Well
Easy will do that with
Fields custom fields
but 2 days in and require but I want to list and parades and I want to do this and I want to do that
Not gonna happen so I introduce them to this
Tool
And
He made it happen and he was able while he's not dumb for her is actually quite intelligent so
What is not a diehard programmer
Body could make it happen with some out now I must say that
When we started
Yeah they were weren't
The number of resources were limited to help us so there were a few videos
but something were unclear
Over the last few months
I've been an extensive contact with a developer Llewelyn
And over the months he
Opened up to the idea of a number of challenges that we see
And you will see in the giveaways at the end what that
the result of them
And that will actually really help you in
Getting started
So If you look at
Joomla computer builder I think the first thing that you will see is the dashboard
but control panel
Wiki
Notice board
has some marketing links
But most importantly for you that says Wiki
With
Yeah you find in
Find all the tutorials all the
Links to the YouTube videos so once you install the component Builder
You'll got access to that to that just by looking at
The wiki
So unfortunately it's there is a explicit link obviously because it's
Yeah it's part of open source
unfortunately is not structured in terms of technical documentation whilst the
Videos are indexed in terms of time stands and say he is talking about this here talking about that
Still it's
search ability is limited
There's a forum on the way you can do
Crash on answers
And there's obviously you can directly access that list of videos to YouTube channel to look at
Stuff
So if you look at the WiKi that some general planning and you will hit this is a sample of the
Video on field types it's ok one minute and 5 we're talking about create field types
at one minute 57 is list view
It helps but it's not
Perfect
So let's not talk about
The work for what does it take
And what's possible in creating component
I've put together this
Diagram which is simplified
These are the topics we are called to touch upon so we have to add the components that's the stuff that you want to build yourself
The field types fields
We have bespokel that's really custom code to yourself
We have a dynamic get the view list view item view custom view.
Stuff that has to do with interacting with the data
Of your model controller
Salivary some graphical stuff
I will touch on each of these items
Let's starts on the components first I've applicated
the diagram
So this is what you see when you
Look and added a
Component
These are the tabs you have we'll cycle through and so well your details tab where you can setup
The name the first name
Do stuff with debugging line numbers yeah anything
really you related to a
Component
We have a settings manual
Why you can configure that thing more in depth
You see the list the reference to the administrator views the site views
custom admin views
I'll deal with it later
Libraries and helpers
The dashboard where you can create a custom dashboard for your extension with icons and stuff like that
MySQL data
The ReadMe file which is readme that gets
Exported with your
Extension
And as Dynamic integration after
Last part of the
Presentation
So
How do we build a component
The component
How Michael come as a surprise we have field types
I we have
Fields
So field types so basically the things that we know a lot from Joomla
There's a calendar category checkbox check boxes colour
Anything like that so That's the extra definition of something that you would want to
Create
You could
Add your own
Filter type to that
These types
And those are the fields are share between all your
Components
So you don't that's where you get part of the reuse of
You create a month and then if you've got a very specific field for a specific action
Some kind of zip codes address validator thingee
you create it here
And then you can setup
Fields and
So are the institutions of field types
You can create your own Fields you can paste special fields with dedicated validation
Stuff like that and the fields are the stuff that
Eventually will end up in the database
in the tables
Probably unto now nothing is stored it
it's just abstract
You can set up your bespoke Fields so stuff that you
Like yourselves so there is the type value let it has can assign items
And as you can info here
You can have a lot of attributes to
And if you just about anything that you would
Like
You can add extra properties
Here
you can
here you see
And That's what we coming to where this is in this field in which views
It's used
So it is an admin view series in admin view preacher and admin view sermons
That's of the installed applications that I have
and here is Information on the
Attributes used to filter so there's a lot of stuff
That you can configure per field type
To set it up
Here in the bottom on the right corner we gonna saw
The views it was used in and
That's where it gets tangible so once you set up your field types
and your fields
If you at least need new ones that are not default with the tool
You're gonna set up your views and I think you're familiar with the list views and the item views
so the List views is where you got your tabular tabular display of multiple items
and your items used a typical
View of one of those
Items so that's the item View
Component
Builder it uses also a custom View
Which is used to like for reporting where you can do graphing or anything special that's not
Necessarily in the realm of a
Item view
Itself or list view
So these fields are the stuff that's gonna get
Added to the database
You can add all kinds of conditions in the view
For that
You can add buttons to a view
Not necessarily understand what is saved I commit or
Any other actions
And there's a plethora of options to hook into your
Code so
Adding an Ajax
called
PHP that's run on the get item so when you get a singular item
At the PHP for batch add PHP for
After publishing
Before deleting
Post save well
For the list query so you could
Read data from the database and manipulate it
Too show it in the different forms or if you have
Like numeric presentation of whatever attribute you could change that then to display as and item or
What you would wish
Lots of options
Here added got a lot of
Items already
So basically it tooks into while  if you looks out to do if you would also it model and control apart
At last part you saw something about the MySQL so you can add a MySQL done to initialize
That table on installation
And as the usual stuff regarding publishing
And commissions that we all know from
Hanni
standerd Joomla thing
But that also means that
At this level you
The entire workflow in component Builder you can add the same restrictions to
As we had a for other component so you can have some people in some groups have the right to
Create fields or
Not create Fields create tables
Anything
But you would want
So here we have
The Linked fields the fields that are linked to that table so that's a view of it so
And a overview you can see ok is this sortable
Can I search it
So you can turn it on and off
Where does it show in a tab
So not everything shows in long how does it
Order
What's with the permissions that's nothing here but links areas
So there is a whole overview and you can add it each
Item from here so you can added the attributes of how you behaves in a list view or in an item View
To your hearts desire
He has an opinion that I shouldn't be more than 60 fields in
Admin view yeah
Not
Unrealistic
You can also add conditions
To a field
When it's supposed to be shown
On which circumstances so that you can have a
More
Clean display
And that's all
Draws back in in one building on the standard Joomla mechanisms
That we have in the XML files to show hide or show on
but you can show on
Something of another field in the XML file
So
That in basic covers
Of view and the stuff that we have in the
basic table
Now obviously you want to
visualize that
It allows
Dump the thing as a it's called
I hope everybody recognize this structure while you have the default
PHP if that's your site view
And then you can split it up in
Separate parts and make it more readable
And those are called the tablets
so you can multiple tablets that you can use in different
Base views
oh site views
To set up your view
And there's an option to
Add
Layouts
These are basically the
Joomla layout you set them up through the gooey and then you can reference
them in the
Usual way
The point being that the gooey gives you access to all of these
Items that typically are
Normally called
Furthermore we are the options to add libraries those are the
Global URL
Stand of support stuff for
Bootstrap 4 UI kit
a number of libraries what if you have a lot of a framework that you like for JavaScript
You can find that for that views for who loads it in
And it's reference
and you don't need to worry about it
It's just an example of how it looks like
where if you got the URL
URL
The type
Yes. If you drags of the libraries is it the always gets latest
No probably not depends on what URL you can provide here so I think in this case is get UI-kit
3.0.0 beta blah blah blah blah for that version
Of
Your created components
So once you bring out the new component new version
Your could
Check if there's new version UI-Kit
Put it in here and generator
your component again. Does it reference or does it really save are just lost.
No what's answered here just ends up as a piece of code
in loading the data but it said we interface to ensure that it gets on all the pages that
is reference
try to gooey
Depending on so this is on cloudflare CDN
So it gets it from there so it will just be a reference in the code to load it from there but there's nothing
Calling you back to actually set it up locally
you just change the URL here and then
Tweak it
Whatever you where you would want to
Now we had a very basic
Table
Field that's one table
But
Yeah that's
At least not our typically my components work
Because we have
Want to enroll and relations in decompose on normalizing in your data
So you would want to be able to
Combine that
In a view
And that's why the
Dynamic get
Comes in
The dynamic get has two basic tabs. The one that says
Filter. It says tweak.
I hope it's visible and here you can see where it says access level ID in
A dot access so that the
so it actually knows about the access level
Of the user
And since we have a access level in the in that table
Or for that element
It will ensure that it'll only show
So in the gooey you can
Restrict access
to stuff you can
Have where feel things where you can say Ok I
Only want the published ones
You can
Sort it
you can even set Global thats you can use in your code while Globals is not the best practice but hey
Here you can do a lot of
Things in
Extending your data filtering it you can add this is where you
Add search
For it by
Here addressing the search
Elements from the post
And let me make sure that you filter on that so
it is very powerful
This August translated into
Basic database language so typically it's MySQL queries
And all the aspects obviously is
How to
Create relationships because having one table
Probably he refers to other tables
And that's why I this
Is called a joint. I don't think
But
Now you see your OK series single as B joint a series equal
Yeah you find your joining queries between your tables
So for that view
You got
1 combined table
That's also all the information
To be displayed
Which is kind of very
Powerful. So indirectly I have joints to the gooey
No define dynamically you can add. Can you multiple joints. Yes you can add as many as you want here.
So there's no actual limitation
to it this will just
really translate 1 to 1 in
MySQL stuff
Yes this is a repeatable field you can an add in as many as you want them as complex as you want.
I can see but you can make any kind of joints.
Yes
Left joint right joint in a joint out the joint
So in just that combination we being able to
Joint tables
Add the filtering
That's an awful lot you can already do
At database level
What you can't do a database level you can do at the PHP level where I sort the
Get list items you could do additional stuff there
So options are
Forcefully Limitless
Custom code
Not to be
confusive be spoke code
There is some options to have
What is called custom code in the code snippets that you are defining and The Custom code
Could be
it's basic in the Micros
So it's a research and replaced thing you define Snippets
by
Adding this in an axle piece of
Code it will
fetch in that larger piece of code so that you don't need to
Recode your get view ID
Every time
You can also pass values to that
Snippet of code basically it's going down the function
So that's just a centralised your code
have Functions
At the gooey level
Then
Ok this should have been the bespoke code and not the custom code
Because that's
To me that's
The Unicorn
thing of this
Component builder and this is what got me
Interested in it
There's a lot of options in there
but
For whatever reason I always end up wanting to change something that can't be changed
Directly
in the gooey
and That's why I this
Computer component builder excels I think
Because it will allow you to
Add code or change code anywhere
In your compiled component
The only limitation is that you have to
Add some
Structure on that are commenting on that so that it can be found so that's insert place like this
and in with that anything in between there
Will be inserted
The beauty of it if you do that
The
Builder tool will extract these pieces of code
And the next time around you build it it will re insert them
So you will
Be able to change stuff at any location be it and PHP or HTML
And
Have it be imported
So that would for example mean if you now have a
3.x components
Which has a shortened file layout structure etc. etc.
If
In a few months time
There is a version that can build for
Joomla 4.0
Your changes will be put
In the relevant files in all the locations
I won't need worry about it
It will just build
With your cross and changes that with Joomla 4
for those
Familiar Joomla 4 has a slightly
Was it works with Joomla 3
The directory structure and file structure
That's not the best practice the best practices
Baffles or Shuffle around a little bit
Anybody wants to know just ask George
He'll be happy to tell you about it
There is a
I've listed the number a number of stuff so you can say insert this or replace a piece of it
existing code
And
So when it so you see what happens when it gets
Added back in the get again
And add some tags so that it can do its homework and actually knows
which piece of soft phrase change that what
Location
So this was really what got me enthusiastic about this tool because this is not something
I've seen
Before
And it'll allow for
Roundtrip development
created it in gooey
Modify to your extent in you can already modify lot in the component builder itself
If not you can change it anywhere else
And it will be sucked in again
And then if you want to add a new
Database table in new few extra columns
Joomla component builder will take care of that it will create a associated update script for the MySQL databases
It will do everything
Obviously some stuff needs to be compiled
and this is
A bit what you can see when it gets compiled
So
You select your component
In this case I've got component builder, sermon distributor, question and answers, demo and demo advanced
select one of them and hit the compile button
and that's it
Once it's done it make some assumptions assumptions about the time you saved
It's assumptions but yeah so much time you have at least
get the sense that you actually save time because you didn't have to create the
Directory structure
Nothing like that
Once you compile you can
Click on this one to install it immediately or you download it
or you
Reference what ever that code is.
And if you have it somewhere else Ryan you can use this
URL or path depending on where it is
Now you could if you have one development site is easy to run component builder there
And because every package can be exported
An imported in an other site
Without problems
There is a option to if you have a commercial component to have it encrypted and
secured by a key
So that it only can be installed if you have that key
Watching like this in Waterberg
Yeah
Started with some misc stuff you'll find some example for example in there that
in the tutorials which I thought really a nice one that adds deals with
Drag and drop uploading with all kinds of
Filtering on content type security looking if it's PDF
Filesize resizing images
There's a very complex example there on how to use that with ACL so that only certain group
People can do that
Yes very
Interested
Another thing that
Probably Rene also would like to see is that there is a sorry
I would say I know you but I know most of the people in the room so
So familiar
Collaborative workflow
If you work on so you can work on the
Sing
Installation
But then you deal with the normal Joomla
Problems of locking up
your article
And then your article is locked and somebody else cannot work with it
What does actually
you can't do stuff simultaneously
There's actually a workflow setup while you can do
We've multiple developers work on their local insulation
Where the changes get merge
Using git
So you can have a collaborative workflow
on that
So the mapped component gets
Versions in your own git stuff
There's also community components that used the same workflow or similar workflow
As a similar way of working we have
The
Upstream repository
So you forked that in your local Github you Clone it to your local development and environment
You make changes to for simple question and answers component
You set up your upstream
And than you
Push it and make a pull request and then
Pull request may not be accept it
And then you can download the new question and answer component again but that works ok you can also setup locally
Now for the giveaways
So until today are actually until the start of this presentation
VDM
That's the company for of Llewellyn
Sold the mapped component
Packages
So
The question-and-answer modules
would cost you 94 dollars
The Sermon distributor
would cost you 46 dollars
And
The big thing
The component builder so the thing that
We are actually talking about which bills itself would such a half
800 dollars
Totalling over a thousand dollars which is a lot of
Money
I have in the last months talking to Llewellyn and he he talking to his team
It was a big change in his attitude and giving back
So anybody that here
If you use this link
Take time to take pictures I'll step aside
So you can fetch time I meant this presentation this one
Why you can
Hit on me later if you need it
All that dates you can get these three packages
If you open that page now you will see that you can access these and you
Can get the keys the only thing
To be eligible for the keys is that Llewellyn asked you stared share or preferably fork
preferably fork
The respective components
If you have a public email address you we should get send the key
Automatically so public email address in get that publicly accessible
If not
You can claim
Your key on this page
So
You can get
The sermon distributor or the question and answers and the Joomla component builder itself
Watch watch fork or stared it
And you got notified if you have a public email address in get
That is very easy in terms of
You got to the components you can import the package is here
So it has an
Import JCB packages that you can
They were list
No need to search for them you can also see that you can export packages
And then you got something
Like this
here you add the key that you got distributed
And this is what shows when you
Progress so I got component build that pay a lot that it's installed
and here it shows the
All the extensions I've got a little privilege in getting these
upfront
So
And so I have keys but don't ask me for keys I will not give them
There's a perfectly simple way to get them
Just stare fork and share
And you got your own key
and with that
I want to say huge thanks and shout out to
Llewellyn van der Merwe
who is somewhere in
Africa
And sure to look this back
Any questions
of this
It's a lot to take a knife and try I actually don't know
I know he has employees
But I actually don't know how big his company is the
Picture of the office building is huge office building but I don't think he owns it all.
This is a huge thing I guess you didn't click this together in one afternoon at least he didn't no absolute not he work very hard the last days.  It isa real good package. why didn't we heard of it before
I don't know
I have you have heard or came across it before and that's actually how
I urged it my son to use it
I actually heard of it years back but to me it's a bit like Joomla itself
I heard about it but only when I saw that it started to be multilingual and that access control
in the core I got interested
And the thing that got me interested in here is the fact that I can do modification in any location of my
Component I have no limitations on that and I can still do aroundtrip development
By giving back obviously Llewellyn hope someone's
Everybody to contribute as so that we
He can extend this even further
And I've already started to talk with my friend from the JoomDD
To see if there's maybe that's Common Ground because I also very much like their idea about having model driven
Development
Don't know how to reach it yet but since it's now going to be open source two ways
the option exist
And that's really exciting to me.
Yeah you could use it but you couldn't change it and
It was totally free
And you could use it for free but you could you couldn't have the mapped component and so the one that builds itself and change that
And you wouldn't have the
Example components example components so that you could look how does he do this how does he
Filter how does he do this
And starting
Yeah but starting today you have two example components that
Will really help you on the libs that I struggled in finding things out
And you have a Joomla component builder where I hope that the community will take it up and
Ok
So i've been
signal that it's Janz
Thank you Janz
If there's any more questions just
Ask me when I'm moving around