I would like to explain it all more to you
About all the changes we've made
To the field area
The field area is really the foundation of most
Of your component
As it is what actually causes many of the behaviour and
Concepts
Which you might have in your views
Are all based on the field
So the field area was a difficult place to change
And it is still in progress
So of this video
The interface most probably won't change much
Just little tweaks here and there
But the backend of how we deal with the data we're certainly going to
Continue improving that
Just give you a quick recap of how it used to look
If we go to an older
Install
Of JCB in
So that's open a field here
if we open the Elias here
We would see that it has this XML field definition area
As in the past it was very easy to leave out
Maybe leave out
Anything by accident change
Something and then it breaks
So
That was a little bit
Yeah we had lot of Freedom and as developers I'm sure there's didn't feel
Anyway to be a problem
I mean
Whatever you selected we build the XML for you and you could just adapt
it as you please
Yet
Since we are trying to make JCB more stable and obviously eventually
Much more user friendly
This new feature was suggested
From
Inside of the team
And we decided to add it
So what
What did we do we basically removed
This XML definition
And we have replaced it
With a subform we've moved the database values to its own tabs
We also moved the field information to its own tab
And so
We add a lot of more
Structure and tools to the page
And I'm very sure you gonna be very
Happy to see the things we've done so let's show you that
So as of version 2.7.5
Which is the stable release of the Strange
You'll see that if we open that same Elias which we did just now
You see it looks like this now
So you have a subform here
Basically having those values
in a subform layout
And you have now
a lot of new information here
It also got the database in its own tab
And then the type info is still available and you can still come and
You know review
The reality is the new option
Still gives you the
The ability to select
other on add of those fields which
Are not already on the page so you could still say ok I want to add size here and we still load the description of
The field on the page and the default value
Which you can then change
Except like here when it tells you that it must be text
We have not yet
Blocked this field from being changed
Or being removed though it's mandatory so there's still a level of
Caution required , you could still break it
Although no you can't really break it whatever is mandatory
If you actually do leave it out
on compiling
The component
We will detect that it's mandatory
And if you obviously didn't add a value
It will fall back to its default value
So that's how it currently behaves
But I wouldn't
Rather I wouldn't develop
That way best practice is to put in the value
And make sure that is correct
So that's the new
Field area
We've put a lot of work into this
And there has been some
Hiccups and
Bugs which we have ironed out
The predominantly all those we know about
The new we also added this new option it's not yet
Yeah we haven't fully
Release some of the features but there is this option who's gonna sort of
Separate
If use the custom
Field currently
It adds the PHP here
In the rows which
Is a little tedious if you wanna change this
To keep track of the open braces
And all that in this way is little challenging
So what we did
And I can show you a little
Peek of that it will be in
In version
2.7.6
So you watching this video after those releases you possibly
already have it
So the new let me show you click on new this is now the new implementation for the custom
Fields
And also for custom user
So you click on it
It actually takes the PHP
And adds it to it's own little text area
to now here you can easily follow and adapt
The get options methods
PHP values
And that's
Quite
More convenient I suppose
Then using one line at a time
So we look at the user
You got two fields then one folder
Get exclude method and one for the Get group method
And so they also
Immediately available to you
The other advantage with this implementation
Is
We have this new
Extra properties
Option which
Has been available in JCB  for some time now
But many of you may not know that it exists
So there is this what we call list class
If you wanna add a class like a CSS class
Value
To this field when it appears in the list area
That is the
Let me show you
This area this is the list area while any of the
Views we see a list of items and you want this value
Specific value
To have a
Specific CSS class value because maybe you wanna
Style it
Somewhat different
Then you have this option
To a use basically all you do
As you just say
List class
And you add there
My
Class
But whatever you wanna call it
And
Then
It will add that the class
To the
To the field
In the list area which is
Quite stunning
There is also the escape
Option which
If you escape
A value
All the values are escaped by Default
So if you want a value not to be escaped
Because you gonna maybe
have values in it which if it's escaped gets stripped
Like a span tag and stuff like that
You could say files here
And then the specific fields
That what I say escaped I mean in the list area again
This area
When there is a list value
Then this is a being escaped at the moment
And if you don't want that done
Then you add this false escaped
The other option which is also available here is the display option
We'll still add some more documentation to this
But basically it's about when the field gets displayed
In a config
You know your it's component
Has a
let me see here
Got this options area right and you can actually add Fields to that option area
And when a field is added to the option area
It it has implementation structures you could have it show in the menu you could have it show in various
Places. I'll make a
Tutorial
About this specifically
But just to show you quickly that that is also actually available here
And then
last but not least validate
Not all Fields have the property
To validate the value
But here is the validation rules
And you can
Basically
Add a validation to this field
If that property is not available in the field type which you have selected
now
If it is we would suggest you add it
the properties here at the top
And it actually says that
if you have a validation set
as a field property this extra property will not be needed
Because you can just use that one
Ok so that's just a quick demonstration really
Of the new field area and
We trust that it will
Be as easy and as comfortable as we hoped
It would be
that the Strange would
Will not frustrate you but actually be great
Because of the reason that for example
One of the
Sort of unforeseen
Outcomes
Is if you have a field like this which already has all it's values
And you thinking on changing it
And you say, let me just check
How will text look
You can change it and it really adds all your text value here with its defaults
And if you say no I wanna go back
You can actually just click back
And
lo and behold your old values
Are again added to the page
The values that were there originally
And that is even true if you were to remove a specific
Property
Then wanna add it back
It actually adds the
Original value back
Which was
What we intended because
By accident
You might remove it and wanna just put it back and it should be as easy as that
You could obviously still go to
Type info to see
What what could be the
The actual values
Default values
And adapt them
So it's not like you don't have access to the default values
it's just that we
want to
Recover your
Current saved value for you
And then whenever you add another field which isn't already here
This drop down list only shows the fields
That are not already on the page
So you won't end up adding fields
properties the second time
And yes so now it's become much more easier I suppose
To build fields
Based on it's Properties
As before
You really had to
Navigate
Through
Some of the complexities
Of dealing with an XML
Set of values
Which maybe some of you don't even know exactly what's going on here
And those of you that do I mean
It's it's not like you're losing any advantage with the new implementation
You still targeting that value with any value want
And it's still as easy as clicking a plus and selecting a value and adding it
And so I
I do hope that all of you will be as excited about this change
As we are
.
We are now at the point where
Making JCB easy-to-use is also a priority
K well thanks for watching