This is a quick
Sort of tip on how to add a language string
To your component
Without a language string
Being immediately
Added to the J text
Object function
Which translates it of course
So let me demonstrate
So normal language string you use this J text
And you'd
Add your string in there
And then JCB when it compiles
It
Actually adds that string to your language file
And then when your component runs that string is translated
because it has a
Placeholder in its place
And you can then have multiple places where the string is used
So that's
Already there and works well the new feature
Is
Mostly used when you are dealing with a class
And you working with a
Array
In the class
And If
You want to have class method or rather
Fields
That is an array of
Strings but you can't of course use this
In the array of a class
Value so
That is one place but there are many places
Where you could see this in action
So what you would wanna do is you want the placeholder to be generated
You want the
String to be added to the language file
But you only want a placeholder as a string to be added to your
Script
Because only later in the script you're going to add it
to the Jtext
Option to translate this place holder
And so often you we would run into such a case well I have in anyway so
The way we've
addressed this
Is with a new
Basically a new name
Just text
Like that
so
This part looks exactly the same as the J text
So this almost seems like this is a class but it's not really it's just
Something that the JCB compiler will pick up
And it'll convert this let me show you how it will look when it
has converted it
And you'll see why it makes sense you see I've got this extra field Properties
And it's got these
Keys
And I want to use the key to get the string
So if we go a little lower in the script
You see I'm here I'm looping through that
array
And
The value description
I'm only here passing it to the J text
To translate it
So that means
I wanna do the this translating later
And I actually all I want in this array above here is actually the placeholder string
So let me show you that in the code how it actually comes out
So in the code here you see the extra field properties and you see it's simply a
a string
It actually took away the bracket here
if you look at the way it was
So I'm going to paste in the
The one from the code
Just so that you can
see
What it's done
So here you can see
This is what we added in JCB
And this is what it did
In compilation
It added the placeholder string
Which we can then use
Down here
In our Jtext
To translate it to get the
Specific translated string
So that's a way to get the placeholder and to get obviously the string into your language file
That's just a little tip I know that
It's not very obvious
So I hope it will come in handy to those of you who want to add language strings
To JCB
But you don't want to have it immediately be
Part of the  Jtext object
Call you want to just have the actual placeholder available
for use dynamically
This is the way you can do that
Thanks for watching enjoy