I would like to talk about the expected or anticipated New Library feature that's being added to JCB
I'm still in the development phase of this
I've been working on the UI
Which really is just how I anticipate it should function
It's not yet set in stone
Because I have not yet started
Adapting the compiler to make use of the
This new feature
But it is anticipated to actually eventually
Become
More fixed and
Steady
So I wanna basically illustrate
two things
one is
We have this Bootstrap library
Set up now This Bootstrap library the specific name here
Is linked
Too many many Snippets
And so it it can never change even
I've made it that even if you try to change it
Can you click save
You know it will actually revert back to the correct name
That's only with regards to libraries that already become part
Of the
Joomla
Component Boulder Community Snippets libraries
So Everytime We have new libraries contributed
To the community
Then
That library's name
Will become fixed
So It cannot be changed
And that a way of protecting the system from collapsing on itself
Because if people could just change these things in their own JCB
Then
It could end up making so many confused
Results
Anyone
What they still can change is the way that the library is actually
Added to
Components
I currently I said it up that it basically links to this two URLs
And it has this always add
But that means
On every page where Bootstrap 4 is being used
It will always add
These
Files
Now we might later see when Joomla 4 is released that there are some local Joomla 4
libraries we would rather use like you have for jQuery at this stage
If you wanna use jQuery on a page you wouldn't do this kind of inclusion
You would rather use the internal Joomla API to get those libraries on the page
And for that I added this custom script option
there are two places where in every view there are two types of functions used
To add
The
Specific library to the page
The one function is this prepare document function
And the other one is set document
And the one function uses the document
Directly
Variable naming
And then add script because it actually adds document to the document variable
The other one grubs upon a global document variable
And it's really based on
Which class it is inheriting and so forth
So they are basically there for two methods
Being used to adding the custom or the library to any page
And so when you
Use this custom script option
You would
Target
These two functions or methods
Class methods
Which will then adequately be
available
For every
A page that makes use of this library
The other one is a conditional option
the conditional option is the better option really
Because this one
Would actually adapt
The code
On the basis of the the implementation
per view
So here you would select the files that you have
and say whether it include or exclude You obviously if you select exclude
It means it will always include it
Unless these behaviours that you gonna set over here
Is actually you know
.
valid
Now those of you who know the conditional concept within fields
This I just taken that same conditional concept
And I'm now just applying it on adding
Or not adding a file
So it's really very much the same so you still have this isolate or chain option
And the reality is you can now
There are no config Fields yet you need to first go here and create a config
Field
Now config field is really an existing
Field that you've already created
Before coming here so
I haven't saved
This as a condition so I'm just gonna
save that
And then I'm gonna go here to edit
And you'll see
The config library if I click on it here
I basically can select
Any field out of my
A whole list of fields so I've already made one just for our illustration
Bootstrap 4 Radio
And
That's really the field I wanted to be in the library tab
So this again is very much similar to the component
Config options area
except now we are selecting fields for the library which will then in effect be added to the components
Global
Options area
Ok so let's save and close here
Now we'll see in this drop down that that field comes up here
If we selected
That fields have two options yes or no
So if this library and that
Library
File we wanna include it
When add Bootstrap button is set to
Yes
So here is a selection option
Now so that's the conditional way of doing
So basically at this stage we will have
3 to 4
ways of
Actually adding the the fields onto the page
The reason why this conditional one
Is not being shipped
This way the moment
Because I'm not shipping these fields
And
The whole idea of
You know creating a field on all of those who
In all the systems of those who used JCB
I'm still pondering whether I should write a script
To do that
So it's that's really the issue if
If we shipped this as the
The standard way of including the Bootstrap libraries
Then I will need to create this add Bootstrap version 4 field
On every system
And then link it in here with correct IDs ans stuff
And
So I haven't I haven't actually done that
Like I said
We are now looking at how can we do this
We wanna make this dynamic
Because now let's say someone
Has a specific
File
The day so let me just save this
that specific file
Which
If if someone is using Bootstrap and they wanna add a specific extra feature and I need more
More JavaScript on the page
You know they could create that file
Click here
By going to add new files
I know let's say it's a local file they could click here
And they can collect
Any file of just gonna make it
Any file
And just like with a component include
When you add custom files to your component
You have that same feature really here except you can also use URLs
So it's the same custom adding of files or folders
So now you want to have this Bootstrap
Min.js
In the media
Boot
Strap
Bootstrap 4 there we go
You wanted in that folder
js
That's really where you want to put this file
And you don't want the file itself to be updated
that filename you wanna keep
And you want to have it available to the library
So now you click save and close
So now if we look here we'll see now there is a file called Bootstrap min.js
But you don't want to always be included
You wanted to be included only if there is a specific
Switch
Tripped
On on this
Use of this file
The idea is now that you would go to the config library
And you create a new field
And
Let's say that this new field is
Let's say I'm just gonna use a
Add more
And
Obviously it should be more related to Bootstrap but just for explanation
Then you would say that specific field which it
Is this cases
It's this one
Should
When add more is set yes
Then it should be
Added
Now
That is as far as I've come to
Sort of
Think about
Implementing
These kind of features
Dynamically
You see previously I wrote all this hard coded right into the compiler
And based on its own automated
Observation of the you know UIkit version 2
If it founds specific classes it dynamically added files or didn't add files
Now
I'm thinking that
If you wanna be so
Customised and dynamic then you won't use the conditional option you'll rather use the custom script option
You still have these two buttons
That you can then use
The global
Values of
You can still get those values
In the scripture
And act upon it and load in the libraries with custom scripting now I
I did some Prep on that kind of approached
here in FooTable
It's actually
Says here
This FooTable Style
So
You need to now
Actually line up a field value
With FooTable Style
And then it will dynamically add the specific
CSS classes
To the
to the table to the page
For both this prepared document
And for Set document
So you have
Add always then you have add conditions
Or custom script
Let me just say another thing about the condition option
The condition option
I'm pondering
Whether this condition option should have a global value
And also a page value
You see if it have a page value
Then you can overwrite the global value with the page value
So it's almost like if we detect
That let's say bootstrap 4
Is being used in a specific View
And that view has a menu
Then dynamically will add to that menu
The function of these buttons
As well as having it added up into the global options of the component itself
So it'll  be Global options
And the page will fall back on to the global options
Unless someone with manually overwrite that in the because when when is that usually the case
If they have another library or another component
That already loads the files
and they wanna excluded from the page because it's already there
And that's why I'm thinking about
You know having it on the page as well as globally
And if you feel well I don't want to use it to really decide whether these
You know
Libraries Should Ever Be on the page well then in that case add always
And then these files will
Including this one
Will always be added to the page
And we will take care of the script
The code to achieve that
And now I was also thinking if we
Wanna have some files only be added always then
Then it is the files that you do not actually
You know
If you want
For example if you want
These two files to be always added
Then within conditions you will only create a condition
For the files you want to have a condition for
So that the files that is not being targeted by conditions
Will automatically always be added
Anyway
That is at this stage some of the thoughts I have
I'm thinking
I'm gonna
Say that if any of you wanna give more ideas
Then grab out your screen recorder
Open this page
And talk through and explain some things
In a little
tutorial
Post it on YouTube as a response to this tutorial
Or go to our GitHub discussion area
You know we are busy
with this
Discussion here
On GitHub
it's issue 92
Bootstrap or
UIkit Version 3 or Bootstrap option
It's in this issue that this long discussion is going on
And where this whole library idea is actually
Forming and
Expanding you'll see already typed a little response here what I wanna post
With this tutorial that I'm making as a URL
So
Really what I would like to say is I'm busy
Trying to
Answer this new functionality
And
This is the way I've gone about doing it at this stage
I I know that these
Libraries that are already in our a component Bootstrap UI kit and fooTable
I'm gonna end up
Adding enough information for these libraries
So did they all just work out of the box
That's gonna be my responsibility to
To put all the necessary
Code and scripting and everything in place
So that this option will just work
All of them
And just when someone wants to expand on them
Will they need to do so
But it is obviously a once off situation
Once I've implemented this new feature and set these functions and
Properties in place
And people make adaptations to it I cannot update it again
And so having enough input
to think about all possible angles
And to approach this in a way that really makes it dynamic and really doesn't overcomplicate things
Is really what I'm trying to achieve although that seems difficult
Anyway
This is just a heads up tutorial
Looking at how to
Use the new libraries area
And obviously if you want a specific functionality in Bootstrap 4
You cannot now create a new Bootstrap 4 library
With new files you need to expand on the existing one
And that's the whole point
We wanna make it that the existing library can be adapted and changed
An improved
At this stage that adaptation in those improvements will only be relevant to the one who's doing it
And so that might be something we were gonna think about
We gonna
you should talk about would we want everybody to share their adaptations
Or will we just set the stage with your regional adaptation and then whatever changes they make is up to them
Anyway this is a
Again a tutorial I just made
In the outset of this new functionality
Looking in asking please give me feedback
And let me know what you think
Thank you