Well I'm happy to announce that we have added a very
Long awaited feature
To JCB
You need to upgrade to
Version 2.8
To actually get this feature
This feature though
Does effect
How JCB builds the Admin View
List View
So that means
Basically
These areas
Where you got list of items
So if you got custom scripting in your component
In these areas
The
New when you install or upgrade to version 2
You would experience that your custom scripting doesn't get added
you know
Correctly
We'll still add it will still be added to the document
But you have to go and move it into the correct place and an commented and
You know do the
replacement of the code
Add those diamonds to
Notify JCB to update the placement
So that's
Just a heads up because the list views are
Improved actually
The way it's being built
The this extra
Sort of
Changes to the code snippets changes the fingerprints and all that
So enough that what the new features is all about is actually
Taking specific values like maybe this value
And that value
And to combine them into one value into one column
And yet have the option of still being able to filter with those values
Now we forgot this component
Sermon Distributor
And I am planning
To take the preachers
List View
You'll see that it now shows the name and a short description or whatever description you've added
I want to have it also show
If there is an email address
So if this email address is filled in
Then it should show the email address
Or
If it doesn't find an email address but it finds a
Web address it should show the web address
so it should show other one or the other
And it must connected next to the name
And and I think we'll use that as our demonstration of this feature
Ok so now let's go back to component Builder
And then we would go to
The admin views
And
If you
Or not if you haven't done it yet there won't be an icon showing up anywhere here
But once you've done it there will actually be one I'll show you that
So we will go to the preachers admin View
So just go to the the one you want to change
And then under the settings area
Sorry not the settings area
It's the fields area
You'll see that there is now
A new area called admin
Fields relations
and here at the bottom
You'll see a field relations
So that's the new area that's the new feature
You could either click here
Or
You click here
both of them will achieve the same
Taking you to the
Same place
So I'm the click on this one it's ok
And then
You basically in the admin Fields relations Builder
so you could click here on adding a
Admin fields we gonna set we gonna use the name
And we gonna join that up with the email
And with the web URL
Now will see that there is this area
Column
The area column actually
Can
Target three places
Before modelling the value after modelling the value
And the view
So
If you know I'm what a model is that means the area where you still working
Just with a code
Where as in the view
You must think of you already have a
HTML trunk
That represents that field
So if I could show you that more
Directly in the code
In first looking here at the folder structure you see I am in
administrator components
Then sermon distributor
Then here's the views and here's the models
So if we go to the model of the preacher
Plural one because we going to the list View
You'll see
That it has
Items
Now
At the moment there is basically nothing being modelled
Modelled usually would imply
If it is a json object
And it needs to be taken from json to an array
Or if it's a encrypted value in a needs to be decrypted
Those kind of things
Oh whether you wanna work with the value before that happens or after that has happened
Ok so then if you want a you work with the actual
Item
Where it's still just an integer or a string and really that's all that is
Then you'd target the model
If you wanna target the view
Which in this case if we go to preachers
And then the body
You see that
Basically
Everything from here
Up to here
Is representing
The ID
Everything from
here up to here
Is a presenting the name
And so if you wanna target this chunk
Because it still gets generated
of course
Then you would target the view
Because then JCB will still build this whole block for you
Basically this block
And you can move this block around and join it with the other block for the other field
As you like
So that we could be that you didn't have two links
Or that
Yes
All kinds of interesting things can happen my best
Advice is you know try it out take it for a spin
Make some changes compile it install it
See what's changed go to the areas
Which being
either the view
Or the model and see the code that was generated based on your selection
Now we gonna
Make multiple changes and show you what will happen so save you some other time and then understand
What's happening
And so let's go
Do it
The first area I'm gonna target is the model area
Then it has a joint type which is either a concatenation with
With a glue option the glue option is basically what do you want to be placed
Between the values
You could say no I want them to be completely crank up against each other like that
And usually it'll still add a little space it'll still add a little space in
And
You can say no I want I want a little Arrow between them
Like that
But it's basically a value you want to place between these two values
Ok so I'm gonna just leave it as a comma for now
And then save and close
And then also save and close the view
And now you'll see
That there is a new icon here
We can click and directly go edit the relation
So
That is the new icon added
Now if we go to the compiler
We will be able to compile this and see it in action
So I'm not gonna
Do that just gonna compile sermon distributor
Install it and now
First thing is let's open sermon distributor and let's go to the preachers table and
See how it looks in the interface
So here we see
It basically adding
Both of them adding the email as well as the
URL
And because it's exceeding a specific length it is escaping it and we have this little
Pop-up come up here
It so there's that comma we added as a concatenation
Between the values
So that is really what we expected
Let's go back and make some changes
Well let me let me first show you the code that was built
So we were targeting the model so basically it just
Add this
As a glue
To glue these values together
Concatenating them
Yes
So that was the model now
Like I said this specific view doesn't have
Really any modeling it does to the values So even if I would to say it select after
It won't necessarily change anything
Ok so
Let's make another change
Let's instead of using the default glue option
Let's say Ok we wanna do a code option
Then you'll see the JCB cranks out sort of ok
to
Give you the
Freedom to actually write code
We are using the IDs
Of the fields
In in braces
Curly braces because
Well
Many reasons I'm not gonna
Waste your time
More or less
Boils down to the fact that it's difficult to know exactly what the field names gonna be at this point
For every kind of type of field that is there
So working with the ID just saves us a lot of
Effort
But since it's difficult to know which field is which ID we had this little comment
to sort of give you a heads up ok so this value is basically the website this one here is basically the
Email
And I would suggest if you are sure of what is what
To just take the comment out because otherwise it'll be added to the code
So that is just
What I would suggest so this stage we know
That what this is saying is basically what we saw
In the code it is almost exactly the same
Except that it is using numbers here so now we can do some little PHP
So we can say something like this
So we basically checking
If this is not empty
Then we use that which is the email otherwise
we fall back onto the
You know the URL
and when the URL is empty it just means that there will be an empty string
So maybe that's not that ideal either
So let's make it a little bit more advance
So now it's saying if there is an email use the email otherwise check is there a URL
No
If there is sure then add it if not then add nothing
And it just stays without the comma and everything
So there we go
Got a little
Adaptation there
So just make sure that this Convention is kept
So the Curly braces with the ID and then the closing curly brace
This will then be updated with the actual name of the field and so you can do full HTML
Sorry PHP coding in this area
And it will be implemented that means you could also pass the value to a function which then
Passes it back to the value
And this is in the model
And this is before modelling and after modelling oo
That's a
Good thing that happened every time you change anything here
It's going to update the code
Because
Sometimes it is expected that these two
Values might look different at this stage it doesn't but it is a JavaScript that fires on
Changing of any of these fields
And so I have to type all that over now
So the Best Idea is you wanna make changes here
First copy the value in here
And then you can make changes
And see
you know what what happens
And
Then as you decided what you want
You can just paste it back in
Ok so there we have it
If it doesn't behave exactly right just change it a few times
We will
Will still tweak the JavaScript here to make sure that it's
You know working exactly 100 Percent
So this is sort of
Beta phase sort of but it works the
The same functions as it should
It's just that the I'm still ironing out some JavaScript here
Another thing
You can only
Target
The name list field
Once
You cannot add it a second time like this
And say ok you're here we gonna do it again
But now
Using maybe some other values
To also target it
In some way
You cannot do that only one of them will get implemented the other one will be dropped
It's a limitation I know but believe me
This feature as it is now is already really stunning
And able to achieve quite
Impressive results
Ok so here we have it we've adapted it it will only show an email or a web address
If there is actually one set
And that There is None set it won't show any
That's the expected result so let's save this and see it
In action
So we will compile it
and install
So there we have it
The preacher showing up with an email address and that's it
Let's Create one
Without an email address
So we created one
With no email address if you see
There's none here let's add a web address let's just close again show you
Now there is nothing not even a comma
But as you see this now is a link the whole thing is a link
And
That might not be exactly what you
Actually want
Ok let's
Let's add a web address
And then save and close
and so here
Because your web address was a little long
It created a a pop-up
Now all that can be changed
But let me just
Do something else
Let's use a shorter address
Save and close
And now there you have it
That looks more acceptable
And so it detects now whether there's an email or a web address and if there's none it shows none
So that was now with this new combine
Feature
So let's, let's do something even more interesting
So again we go and open that area clicking this icon
This is sort of a shortcut
And now instead of targeting the model
We gonna target The View
And this is where it really gets interesting
Because now this little place holder called field=199
Is basically a chunk of code as I explained
Initially in the beginning
Where we are saying
Ok
Instead of
Targeting the actual value database value
You are now targeting the produced code which JCB builds
The html block
For that specific field
So
We can now also I would also encourage you removing the comment this is the comment that shows you that that is the name
That's the email
And that's the web address
So I would also encourage you to once you seen it or just remove it we might at a later stage
Take the comment and added underneath the box so that it
Clearly is nowhere
In the way
But it is for you to just sort of know that this chunk
Is for the email and this is for the website
Address ok so again
I want to add a little bit Dynamic Script here
But I need to keep in mind that I'm actually in
HTML
So if I wanted to add
PHP here
I actually need to
Do the correct PHP tags
And all the rest of it
Ok
And that means you can actually
Target the item value
You can remove this and work with the actual item value
But this little placeholder will produce the whole
Block of code which if it's going to be a dynamic link
Or something like that
It'll produce all of that for you
So if it's a
If it's an
A custom field which links to a to another View
Then all of that can still be produced in this
Sort of dynamic placeholder here
But you can remove this all of this and you can
Yeah have it
Echo out anything
So which you just have to code of course
I think
Best to demonstrate is first used in concatenation option
And which would just put a break between the values
And then save and close
And compile install
So we refresh this area
And now we see that
This value is a link but the other two
It's actually just text
And that's exactly
What we wanted to achieve
Going into the code
We open the body
And you'll see
The JCB added the brakes
There is a break
There's a break
And there's the chunk of code that JCB build
So
It really build all of this
It's still built a link to the preacher
And then
It's still built this
As well
So if this was going to be a link to another View
It will produce that code
Checking again the permissions and everything
Which is really what makes
This areas implementation quite exciting
Because it still takes care of the hard work of producing
The actual code needed to display the value
If you pick up any behaviours in this new feature that sort of unexpected
Then please give us a heads up on Github open an issue
And we will try and address it as quick as we can
Again thank you for watching
This is the new feature of
Combining
admin view values
In a
Very easy way
It could have been done previously with some custom scripting
But this sort of helps you and I'm sure
Makes it easy for you to just select the field you want to Target of course that means
You first need to add the fields that you are ready going to show in the list View
And then select the field you wanna join to it
That's sort of
I expected you understood maybe that but
I realize I must mention that separate
So that means if we go into the preacher Fields area
you'll see
That
We actually just got two Fields the name
As shown in list
And the description shown in list
So here we don't make any changes we don't say that the email and then
Website
Must also show in the list View
In fact
Only the fields that I'm not showing in the list View
Show show in the relationship view as joint options
So that's just a heads up
What is exciting though as you can
Actually
Do a
a filter
And a
Yeah you can do a filter or a search
On these Fields that are not going to be placed but you know you gonna later select them as relationships
And then the end up creating JCB will in upgrading the filter
And make it searchable at even if it's a link
to
To another page you can click this to be a link
And then it will generate the link
Which is I think amazing knowing that it's gonna set that all the permissions in place
And everything else
Ok well maybe I should
Demonstrate that
Just quickly
So here in the sermons area
We see that we have a Preacher table and we gotta name table
So
That means we can actually
We have these two links this one will open the preacher
As
We know
Same as opening it from the preacher list view and then this one's gonna open the sermon
So
This is going to be easy because now
We can decide Ok we got so many rows here let's Combine the preacher
With the name row
And yet we wanna retain this link
As it is working now and we wanna retain the option to actually filter by
The preacher
So let's show you how easy it is to do that
So we'll go to the sermons list View
or admin viewing and then
Also again to the fields and click on create fields relations in this ad o wait before we
We do that
I first need to remove
The preacher
From the list so we first gonna go to the
Where we selected the fields
That needs to be linked
To the
List the admin list View
And the one we want to remove
Is the preacher value
So it's this one
Sermon preacher we gonna say no
Don't add it and when you do that is gonna wipe out all the links that usually
Should not be selected if it's not a listview
But since we still wanted to be a link
And we still wanted to be a filter
We gonna leave those checked
And then click save and close
So now
Getting back to this page
And going to Fields we'll see that
The the preacher now
Is
No longer going to show the list View
But it's still
Going to be
A filter in a link
And if you compile now it won't show up at all
You still need to now go and select the relations area
click on new
And then select name
Here
You would now
Need to select
The
sermon preacher
And then View
And then
Well we could either say
We wanna do this ourselves
Or
We could
Use glue
Which in this case
I'm just gonna use a space
just an empty space like that
And save and close
And then we compile
Install
And then refresh the sermon page we see that now
They are
Two links here
The one is to open the
Actual
Sermon and the other one is opening the
It's going to open the preacher
So if we click on it it still behaves as before the preacher gets opened
we closed again
And we back here and we still have the preacher filter
Here at the bottom of our page
As we had it before
And so
This is really
Great
We can also then open here
And
All is working as expected
Now as easy as it was
To combine these two values into one column
While still retaining the actual links and everything surrounding this value having a
Dynamically get the name
Because obviously in the table it's taught the ID only
And now showing it here it means it's actually remapped it in the database so let me show you that
So we open the sermons
Model and we scroll down
We'll see here in the the list query
It's still
Maps the preacher table in
And
Builds the connection on the ID in the preacher
And still selects
The preacher name
Then going to the view of that
Sermons
We see if you scroll down
Here
It has
Produced this chunk
Of code
For the for the preachers name
And this chunk of code
For the
Sermon name
So it still does all the
Producing of the
HTML code and all the permissional checking whether
Does this user actually have
The edit permission
to
To change this value
Of the specific preacher
So yes and yet it's showing the preacher name
As the linking up in the database was done
So it's quite exciting
I really
Hope that you would find it as useful as I am already doing
And like I said if you discover anything not to work as expected
Please do contact me and on GitHub open up a issue
And we will
Take it from there. Thanks for watching.