I would like to talk to you about changing the licence template
For your component
This would be expected that you've made at least
40% change
To any of the demo components
Yes so
Let's say you've changed this component
Quite considerably
Then there is this place called
Licensing template
Now it actually tells you there what you should do
Select a file
That should be used for license all files
Found in
Administrator component
Component Builder
Compiler
Now the files
What I should add to the note is actually the txt files
So that means you could put any txt file in there
And then selected here as a license template
Now let me show you how that works
Ok first of all
It must be done
When the Joomla component Builder's ready installed on your website.  So here I have a website Joomla Mount
So in Administrators
Component
or administrator
components
component builder
There is a folder called compiler
And in it there is
4 txt files 5 txt files
And going back to the component
There is
12345 files I see it's also using the HTML
That one will obviously not come out right
Ok
So
These ones with the .txt's the one that you would
Select
Any one of those
To be the template that you are going to use
Now if you use one of the existing templates and just change it then with the next update
Your changes will be overwritten
So you wanna do it in a way that sort of
Preserved your changes
And the way you do that is you actually go
Back to that area
And then you select
Or let's say were you selected default one
And maybe you don't like this
So you want to take that out
like that
And maybe you don't want to really support
Or show that you used JCB so
Take that out
I really don't mind
in fact
I'm so much so supportive open-source that
I don't
I don't mind you changing
Anything here
And anything else in fact anything there
And anything there
This I would want you to leave
Basically
Because you could set this in the
you know these placeholders are being replaced
By the settings of your component
So that means you could still tweak this
But do it in the component
But leave a license somehow
Copyright notice
So that people know how to use your program
But
Having said all that
You do realize that the lot of the code between all the components at JCB built are more or less the same
It's just little names here and there
and that's really the only thing you copy writing
Just keep that in mind
You're not copy writing the
Every little line really your copy writing the changes because
The
The idea of how built is already been copyrighted either by Joomla itself or by
sorry
JCB yes that's right so just keep that in the back of your head
Your copy writing the changes you've made
And that would you done
And maybe when someone uses your component they won't think about it that way and I don't I don't mind and I nothing
Anyone would because we are open source community
But
If you do change your program to a proprietary software
You might have
to
Yeah you know you need to look at What would be the implication because
I think
There's a possibility that some areas
Cannot be made proprietary be
Because of the Open Source license already being on JCB
And on
Everything that it's
done
Ok so that's just I'm not sure I'm not a lawyer I don't know how all that works out
But
I want to give many people so much freedom and I'm not really gonna check people up
Someone else may there is actually places that
Might feel obligated to do so
I wanna be busy with code
Writing programs
Ok
So this is how you change the template
More or less you could leave things in the one that think that's the most let's see
You can check between them
You see like this the way to know what is all the place holders that are available
Is really to go to the
Let's see helper
Compiler
I think it's that infusion is 1
So
You should look at the infusion
Now like
There is a company name you see there's a creation date
There's the built date there's author, author e-mail website copyright license version
Actual version
Component names for short description description
Image type access so they are
Really
Most of these aesthetic
A content placeholders could be used obviously some of them won't make sense like custom helper
Script that
Means it's got add the custom helper script in that lines It's not gonna come out right
So these Place holders are really from where
The content is being updated in the file
Ok so you'll see
That it is the same
This is a new method we are using to put it in the hashes these these hashes here
So
Basically the creation date
Is this one here
And it's getting it from the infusion which is found in helpers compiler
So you can check out these and use any of those as you like
The point being
It's best to leave this in
And at least tell people who who who you do did it so someone
Can be blamed anyway
And
There we go now
If you just save now
It'll still work the default template will be updated
But the problem is the sooner we released a new update for JCB and you install that update
Is actually gonna over right this
So what we would suggest the saying save as
And then give it
your name I'm just gonna say
q
Default q
Save
Now we have a new file
And we can actually go back to JCB
And we can just refresh the component area
And now we'll see that there it is
The new
Template
Now if I save
And compile this component
It will actually
Use the new template now let me first see do I have it installed yes I do let me show you that
So in the code we go down to sermon distributor we just open any of its files
And that's how it's current template looks like
Ok so there is the current template
All the way down to there
Now let's compile and see
It'll update every file across the
Spectrum
So we just gonna say
sermon distributor and compile
Ok and then this install it
Now let's go check out our template
And now if we scroll up we see up it's got the new
The new
Template is being used no longer the old one
It's the same file I just it just refreshed it
In the background
Ok so
That how it works
Easy
To change the license and that's really means you can make it a small or is big as you like
Any shape and size
Just keep in mind that you need to escape it and unescape it
Because otherwise it will mess up the code
Ok well that is how you change the license template
Now
So
Make a wise decisions and how you deal with this area
I don't wanna say too much more and put
You know restraints up because really
I know that
The initial Desire here
Was really to give everybody as much freedom as they need
Thank you for watching.