Would like to
Show you how to
Use code across JCB
In a very inherent kind of way
By taking the advantages of a few features that JCB has
Features that most may not know is there or maybe they do but they not seen it's advantage
And then recently there actually came up a question
On the Forum
By Alex Tings asking
About
You know he ask admin views but
Generic code that runs in
Multiple admin views and then some of it runs only in specific admin views
And how I could how I could speed up the maintenance of this kind of thing
So his first question is is the helper admin class the best way to put this code and then is there a way
Keep the direct admin forms functions I wrote separate from these specific ones
Ok
I'm sure some of your might even be listening here and I'll understand exactly what we trying to do
And I'm not even sure if I'm exactly going to answer this you know
So I'm gonna quickly pull up a docker image of Joomla
I have a docker file there just quickly gonna pull it up
And then we gonna go and use it
Ok
Ok so I've got it up running
I think it's default is user
Ok so where in here I'm gonna go to extensions and install
And
Basically add the web tab
The JED
JED
Then type JCB
and here we have
Description can look at that
And install
Sort of getting the
JCB install from GitHub
Ok we're done
Go Joomla component builder we're almost there
Then
We could
Grab a demo component
If you don't know how to get access to these components just follow this link and
Follow the tutorials
So I'm just gonna get the JCB package
And then the key that
You were send you will add here
Maybe force and update
is always good sort of
get all your Fields updated
OK now
Continue
And within moments we have
JCB
Installed on JCB
Now we can start looking at the examples
That's really what I wanted to get to
Because the question is being answered by the demo data
Already
So
In JCB there we already doing a lot of this multi
Inheritance structure kind of relationships
And
So the best way to sort of demonstrate this is to actually look at JCB itself
OK we're almost there
OK we got JCB
Here
Now if we go to custom code
We'll see there's a whole lot of custom code
And
Many of them is this hash
Automation
Now we wanna look at this JCB manual option
For example let's look at the getviewID
Which is a custom code
Basically that is its name
This is how you use it
And
Here
We are having a view
Called admin View
That is using it
So if we click on that
Is going to open for us the admin View
And when we get here we'll see there is the the code now
This actually is the I'm using this specific get view ID
All across my components is just
It's also being used in JCB
But it's it's powerful
So I'm using it everywhere
So that's one way
To use
A a specific snippet
Which you add here use the JCB manual
Give the function and name
You could pass values to the function like this
And
Please read the explanation here
To how that is done
And the end of the day
You can then adapted the value structure for example if
If this value here needs to change from instance to instance you can pass it by
This value one
Which that will be arg0
And then you can just actually replace this here with
Then arg0
and 3 again like that
And then you just remember to pass
At least one value
To update
This value
Where ever you using it
That's one way to use the reuse the scripting
Now the other way
Which is the one that actually gets used in the helper class
It's like here I got one called get file path
To get file path is also a function
Which I am using across my components
It is just also being included in JCB
But many of my components is using get file path
And basically
It is a little function
That I can pass a few parameters to and can consistently give me back a path of where I want to place or get
files from
Now in the
PHP helper there is a function
And the component itself
That's me here
There is a function called
Helper classes for both admin and site
So anything you put in here will be not only added to the admin helper class but also to the site
Helper class sort of a way to
Avoid doing it twice
And
As you can see
There is one to just put it in the admin
So you could just take care and just target the admin helper
Or you could just target the site class helper
But in this case most of this code I wanted to be everywhere
And if we were to
Go down to the very bottom suppose
here
Is the
Get file
Path
So it is forming part of a whole bunch of code that I'm adding to the helper class of this component
And which I'm also using another components so
I don't need to redo this code anytime soon unless in in sorry
I don't need to come and open the
Component when I want to change this code
I can just change the code
Right there
In the
Place that it's in the custom area
So that means if we close out here
And we go back to the custom code
You can see that the function is being used in component builder and in what field there PHP helper both
It's where it's added
And
If you'll need improving the code you can always at the bottom see in which areas is being used
So that is the option for multiple reuse of custom scripting
So you could put it anywhere you like in JCB either in the component helper class or in the component
View
You know PHP areas
And by doing so it gets reused it gets placed into that code on compilation
And that's really the answer I suppose
To the power of the customer code area
I realize it could be confusing because we are mixing it with the IDE custom code which
These are
This hash
Automation
Is basically where you
Edited your code in the IDE like I did here
And the JCB is keeping track of it
And it's saying ok this is for the admin views template default body php file
And on the on this starting hash
Value
We are doing an insert of this code and you cannot maintain the code here
But it's only for one file one location one place
Then there's the JCB manual and the JCB manual
Is the implementation or the mutated implementation
Of using custom code snippets this snippet
All across in custom code areas
So that means
I'm using the same word custom code
For different implementation
And
That might have been a mistake because
You could miss it's possible differences
But there is most certainly a difference this doesn't target a file but a actual area
Somewhere in that JCB compilation
So
Yeah I hope that helps
Let me know.