I wanna give you a quick tutorial on how to use bitnami on your local development environment
Bitnami is a very well known
Distributor of images
They actually have
Association with Amazon
They really know
What they doing
And for local developing environments
I found them to be the most convenient
But then again that is if you are not afraid of command line
Would you shouldn't be
Command line is an amazing world for you to make use of as a developer
And
It'll be good for you to just you know
jump in.
Ok so the first thing I did it's just Google Bitnami
Joomla together
And you'll see there is actually
A
Download Joomla Bitnami and Bitnami Joomla installer
And how to install Bitnami Joomla and here's even on Joomla even a documentation
installing Joomla using Bitnami
Joomla
Now
We can we can open this
And
we'll see
That it has a
Recommended stack for Windows Linux and Mac and it basically deploys all this
You get a little
Setup Bitnami Joomla setup tutorial which takes you through the process of installation
Helps you select
the place
And adds information and then
That's basically it you done
So it's sort of does what
Other
Similar components do but I have experience because it's targeting Joomla
It really does and places everything so you could you could just click on this link here or
You can if you check there at the bottom it says Bitnami.org stack Joomla
And that's basically the same
as the first one here
So you could also just clicked on this result and
I'm gonna well maybe I should just download it and run it but because
I'm on a Linux environment you would basically take click on this one here
And then
You select the environment which you're in
And you would just click and
Download
No thanks I don't want to register
Just wanna download it
And that's really it
Just click and download
So I'm just waiting for the download to start here
And then just save the file to your local system
And then basically run the file now if if you if I just click back a few
If you used Microsoft
They have executable
see it's exe file so you just double click on it
And and that should get you going
And the same goes for Mac
So you you just double click on the file and it will run you through tutorial
I'm using Linux which is a little bit a little bit different because it using run
File and you need to start it from command line
As you can see
I just downloaded it is already got Joomla 3.8.11 it's it's always up-to-date
So if you're on a Linux system you would say open in terminal
Do me a quick ls la and I will see the file is not executable
So we'll make it executable
So they will be sudo chomd
plus x
And then the file name enter
I'll ask you for your password of course and you typed that in
Wrong wrong command
the typo it should be chmod
Ok now the file is executable
Check it out it's sl
correct
Once you've done that you can close to the command line so basically it was just to run
this chmod command over here
To make the file executable
Which is a safety
and making sure that it runs
Correctly
Now
You could just double click on the file
in your file system
And it should start there Bitnami
Tutorial
So I select language
And welcome to Bitnami Joomla Stack
And yes we want all of this installed
And we just gonna select
Well let's just say
Like that and called it
and next
And then you can give some
Yeah some defaults here
And I'm just going to give her a simple password
And next
And it's asking for the MySQL port
The I know that I've already got MySQL installed here
let's see
which is 3 0 6 so 3 0 7 should be OK
just gonna give it a name
I'm not gonna do email here
And I'm not gonna
Try and link up with Bitnami's
Cloud
And then
we're done
Next
It's basically going to run the installer
And deploy
Everything you need the PHP the MySQL
Joomla with its Database
It's really setting everything up for you
And if you gonna be doing local development I suggest using this path because it takes care
Everything for you
And does it in a way that doesn't affect
You're already existing PHP
And you're ready existing
SQL and everything else
it really packages it into a folder
Which
I've just like using
we're almost there
doing now the MySQL Database
creating the databases
This can take long depending on your systems resources
now to removing the
Things that it doesn't need
Well actually it's setting up and uninstaller Script so if you didn't like
This you could
Then undo it
Are we done
Now you can launch the Bitnami Joomla Stack and just click finish
And there we go
we got it installed now to access the Joomla sign
It basically using my
Local IP right and then we go Joomla
and there is our Joomla website
And obviously to access the admin
Admin
There we go now to login here they have default passwords and stuff set
Basically the one that you typed in during the installation
And there we go we are
Here and we want to get JCB
So we install the
The web tab
and we type here JCB enter
And it comes up we click on it
And we say install
It usually will grab the master branch which
Is usually in sync with the latest release
And we install
It's also not counting these downloads so that's one of the reasons we don't have any idea
How many are using JCB at the moment
Ok once it's installed
You can actually go and open JCB
We are now on a little
Screen issue here I just downsize a bit
But here we go
let's grab
A demo package by going to install JCB packages
And here is VDM packages
And there's the community packages
And we can
Grab
Any of these let's just take the Hello World
And get the package so as you can see I've done nothing I've just deployed
Bitnami, I haven't touched any other feature of PHP or anything else
it just grabs the package
And it validates the checks sum for us we force it to update
And we click continue
And now it's importing the hello world component
And there we go it's done
Just to show
we quickly go here and we compile Hello World
And install
And here we go Hello World is there
And it is working
We can add a greeting
And
It's It's doing everything is expected
We also can check the front end
Main menu
Change the main menu by
Using the Hello World greetings
And save and close
Just before we do that we go back to Hello World we opened the options
check out the permissions we search for
Site
We see there is
two and they're already set to allowed greetings if not you just change them to allowed for the public
And that is the the two areas you would like
And then you can click here
And there is some text you see it
We have not
Given the public actually the edit rights so it will say that it's not available
But it can actually check some text and go back to home
So we see that the Hello World tutorial is functioning on our Bitnami
Within
How long did this take
11 minutes
Anyway
Thanks for watching that just a quick demonstration of setting up a local developing environment with Bitnami
And the reason why I take this path
Is primarily because of what I'll show you next
Here you have the bitnami folder remember we've typed it in
And there's your Apache
There is all the files
And
You want to go into the apps folder
Then into the Joomla folder
And into the htDocs folder in here is your whole Joomla website and you can you can open
And go in and actually
Work on your components
And edit it's files so this this is really the biggest reason I want to be able to
Easily access the files and work with them
And so it is it's very doable here
The other feature which just comes out of the box by Default
Is actually if you go back enough
You'll see
It is that it has
In the apps folder, you can see that has the PHP my admin installed
So that means
You could type here
PHP my admin
And be right there able to access PHP my admin and check out of databases
This all Bitnami did out of the box without real complications anyway that's the
Reason I like using bitnami on my local developing environment and they are quite quick
With the updates you can actually if we go back to that folder
You'll see that it has your and uninstall and a manage
Files
So you could run this one to uninstall and you can run this one to manage the environment
Which does actually check whether the server is up the configurations and
Civil events and stuff like that
You can stop all
And then the other one which I like is that you can click here
Uninstall
Do you want to uninstall Bitnami Joomla stack and all it's models. yes
And it starts to uninstall everything removes everything so you could run
This do some work save your components export your JCB packages and then completely
This thing and
Move on
But it's dangerous do keep in mind it really removes everything
Ok well that's this is now the end