I would like to give a
And demonstration and maybe some explanation around how the functionality of a
Custom field works I think we've had some tutorials about this in the past
But it
JCB has improved
And there is
a little bit of a different look
to that area
So let me
Let me do this again and maybe I'll even try and
give some code
I mean
Show you in the compiler
What what is actually doing
And then we take it from there let's see
We have
a few views here
I've imported Sermon distributor
Which is the most common demo component
that I have used
And
It has a few custom Fields so I could
I could actually change this where's it
This one
Is changed to custom
And we see that we've got a few custom Fields here
The idea was that you would
Use the demo components and then
Figure out
How their custom Fields work
And it's doing so
know help us and fields work but ok
I'm gonna
Well first of all
Custom fields is a way
To connect
a table
From another view of course
Into another view so it's it's a way to build relationships then you can
Have more than one custom field
In a table
And
You can do that to build relationships
You could even
Take
Different tables
And
Create
A different combined list of values
You can't really do anything with
Custom Fields it is
Maybe one of the most powerful
Field types in JCB
Now if we If we open let's say editor let me just do that
I wanna show you that
Custom fields are basically a Joomla implemented
Concept
Implementation or how can I say that
So you have in models you have well let's open the
Correct folder here
not this one
This one we wanna go to sermon distributor
You have in your models folder you have a folder called fields
Now and Joomla 4 this is changing the folder structure but
in for now you'll you'll know it's it's here
and so here is our custom fields is basically a field that you create
By creating a file in this folder and then
Using the field name
In your XML so if you look at your form
And let's say we use
Sermon
You will see that in the XML
At the top we have add file a field path
And you see that it edits in the model
So
Because of how we do it it
Expects it to be here
So even yeah anyway
So
That's why it knows to go look for the field here
Now if you scroll down
You'll see that we have a normal
And wherever it says Joomla
It means it's a normal field
At the moment it says custom
It means that this is not a normal field this field was made custom for this component
Now this is just a
Note it's like the comment doesn't do anything
It's just is for you
So this so you can come here
In the fields area
And there's preachers this is the
File that makes this work
So
That's basically what JCB builds
He puts this in place and then builds this file and that's it
And so
In these files
Depending on what type of file we are extending so now we are extending here the list
Option now to know what is all the available extending options we go to
Joomla component builders File
We go to the compiler
We go to Joomla 3
we scroll down we'll see there is
the checkboxes
Option
There is the field list the field radio
And the field user but the field user we actually made a whole custom field to just target the field user
But the checkboxes and the radio if you if you go back to JCB
And create new
And you select
Custom
you'd see
That it
At some point where is it
Let's see
It asked here what do you extend
And you have these three options you can extend that a list as a radio button or a check
Checkboxes
That is what this
Extend is for
So
That's currently the only 3 that is
Ready to go in JCB there there are of course others
But then we'll have to expand JCB it doesn't reach those yet
Ok so getting back to this
If you are using a form list which is the most common one because you wanted have a list of things in
Another table
Then
You're gonna have to populate
The get options function
Now the get options function
Or method
Is
Requiring this chunk of code
Now
Instead of making it that you need to write out this whole thing
In JCB you are just adding this part
For the
List
For the radio
It's also just
The
Get options
For the checkboxes again also just get options
So
It is basically the only code we need to have it's only with the user one
Which
We have a get groups
And exclude
And
If you create in JCB
Excuse me if you
Here select custom user
You'd see that that is exactly what you get you get exclude area
and you get get group area and these two chunks of code
Is What is going to be placed
In in this area here
That's basically what is gonna happen
So you could at any time
Coming here fiddle around with this I mean it in the PHP in when the file is created
Like like over
over here
I've got this preacher open right
You can come in here and fill with us and then take your changes just back to the view to JCB
And just place it in here
not well not in this one this is the user
But in a custom
Ok so
Basically that means that this did the type is movable
Because it's new but it must be something that doesn't already exist in Joomla
And if you don't know what all the field types are that exist in Joomla then
A good place to start is to go to field types
And check out all these
And if that still isn't clear you can go to this place
This URL here
This has a list of all Joomlas field types so you could
You could open that
Scroll down
And here is a list of all the field type names that you can't use again
You can't
Well it will be conflicting
Because it will break that name in that form
So
Best use names that are not used by Joomla
Ok so that is that
Going back to creating a custom field
We could start with sermon preacher which is the one we looking at
So
Again the name up here is just for the interface for you it's just that you can see what is the field
You can call this anything
It only fall back onto this name
If
If there isn't a
A label
Set here
Then it will fall back onto this name
But the ideal is just set the label you know
Then the name here
This name again is actually the code right
That we know this is the type this is what is going to be
To be new unique
the rest is sort of the same as everything else multiple
the default value because it's dynamic
It's not really practical
But it's really gonna be whatever you choose to be the ID of this
Memory right
Required read only this is all &&&&&ok extend here you make your choice what kind of
Field do you want to create
Then button the button feature is one of the
Features that are actually quite exciting
Let me show you some of that
So I was seeing a strange behaviour here I was seeing that the button says true
And then when I go to the code
I don't see the button code in here
And I was wondering ok what's going on here and then I remembered
when JCB detects that
There is
Two
Custom
Fields with the same type
It only uses one
For this area
And for the button
Because one of them
Is going to be there
Dominant one
You can decide which one it is so you want to share the field type among multiple
Custom
Fields
so you want to reuse that field type you can
But you want to make sure that
One of them is the one which you know
Is going to be the leader if you will
The one who decides how things happen
So that if you change that one the field type updates where is if you change the wrong one it doesn't do anything
So just one of those will be the
The dominant one so you could do that by making it the prime
prime  PHP and make that one so here is a little explanation of that
So you wanna be sure this field
Called preachers
Should be the dominant and you wanna say I want the buttons to be true
And now you save and compile
You you will get what you expect
And so that's another feature of custom
fields that
people are not aware of this feature but it's it makes it very useful
So if we now go back to the code
We see now a new set of a script here called get input
And that's really how the button gets added so basically asks
Get the attribute button
it checks if button is true
If button is true
Then it already got the parent HTML which is what
The button the whole field is in this HTML
Then we do some
Because if you have a button and someone Clicks on it you might want them to
Be Redirected back to this page where the field is once they done on the other page
So this is what it does here it checks if there is a
Referral
And also we've added the return value
As well so if there is a return value
We are going to detect it
oh no, wait, sorry
We are building a return value as well that's right
Ok so we come down here
And we're starting to build the button so there is the the button being built
And that is to create
And then there's also one now
You see that if the button name
Preacher
Or preachers
Is
Is the same as the area to which you are
The preacher..... OK because this this inputs name is preacher right
If we
go back here
This is called preachers right and down here
We have a view called preacher and preachers
So that is the Single View
Right
Single View name of the place the field is added
And this is the listview so we are grabbing the field data from the preacher
View and it's list name is preachers so
It's the table where the data is being captured from
Not the table where you gonna show the field but
The table where you are taking the information from
Now you taking it from multiple tables then he must choose a dominant table
The one that you want to be
Always available
So that's what this is as well as this as you can see
It is obviously usually the case that this and this values the same
But I decided to just give us
The option to change the table name anyway
Ok so we
Will get to these again
Just wanted you to see you
Sorry show you that if those two
Actually line-up
The button name lines up with those two
Then
it checks whether this is current user has authority to actually edit buttons
We come down here
And we create and edit button
So
And we also write JavaScript
to
Give that
Button behaviour when you click
Change the field it checks ok
Is that value and then it
Updates that you can check out this JavaScript here.
This one up here is used to generate the create button and it also validates
Whether
This user
Has create
Options
And is there is a user in the admin area currently this feature is
Is not available to the site area and
It's because of many conventions in the site area is so custom it'll probably
Break this button so
We'll have to work at this but this is where we are at we were able to Target the admin area with this kind of button
And then if we have a button
We actually add the button declaration
To the document
And then we add the buttons
To the field with this
Input append this class here
Is a Joomla
Class
Which means we falling back on their implementation on how to add a little tweak to the button sorry to the field
So we just add this and that is how the button gets added and how it works
You mean you can come through this I mean this is quite simple
It's very easy code here
This this implementation here is just to make sure that the button name follows the convention
And naming convention
And
Yeah so that's that's the HTML and JavaScript that sets up the button and
The reason why you would sometimes see the edit button there and sometimes not is about this relationship here
The
Button name
Must match one of these
So if it doesn't
It won't add it
It's sort of
It's necessary for that to be like that because of
You wanna have a
Button that already knows where we going right
And how can I know those values at the moment the only values we have here
Are these values it's come up here
These values
We don't have
Other values
This is the values we have the view ID
So That's what we have to work with and so if there's no relationship
Then how can we How can we set the edit button the relationship must be set so this is the way we
Set a relationship that's quite simple right you just make sure that the name of the
The button this one won't work
So although we said the button here to be true
It will check the name and see how this doesn't match and it won't add a button and that's good because we don't want that
Actually a button here we want a button to show up in this one
And so when it loads this button
It will check the name it'll say ah yeah this one matches and it will add a button
So
That's the right behaviour That's what we want so if we compile it now
&&&&&&&&&&&@@@
We can just come here
And go to
sermons
Click here
We'll see it now has an edit option
If we select none and has a great option
Select this it has a edit option
That is sort of how that relationship comes together
So were are we
go back
To the field
Ok
So
Oh this is a wrong one
So now we have the buttons set
That's really the whole discussion
And you could if you don't want the button set
But you want the button on the page
Set this to false
Or just leave it out yeah it will take the button away completely
Now this table value is a mandatory value
Because it gives us a dynamic value which we can use in
In many places including here
You see a list button gets added to a page as well if we
If we look back here at this implementation we see that here is a list
Again
But this isn't even in the view
This is in the list View
So you can
Have a filter
Dynamically in place for this again in the batch as well if you if you select batch
There is also one available to select so all of these fields
Are still using the information that we give here
So if you don't have this information then some of these Fields functions will just
Disappear
It will
Most probably not break
But it will not be there so if you to see the fields filtering option is not working then it's because of
these settings that are not right
Now to give you a perspective on how it adds that
This little
Drop down here how does it do that
Well in the code again if we go to that View
Which is the
plural preachers
And we scroll down
We have a
Function
Called
here it is
Filter
Ok so we go up
And we see
There's a preachers one
Import data
What is the buttons
filters
Looking at the wrong one
I should be looking at
Sermons
So here we have a load field type
Preachers
And it basically gets options
see
So this is really targeting
This
Options area this get options it's calling that function
And
Then if we have values it actually adds them into the filter
And it checks are we doing badge and if this can create can edit validates
Yes then it adds it to the batch as well
So
We are falling back onto the field type get options even in your filter
And so
That's why we have the filters easily integrated and it's the value is still use
Using
The
Values that you placed in the field
So
That's how we get this value that's how we get that value
Yeah that's basically it
Ok next
We have the components name now the reason why these can be dynamic
Is because
The table as well as the component name
It
is possible for you to reuse fields in different admin views and different components
and then that can be dynamically update it
And it should just work when you want to have a relationship from one
Table into another component altogether
Then you have to hard code
Component a
So let's say you have component a where you have a view
adminView where this field is used
And you want to take the data
From
That View
Into another
Component altogether
Then you have to add component a's
Static name in here and not the placeholder ok that's enough of that there has been discussions on
forums about this so you could search up and find answers I suppose
Then we have a field value and a key field
Value field and key field
I should have maybe given this different names I suppose because
Basically the key field is the ID field
Down here that place holder is the same as here and I'm actually saying it over there
The field value
Is the text value
Over there
Now
The code text
Is basically
This text value again
But it didn't gets placed over here so this and that value is basically the same value this is
just the one that gets taken to the code
Well it's what becomes available in the item
So
You could
Change this to whatever you like this place holders are there only to make your life easier
If it doesn't help then just replace them with static values
But the advantage of them being like this is you can come up here and decide I no longer want to store the ID
Because this is the value that get stored right it is the value that is over on this side
J HTML method setting up an option
Takes the second value which is this one has the value that get stored in the database and the third the
Value as the value that gets shown in the drop down list
So these are the two values that you're working with
Now you can add here any
PHP you like
I mean you could you could grab from any other table you could do a very complicated query here and
Generate a whole different list
And just make sure that the ideas are not going to Clash
And if you expect
ID clashing then if you need to add
Maybe ID underscore something for one
Place's information ID underscore something else for another place's information you could do that because
Because this this selection concept
We'll keep on using this pattern all across JCB
This is where you set
The
Relationship
Inheritance structure everything this is just this area and it affects everything across JCB
Wherever this field is going to be used
This is going to be available
So it always
It means that you have a lot of Freedom in this little
Block because that's what's gonna be at the end of day end up being placed here
And
You can
Get from other tables you can do other and you know interesting relationships here
But
That is
Important that at least the main table
Is the one that you mentioned here
And the main component is the one you mentioned here
And it
That
Tables
View and list views names are used here and then the value
I mean in this table this one here
You are grabbing two values you're grabbing a value to show to the user
And value to save in the database that's the key value the key field that is the value
Get stored in the database if you're using
This implementation
If you're not then this doesn't really
Yeah you can just leave it out if you if you're not gonna use this
You can hardcode whatever values you want down here it'll still work infact I would
Encourage you to test it
You know
I have built Fields custom Fields which I left out
All of this information
And only did everything in here
And
It still worked
Because I was actually having such Dynamic value retrieval based on so many other concepts
Of the current view I even grab the ID from the from the input to determine the
Get relationship so
They are very nice
Options let me show you one of those fields
Here is the field it's called member it's an external I'm using it in a
external component
The field type is member
Ok so I hard coded the table and the component names
But down here in the option the get option
You see I have a whole different set of PHP script
Which
Is using
Custom help methods to check access
It's also up here
We were basically where is it
Yeah I'm getting the input and I'm checking is there referral values to a field ID value and if
there is it I'm using this
This values
Down into the searching and getting here it says
Load the main member only
You know there's all kinds of
Tricks I'm doing and it's all happening in the PHP and I know
That this PHP
Is getting dumped
Into this area here
So the get options is what is being used across JCB for the field
And so I'm able to do anything that you can with PHP in here
To determine what the options must be for the custom field
Always remembering that there needs to be in
This area here the needs to be a value which I want to be placed in the database and a
Value I want my user to see these values can
Theoretically be exactly the same
Like that
I didn't have to be
really
doesn't matter
You decide the only reality is if that's the value you place in the database that's the type of value
You need to set up
So if this is going to be a string
This value here
Then you need to come back
And you need to
Check
That your database is not an integer
Because if you saving a string you want at least have a Varchar
about 250
Now that'll work
But if you change the
Multiple
That means
Can a user a select more than one value if you change that true
Again you need to change your database to at least text
to
Be able to store or a very big Varchar which is also possible
To store these values
if they are gonna be strings then I usually just use text I just like it
Easy enough
And if it's going to be lots of options you can go
bulk ,there is even
way more than I think you would ever need but ok so
The reality is we can
determine what these values are so here I'm making sure that the member value is an ID
But I'm using a helper method
To take this ID
And get the members name
Why because the member's name is difficult to know because it could be different values based on the
Different member types some members there having their name in the user table some members they have in there
names in the members table
So that's different places the members name can actually live
So with this little function I wrote in the helper class
I can determine the members name by simply the ID
Or I could add the user and the name and it makes it quicker to for the function so this function has
Little bit of a speed up if I have these values available but like over here I don't so I only pass the ID and
It still works
And so
This is the  maneuverability of a selection
You can adapt this to whatever you want the only reality is that the moment you set
Your I would call it convention
Of this field type
Then you need to honour that Convention across your component
If you decide that you're saving a string in that field
Then you need to everywhere now you dealing with the string
If you're saying you're saving a multiple select then you might wanna
Do
You know the default storing method usually works
Out of the box
If it doesn't you can come and try Json
Especially when you have multiple values but usually it does it out of the box and I can show you why
If we go to the compiler
We go to the fields
Class in the compiler it has a function called set Builder
Now the set builder function is really a little oversized at the moment it started out
Small believe me
And I could
See the option of decoupling some of this out into its own separate methods but
It works very well and it's easy to understand so
If I just collapse this here we can see more
So now we come down here we ask what is the data type
Is it set
And if it's set we determine
Through various methods ok
This is what we have and we go ahead and we set database keys and all kinds of database relationship
information query builder gets updated with a lot of information and stuff
So the database information gets used up here
If we have
....... it is a different concept
if we scroll down
We wanna look at the storage switches
So coming down here
Where we get to setup checkbox and other joint items for this view
We are basically
Going to check
What type of field is this
If it's a subform if it's check boxes
Or if the store method is not zero which is default
If we have a database switch
And
That it's not a tag the type name
Ok now we coming here if it's any of these fields
It will check if you set your own storage
Switch
Obviously if none is set it will fall back onto the Json
It needs to be Json
If it one of those fields
So it automatically builds it so that means the default will be Json then if you select Json it
It will still be Json
So that's just how this catch works if you don't know it should be we will
In the compiler sort of help you
Get to the same place
Now
That also means that sometimes
You might have a multiple select option in a list field which is not a subform not
check Boxes
But it's multiple
The multiple gets triggered the multiple switch so it will still come in here
So what even if you set
it to be Json
Where in the compiler have the multiple
Switch to check is this field having multiple selection
Yes well then we need to save save it as a json
That is what this does so takes care of the fact that it's Json but
It mustn't be a tag and it must have a database switch and database which just means the data
Must be going to be stored into the database if there's no storing of the data in the
Database we obviously don't need any of this. So the multiple switch
If we search it up
We'll see that it actually gets passed
To the builder right there one of the it's
parameters
We go and search
Where the Builder all is used will see that the multiple switch is also in a variable
So we can go up and you can search
You can search for this where does multiple get set
Ok so we started of
This this method
Didn't start with multiple so that scroll down let's see
Where is multiple come from
There's multiple
And it's set to False to start with
Ok
So we're in the beginning of set the dynamic field
We check multiple is false then we get set field attributes and multiple gets passed to it
Let's check field attributes we go let's go to the actual function
We see here comes multiple but it's passed with a reference that means he whatever we do to this value
In this method
We'll go back to where it started
So over here
We doing a check
At some point Let's see we got Properties
Validate
Let's search that the variable multiple
That's go ha
Here we found the property name which is multiple
We retrieve the value
From the XML
Check that the value gets added here and we check is that value true and if it's true we
trip the switch
To multiple so that literally gets down the through what you put into the JCB
Interface
This little
Field
Where is it
If you
Set this to True it will trip that behaviour
So that's how that works
So the multiple switch is a powerful switch and it
Really helps you even if you miss
The the storage
Obviously it doesn't update the database
Selection but if you miss the storage thing
The default will work
Ok
But if you did that it will still work even if you select one of the encryption options it will
Still work
Because it actually is a little bit intelligent
Ok so if we go back here
And we go back to the
Set Builder
The set builder function is one of those places where you could figure out a whole lot of things
About how they JCB compiles
Custom fields
So this is a good place to start you know your search
The other one that we already looked at is the set attribute
This one here
The set attributes is where we actually work with the original values that we get from the database the properties
As well as the actual field
So
We use the field value to determine many things
And we parse every value, the reason why we remapped this is to make sure we can
Sort of fix things if you made a mistake
So there is some some things here to try and catch
Any
Human error on the side of JCB that also means you could be doing something wrong
and things still work
That happens
And then someday maybe someone decides no they don't want to catch that fix anymore
You know which I'm trying to
You know prevent I wanna keep the
The fixing place
And then suddenly your
Project
Doesn't work
I'm trying to avoid that
But it's good to know how it must be done
Right
So you just do it that way
To start with
Ok
So
That is
Basically a little bit of that, let's go back to the field
Suggest in conclusion
You could add any kind of code here
Basically it is what gets
The list and it's with this string here
That you are adding options to the list so basically in this little chunk here
Basically you check do I have the items if yes you can decide if you want to put a placeholder you
See there select a Preacher if we go to sermon
And
We
We see that it's first option is select a Preacher
And it is basically this little snippet here that does that
So you could
You could do that now
The
When you do multiple select
Then this
Doesn't work well
just take it from me
If you up here
Chose
To allow multiple
Where is it
here
True
Then
I would suggest you take this option now
Because it will be look like an option to select it won't
Behave the same as now
Where you actually click away and it's gone it will be an option and
The option is a blank there's like a no string
That is how
We detect
That it's empty
It's this no string value here
Ok so
That is what that is up there and then you start looping this t forward slash is basically
A tab so you could put an actual tab in there
The way I do that is I would go to
you copy a tag from here copy go back
And paste it in
And
You could do this
In fact
Most of the time this is the better way
to
To make the code look
Beautiful
And
Correctly spaced This is This is often what I do
Is I move all the code
Just one little knots
In fact I think I needs to be two
So I move it all
Like this and I know it sounds
Crazy
But that is what I do
So now the code will look very nice and good in the display
If I save it
Let's
Let's make a little comment here
Hi there
and then
This is set to be the prime so save and close
And now we can
Go and compile this
Install
And in our preacher table we have that little hi there
And unfortunately the first value should not have a space
Yeah the spacing of
Of field types is still well many areas actually in JCB
It's like where we're at a place where I don't know how we will be able to fix this
So that it always behaves sort of better like that is now with you I need to do to get that space in just right
And I I know that feels a little
Wrong place
That feels a little
Uncomfortable
But it's really
It's difficult to catch it correctly for every
Implementation
So
Currently
That's the work around
so if we compile it
and we go back
We check it's Now it's correct
And there's our little note
So our spacing is working out
If you didn't add the space
it will
Sometimes work out something like that
That's how it look
Ok
Which still will work it just doesn't look nice
So on this view we have this as a custom field this is a custom field
This is category field the tag field
And this is a custom field
So we have
Many different
Custom fields
Which is quite nice
List folder this is a custom field a multiple select
Custom field
External
This is a custom field
So
There are many custom fields on this page
And you can actually
In JCB when you've imported
sermon distributor
If you don't know how to do that
There are tutorials
Maybe the best quickest path to showing you that it's just JCB import
Then VDM packages
How to get
Free keys from VBM
Because sermon distributor
Is one of the three packages
There are many free packages not all of them are
Free like these are not free
But
They are even component builder is one of the free packages that you can get a key for
So you could click here go get a key
I tell you the the
The way that we have
Build components
In JCB
And all the fields that we've used
I mean you can come here you can go to
Preacher
And all those custom Fields that I just clicked
They are here
Wait this is not the right one sermon
This the one had so many
So it's this one
To come to Fields and here they are that's custom
That one is custom
This one
You could click this local file list
Wanna see how to list and local file list
With a custom field
Well this is how I did it I don't even have look here
There isn't even
Any
Table here
There's even the button is false
Extend list yes
I doesn't have a table doesn't have a component none of that I just dumped it
And
I you see the first one is
Back there
Now I get parameters I first get the folder path from the global so if you want to see for
Example oh how did he set this how to get this setting while let's go out of this would come back here again
And out of this
Then let's go to the component
And you'll see that there is a component config area we open that
Going of the path a bit but just bear with me
And one of those
Fields
Let's see set up here no
it's sermon s
there's obviously many in this one
Sermon
Let's see Sermon menu sermon panel box
Sermon media
Sermon
Ok it's not down here
execution time
Download
So
It was up here all along
Local folder path
So it's a It's a text area
Which is in sermon tab so if we go here and we click options
There is a sermon tab and there it is local folder path so you can set the local folder path for this
Where the local files are going to be placed
And
It is because of this file here
This field
Now if you wanna check the fields check the spelling local folder path close it out
And go to fields
And type in
Local
ok
Oops
So there it is this a text one we select that
Are you can see how I built that
Simple field type
For the hint
Nothing fancy
Now I'm going back to our field
If we
Go back to the field we were looking at
We go back to admin View
We don't need to go into the sermons
But ok that that is a easier way right so we go in here
Now we go get into local file
Open that
So basically in our component
We checking this components value for local folder and if it hasn't got one we fall back unto images
The image path
And that's where we start
Now
We do a first option
Which is please add files and we take the local folder path result
And we pass it into here
into options
Now
Then we load the file import Ops classes
And we check does the folder exist
If it doesn't we create the folder
Now check if there is files in the folder
So we do get files This is the
Function in Jfolder
And
If it's true
We actually take the files and we
Reset the get options because remember up here we
told it to add files but now here with this we reset basically the
Options variable
And now we start loading the files and then we give it back
And so we used both value here see file and file
Which is actually very easy way to
To do a local folder setup
And make people select now again we just looking at demo
Component
we just looking at it
external source manual file is also custom how am I doing this
Well it's quite complicated thing so it is a
Basically I'm using a helper class get external source link
And I don't again look at that there is no table
There's no no external component
There's nothing
Just
Just these values go look at it if that's all it is there and it's working that should tell you that you could do the same
And get it to go because this is the actual issue this result
That's what we need to have correct
So having looked at this or get external links source while that's an helper
Class how is that close that out
Helper classes are stored in the component area
So you go to Joomla components
Go into the component
And you go to libs helpers
And here you can scroll down
And get download links
is a big method
get
We should have
Copy that
So here is a function get external source length and has a few arguments
And it does a few other get externals listing
And does a few trip switches here
And
That's how I eventually return
Something to that function
And
We get that list
Ok so
That's how you should take demo components and
Sort of decipher it's implementation structures and don't think it's more complicated than
That it isn't it's really simple
JCB is very
Resilient
It can
Adapt itself to
Specific implementations
So the custom field
Is my opinion one of the fields I
Have enjoyed
Extremely very much
And I'm using it all the time everywhere
And
I am constantly making sure trying to ensure that it's behaviour
Remains
Yeah remains stable
But also becomes sort of surprising like
Just adding this value request ID
If you if you look at Sermon distributor
And
Let's close out here
This is again
This is not only for custom fields
But since we are on
This explore process if we go to main menu
And let's say we wanna create a
Field for the sermon menu sorry and let's say we gonna do
Series
now you see that there is a whole bunch of values here
Look at that
Whole bunch of values
From sermon distributor
In relation to the series
And they all said Global Panel Box I mean this is a stunning feature right and it's
Very easy to do
Because all that I had to do to get those features there is to take this list query ID
This value
Is what actually makes this a selectable item
In the menu so if I
Go back here
You see I have a series and you can select
Test
The way that JCB set this selection option up
Is just by me adding this
Request ID
to
To this field name
Ok that's how that happened
Now how did I get all the rest of the values
These on the page as well
Let me show you
the way to get
All the fields that you add to the config
for example this
We were looking at which one were we looking at the series
The way to get all the series
Fields
That your add here
To show at the menu is the fact that this name matches the site name
That's how it works
And if there is a field here
That you do not want to actually have load here
There is a way to do that so I'm gonna demonstrate that quickly
As part of custom fields in a way
So let's say I don't want them to set the default icon here anymore
Then I want it always just fall back on the global
Then I can actually
Go to
Let's see close out here
Here is the series default icon
I can scroll down and there is this
Extra properties
I can say add
I can select display
Now display switch for dynamic placement in relation to use of the field in menu and global
configuration options
So the config option will only add the field to the global configuration area
Many will add the field only to the menu area and if you don't add this it will add to both
So if we only want it to be in the config area
We basically just add this value here
Now
Let's save and close and compile to show you
How it
Took it out
and now let's go back there and let's create
a new menu
That's again look at
sermon Distributors series
And now we see that the
Icon is missing here no longer showing up
Where are we
If we go to the sermon distributor global area
And to series
We'd see that the icon is still there
So all the rest of these values
are
Showing except this one and this one
Ok so
Now let's Tweak A Little More
Let's instead of config
Let's say only menu I want value only in menu save
And then compile
It install then go here refresh
And there we have it
Now it's here
And if we go back to sermon distributor and refresh
It's no longer here
So that's how you can control
The reason why all these buttons are here is because it's under this tab the reason why all these buttons are here it's because
It is this this view name series's is the same as this tab name series's
That is how the connection is made that's how the buttons gets move and if you
Don't want a button here
Then
This extra
Display
Option here can toggle where you want that button to show up
And is to say none will let the button show up on both
Ok well we're almost over an hour now
I've said quite a lot of things I don't know hopefully this will help you understand little more about custom
Fields and it's amazing
Agility and ability
To bring relationships together
Let me think is there something else
Yeah there is one more thing let me do that
In the components admin
View
You can add what we call a linked view
Right
So I am doing that here
In the sermons
Basically in the preacher Admin View I am linking the sermon
On tap 2 so I'm giving it the name
And
Did the child key
That means the place where we getting the data
No no wait a minute
The the one who
The
View is sermon
And in the Sermon table there is a column called preacher
And that column preacher
Is a custom field right
And we decided that that custom Fields save the ID
Of the preacher so the field name is
Therefore preacher where is the value in the current
Table
Which is again here
Preacher
Is going to be the ID right
This is the relationship between these two areas
And then the placement
Whether is going to have what kind of button
Add new new and close button or add new or close button or just a new button
These are some of the features that is available
So
Now sometimes it happens that you have a multiple selection and you still want to
Set this relationship
So there is a way to do that if it's a multiple selection so let's say this sermon could belong to more than one
Preacher which in this case is not but let's just for a moment say it can
Then you could do this. Wait.
That
Just that without anything else that will mean that it will now check whether
This ID is in the array of this value
If this array is a
Associative array so let's say you have the value but it's in an associative array
And
Dissociation is maybe
Key then you do that so if the array looks like this
So if it looks like that
Then
You wanna target that area
Then you would do
The key
If you are targeting a
More than one
Value so if it's this or that one
We have an one called or
So it could be
Preacher or
Let's say maybe have a teacher
You can say or
Servant
Maybe these are the columns
That mapped to this ID
You can have the or
In there
And it can link multiple values
But ok I think I'm going way over the edge here it's not really custom code
The custom Fields so much there but
Because custom fields are the majority of the time used
To set up this relationship right
You you set up these relationships
With custom fields
That is where that
Livability comes in
And
The linking of a table into another one
Ok
Well thanks for watching
In an hour of your time hope it's been worth it
Thank you. Ok bye.