At last we are happy to announce that we have added Joomla custom field integration
Joomla custom fields are the these Fields that you see on the users it's like there's Fields here in
Field groups
And the same under articles
Fields and field groups
Which basically
Targets the articles all the users respectively
If you add fields on the articles when you create an article
And it
Meets the specific criteria the field show up and you fill them in it shows up on the front end of your website
Now
That whole field and field group
Concept has a Integrative option for third-party components
So we have now changed JCB enough to
Allow that kind of field integration in your
components
And all I'm gonna do now it's just demonstrate how to make use of this
So we'll just use the normal demo component
Basically the way to add the fields to your demo component
Is to actually
You have admin views
And you gonna actually link the field to a admin view you can link it to multiple Admin Views
But I'm gonna demonstrate linking it to only this one called look
As you click on this edit here
And basically go to the area where you
Link the look the view to the component
And you see there's know new field called Joomla fields
Select if the option to add Joomla Fields should be added
To the view so we we just gonna click that that's really all you need to do
To get it working in a backend
The front end that's got little bit more
you know tricks to it
And that is to be expected because the front end of JCB components
Should be unique
And that's well that was the approach
So we gonna close out of this and before making any changes to the front end of the
Component I'm just gonna compile this
And install it on to this current website to see what happened
So we got compiler here when I just compile our
Component
And install it
Quite simple
And then we going to open
The component here
And when we go to looks
We'll see there are now looks Fields and looks Fields groups
So I'm gonna create a group here quickly say new
And say
Let's say
Really Easy and save and close
So we got this group called Really Easy I'm gonna now creative a field
And we gonna just make it a text field in call it
simple field and
We gonna add it to Really Easy group
save and close
here we got a field
If we now go to looks
And click on new
Will see that it has a new tab here called Really Easy
And we can click there and it's got a simple field
So we can say there
The name and
For the field you also give it a value
Just call at input value
And save and close
And immediately
You have the input value stored you got the name and well everything works exactly as expected
So it's created a tab
And if you've added a field
you can
Actually add More Fields to this tab
Simply
By selecting the same group call it More fields save and close
and we got More Fields
You going back to the look
And open it
You'll see that now More Fields was also showing up
With more input
And
That's how the custom field concept works
that's the easy part basically adding it to the component now like I said before you could add
it per admin View
But usually you would have one View
Where you at this
Now in the front end of this component you need to do a little bit more
Because the way that the fields work
Is explained
As triggering
On specific events
On the front end of the component
Now we at JCB have
Also added the option to
Add these events to your site views
But it's a little bit hidden and
Purposefully that way because we added it to the dynamic get area and not the site view
Area
And it is because
The dynamic Get
Is targeting either multiple items or
Single items and the events are really
Actually for single items so it seemed right that we added there
To easily validate and so forth anyway
So let's do that
It go to component
Builder
JCB and go to your custom or your dynamic gets
Now we we wanna add it to the looks
Sorry to the looking because it's a get item
Get so will open this
You see that now there is this new content plugin events
Which you can select
now
The fields if we go back to the fields area
And you open the fields
You see that it has options
And it here got automatic display option
So before display after display after title
And do not automatically display
These options
Is what is used
To Actually display the values that's submitted it to his field
On the front end of the site
So basically you've got before display after display and do not automatic display
And even after title
Now
By Default it is before display but you can obviously change that
In the
So you need in your component
To Target
These
Four events
For the user to make use of these fields
they might decide now they want to
Just use the fields in a back end
And it will basically be related on to this show on
If you do that
it will not even show on the back
So
Yeah this is
This is sort of it's Integrative
Switches
But
You need to Target these switches
Only in Your custom code on the front
At this point
And it's not really that hard to do that I'll show you why
So back into the dynamic Get I'm gonna
basically add title
add before display and add after display as events
And save and close
Now that will just
Practicly put the code
Into your component
So let me first show you the code how it looks now
So the component folder root folder I'm going to components and then I'm gonna go to demo
And basically go to views
And
then open looking
And then this view HTML.PHP file
Now the events
Are going to be added
To the display function
So currently as you can see
There's nothing here
So we gonna compile the component and see what changes
So just recap I've just added the events to the dynamic get
I'm going to the compiler
And I'm gonna recompile the
Component and install it
To see
What those events, you know the changes , how they will change the code
So it's
OK we'll
Go here
If we scroll down now
Will see that it added the dispatcher to the display
And
Down here
It imports the
Content plugin now
it creates in the item
Object it creates a new
Object called event
And then
Basically it checks whether your item has parameters
So it checks is there any parameters
Been passed
That is in your Dynamic get you could grab the params
column
From your
Items
And it's basically checking is it there
If it's not there
it going to fall back
Onto the Globals
So if it's there
And if it's a Json it will
Basically convert it to an array
And had it there or
it will fall back to the global params
And then
It is going to trigger
The on after title and
On content before display
And on content after display
And
It's gonna pass the components
Name
And the actual View
Value here
But now
We know
That
This is basically setting the context
Of this
Event
Now you could be building a plug in
That is actually targeting look
And not looking
And you want
To change the context of this specific
Event that
Has been passed over here
And to do that we've also added a context
Field in the site view
So your site view can
Change its context
So let me show you
So we'll just open the site views
And in the site views we have that view called looking we can open that
And here we now have a new
Field called context
So we have looking selected here as our dynamic get
And here we can set the contacts
To suit
The Dynamic get
And not fall back to the main code
If you don't add this context it will fall back to this code Name
But you could say I want the context to be look
And not looking
And then save and close and if we compile this again
It will actually update the contexts
Of that specific event
And any other event related to that
Will do that get
And which is really what you want so now you'll see it's changed it to look
So it's still past the component's name but the correct context
In relation to your event
And now what's gonna happen
Why we want this to be look
It's because
....
The fields are linked to the look
View the look admin view
And
So it is stored in the database under this context and not under the context of looking
But you are basically having both here on the front
So you couldn't use the name and look again you had to use another name
And so the way too then
Actually get that same context called on your title and is to actually change it like I've just done
I know that's a lot of
Explanation
Maybe some of you don't even understand
What I've just said but
Those who do will know I'll get this is nice you can
Change the context
Through the site view
So that you could have the same context be triggered
Multiple times
As you would have it
It's a little bit of a
Tweak at the moment we might bring more Automation in
But I know it is actually a little liberating so you could
Really be free and how you want to do this
But what now is going to happen
Is these events are being triggered and the values are being stored
Here
So whatever gets thrown back from the plugins
Gets placed into this value here
I'm so the only custom code that you now Actually need to do
After
Fixing up the events being added to the dynamic get and then updating the context to
Target the corrected
View , now just again I'll show you just once again
Why
Do I want this to be look
If we go to our
admin View
We'll see we'll see
That
If you open looks
And then click here
You see hear the top
It says demo and the view
Is look
And so
The context of these fields
Are linked to that value
And that value
So this one is always gonna be correct
But this one could be different
And so you need to in your site view make sure that your targeting
The correct
Context of where these fields are
So you be passing basically the ID
And this context and Joomla will automatically retrieve the values of this fields
And place those values
For you
Inside of this
Object here or actually
It will create a string as you see you here it implodes the array
Into string
And places it in here
So all you now would need to do
Is basically echo out Those values in any way you want them to look
So you could
Yeah you could add it in some diff tags
And
I'll show you that in a moment
So for now
All I wanted to explain is how these events
Actually get the
Field values on the page
So those field values are
Loaded into these values respectively of its switches
Which I showed you earlier in setting up the field
Now the Joomla web site currently is not set up to show the looks
So we gonna go to the menu
And change that
Going to main menu
And I'm going to click here on home
And I'm gonna select
Let's see where is a demo
Looks
And
Yeah that's basically it
And gonna save and close out of that
So now we have looks
On the
The page
The default page of the website
If we click here it should load
And there it is the name
To see a list of looks and here's the name if you click on that
It shows us the name
And it shows as there's been one head and if we refresh that it shows two heads
So
That all works well
But our custom values which we have submitted
Is not showing up
So
This
value is showing up and even we could add some
Description
And
This is
Also going to show up if we refresh the page here
there's the description and we click here there is the description
So all that is showing up but the real easy values are not showing up
And we want them to also be showing up on the page
And That's what we are going to do
For them
By Simply using those
Event
Objects
So over here we have
The
Content after display content before display and content after
title
Now
If you forget
How to use this or how to place this
The component that you can go to his this content
Component
And you can also open it's
Article
View
And you would see something very similar scroll down down down here
You see something well unless they've changed it by the time
But at this time
The default of Joomla's implementation is very much the same
So it's also triggering the content and it's also placing it into these values which means that
That if you go to it's template
Default PHP
You will see
Places basically you could search for it so you could take this
After title
Copy that
Come over here
And place it in there and here you see
Basically
The content is generated by the content plugin event on
And it basically just Echoes it out
So you could use this code just like that copy paste it into your component
After the title
And the same goes with the other events
So with the before display and after display
So let me do that quickly I'm gonna just grab these and place them into our component
So I've just copied them to a notepad like that I'm gonna move them to my other screen
And then I'm gonna go back to to JCB
And
Go to my component
The site view of a component
And I'm going to open looking
And in the component
We have a whole lot of things happening here
Basically we
have a article
Comment here
And over here is the title
So we want
We want that
Value
To actually echo out
After the title
So
We gonna take
That first one
Which is the event after the title
I'm gonna place it
Between the header and this diff
Here
So
Basically
There
So that the content is generated by there and it's on content after title so this is the title
And then when is gonna show over here
Then we have another one on content before display
Have the content before display
I would like to think it needs to go first before anything
So I wanna put that there
On before anything displays
That's way at the top
And with content after display
I  wanna put that obviously at the very end
Below everything
So that's quite simple
We could do more we could wrap it in a diff we could
Do all kinds of styles to it
But that's the simplest way and I'm just gonna demonstrate that
Save and close here
And then basically compile it again
Install
And now let's go refresh that page
Oops I got some errors here
I realised
I'm using slightly different names then
The ones I copied from the content
You know the article area
Content area
let me show you that
So
They are saying up here in the comment on content before display and here it's before display content
it's like a little bit
Different
So I'm using exactly the same
So just
Heads Up
Use the the same as
What is here in a comment
And that's little me that
always trying to
Keep everything the same
We save that it should work now
So here we go simple Fields input value more fields with more input
There are those values displayed on the front
So if we go back here
We can close this out
Go back to the fields and let's say with a more fields
You wanna change that to display after the title
Save
And then go back to the front and refresh this
So now the one is up here and the other one is after the title
So let's say we want simple field to actually show at the very end of our value
go out of more Fields into simple field
I will change that
to
you know
After display
Save and close
So you could move the values
Position
Simply and everyone will move now you see that simple Field is below everything
And if you realise
This whole area here is the block
So that's how the custom Fields can come to the front you can also say you know I don't want this
Area to show up
And you can go to
To the field simple field
And you could say show label hide label
And save
And now if you refresh it will only give you the value
So
That's the kind of behavioral integration
So that's a quick demonstration
Of how to now use Joomla custom fields in your components
And how to then
Model those values into the front end
By Simply making use of the events
And
Wow have fun I'm sure this will
Make things even more interesting
Thanks for watching