Ok we've got a very exciting new
Option available in JCB
Make sure you're on version 2.9.3 for this
We're at beta release now
It's already working and the tutorial
Is made during this period
But
Soon as we've got tested and stable we'll push it up I need to make this tutorial now
Because those tested need to
Know how it works ok
Basically
The past this area field types
Has got all the field types that Joomla has by Default
And you could extended by adding other field types that Joomla already
Has but except this one field called custom
This field has always been a jack of all trades if you will
You can do
Basically almost everything
Because it can extend
3 types of fields
And you can then dynamically generate the
Input values
So if you would open the custom field
You would see
It has a
Option here called
Extends
And has three options here list radio checkbox
And those are the three jform field subclasses that can be extended with
This custom field
Default use a list and that always works well
Now
What we've done is we broken out of the box
I made a previous tutorial explaining how custom Fields work
And
Also how you could expand it
By adding
Files
Making changes to the core which I realize is not a good practice
And so we took some counsel and we've decided to add
The option to expand custom Fields inside JCB without touching the core
And I trusted this would
Yeah be very powerful for some of you that wanna go Beyond the default
So let's see how this works
Basically
All of these field types that are really exist
Mapped pack to
Joomla field types
Now
Except this one as I said
This one has special features
It actually creates a new file
Which
Can be then
Overwriting
The default Joomla field types
Now first of all
The field types are declared in the library area of your Joomla core
So let's quickly look at that.
So if you look at your Joomla website you've got your
Root here administrator components and then you got libraries
Then you have a Joomla
Folder at the moment in Joomla 3
And it has a form folder with a Fields folder
and here is a whole lot of fields
Then there's also
A source folder also again with a form folder and fields folder in
A whole lot of other fields
All of these Fields extend
Some other field
So you can see that here for example jform field list is being extended by contentlang field
Many of these field types are
Joomla core related within the source where is the others
These with in Joomla
Are basically the default Fields that you see mapped out in JCB
Now we are extending this field which extends the form field
So you have basically jform field list
that has being extended
And then we also extending the radio
Field this one jform field radio
And we are also so that you can see it is extending various field types
So this is the place where you can come and say you know what
I wanna create my own custom custom field like Beyond
What JBS custom field already stands for so for our example we can
Take note for example
Let's say you want to
Expand on the Note field type
So you can come here
And you can look at
All it's values we get label
And the get input now the get input it should be
This ok but the get label you might want to overwrite this
In that case I mean you could
You could take any of these field types
Literally any
And you can take any of these methods
And I'll show you now
How to use this to write your own custom field type right in the JCB
Interface
And you no longer limited to what we have done
You can use any one of these and make your own field type now there's a difference between a
Field type and a field
And I know in
My initial tutorials I sometimes may have left a little confusion there but just that you know
Is most certainly a difference between a field type
And a field
Field is what ends up being used in your component is a field type is what is used to build
The field ok
Enough of that
We can extend meter
We can extend colour
We can we can really extend anything
I think to give it the best demonstration note won't be ideal
I think I should instead
Use list
I know list already exist but list has get input and it has get
Options
And it has add options
And
It is it has
Multiple options in currently in JCB You Could Only target the get options area
You cannot overwrite the input area and you cannot overwrite
The
Add options area
So having said that we can
Now actually do that
So
Let's show you how that's done first of all we go to custom
Component type field type
Custom we open it
Now we decide what are we going to do here what are we gonna extend now there's only one
Value
That you must set right
Well there are few but this is the one that trips the switch ok
And it's this name value
You can call it anything you like
But it must have an @ sign in it
So you could say for example list
@
And maybe
It's about
Some kinda list that you you gonna be using often and it has specific purpose for now I'm just gonna call it
Mine it's just simple
So list@mine this @
Doesn't need to between doesn't need to be between words it can be in the beginning
Can be in the end can be anywhere
But it has to be there
This little @ is what makes it different from every other field type
And what makes JCB know that this is a custom custom field
Beyond
normal custom so basically tells JCB this is your own custom field
You can keep this values as it is
You could take values away
I would suspect that there are some values that
You know you can't
Remove like the type the name the label and this will depend on what field type your extending on right
Most of the time the type must always remain because this must be a
Unique value that eventually gets used if you're using a custom field if it's a
Custom list field this cannot be list
Remember Joomla already has a list field option type you know field type
So you must use unique names so this could be you know my list like that
But it cannot be list ok now
If it's adjustable you can tick this
If it's not adjustable leave it unticked
And all this
You can
Change the description here you can do whatever you like
I'm gonna leave a lot of this right the way it is because it sort of makes sense
Here
We need to leave list there
And
We we need to tell those who maybe have staff or other using JCB in house
So the options are
Only list because you are extending list you want
This to work in list you might wanna use the table
Placeholder
Component placeholder The View placeholders
That's all up to you
Let me
I mean you can read here how to access the table value in your PHP
That you're going to add
I'll show you a little of that again let's just keep that in the back of your mind one little
Reality though
Is the button option do not work here
If you want it to work
You must manually code it
So best
Remove it
OK
So I'm not gonna need all of these above values
Because I'm gonna
Well you know what
Let me leave
This one
And maybe yeah
Remove the rest
Just to show you how it works
You can remove this I'm gonna leave Prime now you see that there is this
PH type PHP
Every one of these values represent a line in the code
And this value here is what's gonna show you in the interphase what the code is for
So
Basically you need to update this area for your new implementation
Now
All the options available because obviously you might wanna have different areas for different code
Right
So
Let me show you how the code gets taken into the compiler
Just before we do that all of this actually ends up in the value called type PHP
Ok even 19 all of these values
It gets It's basically like 4 lines 5 - 6 you need to add each line
On its own number
You can't
Have a just like this you can't do that now multiple lines this area only takes one line
at a time
That was unfortunately how we ended up doing it it's not a problem though because
Lot of room here
You can add as many lines as you like
Ok
So
Before we continue with this area let me go show you what is available because obviously
Like I said this is one position
So that show you that
JCB now has a new value called PHP field array
The first option is the one
Which we'd looked at already
This basically
Is
Referring
To let me show you
to
Type PHP this value here because it doesn't add anything value a means type
PHP a
So this value
Represents that value
And so it goes on all the way to n and then x so there's also a
X
PHP type
So you have basically 16 fields
Input Fields available in your custom field area
You could target the normal basic default one which Now looks like this right you
Saw that 1 and 2 and 3 and 4 or you can add a second
Value
Make it a
And then you have one
Sorry
One and two and three and four and as many as you need lines so you have a PHPa
phpb c, els all the way and that's all the available
Placements
Now I'm gonna add 3 so you can see it being demonstrated we couldn't use the First
And then these two you could use any
There's no real it's just what is available at the moment I thought 16 is way more than that we need but
Ok
Let's say we want to Target
just 3 areas in
This
Because we gotta overwrite
Certain methods
And
Maybe
This
This this value
This value
Is being done dynamically by
No sorry not this value
This value
and the
Obviously what is being extended
Is being done dynamically
So that means you only need to Target this either this
Area
Or this area
OK
That's that's the areas you you might want to Target
Ok
So
Now
You can use these various
Values to Target those various areas
And to show you exactly how that will work out let me demonstrate it to you in the interface
So first of all I'm gonna choose this this
Type
PHP
To overwrite the
Method to get the field options
So
I want to actually add the comment to that so I'm gonna start by replacing
That with a comment
Beginning of the comment
Second one
I'm copy pasting this
So you
Just the second one
Then I want a little space there
So
just paste that in there
And then the next comment line
Which is basically the
Return value
then
The next one is
I'm gonna add this
Basically copy this from Joomla
I'm leaving that there just for
my own understanding
And then close the comment area
And then open the method which is a protected method
Get Options
Now
I don't think I want to have this protective
I'm gonna make this public and if if you
Public at the moment
And that is because I like I explain in the previous tutorial of custom fields
This function
This method is being called
To populate
Many selections  across JCB
Now I see that the new list method since Joomla 3 we look at that
Since Joomla 3.7 it has this
Class called get underscore get a magic class to actually get the
Options
And
I should actually update JCB to Target this this method instead
And then
That will be the
Better way to go about this
But at the moment it doesn't do that
And so
It's just best
To just make this
Public for now ok
So I'm making it public
Then
I am
Adding the opening brace for the method
For now please cause I'm just demonstrating this
I'm gonna add a little
Comment
Inside of the method
And then I'm just going to close the method
And remove
All other
Lines so basically have 10 lines
Now to make sure that this is what shows up in the UI  I'm gonna replace all these
Notes
With the
Same
Needs to be the same for this
For this
Collection of code
So we have our first collection or method then set
Now the second one
Before I continue because I know
Something can go wrong here
So I'm gonna save save as copy we opened the custom field to start with
I'm gonna call this
My
Own
Cust
custom list field
OK
And maybe
just paste that in here as well
And save as copy
So now I have a new
Field type called list@mine
And
Basically has these values
Including
This
Now
I can
Over here
Add a placeholder 123
Come_
component
This is a place holder
Which whatever value the user puts in here
Will be updating
This place holder over here so I'm just gonna do that just to show you how that happens
And I'm also gonna explain to you where this comes from and how you can
Expand on this
Ok so
Now we wanna do a
Second one
And
We gonna call this
Type
Must be type PHP always
Then a
Underscore
One because this is the first line of that
So again I'll start by it is opening the comment
and add a few lines here I'm going to need a few of them
And then I'm gonna
Add the next comment line
And you see that every time I'm
Also adding the tab space here
Because I want this to look you know like it was coded
So I'm adding the 10 of spaces in
And
Adding these comment lines first
Hey now we gonna oh
Close the comments
And
Now I'm going to open the
Method
It's phrase
I want it to
Get the parent HTML as well so I'm just putting a little note there
And then grabbing the parent HTML
And then another note that sort of tells
Everyone using this type
That they can now expand
With their own code
And then I'm going to leave a blank one
Which is just
For them easy to start typing and then
I'm going to close the method
Now I need to go up here
I have to copy this
Type A
Make it 2
4 a course you need to do all this just once
And then this type is reusable
So you could after you have done this
You can reuse this type over and over so you need to think generic need to think
Don't make it to type specific if you do you're gonna have to
make many
I tried to make things that easily can be reused
so that's sort of a little
Caution ahead of time because I know that
some of field type you want to make it for a specific project
Well think about the option of the
Making it to be reusable
in
Multiple projects
Ok so I'm gonna use that first comment line to
Just
Give us
just wait
Iet's make it
More than
That first line
Including the 2nd
Like that
I'm gonna use that as the
The identifying note
It needs to all be the same for this
PHP A
Code group
You could do a PHP.... B....,C as I showed you earlier there is
Basically
Wait wait
Basically all these available BCD and you basically just need to
Add it in front of this PHP type
A and so forth don't exceed those that are available at this point If you want to see
What is available you go to the Joomla Component helper class this is the Joomla Component
Helper class
And in it we have a add a PHP fields allowed
So I'm gonna just do this too, I mean you get the point we got
The first one which is the basic default and then A
And you wanna set this values adjustable
And mandatory
Obviously is not translatable so we can just make this to be adjustable
You make it mandatory it might not come out right
So just leave that unticked
unadjustable
Ok
Save and close
If we now go to a field
And we create a new field
And we will see if we're go around to list there's now list@mine
It loads that
Settings that we've sent
And it loads to areas
you see methods to get the input markup for a generic list ,that's the comment
And here is the code
Ready for you to just start typing in that specific
Part if you want to change this area here
And here again is the one for the other
The get options
Again it also starts with that
So
I'm going to add this place holder just in here as well just for demonstration
I'm not gonna add any code I mean you need to know how to do that you need to know how to add that code
Otherwise just go back to the basic default
Custom
Field option it has an amazing ability already so this I'm gonna
Leave it my list simply makes sense I'm gonna also make this my list
And here I'm just gonna say
A
Label
And I'm gonna leave the rest just default
And save as
Need to add this at
Top here
Also set the database value let's make it Varchar
No
Whatever is making sense with the values that your gonna return from your get options right that's what you
And then save and close and you got your field
Which basically is build on the
list@mine
And now you can add it to a Admin View
quite easily I'm just gonna dump it to the demo Admin View
Let's put it left
In the
Details area make it number 1
Get a
a label shows you the field type that is extended and I think that's enough
Let's save and close
And let's compile
See what happens
Before we do
I wanna now go and show you the whole bit of what happens in the compiler
So that you can understand
Some of that Dynamic placeholder concept I've being
Pointing at
So over here
if I go up there's a method here in the
JCB 2.9.3
Call set custom field type file
And it has a replace array
The replace array
Gets the table value if it's set
If it's not set it's an empty value
And it also gets
The component value
And add to it too
com underscore
component
And
Checks if it's there in makes it safe and everything
And then it has the component, an uppercase views and view plural and
And these are all replacement placeholders
That when we start here at the bottom
We start loading the code we are actually using
The replace
Value
to
Actually update the PHP
So all those place holders dynamically get updated
And as you can see
We start the
The PHP type
And we are loading it
One upon another
And again add it eventually to a placeholder and it's maybe not necessary  to explain all this but
Basically it is building
The values for the file and is adding it there
So let's let's see how that file came out
So I'm just gonna compile it here
And then
Install it
And then this quickly go to demo
Looks
new
and it says there
Label
I have a problem here
Of course if we can open that
We have a few things to
fix so there is our field area there is my list to custom field
So we see if we bring in the list class
It's extending the list calling it my list
Your options don't return anything
It's updated to demo component
See there
And here also your input we didn't even return
HTML That's what we should have done
So this should...
Remember to return the HTML we're gonna save this we can go back to JCB and just
Make some change to that we can see it all happen
And here if we refresh this now
Will see that there is
HTML for that area
Now let's tweak it a bit
I said I was gonna go and do much of that but just so that you can
Get the hang of it I'm gonna go back to the actual field types going here
And just make a little fix to my field type because I realised I need to
Help others do this right
Gonna add
two more fields
I'm gonna just
Name them here
16 and they make this 17
I'm also gonna do so I add it
Basically remember HTML I've added those I'm also gonna do something like that in
The first one
and add also three more Fields here
1 just a little extra
Space
Other
Remember the return options and then here just
Return options I think I should add a little thing
Here
So now we have
Options Array, Build Options our little comment
And we need to add a few these 10
11 12
Ok now also just
Move this comment to all of them
I know this is tedious but this is really
at the end of the day not that big of an issue
just to add this little things
So here we go we've expanded it a bit made it more user friendly
and save and close
Now let's go back to that field
Add a label
And I'm going to
I'm going to click away from it
Click like this one and then save it
And then take it back
To that one
Change a
Few things here
again
Just leave all defaults now you see it loaded
The new improvements
And also here
So I'm just gonna
for our purpose say
We need to build the options of course in a specific way
And that's the code that you should know how to write but
I am going to add a little bit
Of
Custom script here just little
Just option 1 and option 2
This obviously you can get these values from anywhere but you need to load it into options
With their J HTML
Underscore select option
implementation
So that it loads everything correctly
And then return
here I'm not gonna make a change just maybe let me just do something for the fun
of it
and add a little text here
OK this should work
So I'm basically added a little space
And then
That little bit of text
To the input value
You can
Do whole lot of things here if you
What you doing
And let's compile and see how it looks
So now if we refresh that we have option 1 option 2
And here's our text "Hi there", that's how easy it is now to expand custom-ally
Any type of field this is helpful if you have any questions
Please ask it on the Forum and
Though
Just
Quickly to show you the file
That's how it came out of the file
So again you got your
extending the list
Because you left at value
over here
let's just look at that
You left this value over here to be list
you must always leave this extends
This is a must value
So the app value and this and of course
The type
The name these are the values that you need to keep there
Because if you want to
Take it out
In the
let me just go there
This get fields
You'll see
That we are testing whether the extent value exists
And
Then
We are coming down here and we testing this
own custom is what that at triggers this value to exist
If you by accident leave the button there will leave you a note that the button is not supported in this area
And
Then we basically
The type
Is determined
By
Custom
that's not important
over here you see we used the extends value
To update this
To place holders
These two place holders
Are what is used
To to populate
This value here
And that's value there
If you if you mess up with this extends value
It will mess up these two values
So you can see that it here it extends the J form field extends
What you put in list radio in whatever of these
Field types you gonna extend
Need to make sure that this is the correct value that you add as an extensive value
And then the PHP gets added here in the type PHP
There is a type,the  type is the name
sorry no
It is this value of here
This type value
That also must be there so it's the name value the type value
of course depending on what type of field you're extending
Then you have a few these
And then
This extends value
Is a must
This Prime PHP still functions just like it would in a normal custom field you can read it here
You could leave that in or leave it out depending on yourself if you left it in it all function
The same way as in the custom field
So the place holders that you can add here
We have component
Looking at our code in the compiler
Just go there
Is again
We have the text and we have the ID
And we have the code text and code
And the view type and type
And yeah these are the place holders now they correlate to the custom field
so
If you start
Close out here
Go back to field types
If you start
With a custom field
Opening the custom of field
You'll see
That we have
Down here
Table
Component
We have
Field value field
So if we look at this
There is
The value field and the key field
these two is the name and the ID
So the value field and the key field
These two values you need to leave them like that because then
They will generate these placeholders see text
And ID
So if we look at the code
We see there is a
Text and ID value
And they correspond to whatever the user puts in these
values
So that's the field type you might wanna leave these placeholders in there
And as well as the component and the table
These view values are also useful but
They're not really particularly practical when it comes to extending your own custom field
But
Like I said you can come in here look at the code
Make changes run it and here you could do the var
dump
But that and then just grab the replace array
Like that
And safe then compile your custom field wherever you implemented it
And
Your own custom field
Then check
All these Place holders
These place holders the B
And D place holders basically referred to those brackets
And the placeholder that you see these
And this
Basic refers to the
hhh
these hashes there
So if you dump this replace array you'll see the available Place holders
That you could use in your code dynamically updating values based on those placeholders
If you didn't follow what I've explained then maybe it's just best you don't even worry about that
It can work without you using placeholders so you can just dump these so I would always say start with your
default custom
Field type and then save as copy give it a
@mine or whatever you want
Save as copy and then start expanding on it
And changing it changing this , you see these codes
Changing whatever it says here
But do insure
to add the @ if you don't you just did this you gonna break stuff
Because custom is already there and the
You wanna make sure that JCB knows this is your own thing so that @
Is important
And I think that should be it