We want to do a quick demonstration of how to build a little bit more advanced
List View
the type that you would find in sermon distributor
this list view is comprised of templates and layouts
And various
Integrations so let me
Take one of them and change them
to
Yeah to be our example
So first of all
we've just looking at the site views already there so there's Sermon Preachers, Preacher series's
Categories category
And an API
So
I think we'll use this
preacher
Because it is a
List query
So let's go look at its Dynamic get
Now
There are two ways for us to build
a
List of items in a site View
Before I go into the dynamic get
I need to just
Show you the difference here
The one way
Which I prefer
Is the Ajax Way
Because I can load up to 10000
rows
Or items
The page
Where is the normal way and that's the dynamic Get way
Can only load
Quite
Yeah let's say
In a way that is
Not too slow
About 100 items per page and so you basically need to use pagination
If you don't use pagination
It takes very long for the page to load if it's more than 100 items
If you wanna load more than 100 items I suggest you go the Ajax Way
Ajax I'm using footable plugin
And it is
Yeah I assure there's other ways to do it
like most things
It's the thing I
The plugin that I have been using for many years now and it's always
been improving the developers are constantly improving it
And if we If we open this
This URL here
let me open that
I'm going to refresh the page
To give you a full idea of what we're talking about
So going to refresh it
Now scroll down here is the example we count 1234 and there we go it's now
in that moment we waited it loaded 10000
Rows which is a 1000
Pages so if I click here to go to the very last one you see it's 10000
Items and I mean it was very quick in loading those items into this table
Why I like
FooTable so much is if you
Now resize your screen here
it will automatically
Load those items like this and I know there is such library also in
Joomla
I realize that
And
Are you welcome to use any of those I just like this
Components approach
Look at our little JavaScript you need
On the page
To basically need a URL
To the column headers which are basically these values
And
Then you need a URL to get the Json
That's the only HTML you need on the page
And that's as simple it is to load 10000
Items like that in a table
It has interesting
Opportunity even with regarding to editing if I scroll down here
Here
It has editing rows
Option here
And the editing rows option
Gives you option to add new rows
And edit existing rows
I mean this is crazy load a 10000 size
Table of 10000 items and then edit any of them I really think this plugin and it is a amazing
Tool
And I'm not even that good with JavaScript
and I can manage this, so I'm sure all of you would be able to do the same
I'm not gonna demonstrate
This now I don't have time it's a little bit more complicated I suppose
Because I need to show you how to build
These
And maybe we can look at that but I'm first going to
To look at
This normal
Implementation that uses Dynamic get because in any case usually if I'm going
This way
I first build something here and then move it there that's how I do it but that's just me
Let JCB write some of the code for me and I move it to the a to the Ajax basically
backend
Ok
So
Back to our component
We have
a few dynamic gets here already
All of them
are list queries
So
That means
They are able to get more than one item from the database now
The request was made to get all the sermons and not have a filter
Which is quite easy I'm gonna use this one
And I'm gonna just change this to
To all
Then
I'm going to the tweak
And I'm going to
Just remove that one option
I'm gonna leave the access level
You know what
That's just good practice you have access levels in your tables and
The user isn't supposed to access an item it's always good to
not allow them if you don't want any filter you simply remove this
This
And you can even remove the ordering
and it will work ok
So
That is all you need to do to get all of the sermons from the table
I am going to
Just
Remove this one for my purpose we can look at the joint options and they seem ok
Leave them that way
And then the custom scripting
What I'm doing here
With a custom scripting
I'm basically setting up links links to the series links to the categories
Links to the actual sermon
Links to the series
And
Basically first create a Slug
And then
This helper route
Get sermon route
Get series route and get category route Is a helper class which
Is common in Joomla for your router now I'll show you how where to find this class
So if we go to
The
Front-end not the administrative area but the front end and we go down to sermons
Are we go to helpers no not helpers
Yeah it is actually helpers we going to helpers then we see there is a file called route
So we open that
And that is where you find the
Route helper class
So in our code
I have used this placeholder option
Which dynamically add the word sermon distributor
To helper route
And that's simply were
Where it builds this class name
How does class is loaded into the component dynamically so you don't need to do it again
And it's doing it here
You see there is registering the class
In the main
PHP file of the component
So now in this class we have some static functions get Sermon route
Get preacher route get preachers plural and preacher
Singular
And categories and category
And
Series list
And series
And
API
And that's about it
So that's where I get the names if I am going to Target any of these areas
I'm coming in here and I can see how it's building it basically just
Building the link right it's grabbing the necessary string
With the right option the right View
Adding the ID then we have a little function here find item
Which is in the same class you can search for it it's way at the bottom
Just give it a little space there
and what this does and I mean if any of you feel you can do this better please make a pull request
Let me know
It's trying to find where this item
Which we're building this link is maybe linked to a menu
So that we can append
The menu ID
To the item
And doing that get the correct URL
Ok so that's what that's all about and then like I said we get the ID
We dump it in here we add the item ID to the link and we return the link
Now
Back in the
Code here
We add just one little tweak and this is this route
Jroute which converts that long URL to whatever the system
Setting is currently in regards to your search engine optimisation so that's what this
String here
Is all about it is basically creating links based on The Slug
Now The Slug is a concept which takes the Alias is of an item and it's ID
Combines it with his double
With this colon between it
So that
You can use it in your search engine optimisation router ok
So that's what this custom code here is about to we don't need to change this that's what's all this issue here
Your filtering doesn't affect this whatever you grab you want these links on the page
So you could click to those areas right you want to have it ready to use
And then here's little tweak we made for the router
To identify the correct Elias
So we want to get the correct Elias in relation to
These different areas
So in this one we going to be in the Sermon we would be doing sermons here
So we could
Change this
S View
to
Sermon
Like that
Because we know
Oh wait a minute we don't we will be looking at a list of sermons
Ok so that case
We not gonna be able to very effectively build a Elias
Because at the moment it used to be them the preachers name so that that would have been
Preacher in here this place holder would have been replaced with preacher now because we're not
going to be filtering by preacher or category we gonna end up having to just
Use the ID because there is
No identity if I could say there's no way to link the page to a specific identity
So what I would usually do in that case
I would just
Turn this off and see what is the default behaviour
What comes out ok
So let's walk through that and see how that works out for us
Ok so now we just gonna save as copy
That's we we gonna do leave the Pagination on because like I said you want to be able to return
Only at most 100 items per page
So save as copy
And close
So now we have a new
List query called sermons all
And it is ready to be used
And it basically only filters by access this is what I want and
That should do that should do it
Now let's go to our site views
We basically took this item
And
We changed it
Get That's what we did
Wait no not this one
This one
Because
You see it has
A Preacher ID but it's actually having a list query for the sermons
And then it has
A bunch of custom gets to get the number of downloads the number of sermons and the actual
Preachers information
So we want to change this now this View
To actually just get all the sermons in the system right
The first thing will do is will change this
To this sermon all
Option
And will change this also do that to see how they will look
Basically looks exactly the same you see so that means we don't really need to change anything
Here all of this should still work
Just the way it was
If you want to do your own implementation here
Then you'll need to
Basically use
These values
to build your own implementation
I'm using
A lot of
Uikit
Classes here you see and in these templates this is also what's being
Done so we have many
Different implementations but now you see we have these params in here now
This params brings to us a certain values linked to the preacher page
But we are going to change this this is no longer going to be preacher because it can't have the
Same codes name of as another page
So we'll have to change this and
We gonna change this to all
Just like that
And change this to all so everywhere where we dealing with
params
We need to change the params so we can highlight them
And we need to change that
Because
We are changing this view
We calling it all
Ok
Like that
Now this I'm going to call this sermon
we are working with sermons
So the context is sermon
Because if we check permissions everything you wanna check that against the sermon
Permission structure
So
I'm gonna use sermon there
And everywhere else I'm gonna just change this to all and remember this because we're gonna have
To go add a whole lot of new fields
To this component to have those values ok
So just keep that in mind
We need we need to have this extra switch
For the all display
All
Sermons display all sermons display
Now
Mind you this area shouldn't even be here now
Because we are not going to retrieve a Preacher information
So we taking that out
So we only want you all sermons all sermons
And then let's look at this
I'm thinking you you know I don't wanna get
Too complicated here
So let me change this
Back
It could work if we just leave it the way it was
But no, you know I started going down this way so let me show you what that mean
to add these values in
It's just that in our
Templates sermon table and sermon Grid And sermon list
Were also gonna have to look at some param values
And make some tweaks
So
When we need to take
Take basically copy these
Down somewhere
So we can
We can go look at them so it's that one
sermon list
sermon grid and table
Ok So those are the three areas we need to go look at
So let's do that now
Save as copy before we do it you want to check out some other things
Ok
let's see
We have some colour settings here
This also be changed to all
So we just checking for these params right so we can
Update everything correctly
Now this
Is for hits
We're not gonna need the hits area
Because
When I do targeting a Preacher
So I'm going to take this out
We don't need this
That should be enough
Just check that it's not up here
Basically take that out as well
I had to take that out because it was calling that function hit
Which was
In in this area here
But I took that out because we not getting a Preacher
So since we not getting a Preacher we don't need to increment the hit
Because we not counting anything so that's why I took that out
I'm here I'm doing some fooTable Styles this is still using an old version of fooTable
So
This might be a good time to update this but ok I don't have time now so I'm just gonna fall back
To this for now
Ok
So here Everything looks fine
I'm gonna say save as copy
Close I did I do that already
No that was good ok so now we have a new
Site view
And we need to go look at these templates
So let's go out of here
Go to templates
So the templates we wanna look at it is these three
So it is first one
Sermons table it's this one here let's open that
Ok
So now we'll see that we have again
A whole lot of
Params here
With
Placeholders
Site view site view site view so now we gonna have a problem
No not really because we are using all so this will update to all
Now I have to set this params for sermons
Description sermon preacher series category so all of these
Params which are actually fields
In the configuration of this component I have to update so this
SView will fall back to the view where this
Template is going to be used so that the site view
Which we working with its code name is all
So
It's going to fall back to the word
All
This is what it's going to fall back to
Ok so in that template everywhere you see S view it is
Going to be call all
So if we go to the sermons list same thing here
let's see
This seems fine
Hear this one
It's going to fall back to all
Like that
So
We need to set a value for this and that will then decide what type of
List file
This will have
The same would go for the grid
If we opened preacher
not preacher, sermons grid
Here
We're again seeing
A lot of
Sview.....Sview
Values
All over the place
And it is going to affect
The component if we don't set these
Parameters in the global settings
Then it won't find this but it will fall back to zero
So you'll still work but it won't load anything because zero means nul ok
So it will not load the preacher
Values
And that's why it might look like things are not working because these
Configuration values are not existing yet
We need to create them I'll show you how
I was hoping to skip that but I realize
It's a helpful thing to know how to do that
So
For now first step would be to add this
Site view
So I'm gonna just add a down here
Under before sermon I'm gonna say
All sermons
I'm gonna give it an add menu it has meta
Country that has access and it's public ok so
I'm adding it in there
To the components site views
Save and close so if I compile this now we will
Get that view added to the component and everything should be there so
Let's do that compile it quickly
Ok now I've got it installed
So we go here Sermon distributor
We have all our values here
We have no preachers or sermons or anything created
So we won't have a fully functional front end but if we go to menus
And we would to change our home
to
Sermons all sermons
Save and close
we'll go back to sermons
And options
Then to permissions and we search for
Site
Then we see there is a site
All sermons access and it said to allow but sometimes if you're busy updating
It may not be set to allow so you must change that
for your public
And
Now if we go front end
OK, we have a error account
So let's look at that
That's on
View HTML 5
No ...HTML PHP
48 let's go look at that no sermons were found
So here
Our
line 48 in the sermons
Views all
Line 48 we have a number of sermons now since there is no number in
And the system
It's giving us an error
Let's so let's fix that that shouldn't be that hard to fix
We go back
To our component in Joomla
In the site views
We open all sermons
Go to PHP
And
It's basically
This one here
So what we can do
As we can
do a little
Check here
We say
Something like that we first check is it a array
And if it is then
We count the array because that's how many sermons they are
And we we added here
And then here we can just say
You know
Nul
If there's none
Ok now we actually don't need these values anymore
Because we're not actually
Getting a Preacher ID and preacher ID so I'm gonna remove this as well
From from the component
Because we don't have a Preacher
In this
Return set
So we don't need those values
So I'm taking them out just
For good practice
And then that should then
Get us going
Let's compile it again
and install
Now we have is no sermons were found
We can go back to our component and we can add a few you know values
Ok so I've Now added
a whole lot of sermons
And just
Randomly
Sorted them
We should have enough to work with here
Let's see that's is about
About 400
400 sermons
Ok so now on the front
We gonna diss refresh the front page
And wallah
We now have all of these showing up
And it is all of the sermons
And there is going to that specific sermon
And then this specific
Series
And it's showing us the hits of every sermon
And
We can page to other pages
pagination we can change this to a greater amount
Click the wrong button here
Ok so now we have 100
Yeah so
Our new list is working as we expected
So but we still haven't set
The
The correct
Values here so let me show you what I mean
In our display we have this all sermon table colour
And we have that set here
Then we have also
Some
If we open the
Default page we have this display
And
Yeah
So the first one
Although if it doesn't find one or two it defaults to list
So we don't have these values where are these values found
They are found in the components
Config
So if I go to the member of the administrative area
And I open the config.xml
Then those values should be in this file
This file
If we scroll down
We will see there sermon default icon
Box scroll down scroll down
Here's the preacher remember preacher display we change that to all display and
list style
Now so we see the Preacher's values are here
How did it get here
In component Builder
If I go back to component builder
There is an area called component config
If you open that
You'll find a whole lot of fields here
And
It's got tab names that bundle them so the series bundles all these
Values
So we'll have to
Go up all the way here
Two preachers
Actually preacher singular this one
And we'll have to go create each of these Fields except
These
Menu this one will have to do
This we won't
Because we not getting the preacher right so we just need to get the values that are related to the sermon
Layout
So it's from here
Basically from these values. We will need the
Will need to get it from after the spacer
Table grid list style colour icon description
Series
Category
Sermon counter
Hits
Downloads and a switch sermon preacher open so these are the
Fields we'll have to go and recreate
For the all view
So we can copy switch sermons
fords
Bracket preacher
And weekend
Search for this in the field area
Basically this string
just to be the same
As the one you see there
So we're going to fields
And we type in that string and search
And so here are all those values that we need to also create
So there are two ways to do this one is I can just copy them all
With this batch
Option
or the other is to do them one at a time
So I'm gonna do them
Just let's just do at least one
So I need to change a few values here I need to change this to all
I need to change that to all
And
This as well all
All
Table grid list
the default is grid
That's 2
Ok so that is the first one I'm gonna save as copy
And then
Close
Now the second one
And So It Goes On
I need to
Convert these fields
For the all view
We can leave this to be sermons
Set if sermon hits to be shown should be staying that's right that's right this would be all hits that
And then
Save as copy
Close
Now description
All
Show sermon description
This would be fine fine that must be all
we change that to
all
Save as copy
I think that's more than enough
Now we go back to the component and to the config area
And then underneath
The
I think I'm gonna do it here
Before sermon
Right here
Just add a few
Fields
So it should be marked as Global we gonna change this to all
All
And then
We'll just search for it
I will use the
The grid
And the hits
And the description I'm just gonna do those 3
So we are doing that for all
The table the hits the description
Save and close
And can compile and install
Now when we opened sermon distributor backend we go to options
We'll now I have a new tab you're called all
And we can change this to table grid or List.  It is already on list so let's let's change it
to table
Let's say don't show hits and don't show description
And save
This value
So it is loading it correctly now
As a table
Now let's make another change here
let's
Let's say show hits and show description and let's make it a grid and save
Now we refresh it
And there we go
We have it all now in gridlayout
Now it's again
Just giving us
The last hundred
And we can
paginate through them
Correctly
So it's it's falling Back To The Way It Used To Work except that it doesn't show the
actual
It's not
Filtering it by preacher it just grabbing all of the values
Ok I think that's all for now
To show you how to
Load a a list of values
in JCB
With pagination without any filter like
For example preacher
Ok well thanks for watching