I'd like to explain a
New feature or
An old feature that is
been revived
Somehow
In JCB. The feature is now visible
On many of the
The pages
It's called
Run expansion
Now
I realize that
When you would click on this at the moment
It'll give you an error
And it will tell you the expansion failed
Please check your settings
in the Global options
Of JCB under the development tab
So you need to basically open these
Global options
And under the development tab
You need to read
Some of this
Instructions
So
Development method tab has
Now there's new switch called expansion
And here is basically the documentation on what expansion is all about
Really what has happened in my developing experience
Is that
We build
Multiple components that have a relationship with each other
Share classes
Share code
And files and
While you busy working on those components
You need to
often times
Basically compile and install them
To test whether Things have broken or everything still stable and so forth
So
That's what I use the expansion method primarily for but
There is a future application of the expansion method
Which is not yet been fully realized
And
When we are able to bring
All of that to the
To the to the community then I'll make
another tutorial in explaining
There you know the expansion of expansion
Might be too much but
For now the expansion method is primarily an option
Of selecting multiple components you can see here
You can select
Multiple
Components
And
Then have them compiled and installed
At once
And quite
Rapidly actually
So you could
You could say ok I want all of these
Components
To be moved
To The Back-up folder
And
To repository
Folder
And
Show The custom placeholder
And give me a message
Not just that it was successful but
Everything which was done
You could have this run on a cron job
Which means
It keeps on running in the background
Always compiling and installing this over and over and over and
That is part of
If we If our feature purpose or plans come to pass
Then you would see why this
Was actually
Necessary
So this point is maybe in doesn't make
That much of sense but for
The previous implementation which is what you see here
Is to basically just
Install and compile
Multiple
Different
Components select the same
Different components
So we would do this it's gonna ask that
Ok there we go save and
Close
So now we have our expansion components selected
If I now click run expansion
It says access denied
And
That is because
The expansion works through the API
There is a
well slowly we are busy developing an API for JCB
It's not fully there yet but
You know we were busy with it and in the API
We need to actually
Have a user selected that has
Enough permission
to actually compile and install components
So you need to select
A user that has that
Level of permission
I ask the API user used during the execution
Of the
Expansion
Method
Ok so let's try again
If we now
Do that
If you think about how long it would have taken to install
Compile and install compile and it's
install compile install
Each of those
Components
Individually
And
The time that it now
Took to compile it and in
Install it
There is a
Somewhat of a difference
And the fact that it doesn't give you the option to download the package
it immediately after compiling it
Actually installs it and removes it from the temporary
folder so you can see
it tells you that all of that
It's been done for
This component
For that one and so forth all the way down here
So all these components now who compiled and installed
Right into the system in that moment
And that's really at the moment
What the expansion method is primarily used for
like I said we have
Some
Future plans with this preacher
When it comes to integrator developing
Concepts where we as teams work together
Then there is the possibility that
We could
Use this feature
Even further
Ok so that is the expansion method hope this makes
Sense
I mean if you don't like it or you don't
See the need for a it
Just ignore it
Even if you did set it
To use the expansion method It only means that your expansion buttons
Will function when you click them
By Default
JCB ships with the expansion method
On
In inactive
So that if someone clicks here by accident
It will tell you that the expansion method is disabled and it you should actually
Enable it for it to work
And I mean that also makes sense right because
You don't want the expansion method to trigger Without You Knowing why and what it's doing.
Ok well thanks for watching
Until next time.