Ok I would like to
Give you a quick demonstration
on how to add a form to a site View
Now
Before I do that
I just again want to remind you that the best practice here
Is the use an admin view as a site view
The reason that is the best practice is because it is the Joomla way of doing it
So that means
If you
Actually want
A view
Or form if we say form
It means in the area where you submit data to be
stored with Database
If you want that the way to do that is to
Add create site view edit create site view for this
Admin View
So you just tick this box here
And it immediately adds it as you know an admin View
It moves it into a site view which you can access from the front of the site
This is the way that the of the code structure and the way that it's implemented is this
Standard way of doing it
Now
The the way to access that edit area you need to actually in your site view
In the I'm going to look here at looks you have to actually add a edit link
now this edit link
Is something that you need to build
It's not being built for you
Now I'm building this edit link if you have the demo component in the main get
Looks
Query I'm building it inside of it
Now we can quickly look at how I'm building it
By going to your Dynamic gets
An opening the looks
And will see that there is this place where I'm first getting the actions
And then I am checking whether there is a edital permission for this specific
user
And it true I actually built the link here
I'm using
J route
I'm adding a
Task
And we are setting up the link here and it's it's a little
little link
That's being built
a link
so and if if the user doesn't have permission it's just an empty string
Ok so that's where we build
The link
now you can build it anywhere but I like separating
The modelling
Of the data from The View
It just helps me sort of know ok well this is to
Do with the model
I'm sitting all that up
In there
And I know we started seeping in HTML and it's a little bit boundary but
Ok
Point taken
The reality is we
We've achieving  it
This way at the moment
Ok so now
You you come this far you've seen this you say no I still want to add my own site form
And
Well there are two ways to do this
The one is if you go into your site view
This area here
If you have pagination
Already is a form
So
Let's let's let's show you that
So I'm gonna open looks again
I'm gonna show you here is says list of looks
Ok it's a caption
And you see that there is no
I have added no form values here
Where is the look
Query
If we quickly opened that again
Has pagination
Set to yes
And that's
Why it adds a form
Even though
In here we don't have any button set
We have pagination set so if if compiled
The code that will be generated will look as follow
There is our caption and our demo list all looks
There's the form
So it's got a form
It's got a name
It has an ID and if you scroll down it doesn't have a task so you can grab submission of the
This form
And add your task to directed to the correct route
And function
It already has a form token
And there is the end of the form so you could simply add a button in here
And actually submit a form
You don't need to add a form again there is already a form
And it is already publishing or posting as in its action
To this component
It is a post for
So you could
Yeah
Actually just Add the trigger if you like
And then obviously some JavaScript
That when you trigger the button
It grabs the form does some validation whatever you want
And then adds the task incorrectly and based on the button that's clicked so you could add multiple
areas
Bind them with IDs and so forth so that would be the one way of doing this
And
That's practical because then your whole
Default View area becomes a place of setting up input values and so forth and you just
End here at the bottom
With a button
Now that button
Could
Just as well
Be a button that you build here
So you could have
JCB
Control
The
Setup of your controller
As well as the setup of your model
With this buttons
So you could say yes I want to add a button
And you can call it submit
You can give it a different icon
maybe let's say
Maybe that
Then you can give the the target controller method
A name so you could say
Save
Save my
Stuff
Like that
You can say that
How does this where does this button show up
And then what type of button is this
And I would leave all that
Just like that and then I would use this
Custom
Option
Copy
And I'll just paste this here at the bottom like that
Now add my button in the form
Because it's already form
So this button will now be in the form
And it will actually have what's needed
To trigger
This controller
Here it our controller
We need to of course
And our function
So you have a little controller method
And
You have to
And in the little token validation
Get the application get the model
you know get the form values
Get the input
Check the task
And then you start going down the list
Now I just copied this from another project so you need to update
These sort of values
To be
Related to this
Area that you're doing
And
Then
Because we
Want to have the option of
you know get the form
Do all kinds of
Neat things
This is part of what you need to know and if you don't know how to do this
I wouldn't suggest you
Doing it because I will just
Make your
Application
vulnerable
To attack their there needs to be a lot of validation here
And so here
We actually do a model validation on the
Formdata
This is quite important
you need to know how to build a form
If you
If you gonna use this form validation class
So
It goes onto
Eventually
Saving the data
If something goes wrong we store the data into the user State so that can be placed back into
the form you know that kind of
Behaviour
and down here if in everything is good we submit the application
Again a method that we build in the
Model
So this this is a function a method from the model
And even there something goes wrong we grab those errors we
Push them out to the user we can also save
We go on and a few things is on this point everything is good we say great
Would be done right
And we clear the user state and we redirect wherever we want to go
And we clear the application from the
Session and we return true so you can
Slowly go through this may pause the video
Whatever you need to do
But this is just
Actually generic
Implementation on the submission of a form
And how it's controller usually would look like so
That's really what this is it's not
That advanced in fact
There might be a many improvements on this to make
and even more
You know depending on what you need is
Now in the model
You'll need to add a few methods
Of course which you are calling from your controller right because here
you're actually using the model
To validate
You using the model
To get the form
You using the model you see that sort of the MVC structure you you separating
What happens where which code decides where
And so here you are getting the model through the controller methods
itself
Ok so you'll have to add the the the custom script into the model there's
no automation for this you'll have to custom script this
Ok again I just
Punch the data over from my other project in
Here
Basically copy pasted it
Just because I wanted demonstrate this quickly
I had a little function that I build you to sort of get the form because this this
Actual site view submission is a dynamically generated
A form so the form isn't a static XML
It is dynamically generated through this little function
And I actually end up building a static XML but I build it through
Yeah various methods
But that's part of
Well I would say your own homework
You need to figure out how to do this
I don't want to because
You know there's some things if you haven't going through the process of seeing how and why
you're always gonna be unsure of why why these things work the way they do and so I wanna save you from that
I want to
Encourage you to really go and see why
Why is should this happen this way
There's a little sort of cheat to this I know
And that is
The compiler component JCB that has a compiler
View
And we've made that public
And in the compiler view
We build a form
And we display a form in a admin custom admin View
Custom admin view is very similar to a site view
It's a little bit more limited
But site views have more power in my opinion
But it's gives you the site view functionality of
you know maneuver and making your own thing happen
In the backend
Ok so that was the purpose of the custom admin view
So here
All I've done
Is I've created a button
I've created a controller
I've set up some methods in the model
And at the end of the day
Now I have placed the button which is really the key and I need to now to
Add a form here
This needs to be replaced with a form which is going to be submitted
With this button I'm not gonna do that
I trust you can do that yourself
I'm gonna just save this and compile it
So you can see
The
The code
Well well when it comes out
With that button then
Place
So here we have it
The form is still
Intact and here is our button
Basically renders the toolbar
So you might wanna see ok well where is this happening
Well it's happening in the view.HTML file
so you'll come down here and you'd see it says
Add toolbar
And it's a
Local
Method so we could scroll down
And see o here's the add toolbar
And here
It is
Setting up the custom button
Look
Save my stuff
Add box
Is the icon there is the button name
And it adds it
It also if there is a helper
A helper menu added to this
Area
You also add the helper URL as a button
And then it adds this whole
Joomla
Toolbar
Get instance to the toolbar
Because you're it loads it then registers a lot of stuff
And then
throws it in here
And basically That's what we rendering here
That's how we get the button
To work alongside all the controllers stuff
Now if you go to the code the open the controller file
Then
You'll see that there is now a new file called looks
Which wasn't there before
So JCB just because of using its own buttons
Added your controller for you
And also if you do that with opening
The the models
There is the 4 the looks model
So we first open here we scroll down and low and behold
There is our
Method
Save my stuff
And there is everything we coded right into the model
So you actually have allow edit
Available here
Ok but
Ok so this is been deactivated to all
to false I see
Yeah
So it's a security measure
to
Allow no tampering
You need to validate everything in your
Function here
Now if you go to the looks model
You'll see that it also
Updated it with our
Get form
And so everything is been placed into the code
From the interface
So
if you look here in the
Interface
It'd It'd added the
The necessary code
in the correct place
Now you could do all this
Without using our buttons
You don't need to use this button
I mean you could dump that and still just use it to setup your controller and your model information
You don't need to use the buttons
The button is just a little cheat in my opinion for you to save a little bit of
Well to ride on the back of
The actual
J
Toolbar helper class
Ok
So you could hand code your button in here
And do your own JavaScript
And so forth
So this is the first way
Or the
The one way of doing it
Is to actually think of this whole area
As a form
Now there's another way to do this
And this is the way which I think will work ideally for let say a search form
or something like that
And that is to actually do it
A little bit of
Workaround way
In the PHP tab in the custom view script this is the custom
View script area so if you open this
It says the PHP script that must run in the head of the file
So I'm gonna add a little
We are here do this
And save and close
And then compile this and let's go look at the code where that comes out
Ok so the code
Where we here
So we are here
That's where it comes out
So it's above
The existing form
And so
We could
Break out of this
PHP area
We could decide Ok we wanna add a new form but we wanna add it on top of this
So we could
You know end that PHP
Do our form
And then at the end
Just open the PHP again
Because that we have you can't remove this tag this is added by JCB
What you could do though you could now over here
Do some HTML
Sorry PHP
Details you know
Whatever you like
And so this is the code that you would now add into JCB so we'll take this just
To show you
And save here and and go back to JCB
Open the looks area
Then replace our we are here
With
Our Little Form
And save
So that will now effectively
Place this form outside of the other form
Above your content
Now you need to ensure that it's name is different
And it's ID
And you can still use the buttons
To manage your controller and model
And then
Rename this accordingly
So that the task actually fits
The controller and
Function
I which is really what is necessary with this area here
Or you could even
Add the toolbar here
And obviously setup your button
And then you are toolbar will actually
Show up here
Because it's a custom
Placeholder
So that would be another way
To get the button into this form
And then obviously you won't be using it
Here as well it will
break things
But if you add it in here it should work
Ok so then
That is how you could set up your form
You could save and then we can compile this
and install
then looking at the code we have
So looking at the code
When now have the form here with the rendering of the toolbar as we expected
And
That's really
As easy as he is to add a form
to site view
You of course now I need to take care of sanitation take care of where these data goes and what the model does
With it and how it should return and what it should return
And all of that is now basically what needs to be done in the controller and in the model
Of this
Forms
Receiving end
Oh well I trust that this would really help your on your way and adding forms to site view
It's really easy
I'm I've done it many times
Because of
Various reasons people want to have
Registration forms or they want to have a valuation forms
And they want that data split up in
Save to different tables and
Used in different ways
So there is often the need to
To do this
There's just a little side note that I wanna make before I actually close up this
And it's by going to component builder itself
In the admin area
And then opening its own
Custom View
admin View
This
Compiler I spoke about it earlier
But I want to give you a little bit of a
Heads up on how to build a form the right way
So in every form you have what is called attributes
Sorry never form field
Now
The attributes themselves
are
What type of field it should be what should be the name what should be the
Label what should be the class description all these kind of things and it depends on what type of field you build
On whether it will have options and so forth
Now
JCB has what we call a field
Get field object
Method
Which is by Default part of a helper class
Now the get field helper method
Takes attributes it takes the default value which could be the saved value that you've
grabbed from the database and it takes the options if there is options
And then it actually builds
The
Field for you
In the Joomla correct conventional way if you wanna I don't have that's right way of saying it but
Does it the right way
And uses the
It's  jform helper
Class it loads the field Type by getting it from the attributes
The type and obviously if it's not been set it will return false so it wants the type in your attributes
Then
There is a simple XML field being created here then there is a XML
Attributes
Method which you could also look at
This is it which then adds the attributes to the XML
Values
And
Gives it back to our
Well because it's a
What you call it
Reference value this XML
It doesn't need to return it to anything it updated it by reference
Then it also checks whether there's options and if there is option there is also an XML add
Options function
Which adds the options to the XML
And then it takes this
Load field type
And it actually sets up the field
And returns the field as an object
This then again
Gets placed into a form array
In this little method in
You can look at this in the compiler in that .HTML.php file
So we building a whole bunch of
Form fields in an array
Then if we go to the template
We're basically gonna scroll down scroll down
And over here
We see that there's
Form we look the form fields
We add the correct HTML
Surrounding the fields because this is how
you know controller group control label controls
This is how Joomla usually sets up a field
Then we Echo the label and we Echo the output
Sorry the input and then we eventually load the whole form onto the page
Through a more
Yeah A more
Easily readable what's going on here way
And it's still obviously being placed inside of the form because we are assuming that
We are we doing all this
Inside of the form
So there is a better way of building form input values that's all I'm saying and that is to let JCB
You're would rather let
Joomla do it for you
And so the only thing that you need to know about is actually this get field object
Which works quite easily with attributes now
You see that here we have a label
And it already has the
You know
The correct
Language string
And that's also quite easy to do
Now
You all know by now that you can get JCB as a mapped component
In JCB
I don't know if I should demonstrate that to you but
Maybe
Well I don't wanna make this video too long so I'm gonna do it very quickly
So back at JCB I'm gonna simply go to Joomla components and I'm gonna say import JCB
Package
Then I'm gonna go and I'm gonna actually select
component Builder
This one
And I'm gonna get the package
Then I'm gonna Force the local update I'm gonna add the package key which you would have received from us if you followed
The correct path in getting that key if you haven't got it
Just simply click here and do what it tells you and you'll get a key
Then I'll gonna click continue
And basically import the whole JCB mapped in JCB
So we have the component now mapped here I'm gonna quickly go to the customer admin View bear with me we are nearly done
We're gonna open the compiler custom admin view
Go to PHP scroll down
And here you see the method that being used to get that
Language string correctly setup is just text
With these two dots underscore
And that's it
Obviously also
This one here
So that's how you set up a just text
To what JCB then does is it
Take this
String
It's puts it into your language file
And
Just cranks out
The uppercase
Related value
Which is what you want to give to the field when you're being built
You don't want to give it
Yeah
The actual
Jtext response
You wanna give it the upper case
Values because that how it's been given to it from the XML file usually
Ok so this is where you can come and look and how to build your own form
Fields
And then actually easily
Grab them
Onto your
Your custom buttons
and the compiler
Everything and here
Scroll down
You'll see ok so this is where we're echoing it out
So this little cheat sheet if you forget about everything you can come back here and if we find better ways to do
This we'll obviously improve this area and as you can see I'm simply setting up my own little form here
Because this view doesn't have pagination
We don't have any form conflicts with fighting with each other who's the boss or whatever
And we still have our JavaScript up here that deals with our submission
And checks whether everything is fine and cranks out
on whatever it wants
And the way we want it so
All that is here and could be used right into a site view with little bit adaptation
to your application purposes
So as well as the buttons and
And some of the
Compiler
You see because you could still use the the controller
To deal with
Like in this case the compiler
Where you're buttons only we'll only have a button
To clear the temporary folder
Which is also a function there it is
But the buttons aren't being used
for
For this compiler
It's actually being done through the form itself
I say you can look
And how we set up the form to achieve that which is quite simple just make the task
Correct
And then over here in your
JavaScript
We deal with that as well
Ok well thanks for watching that was a quick demonstration
On how to add a form to a site view
With the least resistance
Enjoy