The option to update a form either admin or site
View with a selected given parameters
So that certain fields are
Adapted
Just by
Click of a button
That takes them to the form
Is a
Very valuable feature
And is also available in JCB
I'm gonna demonstrate to you
How to get this done
Before I do though
There are
2 things you need to know
One of them is
that there really is off the shelf
The option
To do this with at least one field
Without having to code anything
So if you have one field
Which is the list
Field
Or
If it's a
Text field
I think there are some limitations
What type of fields could be
Targeted
I haven't actually
Tried them all
But I'm sure that if you run into
Bugs or
limitations and
Open a issue on GitHub
We could fix that so
Just let me know
But to demonstrate the first of the shelf easy implementive
Option
Would be to first take you to the code and show you where all is happening
OK
So I'm gonna compile the demo component and then just go look to
The code here
Ok so now I see the code
Ok so going to demo component model and opening a look model
Which is the editing
View
of that look on the front end of this
component
We gonna scroll down to a place
Called
Why function
Actually
Call get form
Here it starts get form as in the get form function that a lot of things happen
Like validation the access to certain fields
So forth all of that is happening here
Because if the user doesn't have access we don't even need to you know
Do anything so we just dump the field right here
Now
You'll see at the very end of the method there is this only load these value If no ID is found
So that means when a field is for some you know if the
If there is a new look being created from the front
There is no ID
So there is a
Value ref
And ref ID that some of you may be familiar with which basically
Grabs a string
From the ref
And also grabs an integer
And these two values are
You know things that are busy
Passing away we are that whole
Referral structure
We've moved
JCB to
Instead use the return
Value
And so although this still exists all around it and it still active I would suggest that you don't use it
Because eventually I think we'll just drop it and the replacement is field and field ID
So you can actually tell JCB
of the bat
That this field and then that bat would basically mean a the fields name
So if the fields name is
Product or whatever
And then
What ID you want to have selected
Because this is targeting a list
Field
So there's a list of it say products
In a list field
And
So
The result in this value should then be
Basically
Product like that
And result in this
Field will eventually be something like
Already this feature
to
Change the actual
Field value
I don't know does that all make sense to you
So you can already in your URL because this is this information here is taken from a
URL
You can already add a value called field
Which then equals the field name
And then add a value called field ID
Which equals the ID you want selected
And that it automatically
Set the value
Now that's only for one field
So we realized ok well
We may want to do this for more than one field
So in the interface
We go to admin views
And we open the look
Which is where we may want to do more we can scroll down and we'll see a place
called
Get form
So we can say
We are here
And save this
Where you would then be able to add more
And the so tells you that the array data that load
the form and the ID
Is all here the how you access those
And you can add your own implementation of what I just shown you
So let's save this and compile so we can
Show you where this ends up
So you see we are here this is where that codes ends up
So you could literally come in here grab this
And
Basically copy it in here
just again
Make sure you you want the ID to be there
And add your own
And you can decide what this must be
You could say
Ok
Whatever you like
And obviously you don't need this
And that was just because we are
Actually
This obviously as the default so we will just make that
Null
And then here
We'll just say 0
And we changed this also to something that is generic now
With these values in your URL
You can update
This redirect
and you can change this from a string
to
Or you can
Make a comma separating I mean you know how to pass values through a URL
And
So doing this you can
Set the stage of the form
With
Predetermined selective
Options very easily
I hope this makes sense to you
If you have any questions please leave
Leave any comments in the
Video
comments area or go to the Forum and
Let me know
So that's how easy it is to
Target
Now
Maybe
Just for
Making sure we are on the same page
This one here needs to be the field name now how how do we know what is field name
If you open the form
And for this
We open look
XML which is where the form exists it's this value name
so
You can
Choose this name
I would suggest that you would be careful
In what type of fields you allowed to be edited through the URL
So that
Yeah your form doesn't become
Hackable
Somehow
Exposing data it shouldn't
Or overwriting data
Well that there are actually catches
To validate whether a form is allowed to be
Submitted by the specific
User that is in place in the controller
Does do a validation so if you for example here look in the controller
There is allow edit
Add sorry allowadd and a allowedit
And it does check whether this user
This current user
Has access
to the look area
And to this specific
ID of
course and then it continues to check whether it has edit
Access so all that is already in place
And so adding this
Dynamic
Updating
Of your value in the fields shouldn't be that risky
But I still like to be careful so I would think for example
If we want to
Change
Something here let's see what field could be done
Maybe this
Name field
So we could
Change that to name
So we know
That it should be name so over here
We could
Change this to field
Name like that
And so we could do some validation
If it's name then only should it actually continue
And then here because we also grabbing a string we can do some string sanitation
Make sure that this is
A string
Capitals
And we also doing null here
And then we can say
Field
Default
like that
And
We can also now
Validate this
To being a string
So we can grab the helper method
I mean
You do know that
Most components it has a helper
Class
And the helper class has a whole lot of methods that ships by Default
And
One of the very
Useful method that is here
besides many others is this
Check string
Is to check
Whether is a string
Is a string and it's actually got value in it
Now you could write this out every time
This little
Validation or you could just go
check
String
Like that
And obviously the helper class
Like that so demo helper
Check string so you can validate that this string has a value
And then only
Use these values
To to update your
field
That you are targeting
And so that way you can add a value to a field
Through the URL
Quite easily
Now I could demonstrate this on the front for you for just quick
demonstration
So very quickly have a
A little
Look value I added one
here from the front end now we want to actually be able to create a
New one
from the front
So we're going to have to make a little change here
To the looks view
We'll have to add a
A link here to create or button
It says create
And we'll have to
Do that
With
So here we do a can do get actions we only need to check whether it can
Create
We then do
Look create
And
Also
You know what let's rather use
The user object it is on the page we don't need to actually go through all the trouble
Checking the action because we not even working with
ID
We just wanna see if the user is allowed to
Create so we use the component name
And this
View
Look
Is the one where we gonna be creating see
it's there
So use that as the area to validate that create a look
And then we create our little button
And we we're using some
Uikit
Classes up here for our button you could obviously do your own thing
And if it can't create then just no string
Just a empty string
And then in the
Default View area we basically gonna just Echo the create link
Ok so this is just to get a create button on the page we haven't come to the field thing yet
we will do that in a moment
Let's just show you the button on the page
Ok so know having compiled and installed there is now create look
The pencil is not that ideal
you should change it to something else
So if you click on it it actually gives you the option to create a look
There we go
And
This is what we expect
Now what we wanna do is we wanna add a value
To this field here
By Default
So that if I click on that link
Automatic adds a value that's just a demonstration
We could do that with any text field and any list field
So going back to the admin view we gonna make sure we got everything set up right for for this catch
So in the get fom method
We now have a validation here to make sure it's a new item then we gotta use this
yhy
Just The generic we can
Anything
And we know that must be just a word no string there
Then we gonna do yhy value and this is gonna be a string and
And we gonna check this string like we said we doing
And we gonna check that the field name
Is not null
And then only
We gonna update that value
So we can just say now set
Field default value
Ok so
We gonna save this and
compile
And then run a few tests
Ok I've installed it so I'm gonna add now without adding it to the link just as a demonstration in the URL
I'm gonna type
Some value
And press enter
And now we see it loads up with that New value in place and
So it works
So we set the
y and y to name
And this value to James
If we left it empty like that and clicked
It'll just be empty so
It is giving us the expected result
Now we can go back to our site View
Where we have our link
And we can decide
Maybe
The user has a name
We want to add that name automatically if it Clicks the link
So let's do that
So we've added the field is name
The value will be based on the
Username
Or actually the name
And if there is none set it will just return empty
String
And so
we've got that setup
Let's save this and install
So now if I go over the button and I look here at the bottom of the screen it actually shows my name in there
do you see it
Now if I click the button
Now I ran into a little trouble here
And we'll have to maybe look at this
But if you remember I actually The Way We Built This URL in the backend
We passed it through a task
We didn't actually use this URL
We actually use the view look
And then task look edit
And that's how we
We passed it then this is because then we will have a well
A redirecting validation right here but doing that it was dumping
These values and it wasn't passing it
Through to the form
I went and then adapted this URL to actually use this URL
Instead so basically did this copy that
Come back here and just updated our URL like that
And it still worked and now it was passing the values through
Now
I'll need to test this a little more to be absolutely sure that this is not gonna cause some other
Headaches
But that is working I'm locked in in the backend at the moment of this
or in the front end
At the moment
As an administrator
So I'll have to login as a lesser permission individual and see how it behaves
then
But if we click look now
It passes the value right to the field like we've been anticipated
Based on these parameters that we've added
And it doesn't remove them
So this is what you would want
And this is working
I'm just not sure how this will relate down to those with less permission on the system
And this tutorial is getting too long to actually spend time on that now
So you'll have to play around with this if you run into something that's quite obviously a problem
Please let me know.  Well, thanks for watching.