Ok let's quickly look at adding and methods to your components helper class
you obviously go to the component
And
Then you go to this
Libs and helpers tab
There is a few areas here to Target the helper class
And
There's one that's called site helper
Then there's one that is called
Admin
So you could
Add this
This is the admin area
This is the site area then there is one called both
So if you want to add and helper method to your
Site area
You basically added here like I've done with this
Fancy date
Added it to the site area of the component
Just to demonstrate the other one
The admin area I'm just gonna
Say
This
Is admin
And then I'm also gonna do the one that says both admin and site
And just say
This is both
So basically
If you want to add a method that it must be accessible from both front and
Backend site and admin area
Then you use that one
If you want a method just available in the admin area then you use this one
And if you want a method available in the site area than you use this one
And so
Let's let's run this and see how it looks
Ok I'm gonna compile it
Ok let's see
Let me just quickly go and remove that I don't want that in there
Ok I'm gonna just install this
Then go let's go look at the code
Ok so we have
I have our Joomla Mount
Project here
and there is the admin area
And there is the front end
components area
So let's first go to the admin area components
Then to demo and then we go to the
Helper area
And then we go to demo again we open that up and if we scroll down it says here this
This is admin this is both see so it added those values in here
And we don't see the date
Function here
Because it was set to for the site area
So if we
Close the admin go to the component
Then again demo
Helper
Again demo
We'll see
That it has this
Fancy date
Set here
And then it has this as both
So
Whatever is placed in both gets placed in both the front and back or site and admin
Helper class
And then you could target specific areas by either just admin or just site
And that's really how you get methods into the helper class quite easily
Now if you want to
Actually add your own file your own helper class
Then you'll have to do a lot more to get this to work
Because the helper method
Is being called in the components
Main file
so you see there is a register
The helper
Method
See it's getting registered here
And so this is the helper classes name
And whatever
Method you wanna call
So if you wanna call for example we are in the site
Area
Say we wanna call the fancy date
We'll basically
Have to call it like this
Which I suppose this
Easy to understand
So that's how we would call it with the
date value
Ok so
That's how you call it and then you obviously put it into
Whatever other variable
you want
And you use it as you like
If you add your own helper class
Meaning your own file literally
Then you'll have to go about this a little different
There is a way to do that let me quickly show you
It's a little bit of a workaround because I've had to do that
Sometimes
First of all you obviously use the
File and folder inclusion
I did the advance one or the basic
Depending on where your file's located
And then you would grab that specific
File
Let's say this one
And you will placed the path
In corresponding to the
Zip file where you wanted and whether it should be updated and all that
Same goes with this I'm not gonna explain how you add the file that much because there is tutorial how to do
this and just go watch it on
on YouTube
If you have questions
But this would be the first step
Second step is to obviously add that
Specific file
Now
We have in the component helper
We have what is called a global event
So the global event
Is an event you want to trigger as often as the helper class gets added
So it's a little bit of a
Little in-house tweak
Because we want to sometimes have a
Event take place every time the helper class gets loaded
So this is the admin
Event
Add a global admin event so every time the global
Admin is going to be added
We want a method to be triggered so
What is that method
First wait to see all that is I'm just gonna add here
The event
So if you can see so I'll just add that little snippet there that's just for the admin area and gonna save and
close
And then compile it again and install to see it
in the code
Ok let's go to the code
Say yes
Now we'll see
This is the site the helper method
Let's go to the admin helper method
We'll see now there is a global event
That says
The event
In the
Admin
This is the admin if we look at that path
It is the administrator component
Com demo helpers helper class so this is the admin event
And it now has the string of the event in it
If we go to the admin area
And we open
The demo
Main file which is what Joomla grabs he's start with this one
We'll see that there is a little bit of a snippet been added
And that snippet
Triggers
The global event
With
The document
Object being passed
So going back here here comes the document we can actually affect the document
With a global event
Every time
A view of this component loads because the helper method
Always Gets
Triggered every time this backend admin
File gets loaded
So
You have a event now if you want to add your custom
Helper class to be available
The way to do that
Would be just to
Add it here
To this event
Because then you can add your own helper class so we'll call this
own
Just just an idea and Let's call this file also
Own
Ok
So
And then save that
And from now on every time in the backend
This helper method will be available
To you to use
Without ever
Sorry helper class will be available to use with whatever
A method is in it
So going back to the UI
You obviously have to load this file in manually like I've showed when
We started looking at this
But now going back
We'll just
I like this thing
Copy
Go to
The component
And
Then
To the event
And basically add that in there
And update our little comment saying
The
Custom
Helper class
Now what's important is you could do the same
For the front end
That is the site event you can add the same here you'll just again
Have to move that file to the front ends helper
Folder
With the helper
Sorry the file including method there is tutorials on how to do the file including
You know and moving it to the helper class and all that there is tutorials and how to do that
I'm not gonna demonstrate again please just go look at the tutorials on YouTube
There is tutorials about this I'm sure you can find that's not that hard
Ok save again
Should have been save
and close
So just to demonstrate
I'm gonna compile and installed this demo component once again
Now let's look at the code
And we'll see now
It's being triggered
Here
As well as in the site
Component is being triggered
And here it is being triggered
In the main document and also here in the main document site and admin both alike
So that's just too quick work around which isn't that much of a workaround it's
Just basically using a global event
To handle file inclusion
If you wanted to only be done per a specific View
Then once again there is a different way to do that
And there is away actually to do that
But
This is how to do it globally for all the views and have that helper file already there
I usually just use the components own helper file mostly
I really hardly ever use this event for
Inclusion of files
Simply because
Why
Put it another place just put it here
But there is other purposes you see me passing the document object there
And that could be because I wanna add some things to the document before any paid loads
And that's what I I have it there it's quite useful for that kind of use anyway hope
This helps thanks for watching until next time take care