I would like to demonstrate a quick
Way to add a validation rule to a field
I just now
What's the validation rules
Video or
Tutorial
And realzsed wow that's out dated very much so
Since now there already is actually a validation rules area
In JCB
Which really makes it extremely easy to add any type of validation rule
Which
You would like to do use in your
Fields
So
Just again what does a validation rule do
Well when you submit a form there are fields in that form
And
Server side
You may want to do some validation on that
Specific value
In that field
And
Validation rule really takes care of that
Basically checks the value
Whether it is
The correct value
And then
If it Isn't you can
Pass a
pass a
Basic return false
And if it's correct you
Return true which then
sets
The field to continue on saving
And be stored into the
Database
The field
Validation rules can also be used for other concepts
But I won't be explaining much of that now I'll just show you how to set it up and it's
Really easy
Ok so
First of course you need to understand where to add them so I'm gonna do grab any
Type of field here let's let's take this name field it's very much used
All over
so I'm gonna open the name field
And and you will see that by Default
There are already a set of validation rules
That are created
Now
There is
A validation rule called exists
And
There is
A validation rule called
Unique field
And some of this is
Things that we've made
Here in this
Joomla install
And others are part of the Joomla default validation rules
So how to create a custom one with be added to click here create
New validation rule
Which should then
Give you this little heads up and if you click ok
Takes you to this a new validation rule area
And it's gonna say you must add a unique value rule name
Which is really what you need to put into this area
Here
So you can say my validation
Which is unique enough and will tell you here
That that rule is fine
Now
Most the time you wanna also leave yourself a little note say
This
Was why
for reasons to understand the purpose of the validation rule
But you may also now
You may not know what is the PHP that you need to add here
What is the
How does a validation rule really look
So all those default validation rules
That already exist in Joomla are listed here
and this is just a selection thing
This value doesn't get stored
So it's just that you can select one and basically
To use it as a base from which to start
Or just to look at the different ways that it's
Done so let's say we use the email one
It basically loads the Joomlas default implementation
or validating an email now you can improve on this and call this my email validation
And that kind of thing
And then use this actual validation
So
Let's say we gonna do
Not this
Let's Let's
Let's choose another option
Let's say
Exist
Ok let's look at this
So
It's going to
You'll have to obviously
Read this read
This PHP here
And
Check
That this is exactly what you want
I'm not gonna explain this that's not what the tutorial is about
You need to know your PHP coming here
And then basically write out what you want here obviously
They are
Even ways to
to go reach out to other datasets in
Do validation
This could be a very exciting place
To do some tweaks
And then you would basically click
Save and close which will then take you back to the name field Where We Were
And if we now scroll down
We will now see in this list
A new validation rule
That's why
That's the
1 we just made
And if I grab that validation with a just a
Control
See on
on the PC
You
Can then
Scroll up here see is there already and validation rule
in place for this field no
If you click on the plus of these
There should be
A valid date option
And you can then this paste this validation rule in there
So at the moment
This
This field is used
Like oh too many time times too many places but I'm gonna just use this as an example
So it it's gonna
It's gonna still behave the same way
doesn't matter that
it is used so many places
Ok I'm gonna save and close out here and I'm just gonna compile
Any of these components that actually
Use
That field for example let's
Let's do component Builder
That should work
I'm just gonna compile this
Ok I've downloaded the package so let's go look inside that package
To see what was done
Ok so we go to admin
and models
And then there is a rules folder we opened that
and we see it has a file in here now called my validation
And let's open that
And here in my validation
It's basically extended the form rule
And it's added that
HTML
Sorry PHP
That we wrote basically this chunk over
Here
It is added it to the file for us
Now
This my validation
Must also now be added to the field right so let's look at that
So we go out of this
Then we go to forms
And
I'm just gonna open this
Custom admin View
XML
Just any
One which I know has a name field in it
And I scroll down and here it is
Name field
And there is my validation
Now you'll see at the top of this file
It is actually pointing
To the correct rule folder
So that it knows that if the rule is not default to Joomla
It should come and look here
To find it and so JCB has moved that rule into
The correct Place already
Now let's quickly
Look at I just another little
Small pointer here
And that is the package has a config file
And if we open the config file
We see that it already has that default rule path
As well set in the config file
So
That means that
Even if you were to use that field
In the configurations of our component it already know
Where to go look
For that component rule
Sorry that field rule
Ok so that was what it did it
We basically created the rule
And once we have created it
We simply added to a field
And JCB automatically
Grab that code created that file
Added that code to the file and everything should just work
Out of the box
Well that's how the new validation rule implementation
Of JCB
Actually works
I trust this would be
Informative enough
In helping you all
Using this validation rule area
Like I said before
There there is a way to get to this area
via the field
But is as you can see here is direct access
Just clicking on the validation rules
And then there is my validation
Here is some of the other validations
That we've made custom ones
That a
That is also in my
Project which is being used
So
The my validation is the one we did
And anything that we put in here
It's basically gonna add up at
Be added as class methods to that file
Now
You can always come back and make some tweaks to it
And every where with this validation rule is used
Those field will automatically be updated with the changes wants to get compiled again
Ok well thanks for watching and enjoy.