So we have a new feature in JCB version 2.9.
It's the latest release if you look at the release notes
Added the new placeholder area for Global
And component level placeholders now
Those of you did know did know that JCB already has a few placeholders
Which you can use across
The
System
If I have to show you those in the code
They are as follow
So once I've set of Place holders is the word component and this HHH is
Basically
It is the same as
3 of those and then again on this side
Three of those
So three opening angle brackets and three closing angle brackets
That's what the hh the sorry no that's what the
bbb
And a ddd stands for
Where is the hhh stands for hashes
one two
three of those the side
And
Three of those
This side
So those are placeholders that you know
Should know about already and gives you the
The possibility to
Add component name
lower case all
Uppercase First
Letter
All uppercase
And then with hashes as well as with
Opening angle
Brackets enclosing angle brackets
So
That's the first set of placeholders which
You should know about already
If not
Then it's possibly
The truth that you haven't watched
Previous tutorials
Which I would encourage you to do the other set is basically the view
Placeholder
The view has a few variations and it's not always available in every area depending on
What the
Area is
So for example in the backend the admin area It has view and views
For the list
And again you have this hashes and you have the open Square
Braces
Bracket
And they closing Square brackets
And
Again all lowercase then one uppercase and then all uppercase
So it's variations of
View
Now the reason why you have the s at times is because there is
A list
View name
And then there is the
As the edit View
Single View name
And so
These place holders are also available but just when you are busy working
In the admin
Admin View area
So
With regards to the site View area
There is also a placeholder
Let me see if I can quickly find that here
Ok here it is
So it has a capital S in front or a lower s
So
Again
It's because we don't have a
Different site view doesn't have a list view it can actually be a listview or it can be
A Single View
Based on the dynamic get
So that's why there isn't really
a difference
So
So we working with S View
Uppercase and lowercase all uppercase again with hashes and with braces again
We have this function to add the list option but you see
It is actually the exact same
Code so
If there by some reason is a
List
Implementation somewhere
It's really just replacing with
With the same code
So those are the custom Place holders or
What's the word
the core place holders
That already exist in the system
And
They already were taking JCB to a place where
We could achieve a lot of dynamic reusability
Of use of Fields and all sorts of
Other implementations
But then came along
The idea
To actually be able to set our own place holders in the gooey
Of JCB
And to reuse them wherever we would like to
Just like custom code with behave accept
It's a string and not
A code snippet so
That's the major difference
And it also doesn't come with an IDE
Roundabout
Editing
Feature as custom code snippets do
It's just a in place replacement behaviour
So
Let's go back to the IDE to show you that
I mean
Not the ID the the gooey
JCB itself
So in JCB there is now a place called Place holders
And
You can open that up
And if you have imported some of my components you might have some values in
here already
If not it might have no values
So we still having these 3
Open Square
Brackets and closing Square brackets
Surrounding our place holders if I was to create a new place holder
And type in any word
It it automatically adds
The
Brackets around the word
An immediately starts a surge all across JCB
To see if it's being used anywhere
If not obviously it tells you it's not being used
Now any word in this case I can add any type of string on this side
So as long as it is a one-liner string it can really be anything
It can have
Dollar sign in it it can have brackets in it
It can have multiple brackets in it
It can have
Even braces in it and again brackets and braces
And it can have dollar signs in well
It's supposed to
If you find something and it breaks stuff
Let me know
in GitHub tell me about it it's a bug it's supposed to be able to
To handle any type of string now I've said all that now let's see if it actually does like clicking
save here
Oh yeah
So it kept it exactly that way
Now
That means where ever in my program I am you all let me just for safety add this as comment
So it's basically a comment string
It could have been a variable name it could have been another string now you might say why not just
Type that string
In that area
Well
You see JCB we are starting to embark upon
A idea
With I'm not sure how far it will go
Or how wide or broad it will expand
But it is the possibility of reusing code
From your custom code area in different components
In different views
This often requires
That certain little strings
Be different
But
There is a place where passing a string at from every component becomes very tedious
Because yes custom codes has this feature
Where you can pass this string
To the
Code and then it updates that string in the code
But
There was this idea that we really don't want to be passing any string
And yet have a
Automated
Updating string behaviour in custom code
So
This is where placeholders come in
So if I save and close out of this
I now have this new place holder any word
And I can now
Go to
A component
And let's say
I'm gonna take this anthropometry component as an example
And
I'm going to just add this place holder here like that
Save and close this is in the helper class
So I just added it to
anthropometry now I'm also gonna add it to this
Medical aid one
Again the same place order like that save and close
Now I know for this implementation what I'm showing you right now
It might not be that exciting
But I'm telling you if
You start to sort of
Think about the
Greater implication
For example if we were to
Go to the dynamic code
And for example get method get member
This get member function oh wait I'm
on the wrong place I'm talking custom code
Now let's say which one
I think I have
This little dot trick which is just a little JavaScript
That sort of runs and
Populates a little dot
Tick tick tick tick tick showing like there's a progress
Just a little snippet
Now
It's being used quite a few places and
I might want to
use like for example
Let's say
Member profile I might be using member profile in more than one component
And
Now
That means this specific
Site view the specific site view is being used in different components
Now
If I want to have the code be different when used in
One component
Then used in another that's where placeholders really come in it's full strength
So if I was to place that snippet here any word
As an example
And save and close this
I now have in this little
Nice little dot trick I have a placeholder which will
Be replaced with
This value
But let's say
I instead
want to
Have it be different in one of the components that uses that little dot
Code snippet
I can go to that specific
Component
And I can add
That place holder here
And
Say not
Like
The other and now for this component
This place holder will be
Basically not like the other
So now you have a placeholder with within this component behaves differently
Then it does within other components
And that's really where placeholders
So let's compile this and see what happens
I have a few here so we got medical aid I'm gonna compile that let's see I don't have it installed
So I've have to first do coral
This is a project
Which we are planning to launch quite soon
I'm quite excited about this project
It's gonna be one of our proprietary projects
Ok so what's happened here oh yeah
We haven't set up the
The path ok just
Put it in
Now so we gonna have to backup folder path setup now I can do anthropometry
And have it
Compile it's actually updating and placing all those
Placeholders and stuff
Ok so we gonna see the difference
And then I'm also going to add the medical aid one
Which is the one that doesn't have that overwrite
So it should use the global
Implementation
Ok so now with basically added
These two
Components to our
Joomla website
And
We have used placeholders
That actually Target
A specific any word
And we've placed that
In those components helper classes
And also within 1
Custom codes snippet
Called
Little nice little dot trick
Now to see in which of those components where there's little nice little dog trick is going to appear
It's basically gonna be in the member profile of Corel
So
Yeah that means we'll go look and see what it did
So first I'm going to open the helper class
Of coral
It's this one here
And then
Scroll down to that where that snippet should have been added
So in the anthropometry component it set not like the other because we added the overwrite
Then in the medical aid component it added those
That's very strange string A typed out
And in the coral component
Nice little dot trick
It also added that little
Snippet
Now to show you how easy it is to overwrite this again on a component level
Let me open this up
Let me go to the components
And
to Coral
An add a that snippet in here
And
That
Easy
Save and close
And then we compile that one again
Now we open the IDE again
And that easy
So
That is the power of placeholders it really replaces only from where the placeholder starts to where it ends.
It means you have the ability to change that little text to have the ability to
Change
You know
This
Yes you actually able to
Change even the little dot
You add a space
Or
I'm not sure about the
Space one
That might be over eager but
The reality is it's really powerful you're able to anywhere add a dynamic string
Which you then can overwrite on a component level
So yes I hope you find it very useful
Because I am finding it at this stage I have components that
Actually
Run together or
How can I say
And all these components build on top of coral
Coral
Itself is a
Sort of
Central
Integration hub if you will
Where all these components
you know connect into
Coral
And create
Exciting kind of
Interface
So that means I often need to rename certain values differently just based
On
The actual component
And
This way I'm able to have that kind of placeholder Power
And replacing it and have the same code snippet
Across these components but just because it's now in this component is actually being updated differently
Then it would in for example this one
And yeah they are even more
Implementations
But I think this would be enough to get you going
and help you understand
Why we added placeholders
And where we think it will be able to
Take the JCB community
With
More creative abilities
Right inside
The
The graphic interface
Of JCB
Well again
As always thank you for watching
Let me know if you have any questions either in the comments or on the Forum
You're most welcome.