I would like to give you the tutorial
How to
Manage your
Global
Options
Also known as the global configuration options
Of a component
As some of you may already know
The global configuration options is also
The same area where you are able to set
The menu option
Of a specific site View
So I'm gonna demonstrate some of that to you
We want to actually achieve
An understanding on how to
Control where which of these
Fields
Appear
You see because you might want to have the field appear in your Global options after component
But not in the menu
Or you might want to have it
Appear in the menu
But not in
And the global option
And so there is ways to achieve that
And so I wanna demonstrate that
And also give a little general overview because I was looking for the tutorial Where I've done this
Before
And
Yeah it's a classic example of dealing with to many issues in one
Tutorial so
I actually couldn't find it
So I'm gonna redo this and
I know it's there somewhere but
Ok this will stand out so people find it easily so let's see
Joomla components I've got a component to your called member manager
If I open it
It's also got a lot of config file Fields already setup. So let's look at that.
So I've got some Global fields
There is a site view called members
Which actually also already has
A number of fields as you can see here
And
That means they are actually also we can also look at some of them
I'm gonna demonstrate adding one because to me
That's most
Explanatory
Then there's some company value data and stuff ok
So there's a lot of config values already here
Usually if there is none you're just click on
this plus and start adding
The fields now
It's really in the field that a lot of the control is managed
So if I go out of here
And I go to the fields
And let's let's open some of those
Field
Like for example
We have this members the first one is member display type list so it is this one
Let's open that one
And so basically see normal
Members display type
And then
Basically nothing
Unique
Now
If I compile this component
install it
And now let's go look
At that component quickly
And it's global options
We see it has only 1, 2
3 Fields showing here so the 3 field showing here
But in our list there are quite a lot more
So let's look at some of the fields that don't show up in the config area
So like let's see
It is panel template
Panel
panels, panel and then displayed type
So
That means this table row template isn't there
This table template isn't there oh wait
Maybe they are
Let's see if I change this
Oh yeah they are there
So there are a few hidden
Fields
Working along here
So let's scroll down
Target member types that one isn't there
Components 1to1 link
to
JMM multi custom
That one isn't
There
And this one too many
Is also not there ok so let's go look at that in the fields area
So here is the component 1 to many linked
To JMM
Joomla member manager
First scroll down
I see a few options here
For now we'll see that there is in this extra properties area
There's a new property added called display
And it set to menu
I'll be here you can read about this this actual property there are a few
And it says display switch for Dynamic placement in relation to the use
Of the field in menu and global configuration options
So that means if this field gets used in
The menu or in Global configuration
You can switch it on and off
to be either in the one or the other
With leaving this blank like not having it in all
We'll put it into both
Which was the default way used to always work
So
So the config option will only add the field to the global configuration area
Where is the menu will add the field only to the
To the menu area
Which means this field is only being added
So let's see if that so
So here in the global configuration of the manager it on the members it is not
Visible no matter which choice we make here
It's still not visible
If we select member manager members
You see there is a new tab here
And here it is actually showing up
Component one to one
So here it is active where as in the
Global config it is not
So that is
Really as simple as it is
In adding a
Field
To just
Menu is to select display
And add the string menu here exactly as spelled there
Or config now if you want it in both like I said you just leave this out like
You don't even need to add anything where is if you want it only in config you would add
Config string in the value here
Ok so let's do that
Let's create a field
We say new
give it a name
Show title
Select an option we wanna do radio
Radio field
Then I'm just gonna add these properties
So as name we set show title as label show title
Select if the title should be shown and yes no the default being one
And for now we gonna leave off any other settings here and just save this
Then the going back to our member manager we can open the config
And add this new tab in here
So we just clicked + here the way we know how to add this tab name
Is it must be the exact same name as the site view
Where we want the menu
Value to be added
So
So we gonna add the correct site view now we here we selecting the field
Which we've just created
So I'm going to add it to the cpanel
And show title and the default again I'm adding it here as one
And we can save and close out of here
Now let's compile this component and see what happens
and install
Now I'm going back to the go configurations
We have this tab called cpanel and it says show title
And it's yes or no
And that's quite to be expected
But now going to the menu
And instead of selecting
Members I'm going to select
Cpanel
and again shows me this member manager tab but now
It says show title and he has this use Global
Yes or no
So you can use Global just leave that or you could say no
Which is a local overwrite
Yes would also be a local overwrite
So
This way
Your parameters in your menu
It overwrites either falls back to the global setting of the components configuration
Or it overwrites it here on this menu level
Ok now we want to change the field so it doesn't show up in the menu
Which is quite simple we go down here
And we
Again
Select the display option
and I wanna it only to be in the config area so we add the word config here
And save
Then we go back and compile an install this component just again
Now back in the menu
We need to just refresh this page here
Basically make sure we have
Cpanel selected
And as you can see the values no longer showing here
There's no longer that Xtra tab
Where is in member manager if I was to refresh this area
The cpanel tab is still there and that option is still available
Now I can go back and change this from config
to
Menu
Again
just save this
And go back compile and install
Now going back to the menu
If I refresh this menu suddenly we have member manager back and has
Show title
But now you see it no longer has the global option
This is a fix in the latest release it's still in staging version
2.9.15
Suppose it will come out in 16 so this is a fix we've noticed that it used to still add global
Here
While there is no longer a global value
So we have fix this
But so from here on forward it should be resolved
Now if we go back to the global configuration area
And we refresh this area
Then suddenly the
Cpanel tab is gone
We we don't see it and that means that the value itself also
It's still in the database
If you
If you've saved it previously and you've done this it's still in the database now the only way to quickly get it out
Just click save here
Oh and we've got some empty values we need to fill before we can so that's just a little
Demonstration
From my side on how to adapt
The
Actual
Config of your component
This area
To be able to add Fields to it
Is quite easy but to be able to add this Fields to site views so
If I show you this if I say a site view
I mean
That this component
If we would open it
In the site views it actually has
A site view called cpanel
See also members the one we looked at
And so
The cpanel
Is its name
If you aren't sure about what that name is you can go to site views
And to that specific
Site view this name here
That says name
That is the name of the tag you must use
And so
That means your Fields behaviour
Is literally controlled
In the field itself
And
Yes that means if you would to add this field to multiple components it will be actually behaving
Similar
In every one of those components
Meaning if you've add this to be menu it will only be loaded to menu
But if you add this field to a site view or sorry to an admin View
It doesn't actually react to this display
Value
Then then this display property is no longer
Really being used
It's only Active
When it is lined up in a few points that is first that it's belongs to
a tab
Which also has a site view of the same name
Secondly
That it
Is in the configurations therefore of course
So it needs to be a configuration field
That belongs to a tab
Which has a site view of the same name then these display
Property actually kicks in
Otherwise it's simply ignored
And so you could use this fields in
Menus sorry not me
in admin views
And then this value won't play a role
It's only when it becomes a config field
Ok well thanks for watching
If you still have any questions
Or even
if you see some
Room for improvement
Please do not hesitate to communicate with us
Either on the Forum or if it's
If you know for sure that this is a feature request or a bug whatever then related to JCB
Then please
Open an issue on GitHub
So look forward to hearing from you take care.