So we've added another nice sort of improvement I would say by request
Of one of our
Shallow
Developers
Whenever you create a field
You always have to answer select the field type
That's a list
Or
It's like it takes 1 hour
Text field
You can set up the properties
Usual
Remove whatever values you don't want and then
You need to save the database values
Every time
Although you might be using the same database set of values for specific type of
Fields field types you need to set an every time he wishes
Is the word cumbersome
So we added a new feature it's not active by default
So that's because we want
You
To know that it's
Does that so it's like they want you to set it
In doing so you will sell it the way it works for you
Which means you still need to know a little bit of
You know how the database values to be stored
Bathroom sample number
It could be
Most unlikely that it's not an integer so
So we could
We could take integer
And leave the rest like that safe
So now we basically have the default database value phone number
If we
Next time open a field in Newfield
And select number
It will
Automatically add that has the database values you can of course still changed
To maybe a larger integer or whatever is is appropriate for your purpose that this state
But it helps you sort of gives you that little bit of
Yes
Can you use of already
Decided values
Regarding a database
For the specific field type
Ok so that's just a quick demonstration
I'm sure that there's not really much to it
You can now go through your field types
Hand
Choose for example ok telephone
Always Gonna
Use voucher you know
Ab64
And
Yeah
Set that up
And
So you could go on
I get said text
Also to
To varchar
And
Yeah the girls just be like that
And so you could set a lot of default
Database values for your Fields well enjoy
Thanks for watching